Book Eight

1. It will tend to avert complacency if you remember that any claim to have lived as a philosopher all your life, or even since reaching manhood, is now out of the question; indeed, it is as evident to many others as it is to yourself that even today philosophy is still far beyond you. Consequently your mind remains in a state of confusion, and it grows no easier to earn the title of philosopher; also, your station in life militates constantly against it. Once all this is seen in its true light, you should banish any thoughts of how you may appear to others, and rest content if you can make the remainder of your life what nature would have it to be. Learn to understand her will, and let nothing else distract you. Up to now, all your wanderings in search of the good life have been unsuccessful; it was not to be found in the casuistries of logic, nor in wealth, celebrity, worldly pleasures, or anything else. Where, then, lies the secret? In doing what man's nature seeks. How so? By adopting strict principles for the regulation of impulse and action. Such as? Principles regarding what is good or bad for us: thus, for example, that nothing can be good for a man unless it helps to make him just, self-disciplined, courageous, and independent; and nothing bad unless it has the contrary effect.

2. Of any action, ask yourself, What will its consequences be to me? Shall I repent of it? Before long I shall be dead and all will be forgotten; but in the meantime, if this undertaking is fit for a rational and social being, who is under the same law as God himself, why look for more?

3. Alexander, Caesar, Pompey — what were they beside Diogenes, Heraclitus, Socrates? These last looked at things and their causes and what they are made of; and their master-spirits were cast in one mould. But the others — what a host of cares, what an infinity of enslavements!

4. You may break your heart, but men will still go on as before.

5. The first rule is, to keep an untroubled spirit; for all things must bow to Nature's law, and soon enough you must vanish into nothingness, like Hadrian and Augustus. The second is to look things in the face and know them for what they are, remembering that it is your duty to be a good man. Do without flinching what man's nature demands; say what seems to you most just — though with courtesy, modesty, and sincerity.

6. Universal Nature's task is to shuffle, transpose, interchange, remove from one state and transfer to another. Everywhere there is change; and yet we need fear nothing unexpected, for all things are ruled by age-long wont, and even the manner of apportioning them does not vary.

7. Every nature finds its satisfaction in the smooth pursuance of its own road. To a nature endowed with reason, this means assenting to no impression that is misleading or obscure, giving rein to no impulse towards actions that are not social, limiting all desires or rejections to things that lie within its own power, and greeting every dispensation of Nature with an equal welcome. For these dispensations are as truly a part of her as a leaf's nature is part of the plant's; save that the leaf's is part of a nature which has no feelings or reason, and is capable of being frustrated, while man's nature is part of one which not only cannot be frustrated, but also is endowed with both intelligence and justice, since it assigns to all men equally their proper share of time, being, causation, activity, and experiences. (Do not look to find this equality, though, in any exact correspondence between one man and another in every particular, but rather in a general comparison of them both in their entirety.)

8. You cannot hope to be a scholar. But what you can do is to curb arrogance; what you can do is to rise above pleasures and pains; you can be superior to the lure of popularity; you can keep your temper with the foolish and ungrateful, yes, and even care for them.

9. Let no one, not even yourself, ever hear you abusing court life again.

10. Repentance is remorse for the loss of some helpful opportunity. Now, what is good is always helpful, and must be the concern of every good man; but an opportunity of pleasure is something no good man would ever repent of having let pass. It follows, therefore, that pleasure is neither good nor helpful.

11. Ask yourself, What is this thing in itself, by its own special constitution? What is it in substance, and in form, and in matter? What is its function in the world? For how long does it subsist?

12. When it is hard to shake off sleep, remind yourself that to be going about the duties you owe society is to be obeying the laws of man's nature and your own constitution, whereas sleep is something we share with the unreasoning brute creation; and furthermore, that obedience to one's own nature is the more proper, the more suitable, and indeed the more agreeable course.

13. If possible, make it a habit to discover the essential character of every impression, its effect on the self, and its response to a logical analysis.

14. No matter whom you meet, always begin by asking yourself, What are his views on the goodness or badness of things? For then, if his beliefs about pleasure and pain and their causes, or about repute and disrepute, or life and death are of a certain type, I shall not be surprised or scandalized to find his actions in keeping with them; I shall tell myself that he has no choice.

15. Nobody is surprised when a fig-tree brings forth figs. Similarly, we ought to be ashamed of our surprise when the world produces its normal crop of happenings. A physician or a shipmaster would blush to be surprised if a patient proves feverish, or a wind contrary.

16. To change your mind and defer to correction is not to sacrifice your independence; for such an act is your own, in pursuance of your own impulse, your own judgement, and your own thinking.

17. If the choice is yours, why do the thing? If another's, where are you to lay the blame for it? On gods? On atoms? Either would be insanity. All thoughts of blame are out of place. If you can, correct the offender; if not, correct the offence; if that too is impossible, what is the point of recriminations? Nothing is worth doing pointlessly.

18. That which dies does not drop out of the world. Here it remains; and here too, therefore, it changes and is resolved into its several particles; that is, into the elements which go to form the universe and yourself. They themselves likewise undergo change, and yet from them comes no complaint.

19. Everything — a horse, a vine — is created for some duty. This is nothing to wonder at: even the sun-god himself will tell you, 'There is a work that I am here to do,' and so will all the other sky-dwellers. For what task, then, were you yourself created? For pleasure? Can such a thought be tolerated?

20. Nature always has an end in view; and this aim includes a thing's ending as much as its beginning or its duration. She is like the ball's thrower. Is the ball itself bettered by its upward flight? Is it any worse as it comes down, or as it lies after its fall? What does a bubble gain by holding together, or lose by collapsing? The like is true of a candle, too.

21. Turn this mortal body inside out, and now see the appearance it presents. See what it comes to in old age, or sickness, or decay. How fleeting are the lives of him alike who praises and him who is praised; of the rememberer and the remembered; how small their little corner of this terrestrial zone — and even there they are not all at peace with one another. Nay, the whole earth is itself no more than the puniest dot.

22. Give it the whole of your attention, whether it be a material object, an action, a principle, or the meaning of what is being said.

This disappointment serves you right. You would rather hope for goodness tomorrow than practise it today.

23. In what I do, I am to do it with reference to the service of mankind. In what befalls me, I am to accept it with reference to the gods, and to that universal source from which the whole close-linked chain of circumstance has its issue.

24. What do the baths bring to your mind? Oil, sweat, dirt, greasy water, and everything that is disgusting. Such, then, is life in all its parts, and such is every material thing in it.

25. Death robbed Lucilla of Verus, and later claimed Lucilla too. Death took Maximus from Secunda, then Secunda herself; Diotimus from Epitynchanus, and Epitynchanus after him; Faustina from Antoninus, and Antoninus in his turn. So it is ever. Celer buries Hadrian, and is buried himself. Those noble minds of old, those men of prescience, those men of pride, where are they now? Keen wits like Charax, Demetrius the Platonist, Eudaemon, and others like them; all enduring but for a day, all now long since dead and gone; some forgotten as soon as dead, some passed into legend, some faded even out of legend itself. Bethink you then how either this complex body of your own must also one day be broken up in dispersion, or else the breath that animates it must be extinguished, or removed and translated elsewhere.

26. A man's true delight is to do the things he was made for. He was made to show goodwill to his kind, to rise above the promptings of his senses, to distinguish appearances from realities, and to pursue the study of universal Nature and her works.

27. We have three relationships: one to this bodily shell which envelops us, one to the divine Cause which is the source of everything in all things, and one to our fellow-mortals around us.

28. Pain must be an evil either to the body — in which case let the body speak for itself — or if not, to the soul. But the soul can always refuse to consider it an evil, and so keep its skies unclouded and its calm unruffled. For there is no decision, no impulse, no movement of approach or recoil, but must proceed from within the self; and into this self no evil can force its way.

29. Erasing all fancies, keep on saying to yourself, 'It lies in my own hands to ensure that no viciousness, cupidity, or turmoil of any kind finds a home in this soul of mine; it lies with me to perceive all things in their true light, and to deal with each of them as it merits.' Remember this authority, which is nature's gift to you.

30. Both in the senate and when addressing individuals, use language that is seemly but not rhetorical. Be sane and wholesome in your speech.

31. Think of the court of Augustus: wife, daughter, children, grandsires, sister, Agrippa, kindred, connexions, friends, Areius, Maecenas, medical attendants, priests — an entire court, all vanished. Turn to other records of eclipse; extinctions not of individuals but of whole stocks — the Pompeys, for example — and the inscription we see on memorials, 'The last of his house.' Think of all the pains taken by their predecessors to leave an heir after them; and yet in the end someone must be the last, and one more whole race has perished.

32. Your every separate action should contribute towards an integrated life; and if each of them, so far as it can, does its part to this end, be satisfied; for that is something which nobody can prevent. 'There will be interferences from without,' you say? Even so, they will not affect the justice, prudence, and reasonableness of your intentions. 'No, but some kind of practical action may be prevented.' Perhaps; yet if you submit to the frustration with a good grace, and are sensible enough to accept what offers itself instead, you can substitute some alternative course which will be equally consistent with the integration we are speaking of.

33. Accept modestly; surrender gracefully.

34. You have perhaps seen a severed hand or foot, or a head lying by itself apart from its body. That is the state to which a man is doing his best to reduce himself, when he refuses to accept what befalls him and breaks away from his fellows, or when he acts for selfish ends alone. Then you become an outcast from the unity of Nature; though born a part of it, you have cut yourself away with your own hand. Yet here is the beautiful thought: that it still lies in your own power to reunite yourself. No other part of creation has been so favoured by God with permission to come together again, after once being sundered and divided. Behold, then, his goodness, with which he has dignified man: he has put it in his power, not only initially to keep himself inseparate from the whole, but afterwards, if separated, to return and be reunited and resume his membership as before.

35. When the Nature of all things rational equipped each rational being with his powers, one of the faculties we received from her hand was this, that just as she herself transmutes every obstacle or opposition, fits it into its place in destiny's pattern, and assimilates it into herself, so a rational being has power to turn each hindrance into material for himself, and use it to set forward his own endeavours.

36. Never confuse yourself by visions of an entire lifetime at once. That is, do not let your thoughts range over the whole multitude and variety of the misfortunes that may befall you, but rather, as you encounter each one, ask yourself, 'What is there unendurable, so insupportable, in this?' You will find that you are ashamed to admit defeat. Again, remember that it is not the weight of the future or the past that is pressing upon you, but ever that of the present alone. Even this burden, too, can be lessened if you confine it strictly to its own limits, and are severe enough with your mind's inability to bear such a trifle.

37. Are Pantheia or Pergamus still sitting to this day by the tomb of Verus? Chabrias or Diotimus by Hadrian's? Ridiculous! And supposing they were, would the dead be sensible of it? Or if sensible, pleased? Moreover, even if the dead themselves were pleased, could the mourners, for their part, be expected to go on living for ever? Were not they likewise doomed to become old men and old women, and to pass away in their turn? — and then what could the mourned do, when their mourners were no more? And all this for nothing more than a bagful of stench and corruption.

38. In the words of Crito the sage, 'If thou hast eyes to see, then see.'

39. In the constitution of a rational being, I find no virtue implanted for the combating of justice, but I do find self-control implanted for the combating of pleasure.

40. Subtract your own notions of what you imagine to be painful, and then your self stands invulnerable. 'My self — what is it?' Your reason. 'But I am not all reason.' So be it; in that case, at least let your reason forbear to give pain to itself, and if another part of you is in trouble, let its thoughts about itself be its own concern.

41. To the nature of the vital force animating our bodies, any frustration of the senses is an evil, and so is the frustration of any endeavour. The nature of a plant has likewise its own frustrations and its evils; and in the same way, any frustration of the mind is an evil to the nature of the mind. Apply all this to your own case. Does a pain affect you, or a pleasure? The senses will see to that. Have you been baulked in an endeavour? It is true that if it was made without any allowance for possible failure, such frustration is indeed an evil to you as a rational being. However, once you accept that universal necessity, you can suffer no harm and no frustration. Within its own domain, there is nobody who can frustrate the mind. Fire, sword, oppression, calumny, and all else are powerless to touch it. 'The globe, once orbed and true, remains a sphere.'

42. I, who have never wilfully pained another, have no business to pain myself.

43. To each his own felicity. For me, soundness of my sovereign faculty, reason; no shrinking from mankind and its vicissitudes; the ability to survey and accept all things with a kindly eye, and to deal with them according to their deserts.

44. Make the best of today. Those who aim instead at tomorrow's plaudits fail to remember that future generations will be nowise different from the contemporaries who so try their patience now, and nowise less mortal. In any case, can it matter to you how the tongues of posterity may wag, or what views of yourself it may entertain?

45. Take me and cast me where you will; I shall still be possessor of the divinity within me, serene and content so long as it can feel and act as becomes its constitution. Is the matter of such moment that my soul should be afflicted by it, and changed for the worse, to become a cowering craven thing, suppliant and spiritless? Could anything at all be of such consequence as that?

46. No event can happen to a man but what is properly incidental to man's condition, nor to an ox, vine, or stone but what properly belongs to the nature of oxen, vines, and stones. Then if all things experience only what is customary and natural to them, why complain? The same Nature which is yours as well as theirs brings you nothing you cannot bear.

47. If you are distressed by anything external, the pain is not due to the thing itself but to your own estimate of it; and this you have the power to revoke at any moment. If the cause of the trouble lies in your own character, set about reforming your principles; who is there to hinder you? If it is the failure to take some apparently sound course of action that is vexing you, then why not take it, instead of fretting? 'Because there is an insuperable obstacle in the way.' In that case, do not worry; the responsibility for inaction is not yours. 'But life is not worth living with this thing undone.' Why then, bid life a good-humoured farewell; accepting the frustration gracefully, and dying like any other man whose actions have not been inhibited.

48. Remember that your higher Self becomes invincible when once it withdraws into itself and calmly refuses to act against its will, even though such resistance may be wholly irrational. How much more, then, when its decision is based on reason and circumspection! Thus a mind that is free from passion is a very citadel; man has no stronger fortress in which to seek shelter and defy every assault. Failure to perceive this is ignorance; but to perceive it, and still not to seek its refuge, is misfortune indeed.

49. Never go beyond the sense of your original impressions. These tell you that such-and-such a person is speaking ill of you; that was their message; they did not go on to say it has done you any harm. I see my child is ill; my eyes tell me that, but they do not suggest that his life is in danger. Always, then, keep to the original impressions; supply no additions of your own, and you are safe. Or at least, add only a recognition of the great world-order by which all things are brought to pass.

50. Is your cucumber bitter? Throw it away. Are there briars in your path? Turn aside. That is enough. Do not go on to say, 'Why were things of this sort ever brought into the world?' The student of nature will only laugh at you; just as a carpenter or a shoemaker would laugh, if you found fault with the shavings and scraps from their work which you saw in the shop. Yet they, at least, have somewhere to throw their litter; whereas Nature has no such out-place. That is the miracle of her workmanship: that in spite of this self-limitation, she nevertheless transmutes into herself everything that seems worn-out or old or useless, and re-fashions it into new creations, so as never to need either fresh supplies from without, or a place to discard her refuse. Her own space, her own materials and her own skill are sufficient for her.

51. Dilatory action, incoherent conversation, vague impressions; a soul too inwardly cramped; a soul too outwardly effusive; a life without room for leisure — avoid such things. Martyrdom, mutilation, execration; how can they affect the mind's ability to remain pure, sane, temperate, just? A man may stand by a clear spring of sweet water and heap abusive words upon it, yet it still goes on welling up fresh and wholesome; he may even cast in mire and filth, but it will quickly dissolve them and wash them away, and show no stain. How be lord yourself of such a perennial fountain? By safeguarding the right to be your own master every hour of the day, in all charity, simplicity and modesty.

52. Without an understanding of the nature of the universe, a man cannot know where he is; without an understanding of its purpose, he cannot know what he is, nor what the universe itself is. Let either of these discoveries be hid from him, and he will not be able so much as to give a reason for his own existence. So what are we to think of anyone who cares to seek or shun the applause of the shouting multitudes, when they know neither where they are nor what they are?

53. Would you wish for the praise of one who thrice an hour calls down curses on his own head? Would you please one who cannot even please himself? And how can a man be pleased with himself, when he repents of well-nigh everything he does?

54. As your breathing partakes of the circumfluent air, so let your thinking partake of the circumfluent Mind. For there is a mental Force which, for him who can draw it to himself, is no less ubiquitous and all-pervading than is the atmosphere for him who can breathe it.

55. The general wickedness of mankind cannot injure the universe; nor can the particular wickedness of one man injure a fellow-man. It harms none but the culprit himself; and he can free himself from it as soon as he so chooses.

56. My neighbour's will is of no greater concern to my will than his breath or his flesh. No matter how much we are made for one another, still each man's self has its own sovereign rights. Otherwise my neighbour's wickedness would become my evil; and God has not willed this, lest the ruin of my happiness should lie at another's disposal.

57. The sun is seen to pour down and expend itself in all directions, yet is never exhausted. For this downpouring is but a self-extension; sunbeams, in fact, derive their very name from a word signifying 'to be extended'. To understand the property of a sunbeam, watch the light as it streams into a darkened room through a narrow chink. It prolongs itself forward in a straight line, until it is held up by encountering some solid body which blocks its passage to the air beyond; and then it remains at rest there, without slipping off or falling away. The emission, and the diffusion, of thought should be the counterpart of this: not exhausting, but simply extending itself; not dashing violently or furiously against the obstacles it encounters, nor yet falling away in despair; but holding its ground and lighting up that upon which it rests. Failure to transmit it is mere self-deprivation of light.

58. He who fears death either fears to lose all sensation or fears new sensations. In reality, you will either feel nothing at all, and therefore nothing evil, or else, if you can feel any new sensations, you will be a new creature, and so will not have ceased to have life.

59. Men exist for each other. Then either improve them, or put up with them.

60. An arrow travels in one fashion, but the mind in another. Even when the mind is feeling its way cautiously and working round a problem from every angle, it is still moving directly onwards and making for its goal.

61. Enter into the ruling principle of your neighbour's mind, and suffer him to enter into yours.

Book Nine

1. Injustice is a sin. Nature has constituted rational beings for their own mutual benefit, each to help his fellows according to their worth, and in no wise to do them hurt; and to contravene her will is plainly to sin against this eldest of all the deities. Untruthfulness, too, is a sin, and against the same goddess. For Nature is the nature of Existence itself; and existence connotes the kinship of all created beings. Truth is but another name for this Nature, the original creator of all true things. So, where a wilful lie is a sin because the deception is an act of injustice, an involuntary lie is also a sin because it is a discordant note in Nature's harmony, and creates mutinous disorder in an orderly universe. For mutinous indeed it is, when a man lets himself be carried, even involuntarily, into a position contrary to truth; seeing that he has so neglected the faculties Nature gave him that he is no longer able to distinguish the false from the true.

Again, it is a sin to pursue pleasure as a good and to avoid pain as an evil. It is bound to result in complaints that Nature is unfair in her rewarding of vice and virtue; since it is the bad who are so often in enjoyment of pleasures and the means to obtain them, while pains and events that occasion pains descend upon the heads of the good. Besides, if a man is afraid of pain, he is afraid of something happening which will be part of the appointed order of things, and this is itself a sin; if he is bent on the pursuit of pleasure, he will not stop at acts of injustice, which again is manifestly sinful. No; when Nature herself makes no distinction — and if she did, she would not have brought pains and pleasures into existence side by side — it behoves those who would follow in her footsteps to be like-minded and exhibit the same indifference. He therefore who does not view with equal unconcern pain or pleasure, death or life, fame or dishonour — all of them employed by Nature without any partiality — clearly commits a sin. And in saying that nature employs them without partiality, I mean that every successive generation of created things equally passes through the same experiences in turn; for this is the outcome of the original impulse which in the beginning moved Providence — by taking certain germs of future existences, and endowing them with productive powers of self-realization, of mutation, and of succession — to progress from the inception of the universe to its present orderly system.

2. A man of finer feelings would have taken leave of the world before ever sampling its falsehood, double-dealing, luxury, and pride; but now that all these have been tasted to satiety, the next best course would be to end your life forthwith. Or are you really resolved to go on dwelling in the midst of iniquity, and has experience not yet persuaded you to flee from the pestilence? For infection of the mind is a far more dangerous pestilence than any unwholesomeness or disorder in the atmosphere around us. Insofar as we are animals, the one attacks our lives; but as men, the other attacks our manhood.

3. Despise not death; smile, rather, at its coming; it is among the things that Nature wills. Like youth and age, like growth and maturity, like the advent of teeth, beard, and grey hairs, like begetting, pregnancy, and childbirth, like every other natural process that life's seasons bring us, so is our dissolution. Never, then, will a thinking man view death lightly, impatiently, or scornfully; he will wait for it as but one more of Nature's processes. Even as you await the baby's emergence from the womb of your wife, so await the hour when the little soul shall glide forth from its sheath.

But if your heart would have comfort of a simpler sort, then there is no better solace in the face of death than to think on the nature of the surroundings you are leaving, and the characters you will no longer have to mix with. Not that you must find these offensive; rather, your duty is to care for them and bear with them mildly; yet never forget that you are parting from men of far other principles than your own. One thing, if any, might have held you back and bound you to life; the chance of fellowship with kindred minds. But when you contemplate the weariness of an existence in company so discordant, you cry, 'Come quickly, Death, lest I too become forgetful of myself.'

4. The sinner sins against himself; the wrongdoer wrongs himself, becoming the worse by his own action.

5. A man does not sin by commission only, but often by omission.

6. Enough if your present opinion be grounded in conviction, your present action grounded in unselfishness, and your present disposition contented with whatever befalls you from without.

7. Erase fancy; curb impulse; quench desire; let sovereign reason have the mastery.

8. A single life-principle is divided amongst all irrational creatures, and a single mind-principle distributed among the rational; just as this one earth gives form to all things earthy, and just as all of us who have sight and breath see by the self-same light and breathe of the self-same air.

9. All things that share the same element tend to seek their own kind. Things earthy gravitate towards earth, things aqueous flow towards one another, things aerial likewise — whence the need for the barriers which keep them forcibly apart. The tendency of flames is to mount skyward, because of the elemental fire; even here below, they are so eager for the company of their own kind that any sort of material, if it be reasonably dry, will ignite with ease, since there is only a minority of its ingredients which is resistant to fire. In the same way, therefore, all portions of the universal Mind are drawn towards one another. More strongly, indeed; since, being higher in the scale of creation, their eagerness to blend and combine with their affinities is proportionately keener. This instinct for reunion shows itself in its first stage among the creatures without reason, when we see bees swarming, cattle herding, birds nesting in colonies, and couples mating; because in them soul has already emerged, and in such relatively higher forms of life as theirs the desire for union is found at a level of intensity which is not present in stones or sticks. When we come to beings with reason, there are political associations, comradeships, family life, public meetings, and in times of war treaties and armistices; and among the still higher orders, a measure of unity even exists between bodies far separated from one another — as for example with the stars. Thus ascent in the ranks of creation can induce fellow-feeling even where there is no proximity.

Yet now see what happens. It is we — we, intelligent beings — who alone have forgotten this mutual zeal for unity; among us alone the currents are not seen to converge. Nevertheless, though man may flee as he will, he is still caught and held fast; Nature is too strong for him. Observe with care, and you will see: you will sooner find a fragment of earth unrelated to the rest of earth than a man who is utterly without some link with his fellows.

10. Everything bears fruit; man, God, the whole universe, each in its proper season. No matter that the phrase is restricted in common use to vines and such like. Reason, too, yields fruit, both for itself and for the world; since from it comes a harvest of other good things, themselves all bearing the stamp of reason.

11. Teach them better, if you can; if not, remember that kindliness has been given you for moments like these. The gods themselves show kindness to such men; and at times, so indulgent are they, will even aid them in their endeavours to secure health, wealth, or reputation. This you too could do; who is there to hinder you?

12. Work yourself hard, but not as if you were being made a victim, and not with any desire for sympathy or admiration. Desire one thing alone: that your actions or inactions alike should be worthy of a reasoning citizen.

13. Today I have got myself out of all my perplexities; or rather, I have got the perplexities out of myself — for they were not without, but within; they lay in my own outlook.

14. Everything is banal in experience, fleeting in duration, sordid in content; in all respects the same today as generations now dead and buried have found it to be.

15. Facts stand wholly outside our gates; they are what they are, and no more; they know nothing about themselves, and they pass no judgement upon themselves. What is it, then, that pronounces the judgement? Our own guide and ruler, Reason.

16. A rational and social being is not affected in himself for either better or worse by his feelings, but by his will; just as his outward behaviour, good or bad, is the product of will, not of feelings.

17. For the thrown stone there is no more evil in falling than there is good in rising.

18. Penetrate into their inmost minds, and you will see what manner of critics you are afraid of, and how capable they are of criticizing themselves.

19. All things are in process of change. You yourself are ceaselessly undergoing transformation, and the decay of some of your parts, and so is the whole universe.

20. Leave another's wrongdoing where it lies.

21. In the interruption of an activity, or the discontinuance and, as it were, death of an impulse, or an opinion, there is no evil. Look back at the phases of your own growth: childhood, boyhood, youth, age: each change itself a kind of death. Was this so frightening? Or take the lives you lived under your grandfather and then under your mother and then your father; trace the numerous differences and changes and discontinuances there were in those days, and ask yourself, 'Were they so frightening?' No more so, then, is the cessation, the interruption, the change from life itself.

22. Your own mind, the Mind of the universe, your neighbour's mind — be prompt to explore them all. Your own, so that you may shape it to justice; the universe's, that you may recollect what it is you are a part of; your neighbour's, that you may understand whether it is informed by ignorance or knowledge, and also may recognize that it is kin to your own.

23. As a unit yourself, you help to complete the social whole; and similarly, therefore, your every action should help to complete the social life. Any action which is not related either directly or remotely to this social end disjoints that life, and destroys its unity. It is as much the act of a schismatic as when some citizen in a community does his utmost to dissociate himself from the general accord.

24. Childish squabbles, childish games, 'petty breaths supporting corpses' — why, the ghosts in Homer have more evident reality!

25. First get at the nature and quality of the original cause, separate it from the material to which it has given shape, and study it; then determine the possible duration of its effects.

26. The woes you have had to bear are numberless because you were not content to let Reason, your guide and master, do its natural work. Come now, no more of this!

27. When those about you are venting their censure or malice upon you, or raising any other sort of injurious clamour, approach and penetrate into their souls, and see what manner of men they are. You will find little enough reason for all your painstaking efforts to win their good opinion. All the same, it still remains your duty to think kindly of them; for Nature has made them to be your friends, and even the gods themselves lend them every sort of help, by dreams and by oracles, to gain the ends on which their hearts are set.

28. Upwards and downwards,[〔1〕] from age to age, the cycles of the universe follow their unchanging round. It may be that the World-Mind wills each separate happening in succession; and if so, then accept the consequences. Or, it may be, there was but one primal act of will, of which all else is the sequel; every event being thus the germ of another. To put it another way, things are either isolated units, or they form one inseparable whole. If that whole be God, then all is well; but if aimless chance, at least you need not be aimless also.

Soon earth will cover us all. Then in time earth, too, will change; later, what issues from this change will itself in turn incessantly change, and so again will all that then takes its place, even unto the world's end. To let the mind dwell on these swiftly rolling billows of change and transformation is to know a contempt for all things mortal.

29. The primal Cause is like a river in flood; it bears everything along. How ignoble are the little men who play at politics and persuade themselves that they are acting in the true spirit of philosophy. Babes, incapable even of wiping their noses! What then, you who are a man? Why, do what nature is asking of you at this moment. Set about it as the opportunity offers, and no glancing around to see if you are observed. But do not expect Plato's ideal commonwealth; be satisfied if even a trifling endeavour comes off well, and count the result no mean success. For who can hope to alter men's convictions; and without change of conviction what can there be but grudging subjection and feigned assent? Oh yes; now go on and talk to me of Alexander, and Philip, and Demetrius of Phaleron. If those men did in truth understand the will of Nature and school themselves to follow it, that is their own affair. But if it was nothing more than a stage-role they were playing, no court has condemned me to imitate their example. Philosophy is a modest profession, all simplicity and plain dealing. Never try to seduce me into solemn pretentiousness.

30. Look down from above on the numberless herds of mankind, with their mysterious ceremonies, their divers voyagings in storm and calm, and all the chequered pattern of their comings and gatherings and goings. Go on to consider the life of bygone generations; and then the life of all those who are yet to come; and even at the present day, the life of the hordes of far-off savages. In short, reflect what multitudes there are who are ignorant of your very name; how many more will have speedily forgotten it; how many, perhaps praising you now, who will soon enough be abusing you; and that therefore remembrance, glory, and all else together are things of no worth.

31. When beset from without by circumstance, be unperturbed; when prompted from within to action, be just and fair: in fine, let both will and deed issue in behaviour that is social and fulfils the law of your being.

32. Many of the anxieties that harass you are superfluous: being but creatures of your own fancy, you can rid yourself of them and expand into an ampler region, letting your thought sweep over the entire universe, contemplating the illimitable tracts of eternity, marking the swiftness of change in each created thing, and contrasting the brief span between birth and dissolution with the endless aeons that precede the one and the infinity that follows the other.

33. A little while, and all that is before your eyes now will have perished. Those who witness its passing will go the same road themselves before long; and then what will there be to choose between the oldest grandfather and the baby that died in its cradle?

34. Observe the instincts that guide these men; the ends they struggle for; the grounds on which they like and value things. In short, picture their souls laid bare. Yet they imagine their praises or censures have weight to help or hurt. What presumption!

35. Loss is nothing else but change, and change is Nature's delight. Ever since the world began, things have been ordered by her decree in the selfsame fashion as they are at this day, and as other similar things will be ordered to the end of time. How, then, can you say that it is all amiss, and ever will be so; that no power among all the gods in heaven can avail to mend it; and that the world lies condemned to a thraldom of ills without end?

36. The substance of us all is doomed to decay; the moisture and the clay, the bones, and the fetor. Our precious marble is but a callosity of the earth, our gold and silver her sediment; our raiment shreds of hair, our purple a fish's gore; and thus with all things else. So too is the very breath of our lives — ever passing as it does from this one to that.

37. Enough of this miserable way of life, these everlasting grumbles, these monkey antics. Why must you agitate yourself so? Nothing unprecedented is happening; so what is it that disturbs you? The form of it? Take a good look at it. The matter of it? Look well at that, too. Beyond form and matter, there is nothing more. Even at this late hour, set yourself to become a simpler and better man in the sight of the gods. For the mastering of that lesson, three years are as good as a hundred.

38. If he sinned, the harm is his own. Yet perhaps, after all, he did not.

39. Either things must have their origin in one single intelligent source, and all fall into place to compose, as it were, one single body — in which case no part ought to complain of what happens for the good of the whole — or else the world is nothing but atoms and their confused minglings and dispersions. So why be so harassed? Say to the Reason at your helm, 'Come, are you dead and in decay? Is this some part you are playing? Have you sunk to the level of a beast of the field, grazing and herding with the rest?'

40. The gods either have power or they have not. If they have not, why pray to them? If they have, then instead of praying to be granted or spared such-and-such a thing, why not rather pray to be delivered from dreading it, or lusting for it, or grieving over it? Clearly, if they can help a man at all, they can help him in this way. You will say, perhaps, 'But all that is something they have put in my own power.' Then surely it were better to use your power and be a free man, than to hanker like a slave and a beggar for something that is not in your power. Besides, who told you the gods never lend their aid even towards things that do lie in our own power? Begin praying in this way, and you will see. Where another man prays 'Grant that I may possess this woman,' let your own prayer be, 'Grant that I may not lust to possess her.' Where he prays, 'Grant me to be rid of such-and-such a one,' you pray, 'Take from me my desire to be rid of him.' Where he begs, 'Spare me the loss of my precious child,' beg rather to be delivered from the terror of losing him. In short, give your petitions a turn in this direction, and see what comes.

41. 'When I was sick,' says Epicurus, 'I never used to talk about my bodily ailments. I did not,' he says, 'discuss any topics of that kind with my visitors. I went on dealing with the principles of natural philosophy; and the point I particularly dwelt on was how the mind, while having its part in all these commotions of the flesh, can still remain unruffled and pursue its own proper good. Nor,' he adds, 'did I give the doctors a chance to brag of their own triumphs; my life merely went on its normal way, smoothly and happily.' In sickness, then, if you are sick, or in trouble of any other kind, be like Epicurus. Never let go your hold on philosophy for anything that may befall, and never take part in the nonsense that is talked by the ignorant and uninstructed (this is a maxim on which all schools agree). Concentrate wholly on the task before you, and on the instrument you possess for its accomplishment.

42. When you are outraged by somebody's impudence, ask yourself at once, 'Can the world exist without impudent people?' It cannot; so do not ask for impossibilities. That man is simply one of the impudent whose existence is necessary to the world. Keep the same thought present, whenever you come across roguery, double-dealing or any other form of obliquity. You have only to remind yourself that the type is indispensable, and at once you will feel kindlier towards the individual. It is also helpful if you promptly recall what special quality Nature has given us to counter such particular faults. For there are antidotes with which she has provided us: gentleness to meet brutality, for example, and other correctives for other ills. Generally speaking, too, you have the opportunity of showing the culprit his blunder — for everyone who does wrong is failing of his proper objective, and is thereby a blunderer. Besides, what harm have you suffered? Nothing has been done by any of these victims of your irritation that could hurtfully affect your own mind; and it is in the mind alone that anything evil or damaging to the self can have reality. What is there wrong or surprising, after all, in a boor behaving boorishly? See then if it is not rather yourself you ought to blame, for not foreseeing that he would offend in this way. You, in virtue of your reason, had every means for thinking it probable that he would do so; you forgot this, and now his offence takes you by surprise. When you are indignant with anyone for his perfidy or ingratitude, turn your thoughts first and foremost upon yourself. For the error is clearly your own, if you have put any faith in the good faith of a man of that stamp, or, when you have done him a kindness, if it was not done unreservedly and in the belief that the action would be its own full reward. Once you have done a man a service, what more would you have? Is it not enough to have obeyed the laws of your own nature, without expecting to be paid for it? That is like the eye demanding a reward for seeing, or the feet for walking. It is for that very purpose that they exist; and they have their due in doing what they were created to do. Similarly, man is born for deeds of kindness; and when he has done a kindly action, or otherwise served the common welfare, he has done what he was made for, and has received his quittance.

注　释

〔1〕　Upwards and downwards; i.e. changing successively from fire to air, air to water, water to earth, and then back again in the reverse order.

Book Ten

1. O soul of mine, will you never be good and sincere, all one, all open, visible to the beholder more clearly than even your encompassing body of flesh? Will you never taste the sweetness of a loving and affectionate heart? Will you never be filled full and unwanting; craving nothing, yearning for no creature or thing to minister to your pleasures, no prolongation of days to enjoy them, no place or country or pleasant clime or sweet human company? When will you be content with your present state, happy in all about you, persuaded that all things are yours, that all comes from the gods, and that all is and shall be well with you, so long as it is their good pleasure and ordained by them for the safety and welfare of that perfect living Whole — so good, so just, so beautiful — which gives life to all things, upholding and enfolding them, and at their dissolution gathering them into Itself so that yet others of their kind may spring forth? Will you never be fit for such fellowship with gods and men as to have no syllable of complaint against them, and no syllable of reproach from them?

2. Pay heed to what your particular nature requires of you, like one who is wholly under great Nature's governance. Do it and accept it, provided always that it promise no harm to your physical nature. Yet pay heed also to the requirements of that physical nature, and give assent to them all, unless they in turn promise harm to the rational nature (and by the rational is directly implied the social as well). Observe these rules, without wasting pains on other things.

3. Whatever befalls, Nature has either prepared you to face it or she has not. If something untoward happens which is within your powers of endurance, do not resent it, but bear it as she has enabled you to do. Should it exceed those powers, still do not give way to resentment; for its victory over you will put an end to its own existence. Remember, however, that in fact Nature has given you the ability to bear anything which your own judgement succeeds in declaring bearable and endurable by regarding it as a point of self-interest and duty to do so.

4. If a man makes a slip, admonish him gently and show him his mistake. If you fail to convince him, blame yourself, or else blame nobody.

5. Whatever may happen to you was prepared for you in advance from the beginning of time. In the woven tapestry of causation, the thread of your being had been intertwined from all time with that particular incident.

6. No matter whether the universe is a confusion of atoms or a natural growth, let my first conviction be that I am part of a Whole which is under Nature's governance; and my second, that a bond of kinship exists between myself and all other similar parts. If I bear these two thoughts in mind, then in the first place, being a part, I shall not feel aggrieved by any dispensation assigned to me from the Whole; since nothing which is beneficial for any whole can ever be harmful to a part, and in this case there is nothing contained in this Whole which is not beneficial to itself. (The same, indeed, could be said of every natural organism; but the nature of the universe has the further distinction that there is no cause outside itself which could ever compel it to produce anything harmful to itself.) In the remembrance, then, that I am a part of such a Whole, I shall cheerfully accept whatever may be my lot. In the second place, inasmuch as there is this bond of kinship between myself and my fellow-parts, I shall do nothing that might injure their common welfare, but keep those kindred parts always purposefully in view, directing every impulse towards their good and away from anything that runs counter to it. Thus doing, I cannot but find the current of my life flowing smoothly; as smoothly as we may imagine that of some public man whose actions are consistently serviceable to his fellow-townsfolk, and who is ready to welcome whatever task his city may assign him.

7. All parts of the Whole — by which I mean everything naturally comprehended in the universe — must in time decay; or to speak accurately, must suffer a change of form. If by its nature this change, besides being inevitable, were to be a positive evil to them, the smooth working of the Whole could never go on; for its parts are always heading towards some change of form or other, and are all constitutionally liable to decay in their respective ways. Did Nature, then, deliberately mean to inflict injury on things which are parts of herself, making them not simply liable to evil but inescapably doomed to it; or can it be that such things happen without her knowledge? Neither supposition merits any credence. Even supposing we leave Nature herself out of account altogether, and explain all this in terms of the normal order of creation, it is still absurd to say that this mutability of the parts of the Whole is normal if at the same time we are to feel as astonished or resentful at it as though it were some unnatural occurrence; the more so, since all that the parts are doing is merely to dissolve back into the constituents of their original composition. For after all, if dissolution is not simply a mere dispersion of the elements of which I am compounded, it must be a change of the grosser particles into earth-form, and the spiritual into air-form, so that they can all be re-absorbed into the universal Reason (no matter whether this is to be periodically consumed in flames, or to keep on perpetually renewing itself through eternal cycles of change). Observe, however, that these particles, gross and spiritual, must not be imagined to be those which we received at birth; seeing that our entire present structure has derived its increment from meats eaten and air breathed no longer ago than yesterday or the day before. What will undergo these changes, therefore, is not something our mother bore originally, but something we have received since. (Even if we admit that birth does, in fact, implicate us in great measure with these intrinsically mutable particles, I do not think it affects what I have said.)

8. If you claim for yourself such epithets as good, modest, truthful, clear-minded, right-minded, high-minded, be careful not to belie them; and if you should happen to forfeit them, lose no time in recovering them again. But remember that 'clear-mindedness' ought to suggest to you a discriminating consideration of each separate detail and a watchful attention to it; 'right-mindedness' a willing acceptance of all that Nature allots you; and 'high-mindedness' an elevation of the intellect above the workings of the flesh, be they smooth or harsh, and above vainglory, death or any other such distractions. Live up to these designations — though without craving to have them applied to you by others — and you will be a different man and enter upon a different life. To go on in your present state, continuing to be torn and soiled by an existence like this, is the way of a fool and a faint-heart; it smacks of the swordsman who has been mangled by beasts in the arena and covered with blood and bruises, and yet still pleads to be kept till the morrow, when he will only be flung again, wounds and all, to the same teeth and claws. So step on board this little raft of attributes, and if you can contrive it, stay there as though transported to the Isles of the Blest. But if you feel yourself drifting and unable to hold your course, pluck up heart and make for some quiet haven where you will be able to hold your own; or even bid farewell to life altogether, not in a passion but simply, freely, and unassumingly, with at least this one success in life to your credit, a seemly departure from it. In order to keep those attributes ever in mind, it will help greatly not to forget the gods; to remember that what they desire is not to be flattered but that everything which has reason should become like themselves; and also to recollect that a fig-tree is that which does a fig-tree's work, a dog that which does a dog's, a bee a bee's — and a man a man's.

9. Day by day the buffoonery, quarrelling, timidity, slothfulness, and servility that surround you will conspire to efface from your mind those hallowed maxims it apprehends so unphilosophically and dismisses so carelessly. What duty requires of you is to observe each single thing and perform each action in such a manner that, while the practical demands of a situation are fully met, the powers of thought are at the same time fully exercised; and also to maintain (in reserve, but never lost to sight) the self-confidence of one who has mastered every relevant detail. Are you never going to attain to the happiness of a real integrity and dignity? Of an understanding which comprehends the inmost being of each thing, its place in the world-order, the term of its natural existence, the structure of its composition, and to whom it belongs or who has the power of bestowing or withdrawing it?

10. A spider is proud of catching a fly; so is one man of trapping a hare, or another of netting a sprat, or a third of capturing boars or bears or Sarmatians. If you go into the question of principles, are these anything but robbers one and all?

11. Make a habit of regularly observing the universal process of change; be assiduous in your attention to it, and school yourself thoroughly in this branch of study; there is nothing more elevating to the mind. For when a man realizes that at any moment he may have to leave everything behind him and depart from the company of his fellows, he casts off the body and thenceforward dedicates himself wholly to the service of justice in his personal actions and compliance with Nature in all else. No thought is wasted on what others may say or think of him or practise against him; two things alone suffice him, justice in his daily doings and contentment with all fate's apportionings. Every care, every distraction is laid aside; his only ambition is to walk in the straight paths of law, and by so doing to become a follower of God.

12. What need for guesswork when the way of duty lies there before your eyes? If the road be clear to see, go forward with a good will and no turning back; if not, wait and take the best advice you can. Should further obstacles arise, advance discreetly to the limit of your resources, always following where justice seems to point the way. To achieve justice is the summit of success, since it is herein that failure most often occurs.

13. Begin the day by asking yourself, Can the just and right conduct of another make any difference in myself? It cannot. Men who are arrogantly ready with their praise or censure, remember, are the same in their private lives, in bed and at board; recall the things they do, the things they avoid or run after, and the thieveries and depredations they commit — not indeed with hands and feet, but with that most precious of all their possessions, which, if a man but will it so, is the source of faith, modesty, truth, law, and the good estate of the divinity within him.

14. To Nature, whence all things come and whither all return, the cry of the humble and well-instructed heart is, 'Give as thou wilt, take back as thou wilt;' yet uttered with no heroics, but in pure obedience and goodwill.

15. Now your remaining years are few. Live them, then, as though on a mountain-top. Whether a man's lot be cast in this place or in that matters nothing, provided that in all places he views the world as a city and himself its citizen. Give men the chance to see and know a true man, living by Nature's law. If they cannot brook the sight, let them do away with him. Better so, than to live as they live.

16. Waste no more time arguing what a good man should be. Be one.

17. Let your mind constantly dwell on all Time and all Being, and thus learn that each separate thing is but as a grain of sand in comparison with Being, and as a single screw's-turn in comparison with Time.

18. Realize the nature of all things material, observing how each of them is even now undergoing dissolution and change, and is already in process of decay, or dispersion, or whatever other natural fate may be in store for it.

19. Eating, sleeping, copulating, excreting, and the like; what a crew they are! How pompous in their arrogance, how overbearing and tyrannical, how superciliously censorious of others! A moment ago, how many feet they were licking — and for such ends! — a moment more, and they will be doing the same again.

20. For every man and every thing, that which Nature brings makes for their own good; moreover, makes for their good at the precise moment when it is brought.

21. 'Earth is in love with the showers from above,

And the all-holy Heaven itself is in love'

— that is, the universe is truly in love with its task of fashioning whatever is next to be; and to the universe, therefore, my response must be, 'As thou lovest, so I too love.' (Is not the same notion implied in the common saying that such-and-such a thing 'loves to happen'?)

22. Either you go on living here, to which custom has sufficiently seasoned you by now; or you remove elsewhere, which you do of your own free election; or you die, which means that your service is at an end. Other choice there can be none; so put a good face on it.

23. Let it be clear to you that the peace of green fields can always be yours, in this, that, or any other spot; and that nothing is any different here from what it would be either up in the hills, or down by the sea, or wherever else you will. You will find the same thought in Plato, where he speaks of living within the city walls 'as though milking his flocks in a mountain sheepfold'.

24. What is my master-reason to me? What am I making of it at this moment? To what use am I putting it? Is it showing itself devoid of sense? Is it becoming divorced and dissevered from the ties of fellowship? Has it grown so involved and so identified with the flesh as to reflect that flesh's veerings and vacillations?

25. A servant who breaks loose from his master is a runaway. For us, our master is law; and consequently any law-breaker must be a runaway. But grief, anger, or fear are all of them rejections of something which, in the past or the present or the future, has been decreed by the power that directs the universe — in other words, by Law, which allots to every creature its due.[〔1〕] To give way to fear or grief or anger, therefore, is to be a runaway.

26. A man drops seed into the womb and passes on; thereafter another cause takes it up, sets to work, and brings to perfection a baby — what a transformation! The same man puts food down his throat, and once more some other cause takes it over and converts it into sensation and motion and, in short, into life, vigour, and other products both many and various. Consider these processes, which are wrought out in such mysterious ways; and discern the power at work there, in the same way as we discern the forces which attract objects earthwards or upwards — not with the eye, that is, and yet no less clearly.

27. Reflect often how all the life of today is a repetition of the past; and observe that it also presages what is to come. Review the many complete dramas and their settings, all so similar, which you have known in your own experience, or from bygone history: the whole court-circle of Hadrian, for example, or the court of Antoninus, or the courts of Philip, Alexander, and Croesus. The performance is always the same; it is only the actors who change.

28. When you see a man showing annoyance or resentment at anything, think of a pig kicking and squealing under the sacrificial knife. Another who takes to his couch in solitude, silently lamenting over our thraldom, is in no better case. Reasonable beings alone are granted the power of a willing conformity with circumstance; the bare conformity by itself stern necessity exacts from every created thing.

29. Whatever you take in hand, pause at every step to ask yourself, 'Is it the thought of forfeiting this that makes me dread death?'

30. When another's fault offends you, turn to yourself and consider what similar shortcomings are found in you. Do you, too, find your good in riches, pleasure, reputation, or such like? Think of this, and your anger will soon be forgotten in the reflection that he is only acting under pressure; what else could he do? Alternatively, if you are able, contrive his release from that pressure.

31. Let the sight of Satyron call up a vision of the dead Socraticus, or Eutyches, or Hymen; the sight of Euphrates bring to mind Eutychion or Silvanus; a look at Alciphron suggest the memory of Tropaeophorus; a glance at Severus, that of Crito or Xenophon; when you see yourself, think of the emperors who preceded you. Thus, with every man, imagine his counterpart; and then go on to the reflection, 'Where are they all now?' Nowhere — or anywhere. In this way, you will grow accustomed to looking on all that is mortal as vapour and nothingness; and the more so, if you will also remember that things once changed are for ever past recall. Then why struggle and strain, instead of being content to live out your little span in seemly fashion? Think what materials and possibilities for good you are rejecting; since what are all your tribulations but exercises for the training of your reason, once it has learnt to see the truths of life in a proper philosophic light? Be patient, then, until you have made them familiar and natural to yourself, in the same way as a strong stomach can assimilate every kind of diet, or a bright fire turn anything that is cast upon it into heat and flame.

32. Let no one have the right to say truthfully of you that you are without integrity or goodness; should any think such thoughts, see that they are without foundation. This all depends upon yourself, for who else can hinder you from attaining goodness and integrity? If you cannot live so, you need only resolve to live no longer; for in that case not even reason itself could require your continuance.

33. What is the very best that can be said or done with the materials at your disposal? Be it what it may, you have the power to say it or do it; let there be no pretence that you are not a free agent. These repinings of yours will be endless until such time as the doing of a man's natural duty with whatever materials come to hand means as much to you as his pleasures mean to the voluptuary. (Indeed, every exercise of our proper natural instincts ought to be esteemed a form of pleasure; and the opportunities for this are everywhere present.) A roller, to be sure, has not always the privilege of moving at will, nor has water, nor fire, nor anything else that is under the governance of its own nature or of a soul without reason; for there are many factors which intervene to prevent it. But a mind and a reason can make their way through any obstacles, as their nature enables them and their will prompts them to do. Figure to yourself how reason finds a way past every barrier as effortlessly as fire mounts upward, or a stone falls, or a roller descends a slope; and be content to ask no more. Interferences, in any case, must either affect the body alone — which is but an inanimate thing — or else be impotent to crush or injure us unless assisted by our own preconceptions and the surrender of reason itself. If it were otherwise, their effect on the subject would be harmful; and though we know that throughout the rest of creation the occurrence of any mishap involves some worsening of its victim, yet in the case of a man we may even say that he becomes better and more praiseworthy by the right uses which he makes of adversity. In short, never forget that nothing can injure the true citizen if it does not injure the city itself, and nothing can injure the city unless it injures law. What we call mischances do no injury to law, and therefore cannot harm either city or citizen.

34. When true principles have once been etched into the mind, even the briefest commonplace will suffice to recall the futility of regrets or fears; such as, for example,

'What are the children of men, but as leaves that drop at the wind's breath?'

Just such leaves were those beloved children of yours; leaves, too, are the multitudes, those would-be-convincing voices that scream their plaudits, hurl their curses, or sneer and scoff in secret; leaves, again, are all they into whose hands your fame shall fall hereafter. One and all, they 'flower in the season of springtime', the gales lay them low, and anon the forest puts forth new verdure in their room. Impermanence is the badge of each and every one; and yet you chase after them, or flee from them, as though they were to endure for all eternity. A short time, and your eyes will close; and for the man who bears you to your grave, too, the tears will soon enough be falling.

35. The business of a healthy eye is to see everything that is visible, not to demand no colour but green, for that merely marks a disordered vision. Likewise hearing and scent, if healthy, should be alert for all kinds of sounds and odours, and a healthy stomach for all manner of meats, like a mill which accepts whatever grist it was fashioned to grind. In the same way, then, a healthy mind ought to be prepared for anything that may befall. A mind crying 'O that my children may be spared,' or 'O that the world might ring with praises of my every act,' is an eye craving for greenery, or a tooth craving for softness.

36. No man is so fortunate but that some who stand beside his death-bed will be hailing the coming loss with delight. He was virtuous, let us say, and wise; even so, will there not be one at the end who murmurs under his breath, 'At last we can breathe freely again, without our master! To be sure, he was never harsh with any of us; but I always felt that he had a silent contempt for us'? Such is the fate of the virtuous; as for the rest of us, what a host of other good reasons there are to make not a few of our friends glad to be rid of us! Think of this when you come to die; it will ease your passing to reflect, 'I am leaving a world in which the very companions I have so toiled for, prayed for and thought for, themselves wish me gone, and hope to win some relief thereby; then how can any man cling to a lengthening of his days therein?' Yet do not on that account leave with any diminished kindness for them; maintain your own accustomed friendliness, good-will, and charity; and do not feel the departure to be a wrench, but let your leave-taking be like those painless deaths in which the soul glides easily forth from the body. Before, Nature had joined you to these men and made you one with them; now she looses the tie. I am loosed, then, as from my own kinsfolk; yet all unresisting, and all unforced; it is simply one more of Nature's ways.

37. At every action, no matter by whom performed, make it a practice to ask yourself, 'What is his object in doing this?' But begin with yourself; put this question to yourself first of all.

38. Remember, it is the secret force hidden deep within us that manipulates our strings; there lies the voice of persuasion, there the very life, there, we might even say, is the man himself. Never confuse it in your imagination with its surrounding case of flesh, or the organs adhering thereto, which save that they grow upon the body, are as much mere instruments as the carpenter's axe. Without the agency that prompts or restrains their motions, the parts themselves are of no more service than her shuttle to the weaver, his pen to the writer, or his whip to the wagoner.

注　释

〔1〕　The Greek word for law (nomos) was supposed to be derived from a verb meaning to allot (nemein).

Book Eleven

1. The properties of a rational soul are these. She can contemplate herself, analyse herself, make of herself what she will, herself enjoy the fruit she bears (whereas the fruit produced by trees, like its counterpart produced by animals, is enjoyed by others), and always have her work perfectly complete at whatever moment our life reaches its appointed limit. For, unlike dances or plays or such like, where if they are suddenly cut short the performance as a whole is left imperfect, the soul, no matter at what stage arrested, will have her task complete to her own satisfaction, and be able to say, 'I am in the fullest possession of mine own.' Moreover, she can encompass the whole universe at will, both its own structure and the void surrounding it, and can reach out into eternity, embracing and comprehending the great cyclic renewals of creation, and thereby perceiving that future generations will have nothing new to witness, even as our forefathers beheld nothing more than we of today, but that if a man comes to his fortieth year, and has any understanding at all, he has virtually seen — thanks to their similarity — all possible happenings, both past and to come. Finally, the qualities of the rational soul include love of neighbours, truthfulness, modesty, and a reverence for herself before all else; and since this last is one of the qualities of law also, it follows that the principle of rationality is one and the same as the principle of justice.

2. You can soon become indifferent to the seductions of song or dance or athletic displays if you resolve the melody into its several notes, and ask yourself of each one in turn, 'Is it this that I cannot resist?' You will flinch from admitting it. Do the same to each movement or attitude of the dancers, and similarly with the athletes. In short, save in the case of virtue and its implications, always remember to go straight for the parts themselves, and by dissecting these achieve your disenchantment. And now, transfer this method to life as a whole.

3. Happy the soul which, at whatever moment the call comes for release from the body, is equally ready to face extinction, dispersion, or survival. Such preparedness, however, must be the outcome of its own decision; a decision not prompted by mere contumacy, as with the Christians,[〔1〕] but formed with deliberation and gravity and, if it is to be convincing to others, with an absence of all heroics.

4. Have I done an unselfish thing? Well then, I have my reward. Keep this thought ever present, and persevere.

5. What is your trade? Goodness. But how are you to make a success of it unless you have a philosopher's insight into the nature of the universe, and into the particular constitution of man?

6. Drama in its earliest phase took the form of Tragedy, which by its presentation of the vicissitudes of life reminds us how naturally things of that kind can happen, and that, since they move us to pleasure on the stage, we have no right to be aggrieved by their occurrence on the larger stage of reality. For in these plays we are shown that, though actions must have their inevitable consequences, men can still endure them, despite the anguished 'Ah, Cithaeron!'[〔2〕] that breaks from their lips. Moreover, there are helpful sayings to be found here and there in the tragic writers; notably,

If Heav'n care nought for me and my two boys,

There must be some good reason even for this,

or again,

Vex not thy spirit at the course of things,

or,

Like ears of corn the lives of men are reaped, and many another of the kind.

After tragedy came the Old Comedy,[〔3〕] with a tongue unsparing as a schoolmaster's, but administering a wholesale rebuke to pride by its very outspokenness (which to some extent was adopted by Diogenes for the same purpose). But later, look at the aims of the Middle Comedy:[〔4〕] and eventually of the New Comedy,[〔5〕] which was so soon to decline into the mere artificiality of the Mime.[〔6〕] To be sure, even these later writers have a few good things to say, as we all know; but what does the whole scope and intention of all their output of poetry and drama amount to?

7. Manifestly, no condition of life could be so well adapted for the practice of philosophy as this in which chance finds you today!

8. A branch severed from an adjoining branch necessarily becomes severed from the whole tree. A man, likewise, who has been divided from any of his fellows has thereby fallen away from the whole community. But whereas the branch is lopped by some other hand, the man, by his feelings of hatred or aversion, brings about his own estrangement from his neighbour, and does not see that at the same time he has cut himself off from the whole framework of society. Nevertheless it is in our power, by grace of Zeus the author of all fellowship, to grow back and become one with our neighbour again, so playing our part once more in the integration of the whole. Yet if such acts of secession are repeated frequently, they make it difficult for the recusant to achieve this reunion and restitution. A branch which has been partner of the tree's growth since the beginning, and has never ceased to share its life, is a different thing from one that has been grafted in again after a severance. As the gardeners say, it is of the same tree, but not of the same mind.

9. Though men may hinder you from following the paths of reason, they can never succeed in deflecting you from sound action; but make sure that they are equally unsuccessful in destroying your charitable feelings towards them. You must defend both positions alike: your firmness in decision and action, and at the same time your gentleness to those who try to obstruct or otherwise molest you. It would be as great a weakness to give way to your exasperation with them as it would be to abandon your course of action and be browbeaten into surrender. In either event the post of duty is deserted; in the one case through lack of courage, and in the other through alienation from men who are your natural brothers and friends.

10. Any form of nature always outrivals art, since every art is no more than an imitation of the natural. This being so, that supreme Nature which is more perfect and all-inclusive than any other cannot fail to be preeminent in the artist's craft. Furthermore, it is only with an eye on something higher that the arts produce their inferior works; and this is what Nature herself also does. Here, then, we find the origins of justice; for all the other virtues depend on this. We can never achieve true justice while we set our hearts on things of lesser value, and are content to remain credulous, headstrong, and inconstant.

11. It may be that the things you fret and fume to pursue or avoid do not come to you, but rather you go to them. Let your judgements of them, then, remain in suppression; they for their part will make no move, and so you will not be seen pursuing or avoiding them.

12. The soul attains her perfectly rounded form when she is neither straining out after something nor shrinking back into herself; neither disseminating herself piecemeal nor yet sinking down in collapse; but is bathed in a radiance which reveals to her the world and herself in their true colours.

13. Will anyone sneer at me? That will be his concern; mine will be to ensure that nothing I do or say shall deserve the sneer. Will he perhaps hate me? Again, his concern. Mine, to be in friendship and charity with all men, ready to show this very man himself where he is mistaken, and to do so without recrimination or ostentatious forbearance, but — if we may assume that his words were not mere cant — as frankly and generously as Phocion of old.[〔7〕] That is the right spirit for a man to have within him; he should never be seen by the gods in the act of harbouring a grudge or making a grievance of his sufferings. What ill can touch you if you follow the proper laws of your being and accept moment by moment whatever great Nature deems opportune, like a true man who is bent on furthering by any and every means the welfare of the world?

14. They despise and yet fawn on one another; each would outstrip the other, and yet cowers and cringes before him.

15. How hollow and insincere it sounds when someone says, 'I am determined to be perfectly straightforward with you.' Why, man, what is all this? The thing needs no prologue; it will declare itself. It should be written on your forehead, it should echo in the tones of your voice, it should shine out in a moment from your eyes, just as a single glance from the beloved tells all to the lover. Sincerity and goodness ought to have their own unmistakable odour, so that one who encounters this becomes straightway aware of it despite himself. A candour affected is a dagger concealed. The feigned friendship of the wolf is the most contemptible of all, and to be shunned beyond everything. A man who is truly good and sincere and well-meaning will show it by his looks, and no one can fail to see it.

16. The good life can be achieved to perfection by any soul capable of showing indifference to the things that are themselves indifferent. This can be done by giving careful scrutiny first to the elements that compose them, and then to the things themselves; bearing also in mind that none of them is responsible for the opinion we form of it. They make no approaches to us, they remain stationary; it is we who produce judgements about them, and proceed to inscribe these, so to speak, in our minds; despite the fact that it is perfectly in our power either to inscribe nothing at all, or at least to delete promptly anything that may have inscribed itself unawares. Moreover, you must remember that there will not be much more time in which to give heed to these matters, and that our race will soon be run. Do not be aggrieved, then, if things are not always to your liking. As long as they are in accord with nature, be glad of them, and do not make difficulties; if they are not, then find out what your own nature itself enjoins, and make the best of your way towards that; for a man is always justified in seeking his own good.

17. Consider where each thing originates, what goes into its composition, what it is changing into, what it is going to be after the change, and that it will be no whit the worse for it.

18. When offended. Counsel the First. Remember the close bond between myself and the rest of mankind. This obtains, because all of us were born for one another; or to give a different reason, because I was born to be their leader, as the ram is made to lead the flock or the bull the herd; or again — to go back to the first principles — because the world, if it is not mere atoms, must be governed by Nature, and in that case the lower orders of creation must exist for the higher and the higher must exist for one another.

A Second. Think of their characters, at board and in bed and so forth; and in particular, of the pressure which their own ways of thinking exert upon them, and the consequent self-assurance with which they commit these acts of theirs.

A Third. If what they are doing is right, you have no claim to be annoyed; if it is not, it can only be unintentional and unwitting. For just as 'no soul ever wilfully foregoes truth,' so none ever wilfully denies another the treatment he is entitled to; witness their indignation if anyone accuses them of injustice, ingratitude, meanness, or any other sort of misdemeanour towards their neighbours.

A Fourth. You yourself offend in various ways, and are no different from them. You may indeed avoid certain faults, yet the inclination is there nevertheless, even if cowardice or a regard for your reputation or some such ignoble motive has restrained you from imitating their misdeeds.

A Fifth. You have no assurance that they are doing wrong at all, for the motives of men's actions are not always what they seem. There is generally much to learn before any judgement can be pronounced with certainty on another's doings.

A Sixth. Tell yourself, when you feel exasperated and out of all patience, that this mortal life endures but a moment; it will not be long before we shall one and all have been laid to rest.

A Seventh. It is not the deeds of these men — which are the concern of their own directing reason — that are the source of our annoyance, but the colour we ourselves put upon them. Eliminate this, consent to withdraw all thoughts of their heinousness, and anger disappears at once. How effect such erasure? By the reflection that you, at least, have been left undisgraced. For, were it not that nothing is bad but moral disgrace, you would be guilty of a host of malpractices yourself — robbery, and every other sort of villainy.

An Eighth. Our anger and annoyance are more detrimental to us than the things themselves which anger or annoy us.

A Ninth. Kindness is irresistible, so long as it be genuine and without false smiles or duplicity. The most consummate impudence can do nothing, if you remain persistently kind to the offender, give him a gentle word of admonition when opportunity offers, and at the moment when he is about to vent his malice upon you bring him round quietly with 'No, my son; it was not for this that we were made. I shall not be hurt; it is yourself you are hurting.' Point out courteously and in general terms how this is so, and how even bees and other gregarious animals do not behave as he does — but do it without any sarcasm or fault-finding, in real affection and with a heart free from rancour; not in the manner of a school-master, nor yet for the admiration of the bystanders, but, even though others may be present, as if you and he were alone in private.

Keep these nine counsels in your memory, as so many gifts from the Muses; and while life is still with you, begin at last to be a man. Yet in guarding yourself against anger with others, be no less careful to avoid any toadying; one is as much against the common welfare as the other, and both lead to mischief. In moments of anger, let the thought always be present that loss of temper is no sign of manliness, but that there is more virility, as well as more natural humanity, in one who shows himself gentle and peaceable; he it is who gives proof of strength and nerve and manliness, not his angry and discontented fellow. Anger is as much a mark of weakness as is grief; in both of them men receive a wound, and submit to a defeat.

In addition, take this, if you will, as a tenth gift; this time from the very leader of the Muses himself. To expect bad men never to do bad things is insensate; it is hoping for the impossible. To tolerate their offences against others, and expect none against yourself, is both irrational and arbitrary.

19. There are four aberrations of your soul's helmsman which you must constantly guard against, and suppress whenever detected. Say to them one by one, 'This is a thought which is not necessary,' 'This is one which would undermine fellowship,' 'This is not the voice of my true self' (for to speak anything but your true sentiments, remember, is of all things the most misplaced), and, fourthly, when you are tempted into self-reproach, 'This would prove the divine element in me to have been discomfited and forced to its knees by the ignoble and perishable flesh with its gross conceptions.'

20. Although the natural propensity of any aerial and igneous particles in your composition is to soar upwards, nevertheless in obedience to the ordinances of the Whole these are held down under restraint within the body they compose. On the other hand, all the earthy and fluid particles in you, despite their tendency to sink downwards, are held up, and made to occupy a position which is not natural to them. Thus even these particles obey the laws of the Whole; when assigned to a position, they perforce remain there until the signal for dissolution recalls them once again. Is it not grievous, then, that the only part of you which is not obedient, and chafes at its appointed sphere, should be the thinking part? Nothing violent is demanded of it, nothing but what accords with its own nature; yet it will not submit, but breaks away in the contrary direction — for what are all its movements towards injustice, intemperance, anger, grief, or fear, but wilful divergences from nature? When once the helmsman of the soul exhibits resentment at anything which happens to it, that instant it quits its post; for it was no less made for holiness and for reverence for the gods than for justice, and these, being part of the idea of the fellowship of the universe, must come even before justice.

21. If a man's life has no consistent and uniform aim, it cannot itself remain consistent or uniform. Yet that statement does not go far enough unless you can also add something of what the aim should be. Now, it is not upon the whole range of the things which are generally assumed to be good that we find uniformity of opinion to exist, but only upon things of a certain kind: namely, those which affect the welfare of society. Accordingly, the aim we should propose to ourselves must be the benefit of our fellows and the community. Whoso directs his every effort to this will be imparting a uniformity to all his actions, and so will achieve consistency with himself.

22. Remember the country mouse's encounter with the town mouse,[〔8〕] and the flurry and agitation into which it threw him.

23. Socrates' name for the beliefs of the man in the street was 'bogies' to scare children.

24. The Spartans used to seat their guests out of the sun at all public spectacles, and themselves sat where they could.

25. Socrates gave as his reason for declining an invitation to the court of Perdiccas, 'I have no wish to go down to my grave with ignominy'; implying that he would accept no favour which he could not repay.

26. The scriptures of the Ephesians contain an exhortation to practise frequent remembrance of some bygone example of virtuous life.

27. The Pythagoreans enjoin contemplation of the heavens every morning, to remind themselves how changelessly and punctually those bodies perform their appointed task, and also to put them in mind of orderliness, purity and naked simplicity — for no veil clothes a star.

28. Think of Socrates, wrapped in the sheepskin after Xantippe had walked off with his cloak, and what he said to his friends when they recoiled in embarrassment at seeing him so arrayed.[〔9〕]

29. In reading and writing, you cannot lay down rules until you have learnt to obey them. Much more so in life.

30. 'Slavish by nature, reason is not for thee.'

31. '... then laughed my heart within me.'

32. 'Virtue they will but abuse, and taunt her with bitter reviling.'

33. 'The fool looks for figs in winter; so is he who looks for children when the season is past.'

34. 'While you are kissing your child,' Epictetus once said, 'murmur under your breath, tomorrow it may be dead.' 'Ominous words,' they told him. 'Not at all,' said he, 'but only signifying an act of nature. Would it be ominous to speak of the gathering of ripe corn?'

35. 'Green grape, ripe cluster, raisin; every step a change, not into what is not, but what is yet to be.'

36. 'The robber of your free will,' writes Epictetus, 'does not exist.'

37. He says, too, that we ought to evolve some proper system for our use of the assent. In regard to the impulses, we must take care to keep them always subject to modification, free from self-interest, and duly proportioned to the merits of the case. Desires also should be restrained to the utmost, and aversions confined to matters under our own control.

38. 'There is no triviality at issue here,' he says, 'but a plain question of sanity or insanity.'

39. 'Which is it your will to have?' Socrates would ask. 'Souls of reasonable or unreasonable men?' 'Reasonable.' 'Reasonable men who are sound, or sick?' 'Sound.' 'Then why not go seek for them?' 'Because we already have them.' 'In that case, then, why all your strife and contention?'

注　释

〔1〕　If these words are authentic and not a later insertion, they are the only reference which Marcus makes to the Christians. C. R. Haines, however, in the Loeb edition of the Meditations, points out that the clause is 'outside the construction, and in fact ungrammatical. It is in the very form of a marginal note, and has every appearance of being a gloss foisted into the text.'

〔2〕　In Sophocles' tragedy Oedipus Rex the king, in the agonized realization of his guilt and with the blood streaming from his self-mutilated eyeballs, cries, 'Ah, Cithaeron, Cithaeron, why didst thou harbour me? Why didst thou not take me and slay me out of hand?' It was on the mountain ranges of Cithaeron, near Thebes, that he had been exposed at birth by his mother Jocasta.

〔3〕　The three great Attic poets of what is called the 'Old Comedy', in the age of Pericles, were Cratinus and his younger contemporaries Eupolis and Aristophanes. The works of all but Aristophanes are lost; and in the words of the historian Grote, if we had not these before us, 'it would have been impossible to imagine the unmeasured and unsparing licence of attack assumed by the Old Comedy upon the gods, the institutions, the politicians, philosophers, poets, private citizens and even the women of Athens.'

〔4〕　Towards the end of Aristophanes' career the licence of the Old Comedy was restricted by law, and writers also began to dispense with the costly services of a chorus; thus making way for the Middle Comedy (c. 400—388 BC), from which the chorus has disappeared and in which stock types — the soldier, the miser, the courtesan — take the place of living individuals as the subjects of ridicule. The leading authors of this period, after Aristophanes himself, are said to have been Eubulus, Antiphanes, and Alexis.

〔5〕　The New Comedy arose after Athens had become subject to the power of Macedonia, and was a further development of the Middle. Politics were excluded from the stage, and the amorous intrigues of fictitious characters became the chief theme. In this class of writers the outstanding figure is Menander, who wrote upwards of a hundred comedies and was confessedly imitated by the Roman poets Plautus and Terence.

〔6〕　Both in Greece and Rome regular comedy was always less enjoyed by the populace than the Mimes, in which the action was portrayed by the movements and gestures of a single performer while a chorus recited the accompanying text. The mimes of Sophron (c. 420 BC) long remained a favourite amusement of the Greeks; and at Rome this type of entertainment became so popular under Augustus and his successors that in the end it virtually superseded the legitimate theatre.

〔7〕　An Athenian general and statesman, accused of treachery and condemned to death by the people. Asked if he had any last words to say, he replied: 'Only that I have no grudge against the Athenians.'

〔8〕　Thus Marcus warns the philosopher not to exchange the quiet of his own soul for the perturbations of the world.

〔9〕　No record of this incident has been found. We know, however, that Socrates consistently refused to be provoked by Xantippe's asperities. According to Diogenes Laertius, he was once asked if he did not find her continual upbraidings intolerable. 'Do you find the cackling of your geese intolerable?' he said. 'No,' was the reply, 'for they provide me with eggs and young goslings.' 'And so does she provide me with children,' smiled Socrates. Marcus may be referring to some similar instance of the good-natured tolerance which he so frequently enjoins upon himself.

Book Twelve

1. All the blessings which you pray to obtain hereafter could be yours today, if you did not deny them to yourself. You have only to have done with the past altogether, commit the future to providence, and simply seek to direct the present hour aright into the paths of holiness and justice: holiness, by a loving acceptance of your apportioned lot, since Nature produced it for you and you for it: justice, in your speech by a frank and straightforward truthfulness, and in your acts by a respect for law and for every man's rights. Allow yourself, too, no hindrance from the malice, misconceptions or slanders of others, nor yet from any sensations this fleshly frame may feel; its afflicted part will look to itself. The hour for your departure draws near; if you will but forget all else and pay sole regard to the helmsman of your soul and the divine spark within you — if you will but exchange your fear of having to end your life some day for a fear of failing even to begin it on nature's true principles — you can yet become a man, worthy of the universe that gave you birth, instead of a stranger in your own homeland, bewildered by each day's happenings as though by wonders unlooked for, and ever hanging upon this one or the next.

2. God views the inner minds of men, stripped of every material sheath and husk and dross. Acting through his thought alone, he makes contact solely with that in them which is an outflow from himself. School yourself to do likewise, and you will be spared many a distraction; for who that looks past this fleshly covering will ever harass himself with visions of raiment, housing, reputation, or any of the rest of life's costume and scenery?

3. You are composed of three parts: body, breath, and mind. The first two merely belong to you in the sense that you are responsible for their care; the last alone is truly yours. If, then, you put away from this real self — from your understanding, that is — everything that others do or say and everything you yourself did or said in the past, together with every anxiety about the future, and everything affecting the body or its partner breath that is outside your own control, as well as everything that swirls about you in the eddy of outward circumstance, so that the powers of your mind, kept thus aloof and unspotted from all that destiny can do, may live their own life in independence, doing what is just, consenting to what befalls, and speaking what is true — if, I say, you put away from this master-faculty of yours every such clinging attachment, and whatever lies in the years ahead or the years behind, teaching yourself to become what Empedocles calls a 'totally rounded orb, in its own rotundity joying', and to be concerned solely with the life which you are now living, the life of the present moment, then until death comes you will be able to pass the rest of your days in freedom from all anxiety, and in kindliness and good favour with the deity within you.

4. I often marvel how it is that though each man loves himself beyond all else, he should yet value his own opinion of himself less than that of others. Assuredly if some god or sage counsellor were to stand beside him and bid him harbour no thought or purpose in his heart without straightway publishing it abroad, he could not endure it for so much as a single day. So much more regard have we for our neighbours' judgement of us than for our own.

5. Can the gods, who have contrived all else so well and so benevolently, have overlooked this one thing, that even eminently virtuous men, men in the closest correspondence with the divine and living in intimate union with it through their good works and devotion, should know no re-birth after their death, but be doomed to utter extinction? However, should this indeed be their lot, rest assured that if there had been need for some different plan, it would have been so ordained; had it accorded with Nature, Nature would have brought it to pass. Therefore, from its not being so (if in truth it is not), you may have all confidence that it ought not to be so. Surely you can see that in raising idle questions like this you are indicting the deity? For should we even be joining issue with the gods in this way, unless they were supremely good and just? And if they are, how could they ever have permitted anything to be unfairly or unreasonably neglected in their dispositions for the universe?

6. Practise, even when success looks hopeless. The left hand, inept in other respects for lack of practice, can grasp the reins more firmly than the right, because here it has had practice.

7. Meditate upon what you ought to be in body and soul when death overtakes you; meditate upon the brevity of life, and the measureless gulfs of eternity behind it and before, and upon the frailty of everything material.

8. Look at the inmost causes of things, stripped of their husks; note the intentions that underlie actions; study the essences of pain, pleasure, death, glory; observe how man's disquiet is all of his own making, and how troubles come never from another's hand, but like all else are creatures of our own opinion.

9. In the management of your principles, take example by the pugilist, not the swordsman. One puts down his blade and has to pick it up again; the other is never without his hand, and so needs only to clench it.

10. See what things consist of; resolve them into their matter, form, and purpose.

11. How ample are the privileges vouchsafed to man — to do nothing but what God will approve, and accept everything God may assign!

12. No blame for the order of things can lie with the gods, since nothing amiss can be done by them, either willingly or otherwise; nor yet with men, whose misdoings are none of their own volition. Abstain then from all thoughts of blame.

13. How ludicrous and outlandish is astonishment at anything that happens in life!

14. There is a doom inexorable and a law inviolable, or there is a providence that can be merciful, or else there is a chaos that is purposeless and ungoverned. If a resistless fate, why try to struggle against it? If a providence willing to show mercy, do your best to deserve its divine succour. If a chaos undirected, give thanks that amid such stormy seas you have within you a mind at the helm. If the waters overwhelm you, let them overwhelm flesh, breath, and all else, but they will never make shipwreck of the mind.

15. Does the lantern's flame shine with undimmed brilliance until it is quenched, yet shall truth, wisdom, and justice die within you before you yourself are extinguished?

16. At the impression that somebody has done wrong, reflect, 'What certainty have I that it is wrong?' Furthermore, even if it is, may he not already have reproached himself for it, fully as much as though his nails had visibly rent his features? To wish that a rogue would never do wrong is like wishing that fig-trees would never have any sour juice in their fruit, infants never cry, horses never neigh, or any other of life's inevitabilities never come to pass. How, pray, could he act otherwise, with the character he has? If you find it so vexatious, then reform it.

17. If it is not the right thing to do, never do it; if it is not the truth, never say it. Keep your impulses in hand.

18. Always look at the whole of a thing. Find what it is that makes its impression on you, then open it up and dissect it into cause, matter, purpose, and the length of time before it must end.

19. Try to see, before it is too late, that you have within you something higher and more godlike than mere instincts which move your emotions and twitch you like a puppet. Which of these is it, then, that is clouding my understanding at this moment? Fear, jealousy, lust, or some other?

20. Firstly, avoid all actions that are haphazard or purposeless; and secondly, let every action aim solely at the common good.

21. Soon enough, remember, you yourself must become a vagrant thing of nothingness; soon enough everything that now meets your eye, together with all those in whom is now the breath of life, must be no more. For all things are born to change and pass away and perish, that others in their turn may come to be.

22. Everything is but what your opinion makes it; and that opinion lies with yourself. Renounce it when you will, and at once you have rounded the foreland and all is calm; a tranquil sea, a tideless haven.

23. When an operation, no matter of what sort, is brought to a close at the right moment, the stoppage does it no harm and the agent himself is no worse for discontinuing his action. So if life itself — which is nothing but the totality of all our operations — also ceases when the time comes, it takes no hurt by its mere cessation, nor is he adversely affected who thus brings the whole series of his operations to its timely conclusion. But the proper hour and term are fixed by nature: if not by a man's own nature — as, for example, through old age — then at all events by great Nature herself, by whose continuous renewing of her every part the universe remains for ever young and vigorous. Whatever serves the purpose of the Whole is kept always fair and blooming. It follows, then, that the ending of his life can be no evil to a man — for, being a thing outside his control and innocent of all self-seeking, there is nothing in it to degrade him — nay, it is even a good, inasmuch as for the universe it is something opportune, serviceable and in keeping with all else. Thus, by following the way of God and being at one with him in thought, man is borne onward by the divine hand.

24. There are three counsels worth keeping in mind. The first concerns actions: these should never be undertaken at random, nor in ways unsanctioned by justice. You must remember that all outward events are the result of either chance or providence; and you cannot reprimand chance or impeach providence. In the second place, think well what everything is, from earliest seed to birth of soul and from soul's birth to its ultimate surrender; what the thing is compounded of, and what it will dissolve into. Thirdly, imagine yourself suddenly carried up into the clouds and looking down on the whole panorama of human activities: how the scene would excite your contempt, now that you could discern the multitude of aerial and heavenly beings who throng around them. Furthermore, reflect that no matter how often upborne in this way, you would still behold the same sights, in all their monotony and transience. Yet these are the things of which we make such a boast!

25. Once dismiss the view you take, and you are out of danger. Who, then, is hindering such dismissal?

26. When you let yourself feel resentment at a thing, you forget that nothing can come about except in obedience to Nature; that any misconduct in the matter was none of yours; and moreover, that this is the only way in which things have always happened, will always happen, and do always happen. You are forgetting, too, the closeness of man's brotherhood with his kind; a brotherhood not of blood or human seed, but of a common intelligence; and that this intelligence in every man is God, an emanation from the deity. You forget that nothing is properly a man's own, for even his child, his body, his soul itself, all come from this same God; also, that all things depend upon opinion; also, that the passing moment is all that a man can ever live or lose.

27. Ponder the lives of the men who have set no bounds to their passions, the men who have reached the very summits of glory, disaster, odium, or any other of the peaks of chance; and then consider, 'Where are they all now?' Vapour, ashes, a tale; perhaps not even a tale. Contemplate the numerous examples: Fabius Catullinus on his estate, Lucius Lupus in his gardens, Stertinius at Baiae, Tiberius at Capri, Velius Rufus; any instance at all of what pride can set its heart upon. How ignoble are all their strivings! How much more befitting a philosopher it were to aim at justice, temperance and fealty to the gods — yet always with simplicity, for the pride that swells beneath a garb of humility is of all things the most intolerable.

28. To those who insist, 'Where have you ever seen the gods, and how can you be so assured of their existence, that you worship them in this way?' my answer is, 'For one thing, they are perfectly visible to the eye.[〔1〕] For another, I have never seen my own soul either, but none the less do I venerate that. So it is with the gods; it is experience which proves their power every day, and therefore I am satisfied that they exist, and I do them reverence.'

29. For a life that is sound and secure, cultivate a thorough insight into things and discover their essence, matter, and cause; put your whole heart into doing what is just, and speaking what is true; and for the rest, know the joy of life by piling good deed on good deed until no rift or cranny appears between them.

30. Sunlight is all one, even when it is broken up by walls, mountains, and a host of other things. Substance is all one, even when it is parcelled out among the numberless living bodies of different sorts, each with its own special qualities. Soul is all one, even when it is distributed among countless natures of every kind in countless differing proportions. Even soul that is gifted with the additional quality of thought, though apparently divisible, is likewise all one. For the other parts of all those organisms — their breath, for example — are material things, incapable of sensation, which have no affinity with each other and are only kept together by the unifying pressure of gravitation. But thought, by its very nature, tends spontaneously towards anything of its own kind and mingles with it; so that the instinct for unity is not frustrated.

31. Why do you hunger for length of days? Is it to experience sensations and desires, or increase or cessation of growth? Is it to make use of the powers of speech or thought? Does any of these things seem really worth coveting? Then if you think them beneath your notice, press on towards the final goal of all — which is the following of reason and of God. But to prize this, you must remember, is incompatible with any feelings of resentment that death will rob you of the others.

32. How small a fraction of all the measureless infinity of time is allotted to each one of us; an instant, and it vanishes into eternity. How puny, too, is your portion of all the world's substance; how insignificant your share of all the world's soul; on how minute a speck of the whole earth do you creep. As you ponder these things, make up your mind that nothing is of any import save to do what your own nature directs, and to bear what the world's Nature sends you.

33. How is my soul's helmsman going about his task? For in that lies everything. All else, within my control or beyond it, is dead bones and vapour.

34. Nothing will more encourage a contempt for death than the reflection that even men who accounted pleasure a good and pain an evil have nevertheless been able to despise it.

35. When a man finds his sole good in that which the appointed hour brings him; when he cares not if his actions be many or few, so they accord with strict reason; when it matters nought to him whether his glimpse of this world be long or fleeting — not death itself can be a thing of terror for him.

36. O man, citizenship of this great world-city has been yours. Whether for five years or fivescore, what is that to you? Whatever the law of that city decrees is fair to one and all alike. Wherein, then, is your grievance? You are not ejected from the city by any unjust judge or tyrant, but by the selfsame Nature which brought you into it; just as when an actor is dismissed by the manager who engaged him. 'But I have played no more than three of the five acts.' Just so; in your drama of life, three acts are all the play. Its point of completeness is determined by him who formerly sanctioned your creation, and today sanctions your dissolution. Neither of those decisions lay within yourself. Pass on your way, then, with a smiling face, under the smile of him who bids you go.

注　释

〔1〕　The Stoics believed the stars to be divine.

译者导读

查尔斯·狄更斯（Charles Dickens，1812—1870）是英国最伟大的小说家之一，享誉世界的代表作有《匹克威克外传》（1836—1837）、《雾都孤儿》（1837—1839）、《尼古拉斯·尼克贝》（1838—1839）、《圣诞颂歌》（1843）、《董贝父子》（1848）、《大卫·科波菲尔》（1849—1850）、《艰难时世》（1854）、《小杜丽》（1857）、《双城记》（1859）、《远大前程》（1860—1861）等。其文风幽默浑厚、雅俗共赏，因而蜚声天下，迄今不衰。

狄更斯生于朴茨茅斯市郊区，父亲是当地海军工厂附属海军会计处的一名职员。他童年时家境小康、生活幸福。但因父母持家无方，狄更斯十二岁时被迫辍学、到漆鞋厂做童工。这段经历，加上因父亲两度负债入狱、举家随之搬到狱中生活的经历，成为他终生不释的创痛。他作品中的孤弃儿主角、怨忿自怜之情、童话式情节、小人物的悲惨生活等莫不与此有关。然而，狄更斯天生颖悟、酷爱读书、勤奋过人，成就了以后的事业。1829年起，他进入报业，开始了高产、高质的写作生涯。事业的成功为他带来了丰厚的收入，1842年起，他携全家多次周游欧美，积累了大量创作素材。至1870年去世，他著有约十六部重要长篇小说、四部短篇故事集，以及近十部剧本、诗歌、纪实作品。

1850年至1870年，狄更斯先后编辑出版了周刊《家常话》和《一年四季》。《家常话》以普通大众，特别是正在崛起的中产阶级为主要读者群，发表重大社会价值类、重要信息类和娱乐类三大类文章，致力于揭露政府的腐败和渎职、力倡推进医疗卫生事业、呼吁创建面向全民的全国性公共教育体系。这些文章纪实性强、通俗易读，深受社会关注、影响强大。《一年四季》以刊登小说类作品为主，但继续了《家常话》的许多主题。从1860年至1869年，他在《一年四季》上陆续发表了题为《非商务旅客》的系列笔记体和回忆体小说。

本书八篇短文均出自《家常话》和《非商务旅客》。这些短文或浓墨重彩、或轻描淡写地展现了十九世纪中期英国社会的斑驳万象：夜幕下伦敦城中的罪恶与堕落、充满冒险的发财梦、浮躁的下层民众、庞大的海军工业、贫困的伦敦东区、恶劣的工作与生活条件、诈伪的彩票店、狂热的彩民、铺张的葬仪……不一而足。

翻译是一种跨越时空的旅行和洞隐烛微的观察。在狄更斯那随意而锐利的笔锋引领下，这一观察再次揭示：第一，在对华发动鸦片战争前夕，英国内政并非蒸蒸日上，而是同样的矛盾重重、危机潜伏；第二，该时期的英国国力正在上升，但比起前工业化时期，其国民的综合素质并无明显的飞跃；第三，在个体的生存现实面前，自由、平等、博爱等宏大口号不过是蚊蝇的回声；第四，历史不会重复，但故事始终在发生。

伦敦夜行记

数年前，我因心事烦扰，曾短暂失眠。连续几晚，我都整夜在街上巡游。倘若我只是虚弱地躺在床上尝试各种入睡方法，也许得很长时间才能克服病症。所幸我用了一种积极疗法，很快就战胜了失眠症：刚躺下就起床、出门，日出时再筋疲力尽地回家来。

那几晚，我从做业余流浪汉的亲身经历中颇长了些见识。为了挨过长夜，我到处游荡，因而懂得了那些有着同样遭历的夜巡人，他们一年到头夜夜都这般度过。

时值三月，天气潮湿、阴冷。太阳到五点半才会出来，从午夜十二点半之后，夜幕就显得漫长无限。而我，就在此时投入暗夜。

在我们流浪汉心目中，大都市的躁动不宁及其入睡前的翻腾滚动乃是首批娱乐节目之一。它的表演要持续两个小时左右。待到那些营业到深夜的酒馆熄了灯，侍者将店里最后一批吵闹不休的醉汉推到了街上，我们一下就少了许多无眠的同伴。不过，此后我们会遇到一二车辆和三两行人。幸运时，还能骤然看到一名警察咔咔地疾行而来，随之就是一场打斗。但这种消遣通常都难得一见。草市街[1]是伦敦市管理最差的地方，除了草市街上、自治区[2]的肯特街周围，以及老肯特路的部分路段，别处都一派寂静，罕见激烈事件发生。可是，伦敦好像在效仿它的居民似的，在断气前总要抽搐、抖动几下。一切似乎都已安静下来，可要是有一辆出租马车嘎嘎地飞驰而过，随后肯定还会出现五六辆。流浪汉们甚至观察到，那些酩酊醉客好像也带着磁力，彼此相吸：每当我们看到一个醉汉晃晃荡荡地朝某个商店的百叶窗走去，就知道，不出五分钟，另一个醉汉必会晃晃荡荡地出现在他面前，两人不是兄弟般地搂在一起，就是仇人般地大打出手。这类普通的醉鬼通常是些胳膊纤瘦、毛发蓬乱、唇色青灰的金酒酒徒[3]。我们偶尔也会遇到另一类样貌较为体面、身着脏污丧服的醉汉。这类醉鬼十分罕见，二者的比例是五十比一。街道经历夜晚，也经历白天；有些普通人会意外得些财产，也会意外畅饮一番。

这些忽隐忽现的火花最终渐渐消退、慢慢熄灭—清醒生活的最后几粒真正的火星儿从某个很晚才收的馅饼摊或烤土豆摊飘落—伦敦市就会随之沉入梦乡。此时，流浪汉满心向往的就是有同伴存在的迹象：一个亮灯的地方、一点儿动静，以及表明还有人在活动—不，哪怕只是还醒着—的任何事物。流浪汉的眼睛在寻找窗户里的光亮。

雨声滴答，走过大街小巷的流浪汉不停地走啊走啊，眼前除了错综无限的街巷，一无所见。只是偶尔会在某个转角处看到两个警察正在交谈，或是一名警官或巡官正在关照他的部下。夜间，有些时候—但这种时候极少—流浪汉会注意到，有个人头正鬼鬼祟祟地从前面不远处的门口朝外窥视。走上前去就会发现，有个人正紧贴着门站得笔直，试图藏匿在门口的暗影当中，显然没有跟别人作伴儿的意思。流浪汉和这位先生像着了魔一般，在可怕而适时的沉默中彼此从头到脚打量一番，而后一言不发、满腹狐疑地各自走开。滴答、滴答、滴答，雨水从壁架和墙顶上滴落，从管子和喷嘴上溅落。不久，流浪汉的身影就投在了通往滑铁卢大桥[4]的石铺路面上。在流浪汉心目中，去滑铁卢大桥花半便士[5]对收费员道声“晚安”，顺便瞥一眼他身旁的炉火，这是很值得的。那旺盛的炉火、漂亮的厚大衣、上好的羊毛围脖，加上收费员本人，看上去令人备感舒适。此外，他精神饱满、头脑清醒地将一枚枚半便士铜币放到跟前的金属桌子上，发出嘎啦嘎啦的声响，就像一个公然对抗黑夜及夜幕下所有忧思的挑战者，毫不介意黎明在即，令人备感愉悦。桥上阴郁可怖，所以桥头处很需要这样鼓舞人心的事物。我巡游的那些夜晚，还没人用绳子把那个被剁成碎块的人缒下桥栏。他还活着，且那时已经极适宜地安睡着，无梦相扰，不去忧虑自己的结局。但泰晤士河显得十分骇人：两岸的建筑被蒙裹在漆黑的寿衣里；河面的反光宛似发自水底深处，恰如自杀者的幽灵正擎着它们在指示自己溺死的地点。狂野的月亮和云团躁动不宁，好像罪人在床上辗转难安。伦敦市的巨大阴影似乎沉沉地压在泰晤士河上。

大桥和两座大剧院的间距不过几百步之遥，所以过桥便是剧院。夜晚的剧院，灯火尽熄、黑暗狰狞，人面消失、虚席连片，犹如两口巨大的枯井，荒凉死寂。此时此刻，这种种物事当中，除了尤里克的骷髅[6]，恐怕没有一样能够自知自觉。某夜，教堂尖塔在三月的凄风冷雨中敲响四点时，我穿过其中一片宏旷荒漠的边界，进到了里面。我手拿一盏昏暗的提灯，沿着熟悉的路径，摸索到了舞台跟前，隔着乐池向对岸的虚空望去。此时的乐池犹如一个瘟疫猖獗期挖下的宽大墓穴，对岸则像一个辽阔而阴沉的洞穴，枝形吊灯如同其他物什一样已然僵死，在雨雾弥漫的空旷里，触目可见的只有层层的裹尸布。我的脚下便是我上次看戏所在的地方。上次在这里，我观看了那不勒斯的农民们不顾沸腾而来的火山岩浆在葡萄树间跳舞的场面。而现在，这里趴着一条粗蛇般的消防水龙。它警惕地匍匐着，一俟吐着信子的火蛇窜出就会即刻飞扑过去。一个幽灵般的守门人举着黯淡的奠烛在远处的楼座区一晃而过。我退步上了舞台，将灯举过头顶，照向卷起的幕布，只见那幕布不再是绿色，而变成了乌黑色。往上是一个黑暗的穹顶，其中模糊地现出一具船只残骸的模样，上面还带着帆篷与绳索。我想，我的感受可能恰如一个潜水者在海底的感受。

凌晨时分，大街小巷已经了无动静。我去新门监狱[7]转了转，找到了些可供沉思的素材。我摸了摸监狱那粗糙的石墙，想象了一下睡梦中的囚犯，然后隔着布满尖钉的便门望了一眼门房，看了看值班狱卒映在白墙上的火光和灯光。这个时间也很适合在那扇邪恶的欠债犯之门外面逗留。门紧紧地关着，比任何别的门关得都牢。对许多人而言，这扇门就是死亡之门[8]。在那些乡下来客冒险使用一英镑伪币的时期，多少不幸的男男女女—其中许多人都很无辜—面对着可怕的基督教圣墓堂的尖塔[9]，被绞死在刑台上，离开了这个矛盾重重的无情世界！我怀疑，如今的夜晚，那些老经理人懊悔的幽灵有没有重访英格兰银行的营业室？或者，那营业室里是否如同老贝利街上这个衰落的刑场一样寂静？

接下来很轻易地就能走到英格兰银行，一路哀悼着美好的旧时代、叹惋着罪恶的现时代，于是我就这么做了。我还像真的流浪汉那样围着英格兰银行游荡了一圈，考虑了一下里面的财富，也考虑了一下银行外那些守着火炉打盹儿的值夜卫兵。随后，我去了比林斯格特鱼市场，希望能遇到些赶早市的人。但事实证明，我去得太早了。所以我就越过伦敦大桥，下到萨里区一侧的泰晤士河边，穿行在大酒厂的楼房间。酒厂里煞是热闹，那弥漫的烟汽、谷物的气味以及肥壮的货车马匹在食槽前吃草时发出的咯吱声，都是我绝妙的同伴。在它们中间待过之后，我感到精神抖擞、心情焕朗，于是再次上路，奔向下一个目标—老王座法庭监狱[10]，而且决定在到达监狱墙下时，想一想可怜的贺拉斯·肯齐和人患干腐病。

人患干腐病是一种怪病，病因不明。它将贺拉斯·肯齐送进了老王座法庭监狱，又从那里将他脚前头后地送了出来。肯齐正值盛年，相貌堂堂、家境富裕、性格和善，深受朋友们欢迎。他的婚姻门当户对，儿女健康漂亮。然而，他却像某些漂亮的房屋或漂亮的船只那样，患上了干腐病。人患干腐病的首要外部症状表现为下述倾向：偷偷地东游西荡、不明所以地站在街角处、有人碰上就说要四处走走、到处溜达而不是待在一处、不做具体事情而打算在明天或后天履行各种抽象的责任。如果有人发现了这些外部症状，通常都会将其与以前的某种模糊印象联系起来，认为病人只是生活得有点痛苦。观察者无暇反复琢磨这些现象，进而怀疑病人是否患上了可怕的“干腐病”。等病人的面貌变得有点邋遢、衰败，可实际又并不贫穷、肮脏、中毒或患病，他才会发觉：病人感染的是干腐病。随后，病人会在早晨散发出烈酒的气味；之后，挥霍钱财；之后，日夜都散发出烈酒的气味；之后，对一切都满不在乎；之后，四肢震颤、嗜睡多梦、困苦潦倒，最终粉身碎骨。染病者的症状与染病木材的症状一般无二。干腐病的扩散速度如同高额复利计息法，根本算不过来。一旦发现一块木板感染了该病，那么整栋房屋就要完了。这情况就发生在不幸的贺拉斯·肯齐身上，他不久前刚靠一笔捐款得以下葬。熟人们还没说完“他的家庭那么富有、生活那么舒适、前途那么光明—可是，唉，真让人担心，他竟沾染上了干腐病！”这句话呢，哎呀！他就整个地被干腐病吞没，变成了一抔坟土。

那静寂的狱墙与这个极普通的故事有着紧密的联系。在那些流浪的夜晚，离开老王座法庭监狱之后，我接着就去伯利恒皇家医院附近逛逛。这样做的部分原因是，它就在我去往威斯敏斯特[11]的沿途；另有部分原因是，我脑海里有种对黑夜的奇想，只有看着伯利恒医院的墙壁和圆顶，这想象才能发挥到极致。我的奇想是：到了晚上，睡梦中的正常人难道和精神病人有什么两样吗？在生命中的每一晚，我们这些在医院外面的人都会做梦，这难道不正和医院里面的精神病人多多少少地情形相似吗？在夜晚，我们难道不正像他们在白天那样，荒谬地以为自己同大大小小的国王与王后、皇帝与皇后，与各式各样的名人显要有着关联吗？到了夜晚，我们难道不正像他们在白天那样，将事件、人员、时间和地点混成一团吗？我们有时为自己的纷乱睡梦所扰，对吧？我们有时急于说明或解释这些梦境，正如他们有时急于说明或解释自己在清醒时的幻觉，对吧？上次我在某家同类医院中遇到了一位精神病患者，他对我说：“先生，我经常会飞起来。”我有些羞愧地想，我也会飞—在晚上。在同一家医院，一位女患者说：“维多利亚女王常常来与我共进午餐。我和女王陛下身着睡袍，吃的是桃子和通心面。王夫殿下也盛情驾临。他穿着陆军元帅制服，是骑着马来的。”我想起自己曾（在夜晚）多次举办了盛大的皇室宴会，餐桌上放着数不清的美味佳肴，我在那尊贵的场合多么举止得体、气度非凡！想起这些，难道我能不羞愧得脸红吗？真奇怪，那全知的伟大主人将睡眠称为每一天生命的死亡，却未将睡梦称作每一天健全心智的精神错乱。

这样想着，我已将伯利恒皇家医院抛在了身后，再次朝泰晤士河走去。片刻之间，我便到了威斯敏斯特桥上，用一双流浪汉的眼睛贪赏着英国国会的外墙。我知道它是一所完美的庞大机构，并且深信：所有的周边国家和未来时代都会对它赞羡备至。但如果国会的工作效率也偶尔提高一下，也许就更好了。我拐进了旧宫院[12]，在皇家法院待了十五分钟，低声念叨着这些法院令多少人无法入眠，令那些不幸的原告感到深夜是多么悲惨、可怕。接下来的十五分钟，阴郁的威斯敏斯特大教堂[13]成了我的好伙伴。教堂里那些黑暗的拱门和立柱中间埋葬着多少杰出的亡者！每一世纪的来客都超拔无匹，令上一世纪叹为观止。实际上，在那些流浪的夜晚，我甚至还去过一些公墓。守墓人定时在墓地中巡逻，并转动一个指示器那磨得光溜溜的手柄，指示器就会记录下他们触动手柄的时间。一个古老的城市埋葬着数量多么惊人的亡者！倘若他们在生者入眠时全都死而复生、出来活动，所有的街巷里、道路上该拥挤到什么程度！生者要想出门来，会连插针的缝隙都找不到。这是一幕多么骇人的景象！不仅如此，连城外都会弥山遍野、密密麻麻，全是那无量数的亡者。只有上帝才会知道，这支连天匝地的大军向外周绵延到多远。

深夜时分，教堂的钟声突然敲响，流浪汉会误认为是同伴来了，发出一声欢呼。然而，在这死寂的中夜，你会分外清晰地听到，声波一圈一圈地荡漾开来、扩散出去，渐远渐轻，或许（像哲人所言）一直淡入那无尽的太空。这时，你才意识到自己的错误，更深邃的孤寂感随之袭来。有一次，我离开威斯敏斯特大教堂后，转弯朝北走去，到达圣马丁教堂那巨大的台阶下时，三点的钟声恰好敲响了。突然，一样东西从我脚前站了起来，同时发出了一声孤独无依的叫喊。它是受到了钟声的惊吓而叫起来的，那种叫声我闻所未闻。我再向前一步就要踩上它了。我们相对而立，彼此惊惧。原来是个眉毛浓密、长有髭须的年轻人，约有二十岁。他一只手紧攥着披在身上的几件破衣烂衫，从头到脚都在颤抖，牙齿咔咔作响。他紧盯着我—是迫害者？是恶魔？是鬼魂？管我是什么呢—就像一只受惊之犬，那哀号着的嘴巴似乎要向我猛咬。他一边尖叫、准备扑咬，一边后退。我想给这个凶恶的可怜人一点钱，就伸出一只手去安抚他，按住了他的肩膀。可他一下就甩掉了外衣，扭身闪开，恰如《新约》中的那个年轻人[14]。我独自站在那里，手里拎着他的褴褛衣衫。

逢集的早晨，考文特花园市场[15]就成了流浪汉的好伙伴。一辆辆装满了卷心菜的大马车就像是在举行盛会：菜农家的男人们和儿子们就睡在马车底下；这一带人家的凶犬看管着整个市场-花园地区。然而，就我所知，在这里鬼鬼祟祟地游来荡去的孩子乃是伦敦市最糟糕的夜景之一：他们在筐子里睡觉，为争抢被抛弃的禽畜杂肉而打斗，一看到任何可以下手偷盗的东西就飞奔而去，钻到拉车和手推车下躲避巡警；他们总是光着脚跑在这个露天市场的铺砌路面上，阵雨似地发出沉闷的啪啪声。你不由得开始比较：那些人们竭力改良、精心照顾的土地出产的农产品会逐渐腐烂，所有这些（除了被人驱赶之外）无人关心的野孩子显然也在逐渐腐烂，这是多么怪异、多么令人心痛的现实！

在考文特花园市场附近，有家很早就开的咖啡馆，那是流浪汉的又一个伙伴，而且是个温暖的伙伴，这就更好了。咖啡馆还供应大块的面包。面包是那个头发蓬乱的汉子在咖啡馆的一间内室里做出来的。他此时还没穿外套，也没太睡醒，在给顾客送来面包和咖啡之后，就坐在隔扇后面又睡着了，鼾声时塞时通、千变万化，很快就进入了梦乡。这家咖啡馆是弓街[16]附近最早的建筑物之一。一天凌晨，我游荡进了咖啡馆，在桌边坐下来，边喝咖啡边思考着接下来往哪去。一个男人走了进来。他身着鼻烟色的高领长大衣，脚上穿着鞋子，头上戴着帽子。我深信，他此外什么都没穿。他从帽子里拿出一大块凉的肉馅布丁。布丁非常大，把帽子撑得鼓鼓的。为了取出布丁，他把帽子的衬里全都翻了出来。肉馅布丁显然是这位神秘顾客的标志。他一到，睡意蒙蒙的汉子就端上来一品脱[17]热茶、一小条面包、一套大刀叉和餐盘。汉子离开隔间后，这位主顾就直接把布丁放在桌面上，不是拿刀切开它，而是掌心朝下一下刺穿它，就像刺死一个不共戴天的仇敌；之后抽出刀来，在袖子上擦擦，然后用手指撕碎布丁，统统吃掉。这个吃布丁的人是我夜游期间遇到的最像鬼怪的人，至今记忆犹新。我只去过那家咖啡馆两次，两次都看到他直挺挺地大步走进来（应该说，他刚从墓穴爬出来，随即就要回去），取出布丁，刺穿它，擦擦利刃，消灭布丁。其身形令人联想到灰白色的死尸，但那张马脸分外绯红。我第二次看见他时，他嘶哑地问那个爱打盹的汉子：“今天晚上我的脸红吗？”“嗯，很红。”汉子直言不讳。那幽灵就说：“我母亲就是个贪杯的红脸女人。她进了棺材之后，我使劲看了看她，就变成了红脸膛。”不知怎地，那个肉馅布丁自此变得令人作呕，我就再也不去跟他碰面了。

不逢集或者想换换路线时，我就到火车站去。凌晨的邮车到站时，这里会热闹一番。但像世间的大多数伙伴一样，它只能陪我一小会儿：站台灯突然亮起来，搬运员从栖身处冒出来，出租马车、手推车吱吱嘎嘎地到达预定地点（邮局的大拉车已经到位）。最后，铃声响起，火车随即哐哐响着到站。但没有乘客上下车，也没行李可搬运，于是所有车、人都迅速散去。这些火车邮局有着巨大的网络，仿佛是拖着网在国土上打捞尸体。它们的车门倏地打开，喷出一股煤油灯的臭气、一个疲惫的职员、一个穿着红大衣的警卫，以及他们装满信件的背包。火车引擎喘息着、呻吟着、大汗淋漓，像是在边擦额头边诉说：“瞧我这一路跑的！”不到十分钟，灯火尽熄，我又成了孤单的流浪汉。

不过，此时，附近的大路上有人赶着牛群走来了。牛儿（通常都会像牛儿那样）想拐进石墙之中，挤进铁栏间那六英寸宽的空隙，（也通常都会像牛儿那样）低下头去，将货物抛向想象中的恶犬，给它们自己及其所有忠诚的看护人惹来一大堆多余的麻烦。此时，清醒的煤气灯也知道白昼将至，神色开始暗淡下来。大街上已经出现了三三两两的劳动者。夜间，醒时生活随着最后一个馅饼摊的最后一点火花而熄灭；现在，它则随着街角处第一批早点摊的炉火而复苏。这样，白昼的步伐越来越大；最后，它一个飞跃，来临了。而我也已身疲体倦，能够入睡了。在此时转身回家的路上，我曾认为，在夜晚那真正的荒原上，无家可归的流浪者茕然游荡，乃是伦敦最无趣的事情。而今我意识到，情况并非如此。我本就十分清楚，各式各样的罪恶与不幸都在何处，如果我乐意，就会找到它们；但我选择了规避，故此在无数漫长的街道上，我的流浪才能那般形单影只。

（牛云平　译）

迷失金融城

在我年龄和个头都还很小的时候，有一天在伦敦金融城里迷路了。某某（某某的魂灵啊，我忘记你的名字了，请原谅！）带我去观赏圣吉尔斯[18]教堂的外景，作为对我的隆重款待。我脑子里满是许多与那座宏伟的宗教建筑有关的浪漫想法，并且坚信：各种乞丐在工作日都装作瞎子、跛子、肢体残缺者、聋哑人或有其他身体疾病者，可每到周日就抛开伪装，换上节日盛装，到他们庇护人的殿堂来参加圣仪。我约略认为，班姆菲尔德·摩尔·卡鲁[19]的现任继承人会在这种场合担当俗人委员一类的角色，坐在一个高高地挂着红帘子的厢席里。

时值春季，我这些稚嫩的念头随着季节抽出了新枝，搞得我的父母和保护人都头疼不已。于是，某某主动提出带我去看看圣吉尔斯教堂的外景。（我如今猜测）他们认为，那样很可能就会熄灭我的幻想之火，让我的头脑清醒过来。早饭之后，我俩出发了。我至今记得，某某那天的打扮很醒目：下穿质地良好、乳白色的条绒马裤，打着高帮斜纹布绑腿；上穿缀着闪亮纽扣的绿色外套，戴着条蓝色围巾，露着一圈极大的衬衫领子。我现在认为，那时他肯定（跟我一样）刚从肯特郡的蛇麻草地上走出来不久。但当时我将他奉为时尚之典范、礼仪之楷模—简直就是现世的哈姆雷特，只不过没有后者那棘手的家务事罢了。

我俩边走边聊，满意地观赏了圣吉尔斯教堂的外貌。尖塔上那面飘扬的旗子尤其让人激动不已。现在推想，我们随后就沿着河岸大道[20]走向了诺桑伯兰府[21]，去欣赏府门顶上那尊闻名遐迩的狮像。我记得很清楚，总之，就在我满怀敬畏和赞羡地仰望那头大名鼎鼎的动物时，某某不见了。

我迷路了！惶恐倏地攫取了我幼小的心灵。今日回想，那骤然惊惧仍历历如昨。我敢肯定，即便我那时发觉自己是在北极迷了路，而不是迷失在那条雄狮傲视之下的狭窄、拥挤、令人不安的街道上，心中惊悸也不过如此。然而，我边哭边沿街奔跑了几个来回，就将乍现的恐惧抛在了脑后。随后，我怀着一种凄凉的自尊感走进了一个庭院，在台阶上坐下，开始考虑如何度过一生。

我相信，我幼小的脑子里根本没有想到要问路回家。或许那时的我还很喜欢迷路后那种凄凉的自尊感呢。但是，我如今切实地相信，当我为未来规划宏大蓝图时，根本就没有注意到那最简短、最显见的人生道路。我猜，我当时只有八九岁，还非常幼稚。

我兜里有一先令零四便士，小指上戴着一枚白镴戒指，戒指上镶着一小块红玻璃。这件首饰是我的爱恋对象在我生日那天送给我的。我俩发誓要结婚，但也预料到双方家庭将会阻碍我们的结合。她（当时六岁）属于卫斯理宗，我则虔信英国国教[22]。就在我生日那天，我的教父—他是个既懂得自己职责所在又能履行职责的人—送给了我半克朗[23]，我花得还剩下这一先令零四便士。

有这些宝贝在身，我决定去碰碰运气。我想，我一旦发了迹，就驾着六匹马拉的大车回家去娶我的新娘子。想着这幅胜利的图景，我又哭了几声。可很快我就擦干眼泪，出了庭院，按计划踏上了征途。我的计划是：首先（作为某种仪式）前往市政大厅看看那对巨人像[24]，从他们身上汲取力量，相信自己的冒险可能会一帆风顺。如果这一招落空，就转而到金融城里转转看能否寻到威廷顿[25]式的发财机会。如果这一招也失利，就去参军当鼓手。

于是，我开始一路打听着去往市政厅。我当时莫名其妙地认为，“市政厅”就是“石造的”厅，或“有巨石的”厅。我非常精明地觉得，如果我打听通往巨人像之路，会被人笑话，所以就不能提巨人像的事。我至今记得，只剩我孤身一人时，街道显得多么宽阔无边！房屋显得多么高大！一切都多么威严而神秘！到了圣殿关石门[26]前，我目不转睛地盯着它看了半个小时，但还是没看完就继续前进了。我在书上读到过，圣殿门顶上放着许多示众的人头。因此，这个石门虽然是件威严的建筑杰作和实用典范，但似乎也是个凶恶的古老地方。我最终离开那里之后，呀！一下就看到了圣邓斯坦教堂上的巨人像[27]！那些亲切的怪物敲钟的情形，谁看到后还能走得开呢？在他们几次敲响一刻钟的当儿，我到那家玩具店看了看—在我写下这篇文字的此刻，这家玩具店还在那儿，只是已面貌一新了—一个多小时之后，我从那个迷人的地方脱身，来到了高高耸立的圣保罗大教堂[28]前。我怎么能错过它那伟岸的穹顶呢？怎么才能将目光从它的金色十字架上移开呢？去市政厅看巨人像的路途真是遥远啊，而且行进速度很缓慢。

终于，我来到了他们面前，满怀恐惧和崇敬地注视着他们。他们看上去比我预想的要和蔼些，总体说来脸色比较灿烂，可是非常高大。我估计他们的底座大约有四十英尺[29]高，要是他们下来走在石板路上，会是两个庞然大物。我思考着这些，对着两个巨人出神（我估计，孩童们见到他们大抵都会如此的）。尽管知道这些雕像并非血肉之躯，我仍旧认为他们有生物特征—例如，他们知道我在那儿，并在偷偷地注意我。我累极了，就钻到马高格下面的角落里，躲过了他的视野，睡起了觉。

一个大觉之后，我突然惊醒了，感觉那两个巨人好像在咆哮，却转而发现原来是金融城的喧闹声。周围一切如故，与我睡前一模一样：豆茎啦、仙女啦、公主啦、龙啦，统统都没有，也没见任何新的人生转机。我饿了，就想去买些食物回这儿来吃掉，然后继续按计划寻找威廷顿式的发财机会。

我坦然自若地在面包店买了一便士的面包卷，可在好几家美食店前探头探脑地徘徊了一番，却未能鼓足勇气进门。最后，我在一家美食店的橱窗里看到一堆熟香肠，旁边的标签上写着：“日耳曼小鬼，一便士”。这下，我知道想买什么了，就勇敢地走进去说：“请问你们能不能卖给我一个日耳曼小鬼？”他们卖给了我。我兜里揣着那根纸包着的香肠回到了市政厅。

两个巨人仍然待在那儿，偷偷地假装没有注意我。于是，我就在另一个角落里坐下来，眼前只有一条竖着耳朵的狗。是条黑狗，一只眼上面有一撮白毛，脚爪上有一块块白色和褐色的杂毛。它想和我玩耍：它围着我蹦来跳去、在我身上蹭鼻子、从我身旁窜过、摇头晃脑地假装倒着跑，显得友善而滑稽，仿佛它根本不计较个人形象、只为逗我开心似的。那时，我看着这条狗，想到了威廷顿，感到机会就要来了。我不断地说：“嘿，小狗！”“可怜的家伙！”“好狗狗！”，逗引着它。我满意地认为，此后它就永远成为我的狗了，并会帮我谋求发财之道。

这让我感到了宽慰（迷路后我不时地会哭一鼻子），就将那个日耳曼小鬼香肠从口袋里掏出来，准备吃午餐。我先咬下一小口扔给狗，它向那侧一扑就吞吃掉了，就像吞药片似的。我咬第二口的时候，它紧盯着我的脸，等着我再扔给它一块；而我这时在考虑该给它起个什么名字。我觉得，在此情此景之下，“美妙运气”这个名字不错，含义很丰富。如今回想，我那时正为想出了这么个好名字而得意非凡，可“美妙运气”却开始极其凶狠地朝我狂吠起来。

我奇怪地想：它怎能这么没羞没耻？可它才不管这一套呢，反而吼叫得更凶了。它嘴里淌着口水，眼睛闪着红光，鼻子湿漉漉的，脑袋使劲地歪向一边，一边冲我吠叫，一边围着我在石铺地面上鬼鬼祟祟而充满恐吓地转悠，最后突然嗖地一下咬住那个日耳曼小鬼，从我手里扯出去，叼着它跑掉了。它再也没有回来帮我谋求发财之道。我现在已经四十岁了，从那一刻至今，再也没有见过我忠诚的“美妙运气”。

我非常孤独。与其说那是由于我失掉了好吃的日耳曼小鬼香肠（当时我还没听说过有加了大量胡椒粉的马肉这种美食），不如说是因为“美妙运气”那么残忍地令我失望。我曾相信，它除了不会说话，会作出一切友好的举动；没准它甚至也能学会说话呢。我又哭了一会儿，心想：如果我的爱恋对象跟我一块儿迷路该多好，她能和我做伴儿呀。不过，我马上就想到，她可不能参军当鼓手，于是就擦干眼泪，吃掉了面包。从市政厅出来后，我遇到了一个卖牛奶的妇女，就从她那儿买了一便士的牛奶喝掉了。吃喝之后，我的精神头又来了，就开始在金融城漫游，寻找威廷顿式的发财之道。

如今我每次进金融城，都悲哀地感到自己真是个有文化的可怜人。可那时，我只是个迷路的孩子，在那里游逛的时候，想到大英商界和金融城市长，心中满是崇敬。如今在那里游逛的时候，我会嘲笑那些庄重的礼服，并愤慨地认为，金融城市政府是当今世上最严重的恶作剧之一。孩提时的我哪里会懂得今日金融城里那总是遭遇失望的无数大众？他们总是希望在那里遇到个伙伴、得到些钱，却总是希望落空。孩提时的我哪里听说过那个大好人、金融城里的朋友？他要为那么多的人做那么多的事；他要让这个人担任国内的某个职务，让那个人担任国外的某个职务；他要搞定这个人的债权人，为那个人的儿子谋个生计，并确保另一个人拿到酬金；他要“投身于”这家伟大的股份制企业中去，要进入那家人寿保险公司的董事会；然而，他从来不做这些预报了的事情。孩提时的我哪里会了解那个号称是绅士、摩西宗阿拉伯人[30]和其他人的朋友的人？他通常出现在各种赛场上，主要居住在红狮广场一带；他无法减少纸币的总量，身边却恰巧放着一桶醒目的上等雪利酒、一只梳妆盒和一幅提香[31]的《维纳斯》，难道拥有这些物品的他乐意补足差额？孩提时的我哪里会听说那个人呢？在那个单纯的时代，他向那些一脸严肃的秃顶人士吐露机密（这机密从未碰巧证明有丝毫的正确性），后者又神秘兮兮地在饭桌边把这秘密透露给了屏息以待的听众。没有。我是否已懂得他是个可怕的贪婪的家伙、不值一提的骗子、一个纯属虚构的名人？没有。我是否听说过他与金融市场上的资金紧绌有关、与统一公债的沉闷状况有关、与黄金出口有关、与众人面前的拦路石—小麦的度量单位蒲式耳[32]—有关？没有。我对下面这些名词的意思可有丝毫概念？—假公济私、操纵市场、伪造账目、虚构红利、美化事物等。丝毫都没有。我难道没有发现，哈德逊先生本人不正明摆着是头瞪着眼的死金牛犊吗？无从发现。在我眼里，金融城就是一个巨大的商场，遍地都是宝石、贵金属、大酒桶、大捆包，充满了荣誉、慷慨、进口水果、进口香料。每位商人兼银行家都是菲茨沃伦先生[33]和水手辛巴德[34]的复合体。每当风向适合航往巴巴里，而且船长也在家，史密斯、佩恩和史密斯[35]就会将家仆们（包括那名坏脾气的厨师）召集起来，让他们备好自己的船上用品。格林和哈利法克斯[36]二人曾在钻石之谷中经历了巨大困难。霸菱兄弟[37]见识过了大鹏鸟蛋[38]，并随沙漠商队旅行过。罗思柴尔德[39]曾坐在巴格达的市场上售卖各式各样的货物；一位戴着面纱、骑着驴子的女士爱上了他，她来自苏丹[40]的后宫。我就这样在城里漫游，就像一个梦境中的孩童。我盯着那些英国商人，坚定地相信一切都那么神奇，心中溢满激昂之情。我走近府第，又远离府第—走进庭院和小广场，又走出庭院和小广场。我隔着缝隙窥视一下账房外的走廊，然后跑掉。我那羞怯的脚步声单调地回荡在南海公司总部的庭院里。我接着逛到了奥斯丁修会中，好奇地想，过去那些修道士怎么会喜欢这个地方呢？我就这样一直在游逛，不停地凝视着那些英国商人，不厌其烦地浏览着那些商号。为了说清各个地方，我编造了这些故事，并虔诚地相信它们，正如我虔诚地相信金融城本身。我至今尤为清楚地记得，当我发现自己来到了皇家交易所◆◆◆伦敦金融城的皇家交易所（Royal Exchange）位于康喜尔街（Cornhill Street）和针线街（Threadneedle Street）交会于银行交叉点（Bank junction）的一段，平面图呈梯形。交易所始建于1565年，后经两次大火烧毁和两次重建，现有建筑于1844年第三次建成，使用至今。1939年，这里完成了作为交易所的使命。如今的皇家交易所乃是一个奢侈品购物中心。——译者注◆◆◆，看到那些坐在船只海报下面衣着破烂的人时，我内心认定：他们是财迷精，将全部家产都投到了船上，去买金砂或类似的东西，此时正等着各自的船长回来告诉他们将要起航了。我观察到，他们都在大声嚼着脆饼干。我觉得他们那么做是为了预防晕船。

到处游逛是件开心事，但却仍旧没有产生威廷顿式的结果。市长官邸里正在准备午餐，我隔着一个装有窗栅的厨房窗子偷偷朝里望去，看到了那些戴着白帽子正在忙碌的男厨师。我的心开始咚咚跳起来，盼望着市长大人，或者市长夫人，或者他们的某个女儿、年轻的市长千金，会从楼上的某个房间朝外看，并命人把我带进去。可是，什么都没发生。我这样窥视了一段时间之后，一名厨师朝我喊道（窗子开着）：“小子，走开！”我吓了一跳，看到他长着黑黑的络腮胡子，我立刻就乖乖地走开了。

随后，我来到了东印度大楼，问一个小孩那是什么地方。他不作回答，只是做鬼脸，并拉扯我的头发，整番举动毫不文雅、毫无礼貌。我对东印度大楼十分崇敬，这可能让詹姆斯·霍格爵士[41]本人非常满意。我毫不怀疑地认为，它是地球表面上最卓越、最高尚、最清廉，事实上最公正无私、在各方面都最惊人的机构。我那时已懂得誓言的内涵，差点发誓说东印度公司就是一整块完美无瑕的贵橄榄石。

那些去印度的男孩子们，一到印度就开始抽起形如翻卷的拉铃绳的烟斗来，而毫不感到难受。他们的结局就是脚上头下地栽进某个雕花玻璃糖罐里。一路想着这些，我来到了那些赴印装备店。在那里，我读到了奔赴印度的年轻人必备物品的各类清单。我看到“一对手枪”这一条时，想到：能够踏上赴印征程是一桩多大的幸事！但这里仍然看不到哪个英国商人有将我带回他家的意思。只有一个烟囱清洁工例外—他打量着我，好像认为我很适合他那一行，可我赶紧跑开了。

一整天我都深受男孩子们的折磨。现在想来，尽管我当时并没有冒犯他们，但他们不是追着我转过街角，就是把我逼进门口的死角，非常野蛮地对待我。有个男孩子兜里装着半截黑铅笔，就在我白帽子的帽顶上写上了他母亲的名字和（他声称的）地址：“布劳斯夫人·沃平区烟草塞街木腿道”。那字迹我怎么也擦不掉。

我记得，在遭受这般迫害之后，我在一个小小的教堂墓地里休息了一会儿。我考虑了整个事件，觉得如果我和我的爱恋对象能够立刻被埋葬在那儿，就会让我得到解脱。可是，在打了个盹、喝了点水、吃了个小面包，特别是看了一幅画之后，我又精神抖擞了。

如今想来，我那时肯定是游荡到了古德曼菲尔德剧院或者邻近的什么地方。那幅画上画的是某出戏里的一幕场景，附近的某家剧院正在上演这出戏。不过，那家剧院现在已经没了。那幅画使我想去那家剧院看看那出戏。威廷顿计划显然无法实现了，我于是决定：看完戏后，一路打听找到军营，敲开营房的大门，告诉他们我知道他们想招鼓手，而我就是去当鼓手的。我想那时肯定是曾听人说过，而我自己也相信，每个军营大门后面都有个兜里装着一先令[42]的哨兵在日夜值守。我还相信，要是哪个男孩被人以任何方式成功劝诱而同意参军，立即就会当上鼓手，除非他的父亲交纳四百英镑的赔偿金。

我找到了那家剧院。它的外貌我记不清了，只记得剧院的正面用土黄色草草地涂着两个显示忠诚的词首字母“G.R.”。我跟一大群人一起在楼座门外等着开门。那群人中大部分都是水手，他们和身边的其他观众一样，都来自社会底层。他们的言谈不堪入耳，但我对其糟粕不甚了了，所以也没有产生令我堕落的恶劣影响。我至今都在怀疑，与这类群体过从多久就能带坏一个受过我这样教育、像我这般纯洁的孩子？

无论在楼座门外还是在剧院之中，每当我发觉有人注意我的样貌，就假装在寻找某个带着我来却跟我分开了的大人，并对那个想象中的人物点头微笑。这个办法很有效。我手里攥着枚六便士的硬币，准备交费。门开了，门闩吱嘎乱响，人群中的妇女一阵尖叫，我像一根稻草那样，跟着人流前进。我那枚六便士硬币被收费处那鸽巢似的洞口飞快地吞了进去。在我眼里，那洞口就像个嘴巴。我爬上了观众较少的上层楼梯，（像所有别人那样）一路狂奔，要占个好位置。我到达楼座后端时，那里还没几个人。那些座位看上去高得可怕，活像是一组跳台，要将我头朝下抛入楼下的正厅里去。在极度惊恐之中，我紧紧抓住了一个座位。然而，有位带着个年轻女伴的和善面包师向我伸出了手。于是我们三人一起翻过座位，来到了第一排的角落里。面包师很喜欢他的女伴，整晚看戏期间都不停地亲吻她。

我刚刚坐好，突然有件事重重地压在了我的心上，极其可怕地折磨着我的心灵。我得把它讲清楚。那晚是一场义演—那位喜剧演员的义演。他又矮又胖，长着一张非常宽大的脸，戴着一顶（我那时觉得）有史以来最小最可笑的帽子。为了让他的朋友们和观众满意，这位喜剧演员宣布，他先骑着一头驴子唱支幽默的歌曲，然后再把这头非凡的驴子作为奖品，颁发给抽中大奖者。所有获准入场的池座观众和楼座观众都有机会参加这次抽奖。我交那枚六便士硬币的时候，得到了一个号码—47号。如果这个号码被抽中，我就会赢得那头驴子，那到底该怎么办呢？！我一想到这儿，就冒出了恐惧的冷汗。

想着我可能出现的好运气，我浑身战栗。万一47号被抽中，我将根本无法隐瞒该号码属于我这一事实，因为我让面包师看了这个号码，更何况我的困窘也会立即表明被抽中的是我。然后，我想象着自己被叫上舞台，领取那头驴子。我想象着，当全场的人看到大奖落到了我这样一个小家伙的头上，会发出怎样的一阵尖叫！我该怎么把驴子牵出剧院呢？—他肯定不愿意走。要是他大声叫唤起来，我该怎么办？要是他尥蹶子乱踢，我会落个什么下场？要是他驮着我倒退到舞台门里去，赖着不出来呢？我感到，如果我赢得了这头驴，那位喜剧演员一俟我走近就会把我放到驴背上去。然后，要是我把他带出了剧院，该对他做什么呢？我该怎么喂养他？把他拴在哪儿？我一个人迷路已经够糟的了，而带着一头驴迷路就是一场天大的灾难，大到超出了我的想象。

第一段戏演完了，可我的脑海里忧惧盘旋，根本无法安心赏戏。海船上场了—海报上将它称作一艘真正的战舰—庞大的船体在巨浪滔天的大海上剧烈颠簸着。即便这么恐怖的风暴场面也不能令我忘掉那头驴。水手们拿着望远镜和喊话喇叭在船上东倒西歪地到处乱跑（他们在那艘战舰上显得非常高大），看上去真是一幅可怕的画面。同样可怕的是，舵手很可能已经无可避免地背叛了船员们，因为他一边喊着“我们迷路了！快上救生艇！快上救生艇！雷电击中了主桅！”，一边在我眼皮子底下将主桅从插槽里拔出来，扔下船去。然而，在那头驴子引发的恐惧面前，就连这些震撼人心的情节都显得苍白无色。后来，那个（极好的）好水手得到了好运，那个（极坏的）坏水手从一块形状奇特、貌似折梯之类东西的岩石上跳入了海中。甚至在这时，我仍在泪眼婆娑中看到了那头驴子的可怖身影。

终于，那一刻到来了。小提琴手们开始演奏那首幽默曲子，那头令我无限畏惧的动物咔嗒咔嗒地出现在舞台上，背上驮着那位喜剧演员。我根据驴蹄发出的声响推断，他新钉了掌。他身披彩带（我指的是驴子），坚持要将尾巴对着观众。喜剧演员就从他背上跳下，转过身来，倒骑在驴背上，在雷鸣般的掌声中连唱了那首歌曲三遍。在此期间，我一直害怕得焦躁不安。池座中有两个面色苍白、身上溅满街中泥污的观众受邀起身，到舞台上去监督抽签过程，其他观众对他们报以一阵哄笑。这时，我本可乞求他们、恳求他们对我大发慈悲，不要抽到47号。

不过，我的痛苦很快就解脱了。一位坐在我身后的先生的号码被抽中了，就下楼去领奖。他穿着法兰绒短上衣，戴着条黄色围巾，在风暴刮起之前就吃掉了两条炸鳎鱼和所有衣袋里的坚果。这位先生似乎很熟悉那头驴，在他出场之前就认识他，而且对他的一系列活动都兴趣盎然。用一个好理解的词儿来描述他吧—他几乎是凑在我的耳边，自言自语地“赶”着那头驴。每当驴出了什么差错，他就说：“过雷（来），小驴宝贝儿。过雷（来）！”他试图骑上驴背，可被摔在了地上，逗得观众们（包括我本人）开怀大笑。不过，等他再站起来，却娴熟地骑着驴子下台了，而且不久就十分平静地回到了自己的座位上。盘桓已久的沉重忧惧涣然冰释，我平静了下来，踏踏实实地欣赏了其余的表演。我记得，那出戏里面有不少舞蹈场面，有带着镣铐跳的，有在玫瑰丛里跳的。有一场舞蹈中，舞者旁边有一个美若天仙的小姑娘，跟她一比，我的爱恋对象黯然失色、平凡无奇。在最后的一场戏中，她又出现了，这次扮作一个男孩（戴盔穿甲），数次被剧中其他人物所保护。我如今在一定程度上认为，当时的剧情是：一个男爵想把她淹死，但数次被那位喜剧演员、一个鬼魂、一只纽芬兰犬和一口教堂大钟阻止。此外，我如今只记得，我当时很纳闷那个男爵打算去哪里；还有，他在一阵火星儿中到了那儿。火星儿熄灭的同时，灯也全熄了。这让我感到，整出戏—船啦、驴啦、男男女女啦、美若天仙的小姑娘啦，一切一切—都是一个引爆了的奇妙烟花，爆炸过后，只余尘灰与黑暗。

我出了剧院来到大街上时，天色已经很晚。天上没有月亮，也没有星星，大雨倾盆。人群四散之后，我一个人孤单地走着，记忆中那个鬼魂和那个男爵的面目非常丑陋。我感到难以名状的孤寂。此时，我的小床和那些亲爱的、熟悉的面容才第一次浮现在眼前。白天里，我从未想到过家人会多么悲痛，从未想到过我的母亲，从未想到过任何别的事情。我只是在自我调整，以适应所处的境遇，并到处寻找发财机会。

我意识到，如果一个男孩只会哭泣、只会到处乱跑，嘴里嚷着“哎呀，我迷路了！”，那么他根本不可能想去当兵。我放弃了一路打听去兵营的念头—或者说，那个念头离我而去—开始到处乱跑，最后发现了一个在岗哨上值班的巡夜人。如今回想，我很惊诧，他当时竟然还醒着。我倾向于认为，他是身体太虚弱，无力喝醉酒了。

这位可敬的人士将我带到了最近的哨所—说是他带着我，实际是我带着他。因为回想起我们二人那时在雨中穿行的情景，肯定形成了一幅画面，恰如一幅幼儿牵着老人的小插图。他吓人地咳嗽着，每走近一面墙时，都要靠上去歇一会儿。我俩终于到达了哨所—一个寂静慵懒的温暖地方，四壁上挂着几件大衣和拨浪鼓状的物件。他们派一个患有麻痹病的人去寻找我的家人，我随后就靠在炉火边睡着了，好大的一觉！等我醒过来，映入眼帘的是我父亲的脸。这就是我那次迷路的全部经过。我小时候，他们常常说我是个与众不同的孩子。现在想来，他们说得没错。或许我还是个与众不同的大人。

记忆中的某某啊，原谅我带给了你忧虑吧！即便是现在，每当我站在那尊雄狮的下面，都会看到你仓皇地沿着大街奔来跑去，听不进去别人的安慰。从那时至今，我曾多次迷路，而且游逛得越来越远。但愿我那些次迷路带给别人的烦恼，少于我这次迷路带给你的烦恼！

（牛云平　译）

查塔姆造船厂

在泰晤士河和梅德韦河[43]上有一些偏僻的码头，夏季时，我常在那里闲逛。面对流水，人就会浮想联翩。而我，最爱面对着潮汐强劲的河流遐想无限。我喜欢看这样的景象：大船离岸而去或者满载而归；那些矮小的蒸汽机拖船自信满满地喷着烟汽，拖着大船在海平线上来来往往，一派忙碌；一队驳船挂着棕色或红褐色的船帆，那色彩似乎是从沿岸熟透的树上采下来的；笨重、陈旧的运煤船载着少量的压舱物，迎着潮水困难地行进着；浅色的螺旋桨推进三桅帆船和纵帆船傲慢地直线行进，别的船则耐心地抢风绕行；船身小巧、挂着巨大白帆的快艇和小帆船急促地来来往往，为种种消遣或商业任务奔忙着—就像那些小人物，为了自己的琐事而大吵大闹。我眼望着这些物事，却丝毫不必思考它们，甚至不必看到它们，除非当时情景恰合我的心情。我也不必听到潮水的飞溅声、拍击声及其在我脚下起伏的声音，不必听到远处的起锚机发出的叮当声，或是更远处蒸汽轮船的轮桨发出的嗡嗡声。这一切，连同我身下那咯吱作响的码头、淤泥中的高水位线和低水位线、沉陷的堤道、坍塌的河岸、歪斜的断树残桩，都会融入我驰骋的思绪之中。那些断树残桩似乎颇以自己的容貌为傲，倾身顾盼着它们在水面上的倒影。在湿地上吃草的牛羊、在我周围盘旋和点水的海鸥、从丰收的田野上（远离射程）起飞回巢的乌鸦和捕鱼归来的苍鹭，也均可出入我的遐思。那只苍鹭忧郁地高飞着，仿佛天空配不上它似的。在流水的帮助下，感觉范围之内的一切事物都会与之外的一切交汇融合，宛如一支无从确切描述的乐曲，催人入眠。

在其中一个码头附近，有一座古老的堡垒（在那里，我能用放大镜看到诺尔灯船[44]），从里面冒出了一个男孩。在他的帮助下，我原本贫乏的知识大为扩充。他岁数不大，面相聪颖，皮肤被夏日的骄阳烤成了土褐色，长着土褐色的卷发。我发现，在这个男孩身上，除了一只正在消散的青肿眼眶外（我很细心地没问他何故如此），没有一样东西不彰显着勤学好问、乐读善思的习惯。正是从他那儿，我学会了识别位于任意距离之外的海关船只，懂得了那溯流返航的东印度公司大商船在海关官员登船检查时所遵行的全套程式和礼仪。要不是他，我或许永远不会知道“哑疟”一词，如今我已很了解这种病了。要是当初不曾在他的脚前坐过，我或许终生都不会知道，那种帆上印有白马标记的驳船乃是运石灰的船。同样，我也是从他那听到了关于啤酒的种种重大机密。其中有一条是：他警告我不要喝某个厂家生产的啤酒，因为那些啤酒供过于求，已经酸坏了。可这位年轻的智者并不认为那厂家生产的麦芽酒也坏掉了。他还教我触摸湿地上的蘑菇，并温和地责备我，嫌我无知地认为蘑菇里装满了盐。他传授知识的方式细致周到、合乎情境。他在我身旁坐下来，斜靠在岸边，先向河里丢一块小石头或砂砾，随后就开始发神谕般地讲起来，似乎他的话是从河面上扩散着的波纹的圆心冒出来的。他毫无例外，总是以此方式开始给我授讲新知。

这个男孩—我不知他的姓名，就管他叫“堡垒精灵”—是我新近认识的。那天微风吹拂，河水在我俩周围跃动，充满了生机。我在金黄色的田野上看了一番正被运送的禾捆，然后来到了河边。那个红脸膛的农夫望着在自家稻谷堆上的凹陷处忙碌着的雇工，告诉我说，他上周如何收割了二百六十英亩的长秆稻，那是他这一辈子活计干得最棒的一周。整个乡间充满了优美的形态和色彩，一派安宁、丰裕气象。这丰收景象似乎还乘着满载黄色谷物的驳船，沿河而下，飘洒一路馨香，去装扮那从无稼穑的海洋。

就在这一背景下，“堡垒精灵”对着一块漂浮在水面上的铁电池发表了评论。那块铁电池新近才出现在那里。从他的评论中，我了解到他对造船学的看法，还得知他想成为一名工程师。我发现他的才干足以胜任皮托先生[45]和布拉塞先生[46]的所有工程合同中的所有项目：他很会制作混凝土、熟悉铁的性能，而且在枪炮制造和操作方面造诣高超。他谈起打桩术和造闸法时，我一句话也插不上。他容忍了我的无知沉默，令我感激不尽。在讲这些话的过程中，他朝远处岸上的某个地点望了好几次，并且带着含糊、神秘的敬畏提到“那个厂子”。与他分手后，我思考着他的教导，突然想起“那个厂子”是我国一家大型国有造船厂。它就隐藏在风车群后斜坡下的庄稼地中间，似乎是在和平时期谦恭地躲开了人们的视线，不想给任何人带来麻烦。既然“那厂子”如此谦恭，我就决定增进对它的了解。

近观之下，“那厂子”的谦恭美德留给我的美好印象并未遭到破坏。厂子里回荡着铁锤砸铁的声音。隔河注目，巨大的工棚或长廊下，正在建造庞大的军舰，似乎效率颇高。尽管如此，但“那厂子”毫不张扬，而是舒服地隐藏在布满了庄稼地、蛇麻草地和果园的山坡下；它宽大的烟囱静静地—几乎是懒惰地—冒着烟，就像个正在抽烟的巨人。一台剪切机停在厂子旁边，身形庞大却温驯友善，就像只机械长颈鹿。停放在附近武器码头上的大炮显得一派纯真，就像一只只玩具。在大炮上方执勤的哨兵身着红色军服，有规律地移动着，就像个玩具小人。在火热的阳光照耀下，他身上反着光，使他有可能被误认为是另一个一模一样的持枪小人，枪里装的子弹是—铅制的。

我过了河，登上了浮动平台。在我之前，一堆漂浮在水上的垃圾和杂草曾试图登上梯阶，未果，便转而挤进了一个角落。我发现，那里的路灯杆实为大炮，那些建筑装饰实为炮弹。就这样，我来到了“那个厂子”跟前。巨大的折叠门就像一只硕大的专利保险箱[47]，又紧又牢地把它关在了里面。我被这些大门吞下，送入了“厂子”的消化道。乍一看，“厂子”里非常整洁，似乎已经放假，待到战事再起才会重新开工。尽管它貌似十分平静，但就在其整洁的仓库外面，滚落着一些用来制绳的大麻纤维。那可并不像是干草散落在了白净的石头上。

“叮！”“咣！”“咚！”“砰！”“轰！”“嘎吱！”“咣！”“砰！”“叮当！”“砰！”“咚！”“砰！”“咔哒！”“砰砰砰！”这究竟是怎么回事？！原来是（或曰很快就成为）装甲舰阿基琉斯。在船身上有一千二百个人正在忙碌：他们有的站在船舷外的鹰架上，有的在船头上，有的在船尾上，有的在龙骨下，有的在甲板中间，有的在船舱里；里里外外都是人。在船身最狭窄的曲折处，只要足以转动身体，他们就爬进去。一千二百名锻工、测量员、捻缝工、军械士、铁匠、金属工、木匠，一千二百名弄出“叮！”“咣！”“咚！”“嘎吱！”“叮当！”“咔哒！”“砰砰砰！”声响的人！建造中的阿基琉斯战舰周身发出震耳欲聋的声响。然而，在那可怕的一天到来时，竣工后的阿基琉斯战舰将整个投入使用，并发出惊天动地的巨响。与之相比，此时此刻的这一切喧嚣不过是一声序曲，根本不值一提。正在安装中的甲板排水孔此时就像是干燥的导管，而当那可怕的一天到来时，它们将红浆飞泻。这些被烟雾和火焰笼罩的模糊身影正在甲板间躬身忙碌，而比起未来那天被另一种烟雾和火焰笼罩着在甲板间忙碌的身影，却根本不值一提。战舰边的这些蒸汽发动机能让它来回移动，能推动数吨的钢板滑行，宛如推动着许多树叶那样轻快。而到了那一天，如果它们待在舰边，片刻之间就会被撕成碎片。想想铁箱、木柜组成的阿基琉斯战舰这个庞然大物在水上航行的情景吧！想想有什么狂风巨浪能摧毁它？！想想由里而外穿透船侧钢板、随处可见的炽热红点吧！我此时就看到，这儿有一个、那儿一个、还有那儿！侧板外面的高台上站着两个人，他们赤裸臂膀，手拿大锤，一看到红点就照之猛砸，直砸至红点变黑变平。这时，我发现一只铆钉已经牢牢钉实。每一块钢板上都有许多这种铆钉，整条船上的铆钉成千上万。想想我站在船上欣赏其全貌有多困难吧！船上耸立着成群的大铁罐和橡木柜，因此，这条战舰内部，时刻都有什么在结束，也时刻都有什么在开始。即使它的一半被毁坏了，另一半也足够使用、完好无损。然后，我沿船侧折返，下到软泥中，到船坞那潮湿的底部，从那撑托着战舰的止滑木和支柱组成的地下丛林深处，仰视那庞大无边的船体向高处的光亮突展出去，而向我所在的底部则越来越窄。这样地爬下攀上非常费劲，让人觉得这根本不可能是一艘船，而恍然以为是某个古代圆形露天剧场（如维罗纳[48]的那座）中建起的一座巍峨大厦，几乎装满了整个剧场！然而，如果没有旁边那些工坊，没有那些机械动力，这一切事物都会是什么呢？！那些机械动力能刺穿4.5英寸厚的钢板为铆钉打洞，按照战舰设计图用液压力将钢板修整成上宽下窄的形状，并用猛禽鸟喙状的刀子将钢板多余的部分削去，完全达到了设计图上那极端精细的要求。这些力大无穷的机器由一张面庞所留意，由一只手所操纵。在我看来，它们有着与“那个厂子”一样的谦恭品德。“听话的巨兽，按照这些等距排列的粉笔记号，把这块铁从头咬到尾。每个记号都要咬透。”巨兽看着眼前的材料，扬起笨重的脑袋，答道：“我并不想这么做。但是，如果必须做的话—！”坚硬的金属扭动着出来了，巨兽那嘎吱嘎吱响着的牙齿把它咬得滚烫。工作完成！“尽职的巨兽，看一下这块铁。你要沿着上面标出的这条越来越细的任意曲线，将它的边角削去。来，看看吧。”（沉浸在幻想中的）巨兽低下笨重的脑袋，像约翰逊博士[49]那般，贴近了去看那条标记线—贴得非常近，因为它有点近视眼。“我并不想这么做。但是，如果必须做的话—！”巨兽再次贴近看了看，瞄准。一条弯曲的铁板翻卷而出，就像一条火烫的紧紧盘扭着的蛇，滚落在灰烬当中。铆钉的制作就像是有趣的纸牌游戏，玩家是一个成人和一个小孩。他们将又红又烫的麦芽糖[50]浇进一个教皇琼牌戏圆形筹码盒[51]里，立刻就有铆钉从机器窗口落了出来。但那些庞大机器奏出跟这个大船厂乃至这个伟大国家同样的调子：“我们并不想这么做。但是，如果必须做的话—！”

战舰旁边放着一些锚，与战舰相比，显得非常小。它们是用来装在舰上的。像阿基琉斯战舰这么一个庞然大物怎能被这么小的锚固定住呢？这种航海技艺太神秘了，我要向那位博学的男孩求教。就我而言，我倒是联想到了将大象拴在帐篷桩上，或将动物园里的大河马拴在我的衬衫别针上的情景。在那边的河里，一条旧船的残骸旁边，躺着阿基琉斯战舰的两根中空的桅杆。我发现，光这两条桅杆的体积就已非常可观了，战舰的其他器具也同样庞大。我不禁疑心，为什么独独它的锚那么小？

对于这一点，我没有时间多做考虑。我要去看那些生产英国海军全部军用船桨的工场。我觉得工场的厂房非常高大，工作也非常漫长！那厂房很快就让我大失所望，因为工作都是在一间阁楼里完成的。而那漫长的工作—这是什么？两台大轧布机？一大群蝴蝶在它们上空盘旋？轧布机里有什么东西能够吸引蝴蝶呢？

走近些后，我看清楚了，那不是轧布机，而是两台复杂的机器。机器上装着各种刀、锯和平刨。它们把这里切得又平又直，把那里割得一溜斜歪；一会儿锯出一个深槽，一会儿又分毫不锯。这一切动作都是根据机器下放置的木材，按照预定的要求进行的。每根木材都要制成船桨，并早在它们离开遥远的森林故乡、起航来英格兰之前，就已经为此目的进行了初步加工。我也看清了那些“蝴蝶”其实并非蝴蝶，而是刨花木屑。它们受了机器强力的刺激，从木材上跳起来，并在机器旋转造成的气流冲击下，迅速而不规则地运动着，盘旋起舞、上下翻飞，情状恰似人想象中飞舞的蝴蝶。忽地，机器的噪声和动作戛然而止，“蝴蝶”纷纷坠地而亡。从我进来至此刻，一只船桨已经做好，只差手柄还未成形。我目光所及，心思乍动，那支桨就已经被送到了一台车床上。只一转、一刻！手柄已成。船桨已成。

整套机械那精湛之美和效率之高本无须解说，但今天恰逢一次突出展示。因特殊用途，需制造一副非常规型号的船桨，而且必须手工制作。就在这台精湛、灵巧的机器旁，在地上那个迅速增大的船桨堆旁，一个人用斧头造出了这对特制船桨。他旁边没有“蝴蝶”飞舞，他只是从容不迫地凿一凿、刻一刻，仿佛是个异教徒，正在为他的人生终点准备船桨，且要将这对桨作为礼物带给卡戎[52]，让他用在渡船上。就这样，那汉子（大约三十岁）勤奋地执行着任务。他擦拭额头的汗水时，就让机器制造标准桨。制桨的木材在机器上旋转着，切削下来的薄薄的宽木带随着分秒流逝，很快就集了一大堆。那使斧头的汉子还没做完一上午的工作，就可能已被那一大堆刨花埋住了。

看过这一奇妙景象之后，我又回到了船舰旁边，因为这个“厂子”最吸引我的就是船舰制造。我注意到，船台上晾着些半成品木墙板。它们将木与铁的价值比较问题悬置起来，带着傲慢自负的神情等待时机。在这些卓越的木墙板的旁边，有标签标出了它们的名字及其在枪炮制造中的功用—要是这种做法能推广应用到人类身上，将非常有助于人们在社交场合放松自在、心满意足。在一块下垂曲线优美却不太坚固的厚木板的帮助下，我大胆地登上了一艘（钉着铁螺钉的）运输船。这条船刚从承造商的厂子开进来，准备接受检查、获得认可。这艘船非常令人满意：布局简洁合理，十分便于军用；照明、通风、清洁设施完备；还周密地考虑到了妇孺之需。我在观览过程中，突然冒出一个念头：我愿意花一大笔钱，在船厂钟声敲响午夜时上船来，独自待到早晨。因为我相信，肯定会有一大群顽固刻板的老军官来到船上，悲伤地挥舞他们那纯洁的肩章，痛惜时代的变迁。然而，看过了这些当代造船厂中那惊人的运作方式与操作方法，我们便能更加透彻地懂得，在没有这些造船厂的时代，那些驾船出海、进行海战、控制海权的先人是多么可敬！意识到这一点后，我见到一条废船残骸时情绪极高。那条旧船的船身暗淡无光，打满了补丁，铜件上布满了绿锈。我对它脱帽致敬。一个脸上毛茸茸的年轻技师军官恰巧从此经过，他看到了我敬的礼，并窃为己有。我肯定，他由衷地欢迎我的敬礼。

被那些蒸汽动力圆锯、垂直锯、水平锯和各种动作古怪的锯（在想象中）切成碎片之后，我进入了这次考察的闲逛阶段，进而到达了我这一非商业性活动的核心环节。

我在“那个厂子”里到处漫步时，到处都能见到它那安静、谦恭品质的迹象。它那些红砖垒成的办公室和房屋显得非常庄重，毫不夸耀，有着一副“所做工作不值一提”的沉着外表。在英格兰之外，我从未见过这般迹象。除了偶然的几下回声，人行道的白色铺路石上没有丝毫迹象透露阿基琉斯战舰及其一千二百名敲击者（他们可都是在真砸实干）的存在。倘若不是空中传来几声微弱的回响，让人联想到锯末和刨花，你会觉得造桨作业和运转着的锯都在数英里之外。在这儿底下，有一个巨大的水库，木材浸泡在不同温度的液体中。这是干燥处理工艺的步骤之一。水库上面是一条支柱撑起的矿道，矿道上有一辆中国法师魔法车。木材浸泡完成后，这辆车就将它们吊起来，然后平稳地运到预定地点进行堆放。我小时候（那时我已经很熟悉这个造船厂了[53]）常常想，我很愿意扮作中国法师，并因而由一个仁慈的国家授予我那辆魔法车。如今，我仍然觉得，我很乐意试试在那魔法车里写书会有何效果。坐在魔法车里就彻底地与世隔绝了，而且在木材堆中滑来滑去会是一种很方便的国外旅行方式—从北美洲的丛林、洪都拉斯[54]那积水的沼泽、深郁的松林，到挪威的冰霜、热带的高温、雨季和雷雨狂风，全都经历一遍。在船厂竭力规避夸耀、以免显山露水的整体氛围中，这些珍贵的木材被堆置于幽僻之处，尽可能地毫不起眼，不对任何人召唤：“来看看我吧！”然而，这些木材是从全世界的树木里精选出来的，长度要选、宽度要选、直度要选、弯度要选，每一项都是依照造船之需挑出来的。那里还散落着许多歪七扭八、形状古怪的木材，可在造船工匠眼里，它们都非常宝贵。我漫步走过这些木丛，来到中间的一片空地上。工匠们正在那里检查一批刚刚运到的木材。在河流和风车的背景映衬下，这是一幅多么安恬的画面！哪里像是战争期间？就如同当今的美利坚诸国，哪里像是一个联邦？

我漫步走过制绳处，被旋织进入一种祥和的懒散之中。我的生命之索仿佛在此旋转过程中被拆解散开，让我回望到了很早很早的从前，望到了我的场场噩梦都是一种无休无止的编绳过程—那些恐怖的梦境缘何而起？甚至到我成年之后都仍然解释不清。那些极细极长的丝线搓编成股，这些股又在我的眼前紧紧编织在一起，令我尖声惊叫。随后，我穿过许多储存着帆、帆桅、缆索、船载小艇等物件的宁静仓库。我坚定地认为，有某个腰带上挂着一大串钥匙、被压弯了腰的人物掌管着它们，他像蓝胡子[55]那样，在需要某样物件时，就找出一把钥匙来，打开某个仓库的门。那些长长的库房似乎漠然无知，就让电池组来发送命令吧，那一扇扇百叶窗、一扇扇门将在瞬间大开，冲出一支全副武装的舰队，蒸汽腾腾、风帆满满，铺满古老的梅德韦河面，驶向大海，舰上所载值得观瞻。快活的斯图亚特[56]让荷兰人沿梅德韦河攻入，而他那些不那么快活的水手却饿死在大街上。就这样，我又逛回到了梅德韦河，正在涨潮的河水露出一副急切万分的神情，要冲进那个一千二百名敲砸者正在其中服侍阿基琉斯战舰的干船坞，不俟他们完成工作就连船带人一起掠走。

直至最后，“那厂子”仍然一脸宁静。我经过一小片树林回到了大门口。那片树林遮蔽了一处最奇特的荷兰人登陆点。一名造船工匠那落叶点缀的影子消失在小树林的远端，那可能就是俄国人彼得[57]本人的影子呢。于是，这个巨型专利保险柜的大门终于在我身后关上了，我又上了小船。看着船桨在水中出没，不知为何，我想起了牛皮大王毕斯托尔和他的同伙[58]，想起了“那个厂子”里那些安静的巨兽，以及它们说的“我们并不想这么做。但是，如果必须做的话—！”嘎吱。

（牛云平　译）

沃平[59]救济院

我那天无所事事，就去了伦敦东区[60]。我从考文特花园出发，朝都市的那个区域走去。经过东印度公司大楼时，我无意间想起了蒂普苏丹[61]和查尔斯·兰姆[62]。随后，我经过了那个小小的木刻海军少尉[63] ，亲热地拍了拍这位老熟人穿着及膝短裤的一条腿。随后，我经过了阿尔盖德水泵[64] ，经过了撒拉逊人头像[65] （而且可耻地在他那黑黝黝的脸上贴了好几张广告单来丑化他），逛进了他的老邻居黑（或灰）牛（或狗）[66]那空荡荡的庭院，不知这动物于何时辞世，也不知那些车舆流散到了何处。随后，我从那里出来，重新踏进铁路时代。随后，我经过了白礼堂教堂[67]，走进了商业路[68]—这对一个非商务旅客[69]而言很不适宜。我欢快地踩着那条大街上的遍地烂泥，尽情地观赏着制糖商的大片房屋、穷街陋巷两侧狭小后院里的小小桅杆和风向标、毗邻大街的运河与码头、沿着石路轰隆隆前进着的东印度公司大篷货车、手头拮据的大副们典当了那么多六分仪和象限仪的当铺。我真想便宜地买它几个，可惜这些仪器我丝毫都不会用。最终，我拐出商业路，开始向右前进，朝沃平走去。

我打算到沃平老阶梯[70]去坐船，去那里转转，原因并不是我相信（因为我并不相信）那个年轻女子坚贞如一。她用那些美丽的陈辞滥调，告诉她那航海的情人：自从送给他那个标着他名字的烟盒之后，她对他一如既往。我觉得，恐怕他从这种约定中得到的通常是最坏的结果，而且彻底上了当。

我要去沃平，是因为一位东区的违警罪法庭推事在晨报上说，在沃平妇女救济院的妇女都是一类货色，救济院本身的存在就是一桩丑闻和耻辱；他还讲了其他许多难听的话。我去那里，是因为我想看看事实到底如何。要知道，那些东区违警罪法庭推事并不都是伦敦东区最睿智的人，他们或许是在调查该地区圣乔治教堂[71]的奇装异服和怪模怪样时推出上述论断的。这种调查通常是在毫不混乱的思想状态下进行的。他们向有关各方和无关各方详询所涉事由；其最终的解决对策就是：咨询原告，问他觉得应该怎样处置被告，然后听取被告本人对自己的处理建议。

在离沃平尚远时，我主动迷了路，以一种土耳其人式的心情，弃身于褊街狭巷之中，任宿命以某种方式指引我到达预想的地点，倘若这在冥冥之中已然注定。大约一个小时之后，我终止了这命运的指引，决定费神看一看路，发现自己正置身于一架平旋桥上，桥下的脏水里有几绺深色的头发。在我上方对面，站着一个人，依稀像个小伙子。他毛发蓬松、脸色蜡黄，身上又脏又亮又粘，也许是他那肮脏的老父亲—泰晤士河的小儿子，或者就是那个淹死者本人。我和他中间隔着一根花岗石柱，柱子上贴着那死者的讣告，就像戴着一枚大顶针。

我就向这个幽灵打听，此地叫什么名字？他阴森森地龇牙作笑，喉间似乎发出了汩汩的水声：

“贝克先生的陷阱。”

在此类情境下，我向来十分警惕，要听得懂话里的机锋。我一边在心里琢磨此话的含义，一边密切注视着他—他抱着那几绺头发上方的一根铁横梁舔吮起来。我脑中灵光一闪，意识到贝克先生就是该地区的现任验尸官。

“人们都来这儿寻短见。”我说，同时将目光投向那几绺头发。

“苏？”那幽灵讶然盯了我一眼，答道，“没错！还有波莉。也有埃米莉。还有南希。还有简。”他每说一个名字就舔一下那根铁梁。“还有无素（数）银（人）。英（扔）掉帽子或头经（巾），跑几步，在这头槽（朝）下，她们就这么了。总系（是）在这头槽（朝）下，她们都系（是）。好像一点不。”

“你是说，在半夜一点左右？”

“哈！”那幽灵说，“她们可不挑系（时）候。两点也行。三点。一晚上。你只好好听！”说到这儿，那幽灵把身形靠在铁横梁上，讥讽地咯咯笑了。“可系（是），得有银（人）来。要系（是）没警擦（察），没啥男银（人），能听到扑通一僧（声），她们就不在这头槽（朝）下。”

根据我对这番话的理解，我本人就算个男人，或曰各色人群中的一员。我用普通人的谦恭语气问道：

“常常有人把她们捞出来，对吧？而且治好了她们？”

“我可没听学（说）气（治）好，”幽灵说。不知为何，他对这个词非常反感。“她们被送进求（救）济院，放进乐（热）浴缸，就醒了。我可没听学（说）气（治）好。”他说，“那系（是）胡学（说）！”话音刚落，他就不见了。

他显然已有不逊之意，而我也巴不得清静独处，尤其是他乱蓬蓬的脑袋那么一扭，表明“求济院”已经近在咫尺。于是，我离开了贝克先生那可怕的陷阱（其中放的诱饵就是一层浮渣，很像是清洗过乌黑烟囱的滑腻废水），鼓足勇气拉响了救济院的门铃。在这里，我是个完全陌生的不速之客。

来开门的是一位欢快机敏、身形小巧、手拿一串钥匙的女总管。她答应了我的来访请求。我注意到她那敏捷活泼的小小身材和聪慧的眼睛之后，开始怀疑那个违警罪法庭推事所言是否属实。

（女总管暗示）访客应该先看最差的地方。欢迎观看这里的一切。凡目所见，即为一切。

这是唯一的准备工作，我们随后就进入了“丑陋的病房”。这些病房位于一座老房子里，这座老房子被挤在一个石铺庭院的一角，与救济院那更现代更敞亮的主体部分保持着相当距离。病房所在的老房子极端落伍—就是几间粗制滥造、条件简陋的讨厌阁楼而已，唯一的通道就是几段又陡又窄、极其难走的楼梯，要将病人抬上楼或将死人运下楼可得费尽老劲。

在这些悲惨的房间里，这边的床架上，那边的地板上（我的理解是，她们是为了换个姿势），躺满了被各种程度的痛苦和疾病折磨着的妇女。她们的服色、姿态和状况都一致无二。只有那些专心观察过这种场面的人才能讲出这千篇一律外表下隐藏着的万般神情。这个人形微微蜷着，侧着身子，似乎已永远舍弃了这个世界；那个漠然不动的脸孔同时呈现出铅色和黄色，从枕头上消极地望着上空；那张枯槁的嘴巴有点下垂，那只露在被单外的手那么迟钝、冷淡，那么轻，又那么重；每张简陋的床上都是如此。可当我在一张床边驻足，对躺在上面的人说了一句那么简单的话之后，她本有的灵魂就浮到了脸上，令这间“丑陋的病房”变得与外面的完好世界一般多姿多彩。这里的人们似乎都不乐意活下去，可谁也不发牢骚。所有能够说话的人都说：这里已经为她们做了所能做的一切；院方的照料慷慨而耐心；她们苦难深重，但并无所求；这些恶劣的病房是同类用房里最干净、最美好的了，如果管得不好，不到一周就会成为传染病院。

我跟随那位脚步轻快的女总管上了另一段惨无人道的楼梯，来到一个略好些的阁楼间，这是给白痴和低能儿住的。这里至少有采光，而前一类病房的窗户就像中小学生的鸟笼的侧面。这儿的炉火上罩着一个结实的格栅，将炉前地面隔开了，两边坐着两位老女士，似乎正在举行某种仪式。她们虚弱地保持着庄严的姿态，那显然是出于仅存的一点自傲。自傲是我们这奇妙人性的一部分。很明显，她们彼此嫉妒，把全部时间（有些人也是如此，但他们的火焰没有被遮拦）都用于在内心诋毁对方和轻蔑地观看周围人等。在这对谑仿乡下贵妇的女士中，有一位极其健谈，而且表达了想参加礼拜日仪式的强烈愿望。她描述说，若能获得这一殊荣，她将会从中得到最大的乐趣和慰藉。她讲得非常精彩，浑身洋溢着愉悦、友好之情，我不由得开始思考，那位东区违警罪法庭推事应该重新调查此案例。不过，我后来得知，她上一次参加礼拜时偷偷带着一根小棍子，在轮流应答过程中突然拿出棍来痛打会众，制造了一起混乱。

就这样，这两位老太太整日隔栅而坐—否则，她们就会扑向对方的帽子—相互猜忌着，凝视着一个不断发病的世界：除了女舍监，屋里的所有人都会犯病。女舍监是一个上了年纪的穷女人，身体健全，上唇巨大，抱着两臂站在那里，似乎在压抑和节省自己的力气。她两眼缓缓转动着，在伺机抓住谁或控制谁。这位民间要人（我很遗憾地认出，她属于我可敬的朋友甘普太太[72]那一类型，只是块头小些）说：“她们常常分（犯）病，心（先）生。她们常常无因（缘）无故就摔倒了，好像拉车的马从月亮上掉下来似的，心（先）生。而且有一个倒了，另一个也跟着倒，有时候一下摔倒四五个。哎呦呦！又是打滚又是撕扯，老听（天）！—这个您（年）轻妇女，在这边，病得很厉害。”

她一边说，一边把那个妇女的脸转了过来。那妇女坐在地上，在那些饱受折磨的病人面前沉思着。她的脸上、脑中都没有招人厌恶的东西。周围的那许多各种癫痫和癔病患者看上去病情更重，但舍监却说她是最严重的。我对她说了几句话之后，她仍然仰脸坐着，沉思着。一束正午的阳光照进来，落在她身上。

—这个年轻妇女以及其他这些遭受着剧烈痛苦的妇女，当她们或坐或躺，茫然而迟钝地沉思时，是否在那阳光下的尘埃里，有一刹那想到了健康的人们、健康的事物？这个在夏季如此冥想着的年轻妇女，是否想到在某个地方有树木和花草，甚至有高山和大海？不说那么远的了，这个年轻妇女是否曾模糊地想到那个年轻妇女—那个不在此地、也永远不会来此地的年轻妇女，她被人追求、爱抚与热爱，有丈夫、生儿育女、生活在自己的家里，永远不会懂得遭到这种打骂和撕扯是什么滋味？上帝保佑，这个年轻妇女那时会不会自暴自弃、摔倒在地，就像一匹拉车的马儿从月亮上掉落？

在如此无望的地方，传来了婴儿的咿呀声。那些声音合成了一种声响，我分不清它令我愉悦还是疼痛。这声响是在提醒，这个疲倦的世界并非疲倦透顶，而是在不断地自我更新。就在不久之前，这名年轻妇女还是一个儿童；在不久之后，一个儿童有可能成为她这个样子。然而，那位机警的女总管活跃的脚步和眼神引领我经过了那两位乡下贵妇（婴孩们的声音扰乱了她们的高贵姿态），进入了隔壁的儿童室。

这里有许多婴孩和好几位漂亮的年轻母亲，也有丑陋的年轻母亲、愠怒的年轻母亲、冷淡的年轻母亲。不过，那些婴儿并没有任何难看的表情，他们柔软的脸庞非常可爱，有可能像是皇太子和长公主呢。我很欣幸地委托糕饼师的丈夫为我做了一件颇富诗意的事：以最高效率为我和一个红头发的贫儿做块蛋糕并投进烤箱。吃过蛋糕之后，我感觉好多了。要是没有这块点心，我真不知道自己的状态是否适合去看“那些犟人”。接下来，那位敏捷、小巧的女总管要带我去探访的就是她们。她竟在这个岗位上适应自如！此时此刻，我已对她充满由衷的敬佩。她引领我一路走去。

“犟人们”正在一个窗户开向院子的小房间里捡麻絮。她们背对窗户，排成一排坐在长凳上，面前是一张桌子，桌上放着她们的活计。年龄最大的“犟人”约有二十岁，最小的约有十六岁。在这类非商务旅行中，我至今也没弄明白，倔犟的习惯为何会影响人的扁桃体和悬雍垂。不过，我历来都注意到，凡是“犟人”，不管男女，无论阶层—从贫民儿童学校的贫儿到中央刑事法院[73]的法官—嗓音都一样，他们的扁桃体和悬雍垂都有着病态的优势。

“五磅！俺可捡不了五磅！”“犟人首领”说，一边用脑袋和下巴给自己打着拍子。“比俺们现在捡的多多啦！就彻冲（这种）地方、彻冲（这种）条件！”

（这是在承认，她们得到了微妙的暗示：工作量很可能要增加。毫无疑问，她们的工作量并不大，因为当时还不到两点，可一名“犟人”已经完成了当天的任务，正闲坐在那堆麻絮后面。她的头跟那堆麻絮一模一样。）

“总管，蛰（这）冤（院）子很飘（漂）亮，湿（是）不？”二号“犟人”说，“腰湿（要是）乃（哪）个姑娘说拘（句）啥，警察揪（就）来了。”

“然后你就无缘无故地净（进）了监狱！”首领说，同时猛扯麻絮，好像那是女总管的头发。“可哪嗬（儿）都比彻嗬（这儿）强；那样的话，就谢天谢地啦！”

麻絮头抱着两臂，领着“犟人们”大笑起来。她不主动发起什么，但却是那群未参与这场舌战的散兵游勇的指挥官。

“如果哪儿都比这儿强，”我那位机敏的向导极其镇静地说，“你本来有个好地方可呆，却离开了那儿，这很遗憾。”

“哦，从（总）管，哪里？俺没在好地方待过。”“首领”回答说，又扯了一下麻絮，表情丰富地看了一眼对手的额头。“可别那么说，那都是胡说！”

麻絮头又带着散兵游勇上来了，笑了几声，撤了。

“俺没间（见）过，”“犟人二号”喊道，“俺在一个低（地）方呆了死（四）年—俺不想栽（在）不湿（适）合俺的低（地）方呆—哼！不栽（在）不值得尊京（敬）的人家待—哼！俺发先（现）乃（那）家人表免（面）衣滔（一套）杯的（背地）衣滔（一套），酸湿（算是）有星（幸）还湿（是）没星（幸）—哼！腰湿（要是）我没边淮（变坏）没毁了，栽（在）很答（大）程都商（度上），乃（那）可不湿（是）他们的挫（错）—哈！”

她说这番话期间，麻絮头再次带领她的散兵放了几下冷枪，撤退了。

非商务旅行者大着胆子说，他估计“犟人首领”和“犟人一号”就是被送到违警罪法庭推事那儿去的两名妇女？

“对！”首领说，“就是俺们！奇怪的是，警察现菜（在）还没来，俺们就说起来了。彻嗬（这儿）没警察就不能昌（张）嘴。”

“犟人二号”（悬雍垂大幅振动着）笑了起来，那些散兵群起效仿。

“要是谁能把俺弄到哪个地方或扯（者）到国外，”首领斜视着旅行者声明道，“俺肯定会感激不尽。彻（这）个好透了的救济院让俺恶心，俺受够了，是的，俺有理由彻（这）么说。”

二号也是如此，也受够了。麻絮头也是如此，也受够了。散兵们也是如此，也受够了。

非商务旅行者冒昧地提示说，他觉得，若两位“犟人”领袖的自我描述准确真实，听了她们的这番表白，那些想找谦恭可靠的年轻佣人的淑女或绅士，哪个都不大可能乐意聘用她们二位中的任何一位。

“那待在彻嗬（这儿）啥都不是，又有啥好处？”首领说。

旅行者认为，也许值得一试。

“没用，啥好处都没有。”首领说。

“一丁点儿好出（处）都没有。”二号说。

“要是谁能把俺弄到哪个地方或扯（者）到国外，俺肯定会感激不尽。”首领道。

“俺也湿（是）。”二号道，“保争（证）感激不金（尽），俺灰（会）的。”

于是麻絮头站了起来，宣布了一个彻头彻尾的新主意，并说，她知道其新奇程度非同凡响，一说出来绝对会令毫无心理准备的在座诸位大惊失色：要是谁能把她弄到哪个地方或者到国外，她肯定感激不尽。然后，就像她随之指挥道“女士们，一起唱！”似的，所有的散兵都开始说起同样的话来。我和女总管随即离开了她们，开始在许多只因年老体弱而入院的妇女当中穿行。可是，在此穿行过程中，不论何时，只要我朝任一扇俯瞰庭院的窗口望下去，都会看到麻絮头以及其他所有“犟人”正在隔着她们那扇低处的窗户搜寻我。每次我刚一露头，她们马上就会看到我，从不失手。

十分钟之后，我再也不相信金色的青春时光、强盛的中年时期、矍铄的老年时段等神话。十分钟之后，所有的女性之光似乎都已被风吹灭；关于女性，天穹之下再无任何物事可资夸耀，唯余几粒微弱闪烁、行将死灭的灯花。

有一点非常特别：救济院里这些暗淡的老妇人们遵循着一种颇为通行的待客仪式。凡是知道有客来访而且并未卧床休息的老妇人，都会蹒跚到一个长凳跟前，坐到她常坐的位子上，加入到一排暗淡老妇人的队伍中，与一张狭长桌子对面的那排暗淡老妇人隔桌相望。并没有人规定她们必须如此排列，这乃是她们的“待客”之道。她们通常并不主动彼此交谈，也不看访客，什么都不看，只是沉默地坐在那里嚅动着嘴巴，就像一群乏味的老母牛。有些房间里，我能高兴地看到几株绿色植物；在别的房间里，有一位作为护士的、单独的“犟人”正忙碌着。跟别的“犟人”分开之后，她在这个岗位上干得很好。这些病房，无论是活动室、卧室，还是活动室兼卧室，都被精细地打扫得又干净又明亮。我同大多数类似的旅行者一样，见过很多这类场所，但还从未见过哪一家救济院这般整洁明亮。

那些卧床不起的病人极富耐心、极端依赖枕头下的书籍，也极其信仰上帝。她们都很在意相互之间的和谐，却没人在乎有无希望康复。总而言之，应当说，患有许多病症、病得比别人都严重在这里被视为一项殊荣。从一些窗子望出去，能看到泰晤士河生机勃勃地奔流不息，阳光明朗。可我没看到一个人向窗外眺望。

在一个大病房里，在火炉旁的两张特别的扶手椅上，坐着两位九旬开外的老妇人，宛似那群老妇的正副统领。其中那位年纪较小的刚过九十，耳朵聋了，但聋得并不厉害，能设法听到别人讲话。她年轻时曾养育过一个小孩，那个孩子如今也已经成了一个老妇人，比她还要虚弱，也住在这间房子里。女总管跟她说到这一点时，她完全理解总管的意思，脑袋和食指以各种姿势动作了一番，指出了她那个曾经的小孩。扶手椅上那位年纪较大的老妇人面前放着一张有插图的报纸（她却并没有读）。她已经九十三岁了，目明耳聪，身体健康，而且惊人地健谈。她的丈夫不久前刚去世，她本人住进来还不到一年。这位可怜人本可在马萨诸塞州的波士顿市得到特别待遇，在自己的房间里得到照料，并渐渐过上舒适的户外生活。在英格兰，一位在救济院外艰难地度过了九十多年的妇女，能在多大程度上过上类似的生活呢？不列颠经过无数乱局之后，顺应天意，崛起于蔚蓝大海之中，其守护天使何曾在那备受称颂的《大宪章》[74]中明确禁止这一点？

那位动作敏捷的女总管再无物事可示，我此行的目标也已达到。与她在大门口握手告别时，我告诉她：我认为正义女神未能很好地令她发挥作用，而那些东区的智者也并非绝对正确。

我踏上了归途，边走边与自己就那些“丑陋的病房”展开了辩论。它们不应该存在。在现场看过之后，没有哪个正派、仁慈的人会质疑这一点。可是这个联合教区该怎么办呢？对那些病房进行必要的改造会花费几千英镑的资金，而该联合教区已经在资助三个救济院了。为了存活下去，这些教区的居民们努力工作；他们需缴纳的扶贫济困税金已经达到了合理承受度的上限。该救济组织中的一个贫困教区每人要缴纳五先令六便士[75]。与此同时，富裕的汉诺威广场圣乔治教区[76]每人却只需缴纳约七便士，帕丁顿教区[77]每人只需缴纳约四便士，威斯敏斯特市圣詹姆斯教区每人只需缴纳约十便士！唯有通过均摊济贫税，才能解决现有方法未能解决的问题。我这些记录一次非商务旅行的文字篇幅有限，无法展现更多有待解决或者解决得不好的问题。然而，那些东区智者们必须先看看北区、南区和西区的情况，而后才能合情合理地对此发表长篇大论；他们应该每天早晨先到圣殿区[78]一带的商店和住宅转转，先自问“这些穷人还能承受多大压力？—他们中的许多人艰苦度日，免于落入救济院”，而后才能坐到所罗门的宝座[79]之上。在归途中，我还沉思着一件事。因为我最终离开“贝克先生的陷阱”那一带之前，曾敲开了东区圣乔治教堂救济院的大门，发现那是一个能给该地区带来高度荣誉的机构，由一位非常睿智的院长管理得井井有条。在那里，我注意到，顽固的自负和愚蠢能带来多大的间接损害。“我刚刚看到的老年男女贫民就是在这间大厅里聚合来参加礼拜仪式的，对吧？”——“是的。”——“他们有没有在乐器的伴奏下唱赞美诗呢？”—“他们很想那样，他们极有兴趣这么做。”——“一件乐器也弄不到吗？”——“是这样，本来可以免费得到一架钢琴。可是这些令人遗憾的纷争[80]——”啊！身穿漂亮长袍的基督教朋友，你当时若不理睬那些唱歌的人，让会众自己唱，这样做会更好，而且好得多！你应当比我更清楚这一点。但我觉得我曾读到过，从前他们就是这样做的；读到过，“他们唱了一支赞歌之后”，（并没有穿漂亮长袍的）某人上了橄榄山[81]。

一想到这件恼人的琐事，我就心痛不已。我在这个城市的街道上一路走着，每一块石头似乎都在对我呼喊：“老兄，转过来！看看该做些什么？”于是我诱使自己变换了思绪，让心里好过些。可是，我真的做到了吗？我至今都想不起来。我的脑中满是潦倒的穷人，乃至于思绪的变化终究只是从一千个贫民变成了一个贫民。

“先生，打扰一下。”他说。那是在另一个场合，这个贫民把我拉到一边，神秘地说，“我可过过好日子。”

“听你这样说，我觉得真遗憾。”

“先生，我要投诉院长。”

“明确说吧，在这里，我毫无权力。即便我有的话—”

“但是，先生，请允许我说说这事。就是一个曾过过好日子的人对您讲几句话而已。先生，院长和我都是共济会会员[82]。我不停地给他打手势，可因为我处境不幸，他却不肯给我口令！”

（牛云平　译）

东方的小星

昨夜，一直在翻看著名的木刻集《死亡之舞》[83]；今日，又想起画集中那些冷冰冰的古老的木刻画，心中竟生出一种阴森恐怖且乏味无聊的感觉。与此同时，在我的前方，正走着一个瘦如骷髅的人物，手里拄着的棍子不断敲击地面，发出刺耳的“嘎”“嘎”声。不过，这个“骷髅”不是在画中，他/她没有任何煞费苦心的装扮—他/她没有弹着洋琴，没有戴着花冠，没有拿着羽毛，没有穿着长袍，没有跟着队列，没有举着酒杯，没有吃着美食，没有玩着骰子，更没有数着金钱。我眼前的这个“骷髅”衣不蔽体，食不果腹，正挣扎着向前挪动脚步，像是在跳一曲坚韧不屈的死亡之舞。

这一幕发生在十一月的一个雨天，地点是伦敦东部莱特克里夫与斯特普尼两个小村庄接界的地方，混浊的泰晤士河从这里缓缓流过。河两边肮脏的街道和陋巷纵横交错，如迷宫一般；破破烂烂的房子大都隔成单间，专门出租。这里荒凉偏僻，到处都是腌臜的污泥、褴褛的衣衫和辘辘的饥肠。住在这儿的人大都没有工作，即使个别人有幸得到一份工作，也不会长久，失业犹如家常便饭。毕竟，无论从哪个方面来说，他们都算不上是熟练技工。他们是最最普通的靠体力吃饭的人—码头搬运工、滨水区小工、煤炭装卸工、道砟抬运工等，都是些做苦工的人。但不管怎样，这一群可怜的人儿还是活着，并且不断地繁衍着。

且看我眼前的这个“骷髅”，他/她好像正在跟谁开一个荒唐至极的玩笑。他/她把好几份早已被风雨撕扯得支离破碎的议会选举提案贴在很多面墙上，还用粉笔把候选人的得票情况写在一座破败不堪的房子的窗户遮板上。“骷髅”恳请拥有自由独立之身的穷人们要珍视当前的党政制度和国家的繁荣富足（看来两者对他们来说都非常重要），选举议员时不要只投一个政党代表的票；一党执政容易滋生腐败，若同时选举两党的代表为议员，则有助于建设一个永远兴旺昌盛的国家。想必天底下再没有比“骷髅”的这种修士想法更具讽刺性的了！

我不由开始琢磨此候选人和彼候选人以及人民群众的“赐福者”—此政党和彼政党所承诺的那些深谋远虑的规划。他们承诺，将会遏止成千上万英国人（谁知道到底有多少人？）在道德上的沦丧和体质上的衰退；将会为想工作想活下去的社区居民提供有效就业；将会均衡税率、开垦荒地、为想移居外地的人们提供帮助；最重要的是，他们承诺将会救助并重用未来的新人，以便使整个国家从日渐衰败走向步步强大。心里思索着这些看似充满希望的规划，我拐进了一条狭窄的街道，想去看看那儿的人家的生活。

这条街道的一侧是一堵残墙，显得光线非常昏暗。几乎每座房子的大门都敞开着。我走进其中的一座，敲了敲起居室的门，问道：“可以进来吗？”“想进就进来吧，先生。”

屋里的女主人（看起来是来自北爱尔兰地区）刚拿起一些长条木柴—大概是从废旧的码头设施或船只上拆下来的—塞进了原本空洞洞的炉子里，炉子上架着两口正等待烧开的铁锅，分别盛着一些鱼和一些土豆。木柴燃起来了，借着这火光我看到了屋里简陋的陈设：一张桌子，一把坏掉的椅子，还有几件廉价的破旧陶器摆放在壁炉台上。和女主人又说了好几分钟的话之后，我才看到屋角的地板上还有一堆极其难看的棕色物件。若不是以前见过，我可能真的无法相信这会是“床”。床上乱糟糟地蜷缩着个什么东西，我问女主人：“那是什么？”

“那是个小可怜儿，先生。她病得很厉害，已经很长时间了，一点儿也不见好。她总是白天睡不醒，晚上又睡不着。都是因为铅，先生。”

“因为什么？”

“因为铅，先生，肯定是因为在铅厂上工。女的在那儿上工，一天可以赚十八便士；但是得特别早去申请，而且还得够幸运，人家想要你你才有机会去。她是铅中毒了，先生。有的人刚上班不久就铅中毒了，有的过一段时间才会中毒，还有的，不过是少数，一直都不会有事儿。这全在人的体质，先生，有的人体质好，有的人体质弱。她的体质就属于那种容易铅中毒的，而且一中毒还就特别严重，先生；她的脑子都不中用了，总是头痛得厉害。天天就这样，不见好，倒也不见坏，先生。”

正说着，病中的年轻姑娘痛苦地呻吟起来。女主人俯下身，取下裹在姑娘头上的布带；接着，又推开后门，让阳光透进来，好晒晒这条用以减轻头痛的布带。从敞开的后门，我看到了这家人的后院，那是我所见过的最狭小最贫困的后院。

“铅中毒后，她就成了这样，白天黑夜地头痛，先生。这可怜的孩子，头痛把她害惨啦。上帝知道，我丈夫是个干体力活的人；四天了，他天天去街上转，现在肯定也正在街上转呢；他想找点活儿干，可就是找不到；家里没有柴火，没有吃的—除了锅里的那点儿，什么吃的也没有了；救济金又少，两个星期才不到十个先令。上帝保佑啊！我们这儿又黑又冷，穷得没法儿过啦！”

我本应该给他们一些钱，但我早就决定这次探访过程中不给予任何人任何物质上的帮助；因为我想做个试验：看看如果不给钱，这些穷苦的人会有什么样的反应。如果他们真的像我想象的那样淳朴善良，到时候再给也不晚。经过仔仔细细的观察，我敢肯定这家人一丁点儿都没有奢望我给他们钱。能有个人听他们说一说自己的痛苦他们已经很感激了；同情就是给他们的最大的安慰。他们绝不会伸手跟人乞讨，更不会因为我没给钱而感到一丝的惊讶、失望或憎恨。

女主人已成家的女儿从楼上的屋里走下来，加入了我们的谈话。她当天清晨去铅厂找工作了，但没能成功。她有四个孩子；她的丈夫也是码头搬运工，当时正在外面四处找活干，但估计跟她的父亲一样也不会找到。这个已婚女儿大概生长在英格兰，天生丰满漂亮，活泼开朗。她和她的母亲一样，虽然穿的衣服很破旧，但看得出来，她们都很尽力把自己收拾得干净整洁。她了解那些不幸的铅中毒病人的所有痛苦，了解铅中毒的方方面面，包括铅中毒的症状及病情的发展情况—这一切对她来说都太熟悉了。她说，一走进铅厂的门，那股气味就足以把人熏倒，但她还是想再去那儿应聘；除此之外，还能有什么办法呢？如果能长期在那儿上班，每天挣十八便士，就算有一天铅中毒了、不能动了，也比现在看着孩子们挨饿强啊。

再次环顾这个小屋，又看到屋角那个黑乎乎脏兮兮的用作床的橱柜。它几乎顶住了后门，看起来非常不协调。有段时间，一直是那个生病的年轻姑娘一个人夜里睡在那儿，白天躺在那儿。现在，天冷了，可毯子啊，被子啊，又都当到非法经营的当铺里去了，再当回来是不能了。为了取暖，到晚上的时候，女主人、她的丈夫，还有另外两个孩子只能和那个生病的可怜姑娘一起挤着睡在这个棕色的物件上。

尽管一分钱也没给他们，可这个穷苦的人家依然对我心存感激。临走时，他们满含着真诚的谢意跟我道别：“上帝保佑您，先生。谢谢您来看我们。”

走过几条街道，我又叩响了另一座房子里一间起居室的门。开门往里看时，只见一个男人、她的妻子，还有四个孩子正围坐在一个脸盆凳旁吃晚饭，那脸盆凳便是这家人的餐桌，晚饭也只有面包和一些喝完茶后剩下的茶叶。他们的身旁是一个壁炉，炉膛里的炭渣发出微弱的火光；房间里有一个带顶棚的床架，上面架着一张床，床上只有一条被子；房间的前后两面墙上分别有一扇可以通风的窗户，但现在为了驱寒却都紧紧地关着；屋里有一股令人作呕的气味。男主人在我进来时没有站起身；我们聊天时，他也一直都坐在那儿。不过，我进屋摘下帽子时，他倒是很有礼貌地冲我点了点头；说到能否问他一两个问题时，他也很爽快地答应了。

男主人的妻子一看就是个聪敏的女人，反应很快，见来了人儿，立刻起身站在丈夫的身旁。丈夫抬头求助般地呆望着妻子。事情很快就搞清楚了，原来丈夫的耳朵有点儿聋，尽管才三十岁左右，头脑反应已经很慢很迟钝了。

“他是干哪行儿的呀？”

“先生问你是干哪行儿的，约翰？”

“我是造锅炉的。”男人一边回答，一边万分茫然地打量着自己的四周，好像在寻找一个莫名其妙就消失不见了的锅炉。

“他不是技工，您知道的，先生，”妻子补充道，“他只是个干体力活儿的。”

“还上着班呢吗？”

丈夫又抬头看妻子，向她求助。“先生问你还上着班呢吗，约翰？”

“上班！”眼前这个苦闷的锅炉制造工突然大喊起来，像受到了惊吓一般瞪大眼睛看着妻子。接着，又慢慢地把目光转向我，说道：“没班上。”

“哎，确实没班上！”可怜的妻子摇头说道，目光依次投向四个孩子，最后又落在丈夫身上。

“上班！”锅炉制造工看看我，看看空中，又看看坐在自己膝前的二儿子，好像还在寻找那个消失不见了的锅炉。“真希望能上班啊！三个星期了，一天班都没上过。”

“那你们靠什么生活啊？”

听这样一问，这位曾经的锅炉制造工脸上隐约露出了一抹对妻子的钦佩之情。他一边伸出胳膊，让我看他那已经穿得露线了的外衣袖子，一边指着他的妻子，回答说：“靠我媳妇干活儿。”

我想不起造锅炉这样的工作都到哪儿去了，也想不起那位丈夫对这个问题所作过的猜想了。我只记着他当时的神态和表情都说明造锅炉的工作再也回不来了。

男主人的妻子很不简单，她开朗乐观，非常乐意帮丈夫来支撑这个家。她做的是廉价成衣的缝制工作，具体点说，是缝制双排扣男夹克。她把手头的一件衣服铺开在床上给我看—那床是这间房子里唯一能铺得下这件衣服的家具。她跟我解释自己已经缝了多少，还有多少需要机器最后来完成。按照她的计算，扣除针线等配料，每加工一件夹克能挣十个半便士；她一般情况下不到两天就能做完一件。

只是她没有办法直接从货主那里取货，货到她手上还得经过二道贩子，自然人家也不是白做的，还要从中扣钱。那为什么还非要经过二道贩子呢？为什么？是这样的：衣服拿走就有可能收不回来，这个风险由二道贩子来承担，他们取货时要交押金，比如说两英镑。她如果有足够的钱交押金，就可以直接从货主那里拿货，二道贩子也就不能再从中扣钱了。但实际情况是，她手里根本就没有钱，只能眼睁睁地看着二道贩子从中获利，自己的工钱因此缩水，只剩下十个半便士。她非常机敏地解释着这一切，没有丝毫哀叹，没有半句抱怨，那语气中甚至还带着些骄傲。解释完毕，她把衣服叠好，重新坐回丈夫身边，继续他们那顿只有干面包的晚餐。这家人的晚餐着实太简陋，没有餐桌，只能用脸盆凳代替；没有杯碗，只能用又脏又旧的瓶罐代替。这位妻子的穿着也很破旧，肤色也不好看，明显是缺乏营养，也需要好好梳洗打扮。尽管如此，她的身上却有着一种高贵的尊严，她是全家人的靠山，就像锚一样牢牢抓住丈夫这艘遇难的小船，使其得以安全靠岸。我起身要离开时，锅炉制造工的双眼再次慢慢转向他的妻子，似乎只有在妻子那儿才存有最后一线希望去找回那早已消失不见的锅炉。

这家人只申请过一次堂区[84]政府的救济金，那时丈夫受了工伤，实在无法工作。自那以后，他们就再也没有申请过。

往前走了没多远，我又来到位于一楼的一间屋里。女主人在我进门时满含歉意地连声说着“屋里太脏了，太乱了。”那天是星期六，女主人正在洗孩子们的衣服。她把一口锅架在炉子上烧着热水，而热水里泡着的正是孩子们的脏衣服。在这个家里，除了这口锅，再没有别的容器可以用来洗衣服了。在这个家里，没有陶盆、铁盆、木盆或木桶，只有一两个残旧的陶罐和破损的瓶子，还有几个当凳子用的破箱子。屋子的一个角落里堆着已用得所剩无几的一点儿煤屑，旁边是一个没有门的柜子，里面扔着几件破衣烂衫。屋子的另一个角落里放着一张老旧的摇摇晃晃的法国式铁架床，床上仰面躺着一个男人，身上穿着一件褴褛的双排扣夹克，头上戴着一顶运煤工人的粗油布帽子。屋子里到处都黑乎乎的，墙壁更是污浊一片，乍看上去，还以为是故意刷成了黑色呢。

女主人一边洗着衣服，一边说着抱歉的话。我站在她对面，注意到她连一块肥皂都没得用。我假装什么也没看见，故作随意地再次环顾这间小屋，又看到了几件刚进门时没能看到的东西：半磅面包孤零零地放在一个空荡荡的纱橱里；一件破旧的红色衬裙很随便地挂在门后的把手上；几块锈铁零零散散地扔在地上，看上去像是一段炉灶烟筒和一些已经用坏了的什么工具。一个大点儿的孩子站在那儿，正盯着这些废铁块儿在看。还有两个小点儿的孩子坐在紧挨着炉子的一个破箱子上，其中一个长得非常漂亮可爱，另一个时不时地探过头来亲他/她一下。

和刚刚在另外一家见到的那位妻子一样，这位女主人也是衣衫褴褛，面色萎黄，让人心生怜惜。然而，她姣好的身材，活泼的性格，还有脸颊上隐隐约约的笑靥，无不让我联想起多年以前在伦敦艾德菲剧院出演音乐剧《维多琳娜》的著名女星菲兹威廉夫人[85]。

“可以问一下你丈夫是做什么的吗？”

“他是运煤工人，先生”，女主人一边说着，一边扭头瞥了一眼躺在床上的丈夫，无奈地叹了口气。

“他失业了吗？”

“啊，是的，先生！他一直都很难，很难找到活儿干；现在，是彻底没活儿干了。”

“都是因为这双腿，”躺在床上的丈夫开口说道，“我要把裤腿卷起来让您看看。”说着便动手去卷裤腿。

“你们还有再大点儿的孩子吗？”

“还有一个女儿和一个儿子。女儿是做针线活儿的，现在正在上班；儿子就干些自己力所能及的活儿，现在正在外面找工作呢。”

“他们也住在这儿吗？”

“他们睡这儿。因为没有钱再去租房，他们晚上只能回这儿来住。房租对我们来说太贵了。现在，法律规定的房产税涨了，房租也跟着涨，一个星期六便士。我们已经拖了一个星期没交了。房东很生气，说要把我们赶出去；有时候就来踹门，把门晃得吱嘎乱响，怪吓人的。也不知道接下来会怎样。”

躺在床上的丈夫这时候插进来，凄苦地说道：“看我这双腿，肿得这么厉害，皮肤都有点儿涨破了。我还经常做举腿的动作呐。哎，不管怎么说，还算管点儿用吧。”

他低着头看了一会儿自己的那双腿（这双腿已经变得畸形了，腿上的皮肤也差不多已完全失去了光泽），忽然好像想起了这双腿在这个家里是不受欢迎的，于是赶紧把裤腿放了下来。那双腿就仿佛是一张早已过时的老地图或毫无价值的设计图一样，没有人愿意去查阅，去参考。这位丈夫无可奈何地躺回床上，拿帽子盖住脸，再也一动不动。

“你的大儿子和大女儿睡在那个衣柜上吗？”

“是的。”女主人回答说。

“和弟弟妹妹一起睡在那儿？”

“是的。我们得挤在一起取暖。我们的被子太少了。”

“除了纱橱里的那半块面包，你们还有别的吃的吗？”

“没有了。另一半我们在早上已经吃完了，就着白水。我不知道接下来会怎样。”

“接下来有可能会好一些吗？”

“要是我大儿子今天能挣到钱的话，他一定会拿回来的。那我们晚上就有吃的了；而且，说不定我们还能交点儿房租。要是没挣到，我不知道接下来会怎样。”

“情况很糟糕哦。”

“是的，先生。生活很难，很难。您要走啦！小心啊，台阶坏了！再见，先生！”

这些穷苦的人们得不到任何救济；但他们也不会去济贫院，因为他们对那儿充满了恐惧[86]。

在又一间出租屋里，我看到的是一位非常体面的妇女，还有五个孩子，其中最小的那个还不到一岁。这位妇女是本堂区医生的一个病人；为此，她的丈夫便在这家医院里干活儿。堂区间联合济贫院破天荒允许给她和她的家庭提供救济—每星期四个先令，外加五个面包。我想，当各位议员以及公众的“赐福者”—政党领导人最终达成协议，实现了均衡税率的承诺后，说不定她还可以多拿六个便士。到时候，她或许会合着这份“喜悦”，“欢欣”地跳上一曲“死亡之舞”吧。

此时此刻，我无法再继续探访下去了，我实在不忍再看到那些孩子们的眼神。我可以让自己硬着心肠去看大人们所遭受的痛苦，但当我看到那些孩子们时，我的心软了。他们是那么年幼，那么饥饿，神情却是那么严肃，那么宁静，我真的无法再看下去了。想到他们住在条件无比恶劣的巢穴里，忍受着病痛，濒临着死亡，我倒真希望他们可以毫无痛苦地离开人世。然而，他们不能，他们正在遭受着病痛和死神的折磨。一想到这些，我真的是心软了，再也不忍看下去了。

我沿着泰晤士河往前走，来到莱特克里夫村；又经由这里的一条岔路，回到了铁路边上。这时，我的眼睛被铁路对面的一块牌子吸引住了，那牌子上赫然刻着“东伦敦儿童医院”的字样。此时此刻，再没有什么能比看到这样几个字更能让我的内心感到安慰了。我横穿铁路，径直走进了这家医院。

这里看起来原本好像是个造船厂或者仓库。里面条件极端简陋，设备异常简朴。每层楼的地板上都有活板门，每个活板门上都吊着很多东西；陈旧的地板由于踩踏和推拉重物已变得坑坑洼洼；房间和梁柱的设计很是蹩脚；楼梯上下也不方便；因此要想顺顺畅畅地去每个病房看看就显得不那么容易。但是，这里通风很好，收拾得又干净，让人备感亲切和愉悦。医院里有三十七张病床，床上躺着的尽是些可爱无比的孩子，有的大一些，有的还不到一岁。由于饥饿，这些孩子们都面色苍白，形容消瘦。但是我看到，在这里，孩子们的痛苦得到了温柔的抚慰。这里的小病号们每个人都有一个顽皮可爱的昵称；照料他们的是一位十分温婉秀气的女士，她轻柔地帮孩子们撸起袖子，给我看他们那骨瘦如柴软弱无力的小胳膊。每次在她这样做的时候，孩子就会用自己那瘦弱无肉的小手亲热地抚弄她手指上戴着的一枚结婚戒指。

病床上一个刚刚几个月大的婴儿格外引人瞩目，他/她十分漂亮，犹如拉斐尔[87]画笔下的小天使。只是他/她小小的头颅上因为脑积水缠满了绷带，同时还患有严重的支气管炎。孩子时不时会不由自主地发出一声痛苦的呻吟；但这呻吟里没有焦躁不安，也没有抱怨不满。孩子双颊和下巴的线条柔美无瑕，仿佛浓缩了所有婴儿的美丽；那双又大又亮的眼睛更是可爱非凡。我站在他/她的床脚前，这双明亮的大眼睛便开始和我对望，眼神里充满了好奇与渴望—正是我们都熟悉的婴儿所特有的那种眼神。这双眼睛就那样执著地凝望着我，即使那小小的身躯因为痛苦的呻吟而颤动时，孩子的视线都没有从我眼睛上移开。孩子仿佛是在恳求我，要我把收容他/她、照料他/她的这家小医院的故事讲给我能遇到的每个善良的人听。我伸出自己历经沧桑的大手握住那只贴着下巴紧握着的未经世事的小手，心中暗暗承诺，我一定会把这个故事讲给我能遇到的每个善良的人听。

当年，是一对年轻夫妇—都是非常有修养的人—买下这栋楼，并把它改建成了现在这家令人称道的医院。这对夫妇从不张扬，只是静静地守在这里。事实上，他们便是这家医院的负责人兼医生。两个人无论是在内科还是外科方面都有着非常丰富的实践经验；丈夫曾经是伦敦一家大医院的外科住院医师；妻子曾经是医学专业的学生，她勤奋好学，通过了严格的考试，并在霍乱流行期间做过护士，负责照料一些穷困的病人。

凭着他们的资历，这对夫妇完全可以另谋高就。他们风华正茂，成就卓然，品位高雅，气质超群，与周围的邻居没有多少共同语言，与这里肮脏污浊的环境更是格格不入。然而，他们毅然选择了这里。他们的房间位于二楼，即使坐在餐桌前也能听到哪个孩子因为疼痛而哭喊。在这家简陋的小医院里，除了孩子们的病床，你还能看到钢琴、书籍、绘画工具以及其他一些只有文雅之士才可能拥有的宝贝。为了节省空间，这些宝贝都堆放在一处，只有哪一件被用到时，才会单独收拾出来，就像旅客排队上船一样，只能一个一个地来。医院的药剂师原本对这儿并不感兴趣，是这对夫妇的人格魅力以及他们所从事的这项事业本身的磁力把他吸引到了这里。药剂师住在餐厅内的一个小凹室里，他的洗漱用具只能放在餐具柜里。

他们很满足，因为他们把身边所有有用的东西都能充分地利用起来！他们很自豪，因为他们可以用自己的力量把楼内的空间分隔成一个个便利的小间，让白天的诊室摇身变成晚上的吸烟室；不仅如此，他们的候诊室里居然还放着一个朋友送的取暖炉呐！他们对医院周围的环境—如果能够摆脱掉楼后面那个令人不愉快的煤场的话—也很赞赏！他们还有一辆婴儿车，说也是一个朋友送的，非常有用。事实上，是我送的。楼梯下面有一个不大不小的角落正好作这辆婴儿车的车房。他们收集了很多很多的彩色图片—有的已经剪贴好，有的还没有—用以装饰病房。他们还有一只非常迷人的木刻小鸟，头上顶着漂亮得难以置信的羽冠，当你用手往上拨它的头时，小鸟就会忽地把头低下去。我去探访的那天上午，他们举行了一个小小的典礼，把这只小鸟立为医院的公共雕塑。医院里还有一只长相非常滑稽的杂种小狗，名字叫“卷毛儿”。“卷毛儿”经常在病床间穿梭着跑来跑去，小病号们对它都很熟悉。这只让孩子们精神振作的滑稽小狗是在医院门口发现的，当时它显然已经饿得不行了，医院里的人就把它带进来，给它吃的。自此，小狗便在这里安了家。不知哪个孩子，大概因为仰慕“卷毛儿”天资聪颖，给它脖子上戴了一个脖套，上面写着“不要以貌取‘狗’。”我看到这个不卑不亢的呼吁时，“卷毛儿”正站在一个男孩的枕头边上快活地摇着尾巴。

今年一月份刚开业时，人们都以为这家医院是专门有人出钱为他们筹建的；因此把医院提供的医疗服务视为自己应享受的权利，生气时还故意找碴儿抱怨。不过，他们很快就了解了事实真相，对医院的感激之情开始与日俱增。但依然不遵守医院的探视规则，那些母亲们想什么时候来看孩子就什么时候来，父亲们则星期天想什么时候来就什么时候来。这些父母们还有一个不合理的（不过在我看来也是可同情可理解的）做法：孩子病入膏肓时，他们通常要把孩子带离医院，回到自己那个条件恶劣的家里。有一次，一个男孩儿因为炎症严重而奄奄一息，父母便在一个雨夜把他从医院带回了家。这个男孩儿后来又被送回来了，并且经过一番艰难的治疗后居然痊愈了。不管怎样，现在这个男孩儿很快乐。我看到他时，他正在高高兴兴地享受自己的午餐。

食物不足和居住环境不卫生是这些孩子们生病的主要原因，因此治疗的主要方法就是补充营养，保持卫生和居室通风。对于已经出院的小病人，医院依然不忘照顾他们，经常邀请他们来吃饭；还有一些被饥饿折磨的孩子，尽管从来都不是这家医院的病人，也经常得到他们的邀请。这对医生夫妇不仅熟悉自己的病人及其家庭的状况，对周围很多邻居的性格特点和生活境遇也很了解，因为所有这些信息他们都有记录。这些穷苦的人们一步一步陷入越来越深的贫困境地时，通常会隐藏事实，甚至对这对医生夫妇也不肯透露，直到最后陷入绝境。

这家医院的护士都很年轻，年龄多在十九岁到二十四岁之间。尽管医院的条件有限，但护士们仍然有一间属于她们自己的舒适的小饭厅，这在很多条件良好的医院里都办不到。不过，能让这群年轻的女孩儿们坚定地留在这里的真正原因是：她们喜欢这些孩子，同情这些孩子的不幸遭遇—这是多么美丽的事实啊！技术最好的那位护士就来自附近的社区，家庭境况和邻居们一样贫苦，她尤其知道这项工作是多么重要。她原本是一位技术不错的裁缝，在这家医院一年的收入还比不上做衣服几个月的收入。医院的那位女负责人觉得有义务跟她说明做裁缝比在这里做护士要更有前景。但当有一天跟她说起这事儿时，这位女护士坚定地说“不”，她说在哪儿也比不上在这儿让她觉得自己更有价值，更开心；她一定要和这些孩子们待在一起。于是，她真的留下来了。我继续往前移动脚步，这时看到一位护士正在帮一个男婴洗漱。这位护士长得很喜兴，很招人喜欢，我于是停下来去逗弄她正照料的那个男婴。小家伙长得普普通通，圆头圆脑；此时，正紧皱着眉头，用一双湿滑的小手抓着自己的鼻子，身子裹在一个小毯子里，双眼神情严肃地盯着我。突然，这位小绅士踢了一下小脚，对着我笑了。与此同时，护士那张美丽的脸庞上也漾起了欣慰的微笑。看到这样的笑容，我之前那颗疼痛的心有些释然了。

几年前，在巴黎曾上演过一部非常感人的戏剧，名字叫《孩子们的医生》。就在我要离开这家医院时，突然发现我们的这位男医生可不正是“孩子们的医生”吗？那随意系着的黑色领带，宽松的双排扣黑色大衣，忧郁的表情，飘逸的黑发，那睫毛，那胡须，不折不扣，完完全全正是那位巴黎艺术家在舞台上刻画的理想医生形象的化身。但据我所知，还没有哪位传奇作家有胆量来描绘一下在伦敦东部这家儿童医院安家的这对年轻夫妇的家庭和生活。

我离开莱特克里夫村，在斯特普尼火车站乘车来到了芬丘奇街总站。我相信，不管是谁，只要按照这条路原路返回的话，都必将看到我刚刚所经历过的这一切。

（丁振琴　译）

业余警察在巡逻

我有一个癖好，即便是毫无目的的漫步，也一定要有一个目的地。每次离开我在考文特花园的临时住所前，我会给自己规定好，一旦出了门，中途就不能再改变路线，也不能半途而废，没到达目的地之前绝不能返回；这就像不能骗人，不能违背和别人的约定一样。这一天，我的目的地是莱姆豪斯[88]。按照事先和自己约定好的规则，我于中午时分，准时从家里出发了。

每次出来漫步，我都习惯把自己想象成是正在值班的高级警员，而漫步便是在“巡逻”了。遇到街上有流氓恶棍时，我会在心里想象如何抓住他们，并把他们赶出伦敦城。如果我真的能够抓住一个流氓恶棍，我一定会把他赶出去，并且告诉他别想再看到伦敦城。

正在“巡逻”时，我看到三个身形庞大、粗壮有力的绞刑师正走在回家的路上。我敢肯定，他们的家在特鲁里街的某个院子里，地方狭小转不开身；但他们住在那儿，就像我住在我的寓所一样，不会受到任何人的侵扰。看到他们，我心里突然生出了一个想法。我想象着自己作为一名警员，应该把这个想法恭恭敬敬地呈给新上任的首席司法行政长官—我完全相信他是一位可信赖的、能胜任的人民公仆。这时候，我不由想起：多少次，警察报告书里总是带有成见地给我胡乱扣帽子，我虽忍无可忍，却也只能把气咽到肚子里；多少次，警察告诉那值得尊敬的地方法官说某个犯人的同伙就住在某条街或某个院儿里，没有人敢从那儿走；那值得尊敬的地方法官一旦听说了那条街或那个院儿的恶名，便经常—比如说每隔两周—拿那条街或那个院儿当“教材”来教导大家。

现在，假设我们的首席司法行政长官给伦敦的各个警察分局发一则通知，要求他们立即将所有地区所有被吹嘘得那样可怕的街道或院落的名字全都报上来；假设我们的首席司法行政长官在通知中还有一条警告：“如果那样的地方真的存在，证明警察无能，要受到惩罚；如果那样的地方不存在，只是以讹传讹，证明警察懒惰，没去澄清事实，而是纵容这样的谣言，属于渎职行为，也要受到惩罚。”这样的通知发下去，结果会怎样呢？是谣言还是事实，只需用一点点常识去检验，答案便会清清楚楚。如果不厌其烦地告诉大家—直到大家都视其为平凡如旧闻如醋栗一样—像这样的历史上最为昂贵的警察制度在当前的伦敦，在拥有蒸汽技术、照相技术和电报技术的今天，依然存在，那我们和古老的斯图亚特王朝[89]还有什么区别？噢，如果各个政府部门都如此滞后的话，那么两年后我们可能退步到“大瘟疫”[90]时代，一百年后我们可能退步到“德鲁伊教徒”[91]的远古时代了！我的那个想法原来会给社会带来如此大的损害。

想到这儿，我不由自主地加快了脚步，结果不小心撞倒了一个骨瘦如柴的孩子。当时，这个可怜的孩子正一手提着破旧的裤子，一手抓着蓬乱的头发，赤着脚吧嗒吧嗒地在泥泞的石头路上跑。我停下脚步，把这个流着眼泪的小可怜儿扶起来，给了他一张钞票。立刻，我们被包围了。我估计差不多得有五十人，有男的也有女的。他们衣衫褴褛，饥肠辘辘，冷饿交加，浑身哆哆嗦嗦。他们先是讨钱，见我不给，就开始扭打着、翻滚着、吵闹着、尖叫着去抢那个孩子手里的钞票。他们像恶狼一样，凶狠地争抢着，那张钞票一会儿被这个抢去，一会儿又被那个夺走；很快，我便看不到那张钞票落到哪里去了。眼前尽是一片令人厌恶的混战场面，一片飘荡着的破衣烂衫，一片挥舞着的胳膊和腿，一片飞扬着的烂泥。至于那个刚刚被我撞倒的孩子，我在扶起他之后，就已经把他拉到了路边儿上。这一场钞票争夺战发生在围着板围和栅栏的一堆建筑物废墟上；确切点说，是在圣殿关石门[92]附近。

突然，从这群争抢者中出人意料地冒出了一名真正的警察，其他人立刻吓得四下逃散。这名警察东打一拳，西踢一脚，左抓一把，右挠一下，一个人也没抓住。见所有人都吓跑了，他这才摘下帽子，从里面抽出一块儿手帕，擦了擦脑门儿上的汗；之后，又把手帕塞进帽子，把帽子重新戴回头上。他那副样子，就好像是刚刚尽了一份重要的道义上的责任。的确如此，只是这一份责任他是为自己尽的—他抢得了那张别人不敢不放下的钞票。我看看他，再看看泥地上留下的那些杂乱的痕迹，不由想起了地质学家在悬崖壁上辨认出的那些古老久远的雨滴印儿和先人的脚印儿。我情不自禁地陷入了沉思：假设此时此刻这些带有杂乱痕迹的泥巴能够石化，假设这些石化了的泥巴能够在这里完好无损地久存一万年；那么一万年后，不借助历史的帮助，仅凭人类自己的智慧，我们的后人能否从这些痕迹中推断出下面这样惊人的结论：有一个国度，表面看来美丽优雅，可就在她的首都城市，却有一群挨饿受冻的孩子被她残酷地遗忘了；这个国度实力强大，并为其海权和陆权而自豪无比，却从不曾动用自己的实力去抓住并挽救那些孩子。

我来到了老贝利街[93]，沿着这条街往远处看，便是新门监狱[94]。我发现这座监狱看起来有点儿不协调。事实上，这一天似乎处处都弥漫着不协调的氛围。圣保罗大教堂[95]可谓是非常漂亮的建筑，可在我看来，还是有一点儿不协调。似乎教堂顶上的那个十字架太高，距离下方的那个金球太远了似的。

我转身向东走去，离开了土美菲路和老贝利街，离开了绞刑、游街鞭刑（把罪犯拖在马车后面，一边游街，一边用鞭子抽打）、火刑、柴把、监狱、颈手架、烙铁，也离开了祖先留下的那些美丽的建筑—可惜已被粗暴地拆毁了，幸好天上的星辰还依然如旧。我继续“巡逻”，发现了一个奇怪的现象：这一带的街区好像被一根无形的线隔成了很多块—这一块是银行和货币兑换行，那一块是航运公司和航海用具商店；这一块是几乎闻不到任何气味的杂货商店，那一块则是腥味浓烈的肉摊儿；不过最吃香的要数那些小针织品店，里面陈列的每一件商品都明码标价，就像已经被谁预定了或指定了要买似的。

在杭兹迪奇教堂[96]这儿，往东迈一步和往西迈一步，景象便截然不同。就像司各特[97]描述的卡农盖特街[98]一样，在那条街的尽头有一条不算宽的沟，欠债人只要迈过去，就算是进了荷里路德避难所[99]，即使法警就在眼前，也不用担心会被捕；但在沟的另一侧，就是另外一种情景了。在杭兹迪奇教堂这儿，往西迈一步，你可以看到货真价实的上着法国抛光漆的红木桌子或五斗橱，往东迈一步，你看到的则是像抹了一层护唇膏似的廉价的仿制品；往西迈一步，你可以看到规模很小但完全独立自足的面包店，往东迈一步，你看到的则是松松垮垮的只会跟人讨钱的懒汉。接下来，我的“巡逻路线”主要是围绕着白教堂[100]及其附近的炼糖厂一带。这里的建筑层层叠叠，很是宏伟壮观，像极了利物浦码头的大型仓库。离开这条路线后，我又向右边走去，经过左边那个死角转弯处时，突然看到一个幽灵般的身影，这个身影在伦敦的其他街道上也不陌生。

但不知为什么，经常在伦敦街头漫步的人们近来都没有看到过这个女人。今天我看到她，发现她的背因为脊椎的疾患更驼了，简直是在弯着腰；她的头也歪到了一侧肩膀的后边，几乎快垂到自己的手腕儿上了。谁都熟悉她的拐杖，她的披巾，她的篮子；谁都知道她除了脚下的路别的什么都看不见，只能摸索着向前走；谁都了解她从不乞讨，从不停下自己的脚步，永远都在漫无目的地朝着某个地方走去。但是没有人知道她靠什么生活，从哪里来，又要到哪里去，为什么要这样走个不停。我还记得，她那裸露的胳膊肤色蜡黄，瘦得只剩一把骨头和包在外面的一层羊皮纸般的肉皮。如今，这双胳膊似乎又有了一些变化—那皮肤看上去显得更斑驳了。她以前似乎总是绕着河岸大道[101]转，绕一圈大概有半英里长的样子。可今天，她怎么离开“轨道”，往东走了这么远？而且又在往回返。她究竟走了多少路啊？在这一带，她应该是罕见的一大奇观。这一点，从一条狗对她的反应上便可以看出来。那是一条长得不太对称的杂种狗，尾巴长得尤其滑稽。当时，这条狗正慢慢地走着，尾巴翘着，耳朵竖着，和它的“同胞们”（如果我可以用这个词的话）一样，令人觉得友好和善。这条狗在一家猪肉店稍作停顿，然后和我一样，慢步往东行进；它的面容和蔼慈善，嘴巴馋涎欲滴，仿佛在默想那肉的可口美味。就在此时，它看到了这个半弓着身子正向自己靠近的“包裹”。它虽没有受到什么惊吓，但还是有些惊奇—这个“包裹”居然会走路。它停下脚步，把耳朵竖得更直一些，又稍稍往前走一点儿，眼睛瞪得又大又圆，鼻头又湿又亮，嘴里发出一声短短的低沉的“汪”。我在一边看着，不由得心惊胆战。“包裹”继续靠近，狗“汪汪”地叫起来，转身想要逃开；可似乎又想到了“身为一条狗，怎能临阵脱逃”的道理，于是又转回身来，再一次面对那个不断向自己靠近的“包裹”。过了好大一会儿，狗似乎想起，这个“包裹”什么地方应该有一张脸吧？这一次，它孤注一掷，决定冒一下险，找找看看。于是，狗慢慢走近“包裹”，慢慢绕着“包裹”转了一圈，终于在一个不应该的地方找到了那张人脸。狗恐惧地嗥叫一声，便飞快地朝着东印度码头[102]方向逃去。

现在，我“巡逻”到了商业路[103]一带。想到斯特普尼火车站就在附近，我不由加快了脚步，因为火车站的另一侧不远处就是我那颗“东方的小星”，我要顺路去看一看那颗“小星”是否依然在明亮地闪烁。

“东方的小星”是我给伦敦东部一家儿童医院起的名字。再次来到这里，我发现这颗“小星”果然依旧明亮，这家医院果然依旧发挥着重要作用。医院里的床位都满了。我上次见到的那个天使般美丽的婴儿已经永远地睡去了，他/她躺过的那张床上现在是一张新面孔。看得出来，我上次离开后，又有很多好心人来过这里。医院的墙上装饰了好多好多布娃娃，让人看了很是愉快。那些娃娃们伸着手臂，睁着大眼睛，展示着自己漂亮的裙子。不知道“卷毛儿”看到这些娃娃，会有怎样的反应。不过，“卷毛儿”的兴趣好像主要在小病号们身上。它就像是一名医生，在病床间走来走去，身旁还跟着一条小狗—大概是朋友，仿佛它的实习助手一样。“卷毛儿”急切地领我去看一个漂亮的小姑娘。小姑娘看起来非常健康，实际上却因为膝部患癌刚刚做了截肢手术。“卷毛儿”摇着尾巴在她的床单上蹭来蹭去，似乎在向我暗示：你看，亲爱的先生，这个截肢手术很不容易，但非常成功！小姑娘拍拍“卷毛儿”，微笑着开口说：“这条腿给我带来很多麻烦，我很高兴把它弄走了。”我们又来到另一个小女孩儿的病床前，小女孩儿张开嘴，让我们看她异常肿胀的舌头。这时候，“卷毛儿”正卧在一张桌子上，和小女孩儿一般高；它满含同情地伸出自己的舌头，神情严肃地看着小女孩儿，眼神里充满了理解和怜爱。我从没有见过哪条狗能像“卷毛儿”这样有风度、有修养，真想把手伸进口袋，拿出一基尼钱，用纸包好，放进它的嘴里。

离开儿童医院，我来到了莱姆豪斯教堂附近，这将是我“巡逻”的最后一站。我发现离这儿不远处有几家“铅厂”。“铅厂”这个名字吸引了我，这个名字在我的脑海里仍记忆犹新。第一次作为“非商务旅客”探访东伦敦儿童医院及其附近地区时曾听人说起“铅厂”。经过了解，这里的铅厂和当时听人说起的那些“铅厂”没有什么不同。于是，我决定去看一看。

接待我的是一对聪颖灵敏的兄弟，他们和自己的父亲一起经营这家铅厂。兄弟俩非常欢迎我来参观，而且表示我可以随意看，我便仔细地“巡逻”了一下这家铅厂。铅厂工作的主要目的是将铅锭转化成白铅粉。这个转化要通过铅本身的一种连续的化学变化而慢慢地逐渐地来实现。但整个加工过程别开生面，非常有趣；最有意思的要数其中的一个准备环节：把铅锭分别埋进很多个罐子里—每个罐子里还要放一定数量的酸类物质，再把所有罐子一层一层地全部埋到鞣皮下，存放约十个星期。

我爬上一架又一架梯子，穿过一块又一块木板，登上一个又一个高台；到最后，我都不知道我是像小鸟呢，还是更像砌砖工人。不管怎样，我终于可以在一个立足处停下来了。脚下是一排又一排的大阁楼；站在这里可以清楚地俯看其中一个阁楼里的景象，阳光也透过阁楼顶上砖瓦的缝隙斑驳地照着里面。有许多女人正在那里上上下下地忙碌着；每个上来的女人都扛着一个已经放好了铅和酸的罐子，准备把它埋在冒着热气的鞣皮下。一层罐子放满后，便在上面小心翼翼地盖上木板，再在木板上面小心翼翼地盖上鞣皮；然后，开始放第二层罐子……每一层都设有木管儿，保证通风良好。阁楼里的罐子快放满时，我从自己站的地方下来，走进这个阁楼里面。我发现那鞣皮的温度高得惊人，铅和酸混合发出的味道非常难闻，尽管在这个阶段可能还不至于有毒。在有的阁楼里，罐子已经挖出来了，那儿的鞣皮的热度还要高得多，味道也更刺鼻，更怪异。每一层楼都有很多这样的大阁楼；有的里面放满了罐子，有的里面只放了一半，还有的里面则完全空着；身体强壮、动作敏捷的女人们上上下下里里外外地忙碌着。这情景就像是在一个土耳其富翁家里，听说苏丹或巴夏[104]要来，富翁那些忠诚的后宫佳丽们便赶紧上楼忙着把家里的金银财宝藏起来。

和绝大多数的矿粉或颜料粉一样，白铅粉的加工程序也很繁杂，搅拌、离析、洗涤、研磨、滚搓、挤压，一道工序都不能少。毫无疑问，这其中有些环节对人体健康是非常有害的，其主要危险在于吸入铅微粒或皮肤与铅直接接触。为了消除这些危险因素，铅厂为工人们配发了很好的口罩（用法兰绒和棉布缝制而成，更新成本较低，而且还可以用香皂清洗）、防护手套以及宽大的长外衣。厂房尽可能多地安装了窗户，安装的位置也很合理，因此通风条件非常好。根据以往的经验，也出于对铅中毒的担心，这家铅厂还首创了一项安全措施，即经常轮换在最危险的环节工作的工人。据说，这项安全措施非常有效。在最危险的环节工作的工人们穿戴独特而神秘，个个蒙着口鼻，穿着宽宽大大的长外衣。这样一来，就更符合我前面用的那个比喻了—土耳其富翁的后宫佳丽。

这令人伤脑筋的白铅粉，经过埋存、挖掘、加热、冷却、搅拌、离析、洗涤、研磨、滚搓、挤压等程序，终于到了最后一个环节—高温烘烤。蒙着口鼻，穿着长外衣，犹如土耳其富翁的后宫佳丽的女工们在一个很大的石制烘房里站成一排，像在帮厨师传菜一样，一个传一个地将烤盘放到烘箱里。这个时候的烘箱（或者叫炉窖）还是冷的，看起来有房子那么高，里面有很多临时立脚处，站满了男工和女工；他们敏捷地传递着烤盘，迅速地将烤盘在炉窖里放好。另一个刚用过的烘箱（或者叫炉窖）现在已经快冷却下来了，里面的烤盘也差不多全都取出来了，铅厂负责人把顶上的一扇门打开，以便我这个来访者可以从上面观看烘箱（炉窖）里面的情形。我刚一探头，就忍不住立刻缩了回来；那炙热的气息，那刺鼻的气味，让我有一种要窒息的感觉。这么看来，铅加工过程中，最危险的环节便是进入炉窖里面工作—尽管此时炉窖的门已经打开，新鲜的空气已经进来。

但可以看得出，铅厂负责人的的确确做了很多细心周到的工作，以期将铅中毒的危险降到最低。

厂内有专供女工洗浴的浴室（我原以为只是毛巾比较多而已）；还有专门用于挂衣服、吃饭的房间；房间里有很好的炉灶，那炉火烧得正旺。厂家还配备了一名女服务员来给女工们帮忙，并监督她们在触摸食物前一定不要忘记把手洗干净。此外，还为她们配备了一名经验丰富的医疗护理人员；一旦谁有铅中毒的先兆症状，便可以得到及时的妥善的治疗。我看见女工们的房间时，她们的茶壶以及其他喝下午茶的用具都已经摆好了，很有家的样子。这些女工们比男工更能承受这份工作，她们当中有几个已经在这儿干了好几年了；绝大多数女工都很强壮很泼辣。当然，另一方面，她们大多数人也都很任性很随意，上班时想来就来，不想来就不来。

美国的发明家们好像说过：不久的将来，白铅粉的加工冶炼有可能完全由机器来完成。那么，越早越好。和陪我参观的那对坦诚的兄弟告别时，我跟他们说他们没有什么需要隐瞒的，也没有什么可指责的。至于其他，诸如铅中毒的问题，诸如工人们的种种说法，我想完全可以用我在“东方的小星”那篇文章里提到的那位爱尔兰妇女的话来总结：“有的人刚上班不久就铅中毒了，有的过一段时间才会中毒，还有的，不过是少数，一直都不会有事儿。这全在人的体质，先生，有的人体质好，有的人体质弱。”

我要顺原路回家，不再“巡逻”，我“下班”了。

（丁振琴　译）

死亡交易

几年前，很多颇具理性的人们开始清楚地意识到，英国人在丧葬礼俗方面已陷入一种非常可悲的局面。在葬礼上嚣张炫耀、挥霍浪费已渐渐成为一种风气；而这种做法不但不能为死者的名誉增光添彩，还会给生者带来极大的耻辱，因为它将人生中最庄严肃穆的时刻与虚伪的仪式、可耻的负债、铺张的浪费及极度的不负责任紧密联系在一起。对这件事情越是考察得仔细，越是考察到社会底层，便越是觉得这些丧葬礼俗荒谬丑恶；不仅其本身是这样，其后果亦然。任哪一个社会阶层都逃不过去。中产阶级在举办葬礼时互相攀比，排场摆的越大，越显得体面；而那些丧事承办者们便趁机胡作非为，大捞一把。这种风气已蔓延至穷困的社会底层；对于他们来说，举办葬礼所需的费用与收入完全不成比例，足以让他们倾家荡产。为了支付这笔费用，他们只好联合起来，组成所谓的“互助会”。但很多“互助会”的管理者是诡诈狡猾的流氓恶棍，经常欺负这些穷苦的弱者，用非常残酷的手段欺骗他们，压榨他们；还有一些“互助会”，因为对那些最坏最邪恶的“互助会”构成一种新的诱惑，以致引发了一种新的以金钱为目的的谋杀，其罪恶深重至极，即使最为严厉的语言都不足以斥责这种罪孽。一切就绪，丧葬礼俗的邪恶、虚伪及荒谬，俨然已到了无以复加的地步。于是，这滑稽可笑的真相便全部暴露无遗了。无数残忍贪婪之士自称可以提供各种丧葬用品，实则一件也不曾拥有；他们只是真正丧葬用品提供商和殡仪服务员的中间人，他们从丧葬用品商那里租来各种设备，然后就像救火时挨个儿递水桶那样再把这些设备一个传一个地租出去；自然，每个中间人都可以从这份“黑色交易”中大捞一笔。此外，大家都想方设法要把逝者埋葬在本已很拥挤的城镇中，这很明显会给生者带来多么可怕的后果；再加上城镇里的墓地非常有限，墓地所有人又个个贪得无厌，这便又导致了一种有伤风化、恐怖至极的做法，这种做法令我们常人十分憎恶，同时也令我们这个时代以及我们的国家非常丢脸。综上所言，这种贻笑大方的丧葬礼俗可以说已经可悲到了极点。

若不是丧葬礼俗的荒谬可悲已凸显得如此明显，我们恐怕也还正在这个极端堕落的旋涡中苦苦挣扎。现在，我们完全相信，中产阶层中有很多人已通过相关议会文件了解到了丧葬礼俗中的这些恶行，他们不会再将这种坏习俗继续保持下去了；相反，他们将把这种坏习俗作为严正的训谕，告诫最最亲密的下一代人不要将自己的死，自己的葬礼变成腐蚀他人身心的工具。这样的例子，在很多知名人士中并不少见。已故的苏塞克斯公爵为国家利益着想，表明自己过世后，希望以私人形式葬于肯萨尔绿色公墓，不希望举行国葬，亦不希望下葬于温莎堡王室墓地。已故的罗伯特·皮尔[107]爵士要求过世后葬在德雷顿墓园。已故的孀居王后[108]曾就自己的葬礼写下这样的话：“在上帝的御座前，我们每个人都是一样的，我的死亦不足称道；因此，我死后，请不要为我举行盛大奢华的葬礼；请尽可能不要公开，尽可能以私人形式将我的遗体安葬于温莎堡圣乔治教堂。我尤其不希望举行国葬；我静静地死去，亦希望静静地下葬，希望能够远离世界的虚荣和奢华。请不要对我的遗体进行解剖和防腐处理；我希望越简单省事便是越好。”这番话写得令人钦佩令人感动，实在是社会各阶层举办葬礼的最好典范。

这些先例在人们的丧葬礼俗常识中尚属鲜为人知，再加上我们正处于新旧历史交替的时期，那原本已黯淡下去的国葬仪式又开始死灰复燃，美其名曰是为了对已故的威灵顿公爵[109]表示敬意，为了对所有那些在英国历史上留下辉煌记忆的风云人物表示敬意！

在这里，我们想真诚地奉告各位读者：国葬仪式的恢复，不是也不可能是一种荣耀；越是真正伟大的人物，其葬礼越是简单平凡；国葬仪式助长了各种腐化的“死亡交易”，自始至终都不是丧葬礼俗的好榜样。

所有民众，不论其政治主张如何，都明白那些“实权人物”是否曾参与“国葬交易”—是否力图保全国葬仪式，是否视国葬仪式为宝贝，是否充分利用国葬仪式为自己谋利，是否舍不得国葬仪式悄然离去。关于这个问题，我们在这里不想过多讨论。

但国葬仪式的死灰复燃却唤醒了民众借死亡做交易的风气，这种交易与现实格格不入，是那么愚蠢无知，那么荒谬可笑。以下是我们从《泰晤士报》的广告栏摘取的若干例子，以供广大读者评鉴。

首先，关于观看葬礼的席位及观看葬礼时可享用的茶点。某广告称，二楼设有观看葬礼的场所，宽敞舒适，可以举办由钢琴现场伴奏的豪华宴会，这个我们暂不去细看；我们先来看看那“高雅得体”的“每日启事”的内容：“威灵顿公爵葬礼专供红酒”，供不应求，如有需要，请马上订购；“威灵顿公爵葬礼专供蛋糕”，美味可口，由××糕点师专门烘焙；“葬礼寿衣”，由××裁缝师专门缝制；“远近驰名的柠檬饼干”，最能有效缓和悲痛情绪，每磅一先令四便士……接下来，我们逐个看看报纸上刊登的这十几条广告—这众人可以赚钱的大好良机。

路德门山—这里设施齐全、装备完善，可供观看威灵顿公爵盛大壮观、肃穆庄严、震撼人心的出殡仪式。若想拥有开阔的视野、便利的条件、舒适的空间，敬请抓紧时间，查看预定尚余座位。

观看葬礼，有床位提供—出租。位于三楼，共三个房间，两个窗口，视野开阔，可供观看出殡仪式。收费十基尼，含茶点。单个席位，最低收费十五先令，含床位和早餐。

观看公爵葬礼—一流的视野，可供十五人观看，提供床位和起居室，干净舒适，价格合理。

出租葬礼观看席位和窗口—位于河岸大道，库茨银行附近，位置绝佳。二楼窗口，收费八英镑；三楼窗口，收费五英镑十先令；四楼窗口，收费三英镑十先令；另有两扇玻璃橱窗，各收费七英镑。

威灵顿公爵葬礼观看席位—位置绝佳，可观看整个出殡仪式，视野一览无余。位于老贝利街附近。注：从这里可看到圣保罗大教堂及圣殿关石门。

观看已故威灵顿公爵葬礼—出租，位于三楼，两个窗口，有壁炉，设施齐全，条件便利。团体观看，价格优惠。前排观看座位，每位一基尼。视野所及范围：皮卡迪利大街—帕尔摩街。

观看威灵顿公爵葬礼—二楼三楼出租，可按房间或观看窗口租用，尤其适合家庭观看。设施齐全，舒适便利，视野绝佳。一楼亦设有舒适便利的观看席位，最低价格一基尼。适于室内观看。

观看公爵葬礼—价格优惠。二楼设有两个房间，有观景阳台，可直接通向河岸大道。大房间可容纳十五人。小房间八基尼起租。

观看公爵葬礼—橱窗出租，约三十个座位，共二十五基尼。二楼亦设有两大观看窗口。其中一个视野颇佳，视野所及范围可从圣殿关石门直到圣保罗大教堂，收费三十五基尼。此外，还有几个单人观看座位，每位一基尼。

观看威灵顿公爵出殡仪式—位于查林十字路，科克斯普尔街，位置得天独厚，尚余空位若干，价格合理。因座位紧俏，需尽快预定。另：楼顶亦设有座位若干，视野颇好。

观看已故威灵顿公爵葬礼—出租，位于河岸大道，位置绝佳，三楼，收费十英镑；四楼，收费七英镑十先令，每层各设有两个观看窗口；前排座位抢先预订中，每位一基尼。

观看公爵葬礼—出租，二十五基尼，专为上流社会家庭开设，视野广阔，位置绝佳，二楼房间，设有安全阳台及会客室。可容纳二十人，视野开阔无遮挡。若人员不足二十人，可酌情减价。设施齐全，条件便利。

此外，我们要特别注意下面这则广告：

T.C.敬请各位牧师注意—河弯街专门为各位牧师预留了席位，敬请各位牧师入场时着白法衣。第一排四个席位，每位一英镑；第二排四个席位，每位十五先令；第三排四个席位，每位十二先令六便士；第四排四个席位，每位十先令；第五排四个席位，每位七先令六便士；第六排四个席位，每位五先令。所有剩余席位的价格分别是：四十先令，三十先令，二十先令，十五先令和十先令。

这位商人真是富有想象力，他安排二十四位牧师分坐六排，希望以此在自己的橱窗里营造一个神圣而动人的画面，这种创意似乎非常不错；且还能让人觉得他眷顾到了丧礼场合的庄严肃穆的特点。

同类的广告有许多许多，上述几则是随意摘来的，其中很多关于视野范围的描述并不真实，无非是想吸引那些愿意掏腰包的先生们来和自己志趣相投的人儿完成一次集会。为了这样的集会，他们已做好了充分的准备：茶点、红酒、白酒、食物、水果、盘子、杯子、各种瓷器，以及其他许多不胜枚举的小玩意儿；而最最重要的是，他们对这样的集会全部都是热情高涨、激情满怀。我们仔细观察这些人群，时不时地会大吃一惊，尤其当我们看到那件所谓的艺术品时。话说这件艺术品上刻有一句话“渴盼夜晚到来，渴盼布鲁奇王子到来”[110]，旁边还注有传奇故事，讲述的是这位正被大家悼念着的英雄—威灵顿公爵如何评价这件艺术品：英雄以他特有的语气语调评论说“很好，的确很好。”哦，艺术！你也来参与“死亡交易”啦！

接下来，我们再来看看有关逝者亲笔信的广告。私人印章的神圣性、私人信件的私密性，对于“死亡交易者”来说，毫无意义；在他们的字典里，根本就没有这样的词汇。现在，就让我们停下来，听一听送殡的喇叭如何向全世界公开这位逝者独有的亲笔信！

威灵顿亲笔—公爵接连写下的两封回信，绝对真迹（1843），颇具特色；另外还有那两封来信等，

称得上文学珍品，售价十五英镑。

威灵顿亲笔—转让威灵顿公爵亲笔信两封。一封写于沃尔默城堡，时间：1834年10月9日；另一封写于伦敦，时间：1843年5月17日。邮戳及公爵印章均完整无缺。

威灵顿—出售威灵顿公爵便笺三封，有公爵印章、信封。系公爵亲笔书写，非平版印刷；每封便笺长度约2¼页。在迄今已公开的公爵亲笔信中，当属最具公爵特色的真迹。售价：两封三十英镑，一封二十英镑，不讲价。

转让—某退役军官欲转让已故英雄威灵顿公爵的亲笔信和便笺，共五封，其中有三封系公爵当年被称为阿瑟·韦尔兹利爵士时所写。另有一大信封。所有信函、便笺及信封均盖有公爵印章。可现场购买，亦可来信进行交易。

公爵信函—出售公爵亲笔信两封，货真价实，内容风趣幽默，颇具特色。

威灵顿公爵—公爵写给某位女士的亲笔信，颇具公爵风格，有印章、信封。出价高者优先。现场交易。

陆军元帅威灵顿公爵—已故威灵顿公爵家族成员，现有公爵给其所写的亲笔信一封，内容涉及军务，长达六页，保存完好。售价三十英镑。

陆军元帅威灵顿公爵亲笔—转让颇具特色的公爵亲笔信一封，信中公爵曾提及自己将活到一百岁，写于1847年，有信封，印章及家族饰章均保存完好。售价十英镑。

威灵顿公爵—出售威灵顿公爵亲笔信，写于1831年公爵夫人刚刚去世之际；另有两个公爵亲笔书写的信封，邮票、印章均保存完整。

威灵顿公爵—公爵亲笔公务信函，信封、印章、邮戳等均保存完整。信函风格彬彬有礼、独具特色。请按所示地址来现场交易。售价十五英镑。

陆军元帅威灵顿公爵—出售公爵亲笔信两封，一封系公爵六十一岁时所写，另一封系七十二岁时所写，笔迹独具公爵风格，内容涉及重要话题。确保货真价实，敬请放心。

威灵顿公爵—公爵写给某位女士的一封信函，该信函部分由打印机打印而成，部分由公爵亲笔书写，奇特异常，实属绝品，值得珍藏。出价最高者优先。

出售陆军元帅威灵顿公爵亲笔信六封—系有人慷慨解囊，赠与了某位身陷贫困的女士，信封、印章均完好无缺。

威灵顿公爵—一位女士欲转让公爵亲笔信一封，写于今年6月18日，恰逢滑铁卢战役[111]周年纪念日，也是公爵度过的最后一个滑铁卢战役周年纪念日，因此倍加珍贵。信函写于阿普斯利公爵宅第[112]，信封、印章均保存完好。

一位牧师，欲转让已故公爵写给自己的亲笔信两封，系公爵私人慈善行为的极好见证，有信封，出价最高者优先（可买一封，亦可买两封），本月18日前有效。若有特殊情况，价格可商量。

威灵顿公爵—一位悲痛的孀妇，现有威灵顿公爵亲笔信一封，写于1830年，有信封，上面写有收信人姓名和地址，还有公爵冠冕形印章，欲低价出售。

一位先生，欲出售已故威灵顿公爵写给自己的十分宝贵的亲笔便笺一封，写于1850年3月27日，售价二十英镑，有信封，上面的公爵印章及骑士桥地区[113]邮戳均完好无损，清晰可见。该信函充分展现了常人难以见到的公爵贵族笔迹及独特文风。

转让威灵顿公爵晚年所写的亲笔信一封，该信系公爵于临终前一两天时在沃尔默城堡写成，独具特色，印章、邮戳等均清晰可见。该信极有可能是已故公爵留下的最后一封亲笔信，故颇具收藏价值。出价最高者优先。欲见此物，请速申请。

伟大的公爵—出售伟大的英雄公爵的亲笔信一封，写于1851年3月27日。另有珍妮·林德[114]的漂亮亲笔信一封，写于1852年6月20日。出价最高者优先。来信请注明出价。

林德小姐的亲笔信似乎一直躲在暗处徘徊不前，直到出殡的队伍走近，才羞答答走向前来加入了这个行列，还占了个很惹人注目的位置。真不知道我们最应该推崇的是哪一条：有关林德小姐的这则广告设计得如此精妙；有关“极有可能是已故公爵留下的最后一封亲笔信”的广告做得是那样感人，那样巧妙，那样快捷高效，让人觉得卖家是要在出于英雄责任感写下这封信的那双老手尚未在坟墓里枯萎前将信售出；那位急于出售、宣扬“公爵私人慈善行为的极好见证”的牧师—不知他是否曾身着白法衣出现在T.C.的橱窗里且坐在前排—是那样虔诚；那位将“六封信封、印章均完好无缺的亲笔信”赠与身陷贫困的某位女士的好心人是那样慷慨大方。

最后，我们再来看看已故者留下的那些宝贵的遗物—与已故者生前生活息息相关的物品，就像哈迪爵士[115]一直戴在胸前的纳尔逊勋爵[116]的小画像一样。这些遗物很是珍贵，若没有现金支付，广告商是万万不肯脱手的。

已故威灵顿公爵遗物—转让著名已故公爵的一绺头发。确保无假。出价最高者优先。来函申请，请预付邮资。

威灵顿公爵—一位孀居女士藏有已故威灵顿公爵头发一绺，系女王加冕当日早上剪下。现欲转让。来函申请，请预付邮资。

已故威灵顿公爵珍贵遗物—一位女士藏有著名已故公爵的许多头发，系1841年剪下，现欲出售其中一部分，售价二十五英镑。卖家将提供有效证明及遗物来源，确保无假。来函索取，请预付货款。

出售威灵顿公爵遗物—已故威灵顿公爵的已故著名理发师的儿子，现住斯特拉斯菲尔德赛，存有公爵的少量头发，系当年其父从公爵头上剪下。现欲转让，若有心收藏英格兰大英雄的这份遗物，请来信申请、注明出价。

已故威灵顿公爵遗物—出售公爵前些年穿过的马甲一件，保存完好，提供有效证明，确保无假。

下面的这一件更是非同寻常，堪称公爵遗物中的精粹；且据广告所言，人证物证俱全，哪怕是最生性多疑的人也不可能对其真实性有半点儿怀疑，想必这件遗物更是价值非凡。

威灵顿公爵纪念物—现有一本诗集《拿破仑之死》，作者：亚历山达罗·曼佐尼[117]，附法语译文，译者：埃德蒙·安吉琳，于威尼斯。当年公爵乘马车途径肯特郡时将此书撕毁并扔在地上，恰巧一位路人亲眼看见了公爵撕书扔书的全过程，这位路人将书的碎片收集起来，并将它们一一拼好。若想收藏此纪念品，请与我们联系。

最后，还有一部辉煌灿烂、生气蓬勃的文学作品；我们敢说，任何一位有身份有地位的先生若是没有收藏这本书，那他的书房绝对算不上藏书齐全。

威灵顿公爵与罗伯特·皮尔爵士—转让公爵著作一部，内容有关政治经济和自由贸易。该书生动有趣、才华满溢、价值不凡，1830年一经出版，便几乎被罗伯特·皮尔爵士全部买下，现仅剩一本，欲购从速，请来函申请。

考虑到读者的缘故，我们暂且只引用这么多吧。事实上，像这样的广告有太多太多，如果一直引用下去的话，恐怕这整本书都会被广告占满了。

我们认为，国葬仪式扰乱了人心，给广大民众带来了不良影响，误导大家在葬礼上讲排场、多花钱，认为只有这样才能表示对逝者的敬重；而事实上，这恰恰是一种陋习。为了社会各阶层的利益，这种陋习急需革除；而国葬仪式不但对此于事无补，还助长了这种陋习的蔓延。此外，国葬仪式本身以形式替代实质，显然是虚假做作、刻意雕琢、陈腐污浊的，简直就是一场矫揉造作、虚张声势的恶作剧；这场恶作剧不但使得死亡那种令人敬畏的庄严肃穆消失殆尽，还助长了厚颜无耻的投机商在逝者的棺材盖上做生意、发死亡财的风气。我们毫不怀疑，即使威灵顿公爵只是带着军事指挥官的荣誉，在全国民众的无声的敬意中静静地下葬，依然会有人对他的信件及其他遗物广而告之并高价出售；但与此同时，我们也深信，如果威灵顿公爵的遗体能够静静地下葬，至少那些投机商们不会借势撒欢，在葬礼上举行什么“商品交易会”“殡仪员欢庆会”等玩意儿。如果侍从办公室[118]及宗谱纹章院[119]不停止这种奢靡的国葬仪式，民众就不可能心境平和，停止在葬礼上花重金求虚荣的风气。这两者之间有着难以逾越的鸿沟，非凡人之手造就，亦非凡人之手可以填平。如若不然，难道还能有人相信下面这样的事情不成：“法国某政府要员”星期二晚上还在哀悼国家英雄—大将军拿破仑；星期三下午，英雄尚未下葬之时，便开始与休谟先生[120]—威灵顿公爵的私人医生谈笑风生？

本文写于举行国葬的当晚，因为日志的特点就是要及时记录所见所闻。前面我们已经表明，我们认为国葬是一个错误；在此，我们仅希望大家能够坐下来平心静气地思考一下这个问题。国葬仪式所带来的害处很容易想象，但国葬仪式能给大家带来什么益处却很难想象得出，至于国葬仪式能否给威灵顿公爵的下一代带来一丝满足，能否为威灵顿公爵这个响当当的名字增加一点光彩，则更加难以想象。如果有人认为国葬仪式是全英国人民的普遍愿望，那一定只是某些名人达士的错觉，普通民众的想法却被忽略了。希望位高权重的政府要员们能尽快将两者的想法都重视起来，只有这样才有可能是为全国人民考虑。当然，可以肯定地说，我们的期待没有错；换句话说，葬礼上一切都进行得很好，英国人民没有愧对多年来赢得的民族声誉，少数表现得有损民族声誉的蠢人理应感到羞耻。不过，在这里，我们依然要说，我们希望国葬仪式能够在今天—1852年11月18日，乘着那辆在伦敦大街上招摇过市的俗丽的彩车，走向自己的坟墓。我们完全尊重不同的意见，但与此同时，我们也深信，随着历史车轮的前行，国葬仪式会变得默默无闻、宽大仁慈；那俗丽的丧礼彩车—那有资格穿过盛装的圣殿关石门，圣殿关石门也应该开放接纳的丧礼彩车—亦会被历史湮没。到那时，我们会惊奇地发现：历史没有忘记威灵顿公爵那忠实、谦逊、持重、真诚的高尚品德；历史会铭记，为自己忠诚热爱着的国家作出最后一次贡献，结束虚伪奢靡的丧葬仪式的人物正是阿瑟·韦尔兹利—威灵顿公爵。

（丁振琴　译）

[1]草市街（Haymarket）位于伦敦市中心的繁华地段西区内，十七世纪末以前曾是买卖干草、草料的农贸市场，十八世纪以后逐渐发展为著名的娱乐区，街道两侧剧院、酒店林立。——译者注

[2]指萨瑟克（Southwark），泰晤士河南岸地区，伦敦的自治区。——译者注

[3]在十八世纪中叶，金酒（Gin）价格低廉，是包括妇女、幼儿在内的穷人们面对无力改变的悲惨现实，麻醉自我、借以忘忧的主要手段。——译者注

[4]滑铁卢桥是一座位于泰晤士河上的大桥，原本由斯特兰德桥梁公司出资建造，1811年始建，1817年初次建成使用，正值滑铁卢战役两周年纪念日。为纪念英荷普联军的胜利，此桥被命名为滑铁卢桥。该桥为收费大桥，行人收费标准为半便士/人次。十九世纪四十年代该桥成为许多寻短见者首选的自杀地点。1878年大桥收归国有，收费站随之取消。——译者注

[5]便士：一种旧时英国硬币，12便士=1先令，240便士=1英镑。——译者注

[6]在莎士比亚名剧《哈姆雷特》中，掘墓人挖出了一个据说是尤里克的骷髅，哈姆雷特手拿这骷髅回忆说，尤里克是他父王家里的小丑，他小时候经常骑在尤里克背上玩耍。因此，尤里克这个角色在《哈姆雷特》剧中是以骷髅形式出场的，尤里克的骷髅乃是演出该剧的必备道具。——译者注

[7]新门监狱是伦敦市内一座著名的监狱，位于新门大街与老贝利大街交界处。据说初建于1188年，使用至1902年，并于1904年拆除。——译者注

[8]1783年，伦敦城的绞刑架从泰伯恩行刑场搬到了新门监狱的这扇小门外。公开绞刑在此执行，常常吸引大批看客。1868年停止公开绞刑，改在新门监狱内执行。——译者注

[9]圣墓堂（Church of St.Sepulchre）与新门监狱隔街相对，教堂尖塔的钟声常常意味着死刑的迫近。——译者注

[10]位于伦敦市萨瑟克区的一座欠债人专用监狱，中世纪时始建，1880年拆除。——译者注

[11]伦敦所辖的自治市，英国议会所在地。——译者注

[12]旧宫院（Old Palace-yard）在国会大厦西侧。旧宫院再向西不远就是威斯敏斯特教堂的东端。可以步行穿过这个院子，进入国会大厦。——译者注

[13]威斯敏斯特大教堂是皇室财产，是历代英国国王加冕的圣地，也是许多王室成员举行婚礼的场所，还是历代皇家陵园。陵园里还埋葬着牛顿、达尔文等许多英国伟人。本文作者狄更斯去世后也安葬于此。迄今为止，已有约3300人安葬在这里。——译者注

[14]此处典故出自《新约·马可福音》（14：51—52）。在叛徒犹大带人来抓耶稣时，其他门徒都逃走了，但有一个少年人，赤身披着一块麻布，跟随耶稣。众人要抓他，他甩掉麻布，赤身逃走了。随后，耶稣被带走了。——译者注

[15]考文特花园市场是伦敦市一个传统的菜果花卉市场，已有三百多年历史。——译者注

[16]考文特花园市场中的一条街道。——译者注

[17]（英制）品脱：容量或体积单位，约合0.568升。——译者注

[18]圣吉尔斯（Saint Giles，约650—约710）是希腊基督教隐士，据传生于雅典，后在今法国南部隐居，被认为是穷人、残疾人、精神病人、铁匠、动物和森林等事物的保护者。——译者注

[19]班姆菲尔德·摩尔·卡鲁（Bamfylde Moore Carew，1693—约1758），英国有名的流氓、浪子，擅长伪装，自称是乞丐之王。——译者注

[20]该道路英文为Strand，又译斯特兰德街，街上有许多著名的旅馆和剧院。——译者注

[21]诺桑伯兰府位于河岸大道上，是诺桑伯兰公爵的府第，建于十七世纪早期，1874年拆除，在原址上修成了诺桑伯兰大道。——译者注

[22]十六世纪，英国王权在与罗马教廷的斗争中实施了宗教改革，建立了本国的民族教会，一般译为英国国教，又译英格兰圣公会。卫斯理宗原为英国国教中的一派，形成于十八世纪三四十年代，主张因信称义，倡导严格遵照圣经过道德的宗教生活，因此又称“循道宗”或“监理宗”。——译者注

[23]克朗为英国旧币制单位硬币，1克朗=5先令=60便士，半克朗=2先令6便士。——译者注

[24]伦敦市政厅门前的两个木雕巨像。巨人名为高格（Gog）和马高格（Magog），被认为是伦敦金融城的守护神。——译者注

[25]指英国民间故事《迪克·威廷顿和猫》中的主人公迪克·威廷顿。迪克是个孤儿，听说伦敦金融城里连街道都铺满了黄金，就去那里谋求发财之道。他失望地发现，实际情况并非如此。他又冷又饿地蜷缩在一位富商菲茨沃伦先生的府第前睡着了。仁慈的菲茨沃伦先生发现了他，还雇他当了洗碗工。迪克因为住处经常有老鼠出没，就挣钱买了一只猫来驱鼠。一天，菲茨沃伦先生要远航到某个港口去做黄金生意，就问他的家仆们是否愿意送给他些什么东西带上船。迪克极不情愿地把自己的猫送给了他。菲茨沃伦先生一直待迪克很好，但他家的厨师却非常凶暴，迪克忍无可忍，决定逃跑。可他要逃离金融城的时候，却听到城里圣玛丽勒博教堂的钟声敲响了，似乎在说：“威廷顿你不要慌，三次当上大市长。”于是，迪克返了回去，发现菲茨沃伦先生的船已经返航了。北非巴巴里国王的王宫里老鼠猖獗，迪克那只擅长捕鼠的猫就被高价卖给了巴巴里国王，迪克从此成了有钱人。他开始与菲茨沃伦先生合伙做生意，后来又娶了菲茨沃伦先生的女儿爱丽丝，而且最终像钟声预言的那样，三次成为金融城的市长。
这个民间故事的原型是理查·威廷顿（Richard Whittington，约1354—1423），一位中世纪英国商人、政治家。少年时，威廷顿作为幼子，因无权继承父亲财产，被送往金融城学做绸布生意，很快成长为一名成功巨商，并与英国王室来往密切。他数次被任命或选举为金融城市长，并成为国会议员和伦敦地区司法长官。同时，威廷顿热心公益，生前、身后都大笔捐助了医疗、卫生、监狱、图书馆、教堂等事业。——译者注

[26]圣殿关是伦敦金融城的西部边界，向东在金融城内的路段是河湾街（Fleet Street，又音译为弗利特街，也有人错译为舰队街），向西是通往威斯敏斯特市的河岸大道。这里的石门自1670年前后建成后，门顶上经常陈列着叛国者的首级示众。——译者注

[27]这座教堂上有一组报时钟表，表的上方有两个手拿长棍的巨人雕像，据称是高格和马高格。每到整点和每隔一刻钟，巨人像就会用木棍敲击面前悬挂的两口钟，同时转动头部。——译者注

[28]圣保罗大教堂是英国国教伦敦教区的主教座堂，坐落于伦敦金融城中最高处的卢德门山上。现存巴洛克风格的建筑始建于1675年，于1697年年底投入使用，以其壮观的圆形屋顶而驰名于世，是伦敦最著名的标志性建筑之一。——译者注

[29]1英尺约合0.3048米；40英尺约合12.2米。——译者注

[30]摩西宗阿拉伯人（Mosaic Arabs）是英国政治家、小说家本雅明·迪斯累利（Benjamin Disraeli，1804—1881）发明的对犹太人的称呼。迪斯累利出身于犹太家庭，但少时受洗成为英国国教徒，在维多利亚女王统治下曾于1868年和1874—1880年间两度出任英国首相，大力推行对外侵略和殖民扩张政策，建立了强大的殖民帝国。他也是迄今唯一一个具有犹太血统的英国首相。他借其小说《恩底弥翁》（Endymion）中的人物希德尼娅之口，不无骄傲地称犹太人为摩西宗阿拉伯人，宣扬种族主义思想。——译者注

[31]提香·韦切利奥（Tiziano Vecellio，1490—1576）是文艺复兴时期最重要的威尼斯派画家，其作品充满生机和理想色彩，富于热情，享有“西方油画之父”的美誉，在西方艺术史上有着伟大而深远的影响。——译者注

[32]蒲式耳是英国粮食度量单位，其度量工具在不同地区和不同时期都存在大小不一致的复杂情况。——译者注

[33]菲茨沃伦是《迪克·威廷顿和猫》故事中的人物，详见前文“威廷顿”条注释。——译者注

[34]水手辛巴德的故事讲的是，在中世纪的巴士拉地区，生活着一个叫辛巴德的虚构人物。他通过在东非和南亚沿海地区的七次航海发了大财。——译者注

[35]史密斯—佩恩—史密斯于十九世纪合伙成立了一家英国私人合资银号。该银号为早期银行业巨头，资财无数，影响巨大。——译者注

[36]格林和哈利法克斯于十八世纪合伙成立了一家英国私人合资银号。该银号为早期银行业巨头，财富丰厚，一度岁入九万英镑。——译者注

[37]霸菱兄弟于1762年创建了伦敦第一家商业银行，为银行业中的名门。但1995年，这家有着二百三十三年悠久历史的银行因其雇员李森的巨额投机投资而破产。——译者注

[38]阿拉伯神话中，传说有一种食肉的白色大鹏鸟，它下的蛋也硕大无朋。在《马可·波罗游记》《天方夜谭》《水手辛巴德》等东方故事中都提到了这种巨鸟。欧洲人过去曾认为这种鸟确实存在，后来则称“大鹏鸟蛋”为虚幻之物。——译者注

[39]日耳曼—犹太血统的罗思柴尔德家族是著名欧洲银行世家，于十七世纪晚期进入银行业和金融业，其财富在十八世纪达到巅峰。据信，当时该家族拥有的私人财富为世界有史以来的第一位、近现代历史上的第一位，至今无人超越。——译者注

[40]苏丹是伊斯兰国家最高统治者的称号。——译者注

[41]詹姆斯·霍格爵士（Sir James Hogg，1790—1876）是英国律师、国会议员，曾两度担任东印度公司董事长。——译者注

[42]有许多年，英国军队的日饷都是一先令，所以成语“接受国王的一先令”意为同意参军。十八和十九世纪，英国陆军和皇家海军在招募期间，都会付给新兵一先令作为定金。当时的征兵员运用各种诡计，特别是通过请喝烈酒的方式，将一先令定金强塞给毫无戒心的人。由于工作条件艰苦而危险，皇家海军还雇用了抓丁队，通过偷袭、威胁、抓打等各种残暴手段，在大街上强征各种年龄段的水手、平民入伍。抓来的壮丁统统被塞给一先令定金。拿了定金的人要当着太平绅士的面宣誓入伍，然后才能正式成为新兵。如果他在宣誓前不再想当兵，就得交纳一定数额的“解除兵役赔偿金”。到十九世纪四十年代，赔偿金的金额已高达一英镑（合二十先令），绝大多数新兵都交不起。——译者注

[43]梅德韦河是泰晤士河的最后一条大支流，几乎全部位于肯特郡内。——译者注

[44]诺尔是位于泰晤士河口内的一个沙洲的名称，泰晤士河在此注入北海。诺尔沙洲是通往伦敦港航道上的一处天险，因此，1732年这里出现了世上第一艘灯船，警示出入伦敦港的船只。——译者注

[45]皮托（全名Samuel Morton Peto，1809—1889）是十九世纪英国企业家和土木工程师。他的公司建造了伦敦市内的许多重要建筑和纪念碑，他还签了许多合同，承建当时正迅速扩张的铁路线路。——译者注

[46]布拉塞（全名Thomas Brassey，1805—1870）是十九世纪英国土木工程承包商、建材生产商。在十九世纪，全世界的，特别是欧洲、澳洲、南北美洲和印度的大部分铁路都是由他承建的。不仅如此，他还建造了与那些铁路相关的码头、桥梁、高架桥、车站、隧道、给排水系统等设施。除铁路工程外，他还积极参与发展轮船、矿业、火车厂、越洋电报等事业。——译者注

[47]十九世纪初，技术与经济的发展给欧洲人带来了大量财富，保险柜行业应运而生。英国、美国、法国等国的发明家兼商人陆续研发了具有防火、防盗等功能的保险柜，并获得了各种专利。例如，后来成为保险柜行业巨头的英国发明家Charles Chubb和Jeremiah Chubb兄弟，他们发明的防盗保险柜于1835年获得了专利权。——译者注

[48]维罗纳是意大利古城，处于多条贸易通道的交会处，为欧洲重要城市。以其雄伟的圆形露天竞技场/剧场驰名。这里的圆形剧场建成于西元30年，规模仅次于罗马斗兽场和加普亚圆形剧场，至今保存完好，为世界现存的第三大圆形剧场。剧场长139米，宽110米，有44级大理石梯阶，能容纳2.5万多名观众。这里每年夏季都举行歌剧演出，是莎士比亚剧作中罗密欧和朱丽叶的故乡，为著名旅游景点，2000年被联合国教科文组织列入世界遗产目录。——译者注

[49]即塞缪尔·约翰逊（Samuel Johnson，1709—1784），著名英国作家、诗人、文学批评家、编辑和词典学家，他独力纂成的《英语大辞典》（A Dictionary of the English Language）于1755年出版，为他赢得了卓著声誉。他从小就视力不好，左眼尤差。随着年龄的增长，他的视力每况愈下，但他从不使用眼镜。他逝世后葬于威斯敏斯特大教堂。——译者注

[50]即熔化的铁水。——译者注

[51]教皇琼游戏是十八世纪维多利亚时期流行于英国的家庭纸牌游戏。该游戏在传统纸牌上配有一个圆形木盒，从圆心处向外放射状分隔出八个面积相同的扇区，形成八个容量相同的格子，供玩家盛放筹码。也有的圆盒将圆心处开辟为一个盛放整副扑克的圆格。此外，也有用金属制作的筹码盒。——译者注

[52]卡戎（Charon），希腊神话中在冥河上摆渡亡魂去往阴间的神。——译者注

[53]原文创作于十九世纪六十年代初期，英国正试图控制东亚，美国正值内战（1861—1865）期间。因父亲工作所需，作者狄更斯五岁时（1817年）随父搬家到查塔姆的皇家海军会计处（Royal Navy Pay Office）工作，在此地生活了七年。——译者注

[54]中美洲北部国家，玛雅文化所在地。该国北临加勒比海，南濒太平洋，热带气候，全境以山地和高原为主，森林、水利资源都很丰富，森林覆盖率达百分之七十，盛产木料、金属矿。——译者注

[55]蓝胡子是法国民间传说中的人物。据说，他是个极其富有的贵族，但长着令人恐惧的蓝色胡须。在他的前几任妻子莫名其妙地失踪后，当地再也没人敢把女孩嫁给他。有一天，他到一位邻居家做客，并请求娶她两个女儿中的一个为妻。两个女儿听说后吓坏了，互相推诿，谁都不肯嫁给他。但最终他说服那个小女儿同意了这门亲事，住进了他的城堡。婚后不久，蓝胡子声称要出门一段时间，就把家里所有的钥匙交给了新婚妻子，说她可以任意使用这些钥匙，打开任何房间的门，取用里面的财富。此外，他还交给她一把城堡底下一间小屋的钥匙，并叮嘱说，无论如何都不能开那个小屋的门。妻子答应后，他就走了。可是这位妻子忍不住强烈的好奇心，在举办一次家庭宴会期间，偷偷进了那个小屋，发现了那里隐藏的可怕秘密：地板上满是血迹，蓝胡子前几任妻子的尸体赫然挂在墙上。她吓坏了，手中的钥匙一下掉进了血泊之中。她逃离了这间小屋，但钥匙上的血污却怎么都洗刷不掉。她把这个惊天秘密告诉了姐姐，姐妹俩决定逃跑。但第二天早上蓝胡子突然回来了。他发现了钥匙上的血污，知道妻子背叛了誓言，一怒之下，要当场杀死她。妻子请求先做祈祷再赴死，蓝胡子答应了。于是姐妹俩把自己锁进了城堡顶上的房间，等待她们的两个兄弟前来营救。蓝胡子撞开门，正要对她们痛下杀手，两兄弟赶到，杀掉了蓝胡子，救出了两姐妹。蓝胡子无嗣，妻子就继承了他的全部家产，她将其中一部分分给姐姐作嫁妆，一部分分给了两兄弟，其余部分用作她自己的嫁妆，嫁给了一位可敬的绅士，开始了幸福的新生活。——译者注

[56]“快活的斯图亚特”指英格兰、苏格兰及爱尔兰王查理二世（CharlesII，1630—1685），他属于斯图亚特家族，因其放荡的个人生活和享乐主义的朝廷体制，被称为“快活王”（Merry Monarch）。1664—1667年，英国与荷兰进行了第二次英荷战争，1666年9月10日，伦敦发生大火，城市焚毁，英国经济遭受重创，荷兰舰队趁机于1667年6月在泰晤士河口发动了“突袭梅德韦”行动（Raidon the Medway），歼灭了驻泊泰晤士河的英国舰队，破坏了船厂。1667年7月，英国被迫签订《布雷达合约》。——译者注

[57]指俄国沙皇彼得大帝（1672—1725）。1697年至1698年，彼得大帝化名到西欧旅行，考察和学习西欧发达的科技、文化，其中包括荷兰和英国的先进造船术。他天资颖悟、勤奋好学、手艺纯熟，深受师傅的赞誉，在荷英两国的造船厂亲自动手，建造过运行良好的战舰。——译者注

[58]毕斯托尔（Pistol）是莎士比亚名剧《亨利五世》中的角色，亨利五世的随从，极擅吹牛，但实则胆小如鼠。他的同伙有惯于虚张声势的巴道夫和寡言少语的尼姆，二人同样是懦夫加小偷。——译者注

[59]沃平（Wapping）位于伦敦金融城东部，南临泰晤士河。1986年，传媒大王默多克将其新闻总部从英国报业中心河湾街（FleetStreet）搬至此区。——译者注

[60]伦敦东区（East End）位于伦敦金融城城墙以东，泰晤士河以北，为港口区。十九世纪晚期，伦敦地区人口数量激增，这里成为拥挤不堪的贫民和移民区，导致“伦敦东区”逐渐成为一个贬义词。此后的一个多世纪，“伦敦东区”成为贫困、拥挤、疾病和犯罪的代名词。如今，这里的人文环境已经有所改观，但某些区域仍然是全英国最贫困的地区。——译者注

[61]蒂普苏丹（Tippoo Sahib，或Tipu Sahib，1749—1799），印度南部迈索尔王朝的统治者。英国入侵前，他是全印度最强大的国王，曾对英国在南部印度的利益构成了最大威胁。他在位期间曾同英国殖民者（特别是东印度公司）展开了长期英勇战争，但终被英国殖民者和几个邻邦国王联手打败和杀害，一度繁荣强盛的迈索尔王国随之落入了英国人之手。——译者注

[62]查尔斯·兰姆（Charles Lamb，1775—1834），英国散文家，生于英国伦敦，一生平凡而不幸。兰姆家境贫寒，1796年，他的姐姐因劳累过度而出现了精神病，杀死了母亲。从此，他为照顾姐姐，使她免于流落到疯人院而终生未娶。1792—1825年，他在东印度公司任职，工作之余，他创作过诗歌、莎剧论文、故事、随笔等，文风富有个性、亦庄亦谐。他的代表作有《莎士比亚故事集》（1807）、《伊利亚随笔》（1823）、《伊利亚续笔》（1833）等。——译者注

[63]木刻海军少尉是位于利登豪街（Leadenhall Street）的所罗门·吉尔斯仪表店的标记之一。木雕不大，站在店门口的墙壁上，穿着海军制服，双手捧着一只很大的六分仪。——译者注

[64]阿尔盖德水泵（Aldgate Pump）是伦敦金融城内一个历史悠久的水泵，位于阿尔盖德大街（Aldgate High Street）、芬丘奇街（Fenchurch Street）、利登豪街交会处。该水泵原本抽取地下水源，作为公共饮水设施使用。水泵上有个狼头形状的水嘴，据说是为了纪念在伦敦金融城内射杀最后一只狼而造。——译者注

[65]“撒拉逊人”一词源自阿拉伯文sharqiyyin（“东方人”），拉丁文则写作Saracen。古罗马人本来用该词指称生活在罗马帝国阿拉伯行省（包括今约旦、西奈半岛和沙特阿拉伯西北部）沙漠一带的非阿拉伯游牧民。到中世纪时，该词词义扩大，陆续将阿拉伯人也包括在内，到十一世纪末期，该词已经成了“穆斯林”的同义词。撒拉逊人头像（Saracen’s Head）在英国曾是惯用的旅馆标志。——译者注

[66]在英国，许多旅店、酒店都有几百年的历史。许多旅店位于罗马道路两边，多为马车旅店。它们的早期顾客大都不识字，所以店家设计出了各种各样的图像符号作标志，让顾客记住自己，创建口碑。这种做法蔚成传统，沿用至今。撒拉逊人头像就是一例。以牛、鸡、狗、猪、马、虎、狐狸、狼、狮子等家畜和野生动物加上某种（些）颜色为标志的办法也很流行。——译者注

[67]白礼堂教堂（Whitechapel Church）位于伦敦东区，初建于14世纪早期，原是一个为远离教区的基督教徒们设立的小礼拜堂。后经数次重建和毁坏，终于1952年被彻底拆除，其原址现为一个公园。这里的白礼堂大街和白礼堂路原本是在从伦敦金融城出城向东通往科尔切斯特（Colchester）的古罗马人通道，道路两侧马车旅店林立。以此小礼拜堂和罗马人通道为基础发展起来的白礼堂区长期以来都是伦敦最具代表性的贫民区，人口肤色不一、成分复杂，环境脏乱、治安极差。十九世纪八十年代，这里曾发生了恶名昭著的连环谋杀悬案，神秘的凶手被称为“开膛手杰克”，但至今没有破案。——译者注

[68]伦敦东区的一条路，为东印度公司在十九世纪早期所建，西连伦敦金融城，东接金丝雀码头（Canary Wharf），长约3.2千米。——译者注

[69]非商务旅客（the Uncommercial Traveller）是狄更斯杜撰的人物。1859年他自办了一份刊物《一年四季》（All the Year Round），并于1860年1—10月在该刊上发表了十七篇、一个称作“非商务旅客”的文章系列。在其后的十年时间里，狄更斯陆续借用此角色续写了多篇文章，所有这些文章在他死后，于1875年以《非商务旅客》为名结集出版。在狄更斯笔下，此“非商务旅客”酷爱旅行，不仅去欧洲大陆和美洲，而且喜欢在伦敦本地游逛。他不仅观光，而且对其发现进行研究和报道。借此患有失眠症的虚构人物之口，狄更斯揭示了维多利亚时代伦敦的种种黑暗面。——译者注

[70]沃平老阶梯位于沃平大街（Wappping High Street）南侧，是沃平地区通往泰晤士河岸线的阶梯之一，仅在退潮时露出，青苔遍布，泰晤士河在此涨潮落潮，能带来一些诸如古老陶片之类的浮货。这里曾经是水产交易市场，肯特郡的渔夫们带着从拉姆斯盖特捕获的水产到这里来卖。这里也曾是绞死海盗船长基德（Captain Kidd）的地方。——译者注

[71]东区圣乔治教堂（St.George-in-the-East）建于1714—1729年，1729年投入使用，其周边地区称为圣乔治教区。1855年教区委员会成为该教区的地方政府，1927年撤销。教区委员会于每年复活节由本地的纳税人选举产生，教区委员会负责每年推选本堂区的俗人委员，掌管本教区的世俗事务。这些俗人委员可能会与教堂及教区牧师（rector）意见相左。1859年5月—1860年7月，圣乔治教堂爆发了这样的冲突，称为“仪式暴乱”（Ritualism Riot）。1842年，布莱恩·金（Bryan King，1811—1895）被任命为圣乔治教区牧师，他到任时，发现该教区委员会推选的俗人委员是不顺从国教者和非国教教徒，从此展开了一场长期的斗争。他决定改变原来简陋、单调的礼拜仪式，以吸引更多信众：给圣坛披上祭服，放上点燃的蜡烛；让唱诗班穿上长袍哼唱圣歌和应答祷文；牧师穿白色法衣而不是黑色长袍讲道，等等。1857年，有人送给金几件白绿相间的丝质无袖长袍，在分送圣餐时穿用。他起初非常犹豫，但后来开始穿用。这些服饰虽是现在通行的做法，但在当时，在十九世纪中期，那些成分复杂、生活贫困的东区会众对此带有中产阶级调子的“时髦”行为深恶痛绝，双方冲突不断升级，最后发展成为会众暴乱：连续数月，一到周日，成千上万的会众就带着狗涌入该教堂，抽烟、放火、乱扔帽子、起哄，在牧师布道时大声诘问、奚落牧师，在唱诗班唱圣歌时高唱《统治吧，大不列颠》和《上帝保佑女王》等别的歌曲。教堂外也同时发生着类似的暴乱，导致牧师不得不靠警察护送才能从边门回到住宅。金牧师请求从政府得到更有效的保护，但教区委员会的活动促使英国议会上下两院都漠视了他的请求。最后受到起诉的不是暴乱者，反倒是牧师一派。——译者注

[72]甘普太太是狄更斯于1843—1844年发表的小说《马丁·瞿述伟》中的一名护工。她从月嫂到装殡工，什么都干，可她放纵、贪杯，从来不放过任何享受主家好处的机会，而且习惯性地带着一把黑色的破伞。她的形象深入人心，维多利亚时代的人们甚至用“甘普”一词来指称伞。——译者注

[73]英格兰和威尔士中央刑事法院位于伦敦市中心的老贝利街，其原形为十六世纪的伦敦金融城市长和郡长会议厅，毗邻新门监狱，为理查德·威廷顿爵士所捐赠。到1834年为止，该法院已受理过十万多起刑事案件，包括所有死刑案件。后经数次毁坏和重建，1834年更名为中央刑事法院，建筑实体及其运转由伦敦金融城政府出资维护。中央刑事法院为全国性法院，负责受理较重大的刑事案件，庭审对公众开放。可在此开庭的法官有高等法院法官、巡回法院法官和刑事法院兼职法官。该法院的最高常任法官被称为伦敦市首席法官（Recorder of London），其副手被称为伦敦市司法行政官（Common Serjeant of London），地位很高。高等法院的一些重要法官是显赫的终身贵族。——译者注

[74]《大宪章》于1215年由英国贵族与英国国王初次订立，以约束王权、保障贵族的政治权利，从此开创了宪法政治，影响远播。其中明确保护了寡妇的财产权。——译者注

[75]在旧时英国货币单位中，1镑=20先令；1先令=12便士。5先令6便士合66便士。——译者注

[76]汉诺威广场圣乔治教堂（St George’s, Hanover Square）是1711年规定建造的五十座安妮女王诸教堂之一，位于伦敦金融城西侧的威斯敏斯特市内梅菲尔区（Mayfair）。教堂所处为上流社会地区，于是成为名门望族常用的婚礼举行地。1886年12月2日，后来成为美国总统的西奥多·罗斯福就在此结婚。——译者注

[77]帕丁顿教区也位于威斯敏斯特市内。——译者注

[78]圣殿区（the Temple）是圣殿教堂所在的教区，主体部分在伦敦金融城内，西部的一小部分在威斯敏斯特市内，南临泰晤士河，西临萨里街（Surrey Street），北临河岸大道（Strand）和河湾街（Fleet Street），东临圣衣会街（Carmelite Street）和白衣修士街（Whitefriars Street）。该教区为本市乃至全国著名的法律中心。——译者注

[79]据基督教《圣经》记载，所罗门是联合王国的第三任国王、大卫王之子，是智慧、神通、财富、荣耀、权威、美德的象征，流传下来三千句箴言和一千零五首诗歌。他的宝座是用象牙所制，外包精金，有六层台阶，有金脚凳与之相连。每层台阶都有两头石雕狮子站立，宝座两旁有扶手，扶手附近也各有一头石雕狮子。所罗门的宝座高踞一切之上，象征他有着高高在上的威权，他坐在其上进行审判。——译者注

[80]参见前文“东区圣乔治教堂”条注释。——译者注

[81]此处的“某人”指耶稣。这是《马太福音》（26：30）和《马可福音》（14：26）中记载的典故：耶稣及其十二门徒吃过最后的晚餐，唱了赞美诗，往橄榄山去。在一个叫客西马尼的地方，耶稣去远处祈祷时，门徒们都疲惫地睡着了，他去了三次、回来三次，可门徒们谁都没有醒来。等他第三次回来后不久，叛徒犹大就带人来把他抓走了。——译者注

[82]共济会（Freemasonry），字面意思是自由石匠工会，是一个带宗教色彩的秘密兄弟会组织，在世界各地有不同的存在形式，宣扬博爱、慈善、美德，思索人类生存的意义。共济会起源不明，但据信最初为中世纪时石匠们自发形成的组织，其基本徽章是由石匠常用工具—圆规（在上）和直角尺（在下）组成的图案，有的徽章图案上在圆规和直角尺之间还有一个字母G，代表共济会的法典。有记载表明，现代共济会出现于十八世纪早期的英国伦敦，是一个由白人贵族、高级神职人员、上层资产阶级等社会精英人物组成的封闭社团组织，并于十八世纪三十年代传播到了北美殖民地。英王乔治三世、乔治四世、乔治六世、爱德华七世、爱德华八世都是共济会会员；另外，如孟德斯鸠、牛顿、莫扎特、贝多芬、歌德、乔治·华盛顿、托马斯·杰斐逊、本杰明·富兰克林、富兰克林·罗斯福、亨利·福特、托马斯·爱迪生、马克·吐温、爱因斯坦、温斯顿·丘吉尔等许多欧美政要和科学文化界名人也都是共济会会员。后来，共济会放弃专走上层路线的做法，开始吸收普通公民入会，在世界各地现有六百多万会员；其活动也越来越公开化，除了内部表明各级别的暗语及手势仍旧保密之外，其余活动基本上全部公开。——译者注

[83]木刻集《死亡之舞》的作者是（小）霍尔拜因（Hans Holbein, the Younger，1497—1543），德国肖像画家和装饰艺术家，英王亨利八世御前画师。——译者注

[84]堂区，即行政堂区，是英格兰乡村的基层行政单位。——译者注

[85]菲兹威廉夫人，全名范妮·伊丽莎白·菲兹威廉（Fanny Elizabeth Fitzwilliam），是英国十九世纪著名演员爱德华·菲兹威廉（Edward Fitzwilliam）的妻子，曾在伦敦艾德菲剧院出演约翰·巴克斯通（John Buckstone）的音乐剧《维多琳娜》（Victorine），扮演剧中人物伊利斯（Elise）；该剧作者约翰·巴克斯通和狄更斯是好朋友。——译者注

[86]十九世纪时，英国国内有近百万人失业，急需政府予以救济。但在自由资本主义发展的鼎盛时期，资产阶级藐视人权，认为贫困是由于“个人懒惰”所致，因而应由“个人负责”。1834年，英国政府制定的《济贫法》便是以这样的思想观念为指导的。这部法律规定，在各地建立济贫院，凡无生活来源、需要社会救济者必须进入济贫院。但是被救济者在济贫院内被迫从事繁重体力劳动，里面的生活条件又极为恶劣。实际上，济贫院不是在“救济穷人”，而是在“惩治穷人”，其最终目的是为了摆脱济贫税负担和为资本主义生产提供充足的劳动力来源。因此，穷人一般都很害怕进济贫院。——译者注

[87]拉斐尔（Raphael，1483—1520），意大利文艺复兴时期画家，建筑师，主要作品有梵蒂冈宫中的壁画《圣礼的辩论》和《雅典学派》，其他代表作有《西斯庭圣母》《基督显圣容》等。——译者注

[88]位于伦敦东部，有很多的贫民区。——译者注

[89]指1371年至1714年间统治苏格兰和1603年至1714年间统治英格兰和爱尔兰的王朝。——译者注

[90]指1665年发生在伦敦的黑死病。——译者注

[91]指凯尔特民族的神职人员，而凯尔特人是一个公元前五世纪至公元一世纪散居在不列颠、爱尔兰、欧洲、小亚细亚等地的民族。——译者注

[92]旧时伦敦城的入口，位于一所法学院前，是叛国者和其他罪犯首级示众之处。——译者注

[93]老贝利（Old Bailey）也用来指位于老贝利街的英国中央刑事法庭。——译者注

[94]位于新门大街和老贝利街的交角处，是伦敦的一所著名监狱，1904年被拆毁。——译者注

[95]位于新门大街和纽钱吉街的交角处，以其壮观的圆形屋顶而闻名，是英国古典主义建筑的代表。——译者注

[96]位于杭兹迪奇街。——译者注

[97]司各特（Scott，1771—1832），苏格兰小说家、诗人，历史小说首创者，浪漫主义运动的先驱。——译者注

[98]位于苏格兰首府爱丁堡，是那里的一条重要街道。——译者注

[99]指爱丁堡的荷里路德宫周围地区，直到荷里路德公园一带。历史上曾为欠债人的避难所。荷里路德宫曾是苏格兰王室的居所，现在仍是英女王来到苏格兰的皇室住所。——译者注

[100]位于伦敦东部。——译者注

[101]位于伦敦中西部的一条大街。——译者注

[102]位于伦敦东部的一个港区。——译者注

[103]位于伦敦东区的一条路。——译者注

[104]土耳其古代对大官的尊称。——译者注

[105]在英国旧币制中，一先令相当于十二便士，二十先令为一英镑。——译者注

[106]在英国旧币制中，一个金币的面值通常为一英镑。——译者注

[107]罗伯特·皮尔（Robert Peel，1788—1850），英国首相（1834—1835，1841—1846），保守党创始人，任内政大臣时建立首都警察队（1829）。——译者注

[108]指阿德莱德王后（1792—1849），其丈夫威廉四世于1837年去世，从而成为英国自十八世纪以来第一位孀居王后。文中引用部分乃阿德莱德王后1841年在病榻上所写。——译者注

[109]威灵顿公爵（1769—1852），本名为阿瑟·韦尔兹利，英国陆军元帅、首相（1828—1830），以在滑铁卢战役（1815）中指挥英、普联军击败拿破仑而闻名，有“铁公爵”之称。——译者注

[110]这是威灵顿公爵在滑铁卢战役中说的一句话。当时，威灵顿公爵的部队眼看要被打败，公爵正焦急地等待普鲁士王子布鲁奇元帅率军来援助。另，之所以渴盼夜晚到来，是因为夜幕降临后，暂时不用打仗。——译者注

[111]滑铁卢战役发生于1815年6月18日，由法军对英普军在比利时小镇滑铁卢决战。威灵顿公爵指挥英、普联军大胜拿破仑，终结了拿破仑帝国。——译者注

[112]是威灵顿公爵和他的继承者们居住过的地方。——译者注

[113]骑士桥地区位于伦敦中部，主要是住宅区，没有什么办公场所，非常安静。——译者注

[114]珍妮·林德（1820—1887）是瑞典著名女高音歌唱家，在欧洲大陆享有盛誉，被称为“瑞典夜莺”。——译者注

[115]全称为托马斯·马斯特曼·哈迪爵士（1769—1839），英国皇家海军军官。曾在海军上将纳尔逊勋爵（旗舰司令）手下任旗舰舰长。据英国记者鲁宾·珀西（Reuben Percy）（本名托马斯·伯雷（Thomas Byerley，？—1826）在《文学娱乐教育之镜》（The Mirror of literature, amusement, and instruction）第34卷记载，纳尔逊勋爵曾将自己的一枚小画像送给托马斯·哈迪，哈迪爵士便一直将此画像佩戴于胸前，并表明自己过世后，希望这枚画像能依旧陪伴自己，与自己的遗体埋葬在一起。——译者注

[116]全称为霍雷肖·纳尔逊勋爵（1758—1805），英国海军上将、世界著名海军统帅，被誉为“英国皇家海军之魂”。——译者注

[117]亚历山大·曼佐尼（1785—1873），意大利诗人、小说家，十九世纪意大利浪漫主义文学的代表。——译者注

[118]英国皇室下设的一个部门，主要负责礼仪、国事访问、授权仪式、皇家招待会、皇室婚礼及葬礼等。——译者注

[119]英国皇室下设的一个部门，主要负责各种仪式、宗谱调查、家谱记录等。——译者注

[120]全名为约翰·罗伯特·休谟（1781？—1857），曾是威灵顿元帅麾下的一名军医，也是威灵顿公爵的私人医生。——译者注

Night Walks

Some years ago, a temporary inability to sleep, referable to a distressing impression, caused me to walk about the streets all night, for a series of several nights. The disorder might have taken a long time to conquer, if it had been faintly experimented on in bed; but, it was soon defeated by the brisk treatment of getting up directly after lying down, and going out, and coming home tired at sunrise.

In the course of those nights, I finished my education in a fair amateur experience of houselessness. My principal object being to get through the night, the pursuit of it brought me into sympathetic relations with people who have no other object every night in the year.

The month was March, and the weather damp, cloudy, and cold. The sun not rising before half-past five, the night perspective looked sufficiently long at half-past twelve: which was about my time for confronting it.

The restlessness of a great city, and the way in which it tumbles and tosses before it can get to sleep, formed one of the first entertainments offered to the contemplation of us houseless people. It lasted about two hours. We lost a great deal of companionship when the late publichouses turned their lamps out, and when the potmen thrust the last brawling drunkards into the street; but stray vehicles and stray people were left us, after that. If we were very lucky, a policeman’s rattle sprang and a fray turned up; but, in general, surprisingly little of this diversion was provided. Except in the Haymarket, which is the worst kept part of London, and about Kent-street in the Borough, and along a portion of the line of the Old Kentroad, the peace was seldom violently broken. But, it was always the case that London, as if in imitation of individual citizens belonging to it, had expiring fits and starts of restlessness. After all seemed quiet, if one cab rattled by, half-a-dozen would surely follow; and Houselessness even observed that intoxicated people appeared to be magnetically attracted towards each other: so that we knew when we saw one drunken object staggering against the shutters of a shop, that another drunken object would stagger up before five minutes were out, to fraternise or fight with it. When we made a divergence from the regular species of drunkard, the thin-armed, puff-faced, leadenlipped gin-drinker, and encountered a rarer specimen of a more decent appearance, fifty to one but that specimen was dressed in soiled mourning. As the street experience in the night, so the street experience in the day; the common folk who come unexpectedly into a little property, come unexpectedly into a deal of liquor.

At length these flickering sparks would die away, worn out - the last veritable sparks of waking life trailed from some late pieman or hot-potato man - and London would sink to rest. And then the yearning of the houseless mind would be for any sign of company, any lighted place, any movement, anything suggestive of any one being up - nay, even so much as awake, for the houseless eye looked out for lights in windows.

Walking the streets under the pattering rain, Houselessness would walk and walk and walk, seeing nothing but the interminable tangle of streets, save at a corner, here and there, two policemen in conversation, or the sergeant or inspector looking after his men. Now and then in the night - but rarely - Houselessness would become aware of a furtive head peering out of a doorway a few yards before him, and, coming up with the head, would find a man standing bolt upright to keep within the doorway’s shadow, and evidently intent upon no particular service to society. Under a kind of fascination, and in a ghostly silence suitable to the time, Houselessness and this gentleman would eye one another from head to foot, and so, without exchange of speech, part, mutually suspicious. Drip, drip, drip, from ledge and coping, splash from pipes and water-spouts, and by-and-by the houseless shadow would fall upon the stones that pave the way to Waterloo-bridge; it being in the houseless mind to have a halfpenny worth of excuse for saying ‘Good night’ to the toll-keeper, and catching a glimpse of his fire. A good fire and a good great-coat and a good woollen neck-shawl, were comfortable things to see in conjunction with the toll-keeper; also his brisk wakefulness was excellent company when he rattled the change of halfpence down upon that metal table of his, like a man who defied the night, with all its sorrowful thoughts, and didn’t care for the coming of dawn. There was need of encouragement on the threshold of the bridge, for the bridge was dreary. The chopped-up murdered man, had not been lowered with a rope over the parapet when those nights were; he was alive, and slept then quietly enough most likely, and undisturbed by any dream of where he was to come. But the river had an awful look, the buildings on the banks were muffled in black shrouds, and the reflected lights seemed to originate deep in the water, as if the spectres of suicides were holding them to show where they went down. The wild moon and clouds were as restless as an evil conscience in a tumbled bed, and the very shadow of the immensity of London seemed to lie oppressively upon the river.

Between the bridge and the two great theatres, there was but the distance of a few hundred paces, so the theatres came next. Grim and black within, at night, those great dry Wells, and lonesome to imagine, with the rows of faces faded out, the lights extinguished, and the seats all empty. One would think that nothing in them knew itself at such a time but Yorick’s skull. In one of my night walks, as the church steeples were shaking the March winds and rain with strokes of Four, I passed the outer boundary of one of these great deserts, and entered it. With a dim lantern in my hand, I groped my well-known way to the stage and looked over the orchestra - which was like a great grave dug for a time of pestilence - into the void beyond. A dismal cavern of an immense aspect, with the chandelier gone dead like everything else, and nothing visible through mist and fog and space, but tiers of winding-sheets. The ground at my feet where, when last there, I had seen the peasantry of Naples dancing among the vines, reckless of the burning mountain which threatened to overwhelm them, was now in possession of a strong serpent of engine-hose, watchfully lying in wait for the serpent Fire, and ready to fly at it if it showed its forked tongue. A ghost of a watchman, carrying a faint corpse candle, haunted the distant upper gallery and flitted away. Retiring within the proscenium, and holding my light above my head towards the rolled-up curtain - green no more, but black as ebony - my sight lost itself in a gloomy vault, showing faint indications in it of a shipwreck of canvas and cordage. Methought I felt much as a diver might, at the bottom of the sea.

In those small hours when there was no movement in the streets, it afforded matter for reflection to take Newgate in the way, and, touching its rough stone, to think of the prisoners in their sleep, and then to glance in at the lodge over the spiked wicket, and see the fire and light of the watching turnkeys, on the white wall. Not an inappropriate time either, to linger by that wicked little Debtors’ Door - shutting tighter than any other door one ever saw - which has been Death’s Door to so many. In the days of the uttering of forged one-pound notes by people tempted up from the country, how many hundreds of wretched creatures of both sexes - many quite innocent - swung out of a pitiless and inconsistent world, with the tower of yonder Christian church of Saint Sepulchre monstrously before their eyes! Is there any haunting of the Bank Parlour, by the remorseful souls of old directors, in the nights of these later days, I wonder, or is it as quiet as this degenerate Aceldama of an Old Bailey?

To walk on to the Bank, lamenting the good old times and bemoaning the present evil period, would be an easy next step, so I would take it, and would make my houseless circuit of the Bank, and give a thought to the treasure within; likewise to the guard of soldiers passing the night there, and nodding over the fire. Next, I went to Billingsgate, in some hope of market-people, but it proving as yet too early, crossed London-bridge and got down by the waterside on the Surrey shore among the buildings of the great brewery. There was plenty going on at the brewery; and the reek, and the smell of grains, and the rattling of the plump dray horses at their mangers, were capital company. Quite refreshed by having mingled with this good society, I made a new start with a new heart, setting the old King’s Bench prison before me for my next object, and resolving, when I should come to the wall, to think of poor Horace Kinch, and the Dry Rot in men.

A very curious disease the Dry Rot in men, and difficult to detect the beginning of. It had carried Horace Kinch inside the wall of the old King’s Bench prison, and it had carried him out with his feet foremost. He was a likely man to look at, in the prime of life, well to do, as clever as he needed to be, and popular among many friends. He was suitably married, and had healthy and pretty children. But, like some fair-looking houses or fair-looking ships, he took the Dry Rot. The first strong external revelation of the Dry Rot in men, is a tendency to lurk and lounge; to be at street-corners without intelligible reason; to be going anywhere when met; to be about many places rather than at any; to do nothing tangible, but to have an intention of performing a variety of intangible duties to-morrow or the day after. When this manifestation of the disease is observed, the observer will usually connect it with a vague impression once formed or received, that the patient was living a little too hard. He will scarcely have had leisure to turn it over in his mind and form the terrible suspicion ‘Dry Rot,’ when he will notice a change for the worse in the patient’s appearance: a certain slovenliness and deterioration, which is not poverty, nor dirt, nor intoxication, nor ill-health, but simply Dry Rot. To this, succeeds a smell as of strong waters, in the morning; to that, a looseness respecting money; to that, a stronger smell as of strong waters, at all times; to that, a looseness respecting everything; to that, a trembling of the limbs, somnolency, misery, and crumbling to pieces. As it is in wood, so it is in men. Dry Rot advances at a compound usury quite incalculable. A plank is found infected with it, and the whole structure is devoted. Thus it had been with the unhappy Horace Kinch, lately buried by a small subscription. Those who knew him had not nigh done saying, ‘So well off, so comfortably established, with such hope before him - and yet, it is feared, with a slight touch of Dry Rot!’ when lo! the man was all Dry Rot and dust.

From the dead wall associated on those houseless nights with this too common story, I chose next to wander by Bethlehem Hospital; partly, because it lay on my road round to Westminster; partly, because I had a night fancy in my head which could be best pursued within sight of its walls and dome. And the fancy was this: Are not the sane and the insane equal at night as the sane lie a dreaming? Are not all of us outside this hospital, who dream, more or less in the condition of those inside it, every night of our lives? Are we not nightly persuaded, as they daily are, that we associate preposterously with kings and queens, emperors and empresses, and notabilities of all sorts? Do we not nightly jumble events and personages and times and places, as these do daily? Are we not sometimes troubled by our own sleeping inconsistencies, and do we not vexedly try to account for them or excuse them, just as these do sometimes in respect of their waking delusions? Said an afflicted man to me, when I was last in a hospital like this, ‘Sir, I can frequently fly.’ I was half ashamed to reflect that so could I - by night. Said a woman to me on the same occasion, ‘Queen Victoria frequently comes to dine with me, and her Majesty and I dine off peaches and maccaroni in our nightgowns, and his Royal Highness the Prince Consort does us the honour to make a third on horseback in a Field-Marshal’s uniform.’ Could I refrain from reddening with consciousness when I remembered the amazing royal parties I myself had given (at night), the unaccountable viands I had put on table, and my extraordinary manner of conducting myself on those distinguished occasions? I wonder that the great master who knew everything, when he called Sleep the death of each day’s life, did not call Dreams the insanity of each day’s sanity.

By this time I had left the Hospital behind me, and was again setting towards the river; and in a short breathing space I was on Westminster-bridge, regaling my houseless eyes with the external walls of the British Parliament - the perfection of a stupendous institution, I know, and the admiration of all surrounding nations and succeeding ages, I do not doubt, but perhaps a little the better now and then for being pricked up to its work. Turning off into Old Palace-yard, the Courts of Law kept me company for a quarter of an hour; hinting in low whispers what numbers of people they were keeping awake, and how intensely wretched and horrible they were rendering the small hours to unfortunate suitors. Westminster Abbey was fine gloomy society for another quarter of an hour; suggesting a wonderful procession of its dead among the dark arches and pillars, each century more amazed by the century following it than by all the centuries going before. And indeed in those houseless night walks - which even included cemeteries where watchmen went round among the graves at stated times, and moved the tell-tale handle of an index which recorded that they had touched it at such an hour - it was a solemn consideration what enormous hosts of dead belong to one old great city, and how, if they were raised while the living slept, there would not be the space of a pin’s point in all the streets and ways for the living to come out into. Not only that, but the vast armies of dead would overflow the hills and valleys beyond the city, and would stretch away all round it, God knows how far.

When a church clock strikes, on houseless ears in the dead of the night, it may be at first mistaken for company and hailed as such. But, as the spreading circles of vibration, which you may perceive at such a time with great clearness, go opening out, for ever and ever afterwards widening perhaps (as the philosopher has suggested) in eternal space, the mistake is rectified and the sense of loneliness is profounder. Once - it was after leaving the Abbey and turning my face north - I came to the great steps of St. Martin’s church as the clock was striking Three. Suddenly, a thing that in a moment more I should have trodden upon without seeing, rose up at my feet with a cry of loneliness and houselessness, struck out of it by the bell, the like of which I never heard. We then stood face to face looking at one another, frightened by one another. The creature was like a beetle-browed hairlipped youth of twenty, and it had a loose bundle of rags on, which it held together with one of its hands. It shivered from head to foot, and its teeth chattered, and as it stared at me - persecutor, devil, ghost, whatever it thought me - it made with its whining mouth as if it were snapping at me, like a worried dog. Intending to give this ugly object money, I put out my hand to stay it - for it recoiled as it whined and snapped - and laid my hand upon its shoulder. Instantly, it twisted out of its garment, like the young man in the New Testament, and left me standing alone with its rags in my hands.

Covent-garden Market, when it was market morning, was wonderful company. The great waggons of cabbages, with growers’ men and boys lying asleep under them, and with sharp dogs from market-garden neighbourhoods looking after the whole, were as good as a party. But one of the worst night sights I know in London, is to be found in the children who prowl about this place; who sleep in the baskets, fight for the offal, dart at any object they think they can lay their thieving hands on, dive under the carts and barrows, dodge the constables, and are perpetually making a blunt pattering on the pavement of the Piazza with the rain of their naked feet. A painful and unnatural result comes of the comparison one is forced to institute between the growth of corruption as displayed in the so much improved and cared for fruits of the earth, and the growth of corruption as displayed in these all uncared for (except inasmuch as ever-hunted) savages.

There was early coffee to be got about Covent-garden Market, and that was more company - warm company, too, which was better. Toast of a very substantial quality, was likewise procurable: though the towzled-headed man who made it, in an inner chamber within the coffeeroom, hadn’t got his coat on yet, and was so heavy with sleep that in every interval of toast and coffee he went off anew behind the partition into complicated cross-roads of choke and snore, and lost his way directly. Into one of these establishments (among the earliest) near Bowstreet, there came one morning as I sat over my houseless cup, pondering where to go next, a man in a high and long snuff-coloured coat, and shoes, and, to the best of my belief, nothing else but a hat, who took out of his hat a large cold meat pudding; a meat pudding so large that it was a very tight fit, and brought the lining of the hat out with it. This mysterious man was known by his pudding, for on his entering, the men of sleep brought him a pint of hot tea, a small loaf, and a large knife and fork and plate. Left to himself in his box, he stood the pudding on the bare table, and, instead of cutting it stabbed it, overhand, with the knife, like a mortal enemy; then took the knife out, wiped it on his sleeve, tore the pudding asunder with his fingers, and ate it all up. The remembrance of this man with the pudding remains with me as the remembrance of the most spectral person my houselessness encountered. Twice only was I in that establishment, and twice I saw him stalk in (as I should say, just out of bed, and presently going back to bed), take out his pudding, stab his pudding, wipe the dagger, and eat his pudding all up. He was a man whose figure promised cadaverousness, but, who had an excessively red face, though shaped like a horse’s. On the second occasion of my seeing him, he said huskily to the man of sleep, ‘Am I red to-night?’ ‘You are,’ he uncompromisingly answered. ‘My mother,’ said the spectre, ‘was a red-faced woman that liked drink, and I looked at her hard when she laid in her coffin, and I took the complexion.’ Somehow, the pudding seemed an unwholesome pudding after that, and I put myself in its way no more.

When there was no market, or when I wanted variety, a railway terminus with the morning mails coming in, was remunerative company. But like most of the company to be had in this world, it lasted only a very short time. The station lamps would burst out ablaze, the porters would emerge from places of concealment, the cabs and trucks would rattle to their places (the post-office carts were already in theirs), and, finally, the bell would strike up, and the train would come banging in. But there were few passengers and little luggage, and everything scuttled away with the greatest expedition. The locomotive post-offices, with their great nets - as if they had been dragging the country for bodies - would fly open as to their doors, and would disgorge a smell of lamp, an exhausted clerk, a guard in a red coat, and their bags of letters; the engine would blow and heave and perspire, like an engine wiping its forehead and saying what a run it had had; and within ten minutes the lamps were out, and I was houseless and alone again.

But now, there were driven cattle on the high road near, wanting (as cattle always do) to turn into the midst of stone walls, and squeeze themselves through six inches’ width of iron railing, and getting their heads down (also as cattle always do) for tossing-purchase at quite imaginary dogs, and giving themselves and every devoted creature associated with them a most extraordinary amount of unnecessary trouble. Now, too, the conscious gas began to grow pale with the knowledge that daylight was coming, and straggling work-people were already in the streets, and, as waking life had become extinguished with the last pieman’s sparks, so it began to be rekindled with the fires of the first street-corner breakfast-sellers. And so by faster and faster degrees, until the last degrees were very fast, the day came, and I was tired and could sleep. And it is not, as I used to think, going home at such times, the least wonderful thing in London, that in the real desert region of the night, the houseless wanderer is alone there. I knew well enough where to find Vice and Misfortune of all kinds, if I had chosen; but they were put out of sight, and my houselessness had many miles upon miles of streets in which it could, and did, have its own solitary way.

Gone Astray

When I was a very small boy indeed, both in years and stature, I got lost one day in the City of London. I was taken out by Somebody (shade of Somebody forgive me for remembering no more of thy identity!), as an immense treat, to be shown the outside of Saint Giles’s Church. I had romantic ideas in connexion with that religious edifice; firmly believing that all the beggars who pretended through the week to be blind, lame, one-armed, deaf and dumb, and otherwise physically afflicted, laid aside their pretences every Sunday, dressed themselves in holiday clothes, and attended divine service in the temple of their patron saint. I had a general idea that the reigning successor of Bamfylde Moore Carew acted as a sort of church-warden on these occasions, and sat in a high pew with red curtains.

It was in the spring-time when these tender notions of mine, bursting forth into new shoots under the influence of the season, became sufficiently troublesome to my parents and guardians to occasion Somebody to volunteer to take me to see the outside of Saint Giles’s Church, which was considered likely (I suppose) to quench my romantic fire, and bring me to a practical state. We set off after breakfast. I have an impression that Somebody was got up in a striking manner - in cord breeches of fine texture and milky hue, in long jean gaiters, in a green coat with bright buttons, in a blue neckerchief, and a monstrous shirt-collar. I think he must have newly come (as I had myself) out of the hop-grounds of Kent. I considered him the glass of fashion and the mould of form: a very Hamlet without the burden of his difficult family affairs.

We were conversational together, and saw the outside of Saint Giles’s Church with sentiments of satisfaction, much enhanced by a flag flying from the steeple. I infer that we then went down to Northumberland House in the Strand to view the celebrated lion over the gateway. At all events, I know that in the act of looking up with mingled awe and admiration at that famous animal I lost Somebody.

The child’s unreasoning terror of being lost, comes as freshly on me now as it did then. I verily believe that if I had found myself astray at the North Pole instead of in the narrow, crowded, inconvenient street over which the lion in those days presided, I could not have been more horrified. But, this first fright expended itself in a little crying and tearing up and down; and then I walked, with a feeling of dismal dignity upon me, into a court, and sat down on a step to consider how to get through life.

To the best of my belief, the idea of asking my way home never came into my head. It is possible that I may, for the time, have preferred the dismal dignity of being lost; but I have a serious conviction that in the wide scope of my arrangements for the future, I had no eyes for the nearest and most obvious course. I was but very juvenile; from eight to nine years old, I fancy.

I had one and fourpence in my pocket, and a pewter ring with a bit of red glass in it on my little finger. This jewel had been presented to me by the object of my affections, on my birthday, when we had sworn to marry, but had foreseen family obstacles to our union, in her being (she was six years old) of the Wesleyan persuasion, while I was devotedly attached to the Church of England. The one and fourpence were the remains of half-a-crown presented on the same anniversary by my godfather - a man who knew his duty and did it.

Armed with these amulets, I made up my little mind to seek my fortune. When I had found it, I thought I would drive home in a coach and six, and claim my bride. I cried a little more at the idea of such a triumph, but soon dried my eyes and came out of the court to pursue my plans. These were, first to go (as a species of investment) and see the Giants in Guildhall, out of whom I felt it not improbable that some prosperous adventure would arise; failing that contingency, to try about the City for any opening of a Whittington nature; baffled in that too, to go into the army as a drummer.

So, I began to ask my way to Guildhall: which I thought meant, somehow, Gold or Golden Hall; I was too knowing to ask my way to the Giants, for I felt it would make people laugh. I remember how immensely broad the streets seemed now I was alone, how high the houses, how grand and mysterious everything. When I came to Temple Bar, it took me half an hour to stare at it, and I left it unfinished even then. I had read about heads being exposed on the top of Temple Bar, and it seemed a wicked old place, albeit a noble monument of architecture and a paragon of utility. When at last I got away from it, behold I came, the next minute, on the figures at St. Dunstan’s! Who could see those obliging monsters strike upon the bells and go? Between the quarters there was the toyshop to look at - still there, at this present writing, in a new form - and even when that enchanted spot was escaped from, after an hour and more, then Saint Paul’s arose, and how was I to get beyond its dome, or to take my eyes from its cross of gold? I found it a long journey to the Giants, and a slow one.

I came into their presence at last, and gazed up at them with dread and veneration. They looked better-tempered, and were altogether more shiny-faced, than I had expected; but they were very big, and, as I judged their pedestals to be about forty feet high, I considered that they would be very big indeed if they were walking on the stone pavement. I was in a state of mind as to these and all such figures, which I suppose holds equally with most children. While I knew them to be images made of something that was not flesh and blood, I still invested them with attributes of life - with consciousness of my being there, for example, and the power of keeping a sly eye upon me. Being very tired I got into the corner under Magog, to be out of the way of his eye, and fell asleep.

When I started up after a long nap, I thought the giants were roaring, but it was only the City. The place was just the same as when I fell asleep: no beanstalk, no fairy, no princess, no dragon, no opening in life of any kind. So, being hungry, I thought I would buy something to eat, and bring it in there and eat it, before going forth to seek my fortune on the Whittington plan.

I was not ashamed of buying a penny roll in a baker’s shop, but I looked into a number of cooks’ shops before I could muster courage to go into one. At last I saw a pile of cooked sausages in a window with the label ‘Small Germans, A Penny.’ Emboldened by knowing what to ask for, I went in and said, ‘If you please will you sell me a small German?’ which they did, and I took it, wrapped in paper in my pocket, to Guildhall.

The giants were still lying by, in their sly way, pretending to take no notice, so I sat down in another corner, when what should I see before me but a dog with his ears cocked. He was a black dog, with a bit of white over one eye, and bits of white and tan in his paws, and he wanted to play - frisking about me, rubbing his nose against me, dodging at me sideways, shaking his head and pretending to run away backwards, and making himself goodnaturedly ridiculous, as if he had no consideration for himself, but wanted to raise my spirits. Now, when I saw this dog I thought of Whittington, and felt that things were coming right; I encouraged him by saying, ‘Hi, boy!’ ‘Poor fellow!’ ‘Good dog!’ and was satisfied that he was to be my dog for ever afterwards, and that he would help me to seek my fortune.

Very much comforted by this (I had cried a little at odd times ever since I was lost), I took the small German out of my pocket, and began my dinner by biting off a bit and throwing it to the dog, who immediately swallowed it with a one-sided jerk, like a pill. While I took a bit myself, and he looked me in the face for a second piece, I considered by what name I should call him. I thought Merrychance would be an expressive name, under the circumstances; and I was elated, I recollect, by inventing such a good one, when Merrychance began to growl at me in a most ferocious manner.

I wondered he was not ashamed of himself, but he didn’t care for that; on the contrary he growled a good deal more. With his mouth watering, and his eyes glistening, and his nose in a very damp state, and his head very much on one side, he sidled about on the pavement in a threatening manner and growled at me, until he suddenly made a snap at the small German, tore it out of my hand, and went off with it. He never came back to help me seek my fortune. From that hour to the present, when I am forty years of age, I have never seen my faithful Merrychance again.

I felt very lonely. Not so much for the loss of the small German, though it was delicious (I knew nothing about highly-peppered horse at that time), as on account of Merrychance’s disappointing me so cruelly; for I had hoped he would do every friendly thing but speak, and perhaps even come to that. I cried a little more, and began to wish that the object of my affections had been lost with me, for company’s sake. But, then I remembered that she could not go into the army as a drummer; and I dried my eyes and ate my loaf. Coming out, I met a milkwoman, of whom I bought a pennyworth of milk; quite set up again by my repast, I began to roam about the City, and to seek my fortune in the Whittington direction.

When I go into the City, now, it makes me sorrowful to think that I am quite an artful wretch. Strolling about it as a lost child, I thought of the British Merchant and the Lord Mayor, and was full of reverence. Strolling about it now, I laugh at the sacred liveries of state, and get indignant with the corporation as one of the strongest practical jokes of the present day. What did I know then, about the multitude who are always being disappointed in the City; who are always expecting to meet a party there, and to receive money there, and whose expectations are never fulfilled? What did I know then, about that wonderful person, the friend in the City, who is to do so many things for so many people; who is to get this one into a post at home, and that one into a post abroad; who is to settle with this man’s creditors, provide for that man’s son, and see that other man paid; who is to ‘throw himself’ into this grand Joint-Stock certainty, and is to put his name down on that Life Assurance Directory, and never does anything predicted of him? What did I know, then, about him as the friend of gentlemen, Mosaic Arabs and others, usually to be seen at races, and chiefly residing in the neighbourhood of Red Lion Square; and as being unable to discount the whole amount of that paper in money, but as happening to have by him a cask of remarkable fine sherry, a dressing-case, and a Venus by Titian, with which he would be willing to make up the balance? Had I ever heard of him, in those innocent days, as confiding information (which never by any chance turned out to be in the remotest degree correct) to solemn bald men, who mysteriously imparted it to breathless dinner tables? No. Had I ever learned to dread him as a shark, disregard him as a humbug, and know him for a myth? Not I. Had I ever heard of him as associated with tightness in the money market, gloom in consols, the exportation of gold, or that rock ahead in everybody’s course, the bushel of wheat? Never. Had I the least idea what was meant by such terms as jobbery, rigging the market, cooking accounts, getting up a dividend, making things pleasant, and the like? Not the slightest. Should I have detected in Mr. Hudson himself, a staring carcase of golden veal? By no manner of means. The City was to me a vast emporium of precious stones and metals, casks and bales, honour and generosity, foreign fruits and spices. Every merchant and banker was a compound of Mr. Fitz-Warren and Sinbad the Sailor. Smith, Payne, and Smith, when the wind was fair for Barbary and the captain present, were in the habit of calling their servants together (the cross cook included) and asking them to produce their little shipments. Glyn and Halifax had personally undergone great hardships in the valley of diamonds. Baring Brothers had seen Rocs’ eggs and travelled with caravans. Rothschild had sat in the Bazaar at Bagdad with rich stuffs for sale; and a veiled lady from the Sultan’s harem, riding on a donkey, had fallen in love with him.

Thus I wandered about the City, like a child in a dream, staring at the British merchants, and inspired by a mighty faith in the marvellousness of everything. Up courts and down courts - in and out of yards and little squares - peeping into counting-house passages and running away - poorly feeding the echoes in the court of the South Sea House with my timid steps - roaming down into Austin Friars, and wondering how the Friars used to like it - ever staring at the British merchants, and never tired of the shops - I rambled on, all through the day. In such stories as I made, to account for the different places, I believed as devoutly as in the City itself. I particularly remember that when I found myself on ‘Change, and saw the shabby people sitting under the placards about ships, I settled that they were Misers, who had embarked all their wealth to go and buy gold-dust or something of that sort, and were waiting for their respective captains to come and tell them that they were ready to set sail. I observed that they all munched dry biscuits, and I thought it was to keep off sea-sickness.

This was very delightful; but it still produced no result according to the Whittington precedent. There was a dinner preparing at the Mansion House, and when I peeped in at a grated kitchen window, and saw the men cooks at work in their white caps, my heart began to beat with hope that the Lord Mayor, or the Lady Mayoress, or one of the young Princesses their daughters, would look out of an upper apartment and direct me to be taken in. But, nothing of the kind occurred. It was not until I had been peeping in some time that one of the cooks called to me (the window was open) ‘Cut away, you sir!’ which frightened me so, on account of his black whiskers, that I instantly obeyed.

After that, I came to the India House, and asked a boy what it was, who made faces and pulled my hair before he told me, and behaved altogether in an ungenteel and discourteous manner. Sir James Hogg himself might have been satisfied with the veneration in which I held the India House. I had no doubt of its being the most wonderful, the most magnanimous, the most incorruptible, the most practically disinterested, the most in all respects astonishing, establishment on the face of the earth. I understood the nature of an oath, and would have sworn it to be one entire and perfect chrysolite.

Thinking much about boys who went to India, and who immediately, without being sick, smoked pipes like curled-up bell-ropes, terminating in a large cut-glass sugar basin upside down, I got among the outfitting shops. There, I read the lists of things that were necessary for an India-going boy, and when I came to ‘one brace of pistols,’ thought what happiness to be reserved for such a fate! Still no British merchant seemed at all disposed to take me into his house. The only exception was a chimney-sweep - he looked at me as if he thought me suitable to his business; but I ran away from him.

I suffered very much, all day, from boys; they chased me down turnings, brought me to bay in doorways, and treated me quite savagely, though I am sure I gave them no offence. One boy, who had a stump of black-lead pencil in his pocket, wrote his mother’s name and address (as he said) on my white hat, outside the crown. MRS. BLORES, WOODEN LEG WALK, TOBACCO-STOPPER ROW, WAPPING. And I couldn’t rub it out.

I recollect resting in a little churchyard after this persecution, disposed to think upon the whole, that if I and the object of my affections could be buried there together, at once, it would be comfortable. But, another nap, and a pump, and a bun, and above all a picture that I saw, brought me round again.

I must have strayed by that time, as I recall my course, into Goodman’s fields, or somewhere thereabouts. The picture represented a scene in a play then performing at a theatre in that neighbourhood which is no longer in existence. It stimulated me to go to that theatre and see that play. I resolved, as there seemed to be nothing doing in the Whittington way, that on the conclusion of the entertainments I would ask my way to the barracks, knock at the gate, and tell them that I understood they were in want of drummers, and there I was. I think I must have been told, but I know I believed, that a soldier was always on duty, day and night, behind every barrack-gate, with a shilling; and that a boy who could by any means be prevailed on to accept it, instantly became a drummer, unless his father paid four hundred pounds.

I found out the theatre - of its external appearance I only remember the loyal initials G. R. untidily painted in yellow ochre on the front - and waited, with a pretty large crowd, for the opening of the gallery doors. The greater part of the sailors and others composing the crowd, were of the lowest description, and their conversation was not improving; but I understood little or nothing of what was bad in it then, and it had no depraving influence on me. I have wondered since, how long it would take, by means of such association, to corrupt a child nurtured as I had been, and innocent as I was.

Whenever I saw that my appearance attracted attention, either outside the doors or afterwards within the theatre, I pretended to look out for somebody who was taking care of me, and from whom I was separated, and to exchange nods and smiles with that creature of my imagination. This answered very well. I had my sixpence clutched in my hand ready to pay; and when the doors opened, with a clattering of bolts, and some screaming from women in the crowd, I went on with the current like a straw. My sixpence was rapidly swallowed up in the money-taker’s pigeon-hole, which looked to me like a sort of mouth, and I got into the freer staircase above and ran on (as everybody else did) to get a good place. When I came to the back of the gallery, there were very few people in it, and the seats looked so horribly steep, and so like a diving arrangement to send me, headforemost, into the pit, that I held by one of them in a terrible fright. However, there was a good-natured baker with a young woman, who gave me his hand, and we all three scrambled over the seats together down into the corner of the first row. The baker was very fond of the young woman, and kissed her a good deal in the course of the evening.

I was no sooner comfortably settled, than a weight fell upon my mind, which tormented it most dreadfully, and which I must explain. It was a benefit night - the benefit of the comic actor - a little fat man with a very large face and, as I thought then, the smallest and most diverting hat that ever was seen. This comedian, for the gratification of his friends and patrons, had undertaken to sing a comic song on a donkey’s back, and afterwards to give away the donkey so distinguished, by lottery. In this lottery, every person admitted to the pit and gallery had a chance. On paying my sixpence, I had received the number, fortyseven; and I now thought, in a perspiration of terror, what should I ever do if that number was to come up the prize, and I was to win the donkey!

It made me tremble all over to think of the possibility of my good fortune. I knew I never could conceal the fact of my holding forty-seven, in case that number came up, because, not to speak of my confusion, which would immediately condemn me, I had shewn my number to the baker. Then, I pictured to myself the being called upon to come down on the stage and receive the donkey. I thought how all the people would shriek when they saw it had fallen to a little fellow like me. How should I lead him out - for of course he wouldn’t go? If he began to bray, what should I do? If he kicked, what would become of me? Suppose he backed into the stage-door, and stuck there, with me upon him? For I felt that if I won him, the comic actor would have me on his back, the moment he could touch me. Then if I got him out of the theatre, what was I to do with him? How was I to feed him? Where was I to stable him? It was bad enough to have gone astray by myself, but to go astray with a donkey, too, was a calamity more tremendous than I could bear to contemplate.

These apprehensions took away all my pleasure in the first piece. When the ship came on - a real man-of-war she was called in the bills - and rolled prodigiously in a very heavy sea, I couldn’t, even in the terrors of the storm, forget the donkey. It was awful to see the sailors pitching about, with telescopes and speaking trumpets (they looked very tall indeed aboard the man-of-war), and it was awful to suspect the pilot of treachery, though impossible to avoid it, for when he cried - ‘We are lost! To the raft, to the raft! A thunderbolt has struck the mainmast!’ - I myself saw him take the main-mast out of its socket and drop it overboard; but even these impressive circumstances paled before my dread of the donkey. Even, when the good sailor (and he was very good) came to good fortune, and the bad sailor (and he was very bad) threw himself into the ocean from the summit of a curious rock, presenting something of the appearance of a pair of steps, I saw the dreadful donkey through my tears.

At last the time came when the fiddlers struck up the comic song, and the dreaded animal, with new shoes on, as I inferred from the noise they made, came clattering in with the comic actor on his back. He was dressed out with ribbons (I mean the donkey was) and as he persisted in turning his tail to the audience, the comedian got off him, turned about, and sitting with his face that way, sang the song three times, amid thunders of applause. All this time, I was fearfully agitated; and when two pale people, a good deal splashed with the mud of the streets, were invited out of the pit to superintend the drawing of the lottery, and were received with a round of laughter from everybody else, I could have begged and prayed them to have mercy on me, and not draw number forty-seven.

But, I was soon put out of my pain now, for a gentleman behind me, in a flannel jacket and a yellow neckkerchief, who had eaten two fried soles and all his pocketsfull of nuts before the storm began to rage, answered to the winning number, and went down to take possession of the prize. This gentleman had appeared to know the donkey, rather, from the moment of his entrance, and had taken a great interest in his proceedings; driving him to himself, if I use an intelligible phrase, and saying, almost in my ear, when he made any mistake, ‘Kum up, you precious Moke. Kum up!’ He was thrown by the donkey on first mounting him, to the great delight of the audience (including myself), but rode him off with great skill afterwards, and soon returned to his seat quite calm. Calmed myself by the immense relief I had sustained, I enjoyed the rest of the performance very much indeed. I remember there were a good many dances, some in fetters and some in roses, and one by a most divine little creature, who made the object of my affections look but commonplace. In the concluding drama, she re-appeared as a boy (in arms, mostly), and was fought for, several times. I rather think a Baron wanted to drown her, and was on various occasions prevented by the comedian, a ghost, a Newfoundland dog, and a church bell. I only remember beyond this, that I wondered where the Baron expected to go to, and that he went there in a shower of sparks. The lights were turned out while the sparks died out, and it appeared to me as if the whole play - ship, donkey, men and women, divine little creature, and all - were a wonderful firework that had gone off, and left nothing but dust and darkness behind it.

It was late when I got out into the streets, and there was no moon, and there were no stars, and the rain fell heavily. When I emerged from the dispersing crowd, the ghost and the baron had an ugly look in my remembrance; I felt unspeakably forlorn; and now, for the first time, my little bed and the dear familiar faces came before me, and touched my heart. By daylight, I had never thought of the grief at home. I had never thought of my mother. I had never thought of anything but adapting myself to the circumstances in which I found myself, and going to seek my fortune.

For a boy who could do nothing but cry, and run about, saying, ‘O I am lost!’ to think of going into the army was, I felt sensible, out of the question. I abandoned the idea of asking my way to the barracks - or rather the idea abandoned me - and ran about, until I found a watchman in his box. It is amazing to me, now, that he should have been sober; but I am inclined to think he was too feeble to get drunk.

This venerable man took me to the nearest watchhouse; - I say he took me, but in fact I took him, for when I think of us in the rain, I recollect that we must have made a composition, like a vignette of Infancy leading Age. He had a dreadful cough, and was obliged to lean against a wall, whenever it came on. We got at last to the watch-house, a warm and drowsy sort of place embellished with great-coats and rattles hanging up. When a paralytic messenger had been sent to make inquiries about me, I fell asleep by the fire, and awoke no more until my eyes opened on my father’s face. This is literally and exactly how I went astray. They used to say I was an odd child, and I suppose I was. I am an odd man perhaps.

Shade of Somebody, forgive me for the disquiet I must have caused thee! When I stand beneath the Lion, even now, I see thee rushing up and down, refusing to be comforted. I have gone astray since, many times, and farther afield. May I therein have given less disquiet to others, than herein I gave to thee!

Chatham Dockyard

There are some small out-of-the-way landing-places on the Thames and the Medway, where I do much of my summer idling. Running water is favourable to day-dreams, and a strong tidal river is the best of running water for mine. I like to watch the great ships standing out to sea or coming home richly laden, the active little steam-tugs confidently puffing with them to and from the sea-horizon, the fleet of barges that seem to have plucked their brown and russet sails from the ripe trees in the landscape, the heavy old colliers, light in ballast, floundering down before the tide, the light screw barks and schooners imperiously holding a straight course while the others patiently tack and go about, the yachts with their tiny hulls and great white sheets of canvas, the little sailing-boats bobbing to and fro on their errands of pleasure or business, and - as it is the nature of little people to do - making a prodigious fuss about their small affairs. Watching these objects, I still am under no obligation to think about them, or even so much as to see them, unless it perfectly suits my humour. As little am I obliged to hear the plash and flop of the tide, the ripple at my feet, the clinking windlass afar off, or the humming steam-ship paddles further away yet. These, with the creaking little jetty on which I sit, and the gaunt high-water marks and low-water marks in the mud, and the broken causeway, and the broken bank, and the broken stakes and piles leaning forward as if they were vain of their personal appearance and looking for their reflection in the water, will melt into any train of fancy. Equally adaptable to any purpose or to none, are the pasturing sheep and kine upon the marshes, the gulls that wheel and dip around me, the crows (well out of gunshot) going home from the rich harvest-fields, the heron that has been out a-fishing and looks as melancholy, up there in the sky, as if it hadn’t agreed with him. Everything within the range of the senses will, by the aid of the running water, lend itself to everything beyond that range, and work into a drowsy whole, not unlike a kind of tune, but for which there is no exact definition.

One of these landing-places is near an old fort (I can see the Nore Light from it with my pocket-glass), from which fort mysteriously emerges a boy, to whom I am much indebted for additions to my scanty stock of knowledge. He is a young boy, with an intelligent face burnt to a dust colour by the summer sun, and with crisp hair of the same hue. He is a boy in whom I have perceived nothing incompatible with habits of studious inquiry and meditation, unless an evanescent black eye (I was delicate of inquiring how occasioned) should be so considered. To him am I indebted for ability to identify a Custom-house boat at any distance, and for acquaintance with all the forms and ceremonies observed by a homeward-bound Indiaman coming up the river, when the Custom-house officers go aboard her. But for him, I might never have heard of ‘the dumbague,’ respecting which malady I am now learned. Had I never sat at his feet, I might have finished my mortal career and never known that when I see a white horse on a barge’s sail, that barge is a lime barge. For precious secrets in reference to beer, am I likewise beholden to him, involving warning against the beer of a certain establishment, by reason of its having turned sour through failure in point of demand: though my young sage is not of the opinion that similar deterioration has befallen the ale. He has also enlightened me touching the mushrooms of the marshes, and has gently reproved my ignorance in having supposed them to be impregnated with salt. His manner of imparting information, is thoughtful, and appropriate to the scene. As he reclines beside me, he pitches into the river, a little stone or piece of grit, and then delivers himself oracularly, as though he spoke out of the centre of the spreading circle that it makes in the water. He never improves my mind without observing this formula.

With the wise boy - whom I know by no other name than the Spirit of the Fort - I recently consorted on a breezy day when the river leaped about us and was full of life. I had seen the sheaved corn carrying in the golden fields as I came down to the river; and the rosy farmer, watching his labouring-men in the saddle on his cob, had told me how he had reaped his two hundred and sixty acres of long-strawed corn last week, and how a better week’s work he had never done in all his days. Peace and abundance were on the country-side in beautiful forms and beautiful colours, and the harvest seemed even to be sailing out to grace the never-reaped sea in the yellowladen barges that mellowed the distance.

It was on this occasion that the Spirit of the Fort, directing his remarks to a certain floating iron battery lately lying in that reach of the river, enriched my mind with his opinions on naval architecture, and informed me that he would like to be an engineer. I found him up to everything that is done in the contracting line by Messrs. Peto and Brassey - cunning in the article of concrete - mellow in the matter of iron - great on the subject of gunnery. When he spoke of pile-driving and sluice-making, he left me not a leg to stand on, and I can never sufficiently acknowledge his forbearance with me in my disabled state. While he thus discoursed, he several times directed his eyes to one distant quarter of the landscape, and spoke with vague mysterious awe of ‘the Yard.’ Pondering his lessons after we had parted, I bethought me that the Yard was one of our large public Dockyards, and that it lay hidden among the crops down in the dip behind the windmills, as if it modestly kept itself out of view in peaceful times, and sought to trouble no man. Taken with this modesty on the part of the Yard, I resolved to improve the Yard’s acquaintance.

My good opinion of the Yard’s retiring character was not dashed by nearer approach. It resounded with the noise of hammers beating upon iron; and the great sheds or slips under which the mighty men-of-war are built, loomed business-like when contemplated from the opposite side of the river. For all that, however, the Yard made no display, but kept itself snug under hill-sides of cornfields, hop-gardens, and orchards; its great chimneys smoking with a quiet - almost a lazy - air, like giants smoking tobacco; and the great Shears moored off it, looking meekly and inoffensively out of proportion, like the Giraffe of the machinery creation. The store of cannon on the neighbouring gun-wharf, had an innocent toy-like appearance, and the one red-coated sentry on duty over them was a mere toy figure, with a clock-work movement. As the hot sunlight sparkled on him he might have passed for the identical little man who had the little gun, and whose bullets they were made of lead, lead, lead.

Crossing the river and landing at the Stairs, where a drift of chips and weed had been trying to land before me and had not succeeded, but had got into a corner instead, I found the very street posts to be cannon, and the architectural ornaments to be shells. And so I came to the Yard, which was shut up tight and strong with great folded gates, like an enormous patent safe. These gates devouring me, I became digested into the Yard; and it had, at first, a clean-swept holiday air, as if it had given over work until next war-time. Though indeed a quantity of hemp for rope was tumbling out of store-houses, even there, which would hardly be lying like so much hay on the white stones if the Yard were as placid as it pretended.

Ding, Clash, Dong, BANG, Boom, Rattle, Clash, BANG, Clink, BANG, Dong, BANG, Clatter, BANG BANG BANG! What on earth is this! This is, or soon will be, the Achilles, iron armour-plated ship. Twelve hundred men are working at her now; twelve hundred men working on stages over her sides, over her bows, over her stern, under her keel, between her decks, down in her hold, within her and without, crawling and creeping into the finest curves of her lines wherever it is possible for men to twist. Twelve hundred hammerers, measurers, caulkers, armourers, forgers, smiths, shipwrights; twelve hundred dingers, clashers, dongers, rattlers, clinkers, bangers bangers bangers! Yet all this stupendous uproar around the rising Achilles is as nothing to the reverberations with which the perfected Achilles shall resound upon the dreadful day when the full work is in hand for which this is but note of preparation - the day when the scuppers that are now fitting like great dry thirsty conduit-pipes, shall run red. All these busy figures between decks, dimly seen bending at their work in smoke and fire, are as nothing to the figures that shall do work here of another kind in smoke and fire, that day. These steam-worked engines alongside, helping the ship by travelling to and fro, and wafting tons of iron plates about, as though they were so many leaves of trees, would be rent limb from limb if they stood by her for a minute then. To think that this Achilles, monstrous compound of iron tank and oaken chest, can ever swim or roll! To think that any force of wind and wave could ever break her! To think that wherever I see a glowing red-hot iron point thrust out of her side from within - as I do now, there, and there, and there! - and two watching men on a stage without, with bared arms and sledge-hammers, strike at it fiercely, and repeat their blows until it is black and flat, I see a rivet being driven home, of which there are many in every iron plate, and thousands upon thousands in the ship! To think that the difficulty I experience in appreciating the ship’s size when I am on board, arises from her being a series of iron tanks and oaken chests, so that internally she is ever finishing and ever beginning, and half of her might be smashed, and yet the remaining half suffice and be sound. Then, to go over the side again and down among the ooze and wet to the bottom of the dock, in the depths of the subterranean forest of dog-shores and stays that hold her up, and to see the immense mass bulging out against the upper light, and tapering down towards me, is, with great pains and much clambering, to arrive at an impossibility of realising that this is a ship at all, and to become possessed by the fancy that it is an enormous immovable edifice set up in an ancient amphitheatre (say, that at Verona), and almost filling it! Yet what would even these things be, without the tributary workshops and the mechanical powers for piercing the iron plates - four inches and a half thick - for rivets, shaping them under hydraulic pressure to the finest tapering turns of the ship’s lines, and paring them away, with knives shaped like the beaks of strong and cruel birds, to the nicest requirements of the design! These machines of tremendous force, so easily directed by one attentive face and presiding hand, seem to me to have in them something of the retiring character of the Yard. ‘Obedient monster, please to bite this mass of iron through and through, at equal distances, where these regular chalk-marks are, all round.’ Monster looks at its work, and lifting its ponderous head, replies, ‘I don’t particularly want to do it; but if it must be done--!’ The solid metal wriggles out, hot from the monster’s crunching tooth, and it is done. ‘Dutiful monster, observe this other mass of iron. It is required to be pared away, according to this delicately lessening and arbitrary line, which please to look at.’ Monster (who has been in a reverie) brings down its blunt head, and, much in the manner of Doctor Johnson, closely looks along the line - very closely, being somewhat near-sighted. ‘I don’t particularly want to do it; but if it must be done—!’ Monster takes another near-sighted look, takes aim, and the tortured piece writhes off, and falls, a hot tighttwisted snake, among the ashes. The making of the rivets is merely a pretty round game, played by a man and a boy, who put red-hot barley sugar in a Pope Joan board, and immediately rivets fall out of window; but the tone of the great machines is the tone of the great Yard and the great country: ‘We don’t particularly want to do it; but if it must be done—!’

How such a prodigious mass as the Achilles can ever be held by such comparatively little anchors as those intended for her and lying near her here, is a mystery of seamanship which I will refer to the wise boy. For my own part, I should as soon have thought of tethering an elephant to a tentpeg, or the larger hippopotamus in the Zoological Gardens to my shirt-pin. Yonder in the river, alongside a hulk, lie two of this ship’s hollow iron masts. They are large enough for the eye, I find, and so are all her other appliances. I wonder why only her anchors look small.

I have no present time to think about it, for I am going to see the workshops where they make all the oars used in the British Navy. A pretty large pile of building, I opine, and a pretty long job! As to the building, I am soon disappointed, because the work is all done in one loft. And as to a long job - what is this? Two rather large mangles with a swarm of butterflies hovering over them? What can there be in the mangles that attracts butterflies?

Drawing nearer, I discern that these are not mangles, but intricate machines, set with knives and saws and planes, which cut smooth and straight here, and slantwise there, and now cut such a depth, and now miss cutting altogether, according to the predestined requirements of the pieces of wood that are pushed on below them: each of which pieces is to be an oar, and is roughly adapted to that purpose before it takes its final leave of far-off forests, and sails for England. Likewise I discern that the butterflies are not true butterflies, but wooden shavings, which, being spirited up from the wood by the violence of the machinery, and kept in rapid and not equal movement by the impulse of its rotation on the air, flutter and play, and rise and fall, and conduct themselves as like butterflies as heart could wish. Suddenly the noise and motion cease, and the butterflies drop dead. An oar has been made since I came in, wanting the shaped handle. As quickly as I can follow it with my eye and thought, the same oar is carried to a turning lathe. A whirl and a nick! Handle made. Oar finished.

The exquisite beauty and efficiency of this machinery need no illustration, but happen to have a pointed illustration to-day. A pair of oars of unusual size chance to be wanted for a special purpose, and they have to be made by hand. Side by side with the subtle and facile machine, and side by side with the fast-growing pile of oars on the floor, a man shapes out these special oars with an axe. Attended by no butterflies, and chipping and dinting, by comparison as leisurely as if he were a labouring Pagan getting them ready against his decease at threescore and ten, to take with him as a present to Charon for his boat, the man (aged about thirty) plies his task. The machine would make a regulation oar while the man wipes his forehead. The man might be buried in a mound made of the strips of thin broad wooden ribbon torn from the wood whirled into oars as the minutes fall from the clock, before he had done a forenoon’s work with his axe.

Passing from this wonderful sight to the Ships again - for my heart, as to the Yard, is where the ships are - I notice certain unfinished wooden walls left seasoning on the stocks, pending the solution of the merits of the wood and iron question, and having an air of biding their time with surly confidence. The names of these worthies are set up beside them, together with their capacity in guns - a custom highly conducive to ease and satisfaction in social intercourse, if it could be adapted to mankind. By a plank more gracefully pendulous than substantial, I make bold to go aboard a transport ship (iron screw) just sent in from the contractor’s yard to be inspected and passed. She is a very gratifying experience, in the simplicity and humanity of her arrangements for troops, in her provision for light and air and cleanliness, and in her care for women and children. It occurs to me, as I explore her, that I would require a handsome sum of money to go aboard her, at midnight by the Dockyard bell, and stay aboard alone till morning; for surely she must be haunted by a crowd of ghosts of obstinate old martinets, mournfully flapping their cherubic epaulettes over the changed times. Though still we may learn from the astounding ways and means in our Yards now, more highly than ever to respect the forefathers who got to sea, and fought the sea, and held the sea, without them. This remembrance putting me in the best of tempers with an old hulk, very green as to her copper, and generally dim and patched, I pull off my hat to her. Which salutation a callow and downy-faced young officer of Engineers, going by at the moment, perceiving, appropriates - and to which he is most heartily welcome, I am sure.

Having been torn to pieces (in imagination) by the steam circular saws, perpendicular saws, horizontal saws, and saws of eccentric action, I come to the sauntering part of my expedition, and consequently to the core of my Uncommercial pursuits.

Everywhere, as I saunter up and down the Yard, I meet with tokens of its quiet and retiring character. There is a gravity upon its red brick offices and houses, a staid pretence of having nothing worth mentioning to do, an avoidance of display, which I never saw out of England. The white stones of the pavement present no other trace of Achilles and his twelve hundred banging men (not one of whom strikes an attitude) than a few occasional echoes. But for a whisper in the air suggestive of sawdust and shavings, the oar-making and the saws of many movements might be miles away. Down below here, is the great reservoir of water where timber is steeped in various temperatures, as a part of its seasoning process. Above it, on a tramroad supported by pillars, is a Chinese Enchanter’s Car, which fishes the logs up, when sufficiently steeped, and rolls smoothly away with them to stack them. When I was a child (the Yard being then familiar to me) I used to think that I should like to play at Chinese Enchanter, and to have that apparatus placed at my disposal for the purpose by a beneficent country. I still think that I should rather like to try the effect of writing a book in it. Its retirement is complete, and to go gliding to and fro among the stacks of timber would be a convenient kind of travelling in foreign countries - among the forests of North America, the sodden Honduras swamps, the dark pine woods, the Norwegian frosts, and the tropical heats, rainy seasons, and thunder-storms. The costly store of timber is stacked and stowed away in sequestered places, with the pervading avoidance of flourish or effect. It makes as little of itself as possible, and calls to no one ‘Come and look at me!’ And yet it is picked out from the trees of the world; picked out for length, picked out for breadth, picked out for straightness, picked out for crookedness, chosen with an eye to every need of ship and boat. Strangely twisted pieces lie about, precious in the sight of shipwrights. Sauntering through these groves, I come upon an open glade where workmen are examining some timber recently delivered. Quite a pastoral scene, with a background of river and windmill! and no more like War than the American States are at present like an Union.

Sauntering among the ropemaking, I am spun into a state of blissful indolence, wherein my rope of life seems to be so untwisted by the process as that I can see back to very early days indeed, when my bad dreams - they were frightful, though my more mature understanding has never made out why - were of an interminable sort of ropemaking, with long minute filaments for strands, which, when they were spun home together close to my eyes, occasioned screaming. Next, I walk among the quiet lofts of stores - of sails, spars, rigging, ships’ boats - determined to believe that somebody in authority wears a girdle and bends beneath the weight of a massive bunch of keys, and that, when such a thing is wanted, he comes telling his keys like Blue Beard, and opens such a door. Impassive as the long lofts look, let the electric battery send down the word, and the shutters and doors shall fly open, and such a fleet of armed ships, under steam and under sail, shall burst forth as will charge the old Medway - where the merry Stuart let the Dutch come, while his not so merry sailors starved in the streets - with something worth looking at to carry to the sea. Thus I idle round to the Medway again, where it is now flood tide; and I find the river evincing a strong solicitude to force a way into the dry dock where Achilles is waited on by the twelve hundred bangers, with intent to bear the whole away before they are ready.

To the last, the Yard puts a quiet face upon it; for I make my way to the gates through a little quiet grove of trees, shading the quaintest of Dutch landing-places, where the leaf-speckled shadow of a shipwright just passing away at the further end might be the shadow of Russian Peter himself. So, the doors of the great patent safe at last close upon me, and I take boat again: somehow, thinking as the oars dip, of braggart Pistol and his brood, and of the quiet monsters of the Yard, with their ‘We don’t particularly want to do it; but if it must be done—!’ Scrunch.

Wapping Workhouse

My day’s no-business beckoning me to the East-end of London, I had turned my face to that point of the metropolitan compass on leaving Covent-garden, and had got past the India House, thinking in my idle manner of Tippoo-Sahib and Charles Lamb, and had got past my little wooden midshipman, after affectionately patting him on one leg of his knee-shorts for old acquaintance’ sake, and had got past Aldgate Pump, and had got past the Saracen’s Head (with an ignominious rash of posting bills disfiguring his swarthy countenance), and had strolled up the empty yard of his ancient neighbour the Black or Blue Boar, or Bull, who departed this life I don’t know when, and whose coaches are all gone I don’t know where; and I had come out again into the age of railways, and I had got past Whitechapel Church, and was - rather inappropriately for an Uncommercial Traveller - in the Commercial Road. Pleasantly wallowing in the abundant mud of that thoroughfare, and greatly enjoying the huge piles of building belonging to the sugar refiners, the little masts and vanes in small back gardens in back streets, the neighbouring canals and docks, the India vans lumbering along their stone tramway, and the pawnbrokers’ shops where hard-up Mates had pawned so many sextants and quadrants, that I should have bought a few cheap if I had the least notion how to use them, I at last began to file off to the right, towards Wapping.

Not that I intended to take boat at Wapping Old Stairs, or that I was going to look at the locality, because I believe (for I don’t) in the constancy of the young woman who told her sea-going lover, to such a beautiful old tune, that she had ever continued the same, since she gave him the ‘baccer-box marked with his name; I am afraid he usually got the worst of those transactions, and was frightfully taken in. No, I was going to Wapping, because an Eastern police magistrate had said, through the morning papers, that there was no classification at the Wapping workhouse for women, and that it was a disgrace and a shame, and divers other hard names, and because I wished to see how the fact really stood. For, that Eastern police magistrates are not always the wisest men of the East, may be inferred from their course of procedure respecting the fancy-dressing and pantomime-posturing at St.George’s in that quarter: which is usually, to discuss the matter at issue, in a state of mind betokening the weakest perplexity, with all parties concerned and unconcerned, and, for a final expedient, to consult the complainant as to what he thinks ought to be done with the defendant, and take the defendant’s opinion as to what he would recommend to be done with himself.

Long before I reached Wapping, I gave myself up as having lost my way, and, abandoning myself to the narrow streets in a Turkish frame of mind, relied on predestination to bring me somehow or other to the place I wanted if I were ever to get there. When I had ceased for an hour or so to take any trouble about the matter, I found myself on a swing-bridge looking down at some dark locks in some dirty water. Over against me, stood a creature remotely in the likeness of a young man, with a puffed sallow face, and a figure all dirty and shiny and slimy, who may have been the youngest son of his filthy old father, Thames, or the drowned man about whom there was a placard on the granite post like a large thimble, that stood between us.

I asked this apparition what it called the place? Unto which, it replied, with a ghastly grin and a sound like gurgling water in its throat:

‘Mr. Baker’s trap.’

As it is a point of great sensitiveness with me on such occasions to be equal to the intellectual pressure of the conversation, I deeply considered the meaning of this speech, while I eyed the apparition - then engaged in hugging and sucking a horizontal iron bar at the top of the locks. Inspiration suggested to me that Mr. Baker was the acting coroner of that neighbourhood.

‘A common place for suicide,’ said I, looking down at the locks.

‘Sue?’ returned the ghost, with a stare. ‘Yes! And Poll. Likewise Emily. And Nancy. And Jane;’ he sucked the iron between each name; ‘and all the bileing. Ketches off their bonnets or shorls, takes a run, and headers down here, they doos. Always a headerin’ down here, they is. Like one o’clock.’

‘And at about that hour of the morning, I suppose?’

‘Ah!’ said the apparition. ‘They an’t partickler. Two ’ull do for them. Three. All times o’ night. On’y mind you!’ Here the apparition rested his profile on the bar, and gurgled in a sarcastic manner. ‘There must be somebody comin’. They don’t go a headerin’ down here, wen there an’t no Bobby nor gen’ral Cove, fur to hear the splash.’

According to my interpretation of these words, I was myself a General Cove, or member of the miscellaneous public. In which modest character I remarked:

‘They are often taken out, are they, and restored?’

‘I dunno about restored,’ said the apparition, who, for some occult reason, very much objected to that word; ‘they’re carried into the werkiss and put into a ‘ot bath, and brought round. But I dunno about restored,’ said the apparition; ‘blow that!’ - and vanished.

As it had shown a desire to become offensive, I was not sorry to find myself alone, especially as the ‘werkiss’ it had indicated with a twist of its matted head, was close at hand. So I left Mr. Baker’s terrible trap (baited with a scum that was like the soapy rinsing of sooty chimneys), and made bold to ring at the workhouse gate, where I was wholly unexpected and quite unknown.

A very bright and nimble little matron, with a bunch of keys in her hand, responded to my request to see the House. I began to doubt whether the police magistrate was quite right in his facts, when I noticed her quick active little figure and her intelligent eyes.

The Traveller (the matron intimated) should see the worst first. He was welcome to see everything. Such as it was, there it all was.

This was the only preparation for our entering ‘the Foul wards.’ They were in an old building squeezed away in a corner of a paved yard, quite detached from the more modern and spacious main body of the workhouse. They were in a building most monstrously behind the time - a mere series of garrets or lofts, with every inconvenient and objectionable circumstance in their construction, and only accessible by steep and narrow staircases, infamously ill-adapted for the passage up-stairs of the sick or down-stairs of the dead.

A-bed in these miserable rooms, here on bedsteads, there (for a change, as I understood it) on the floor, were women in every stage of distress and disease. None but those who have attentively observed such scenes, can conceive the extraordinary variety of expression still latent under the general monotony and uniformity of colour, attitude, and condition. The form a little coiled up and turned away, as though it had turned its back on this world for ever; the uninterested face at once lead-coloured and yellow, looking passively upward from the pillow; the haggard mouth a little dropped, the hand outside the coverlet, so dull and indifferent, so light, and yet so heavy; these were on every pallet; but when I stopped beside a bed, and said ever so slight a word to the figure lying there, the ghost of the old character came into the face, and made the Foul ward as various as the fair world. No one appeared to care to live, but no one complained; all who could speak, said that as much was done for them as could be done there, that the attendance was kind and patient, that their suffering was very heavy, but they had nothing to ask for. The wretched rooms were as clean and sweet as it is possible for such rooms to be; they would become a pest-house in a single week, if they were ill-kept.

I accompanied the brisk matron up another barbarous staircase, into a better kind of loft devoted to the idiotic and imbecile. There was at least Light in it, whereas the windows in the former wards had been like sides of school-boys’ bird-cages. There was a strong grating over the fire here, and, holding a kind of state on either side of the hearth, separated by the breadth of this grating, were two old ladies in a condition of feeble dignity, which was surely the very last and lowest reduction of self-complacency, to be found in this wonderful humanity of ours. They were evidently jealous of each other, and passed their whole time (as some people do, whose fires are not grated) in mentally disparaging each other, and contemptuously watching their neighbours. One of these parodies on provincial gentlewomen was extremely talkative, and expressed a strong desire to attend the service on Sundays, from which she represented herself to have derived the greatest interest and consolation when allowed that privilege. She gossiped so well, and looked altogether so cheery and harmless, that I began to think this a case for the Eastern magistrate, until I found that on the last occasion of her attending chapel she had secreted a small stick, and had caused some confusion in the responses by suddenly producing it and belabouring the congregation.

So, these two old ladies, separated by the breadth of the grating - otherwise they would fly at one another’s caps - sat all day long, suspecting one another, and contemplating a world of fits. For, everybody else in the room had fits, except the wards-woman; an elderly, ablebodied pauperess, with a large upper lip, and an air of repressing and saving her strength, as she stood with her hands folded before her, and her eyes slowly rolling, biding her time for catching or holding somebody. This civil personage (in whom I regretted to identify a reduced member of my honourable friend Mrs. Gamp’s family) said, ‘They has ’em continiwal, sir. They drops without no more notice than if they was coach-horses dropped from the moon, sir. And when one drops, another drops, and sometimes there’ll be as many as four or five on ’em at once, dear me, a rolling and a tearin’, bless you! - this young woman, now, has ’em dreadful bad.’

She turned up this young woman’s face with her hand as she said it. This young woman was seated on the floor, pondering in the foreground of the afflicted. There was nothing repellant either in her face or head. Many, apparently worse, varieties of epilepsy and hysteria were about her, but she was said to be the worst here. When I had spoken to her a little, she still sat with her face turned up, pondering, and a gleam of the mid-day sun shone in upon her.

- Whether this young woman, and the rest of these so sorely troubled, as they sit or lie pondering in their confused dull way, ever get mental glimpses among the motes in the sunlight, of healthy people and healthy things? Whether this young woman, brooding like this in the summer season, ever thinks that somewhere there are trees and flowers, even mountains and the great sea? Whether, not to go so far, this young woman ever has any dim revelation of that young woman - that young woman who is not here and never will come here; who is courted, and caressed, and loved, and has a husband, and bears children, and lives in a home, and who never knows what it is to have this lashing and tearing coming upon her? And whether this young woman, God help her, gives herself up then and drops like a coach-horse from the moon?

I hardly knew whether the voices of infant children, penetrating into so hopeless a place, made a sound that was pleasant or painful to me. It was something to be reminded that the weary world was not all aweary, and was ever renewing itself; but, this young woman was a child not long ago, and a child not long hence might be such as she. Howbeit, the active step and eye of the vigilant matron conducted me past the two provincial gentlewomen (whose dignity was ruffled by the children), and into the adjacent nursery.

There were many babies here, and more than one handsome young mother. There were ugly young mothers also, and sullen young mothers, and callous young mothers. But, the babies had not appropriated to themselves any bad expression yet, and might have been, for anything that appeared to the contrary in their soft faces, Princes Imperial, and Princesses Royal. I had the pleasure of giving a poetical commission to the baker’s man to make a cake with all despatch and toss it into the oven for one red-headed young pauper and myself, and felt much the better for it. Without that refreshment, I doubt if I should have been in a condition for ‘the Refractories,’ towards whom my quick little matron - for whose adaptation to her office I had by this time conceived a genuine respect - drew me next, and marshalled me the way that I was going.

The Refractories were picking oakum, in a small room giving on a yard. They sat in line on a form, with their backs to a window; before them, a table, and their work. The oldest Refractory was, say twenty; youngest Refractory, say sixteen. I have never yet ascertained in the course of my uncommercial travels, why a Refractory habit should affect the tonsils and uvula; but, I have always observed that Refractories of both sexes and every grade, between a Ragged School and the Old Bailey, have one voice, in which the tonsils and uvula gain a diseased ascendency.

‘Five pound indeed! I hain’t a going fur to pick five pound,’ said the Chief of the Refractories, keeping time to herself with her head and chin. ‘More than enough to pick what we picks now, in sich a place as this, and on wot we gets here!’

(This was in acknowledgment of a delicate intimation that the amount of work was likely to be increased. It certainly was not heavy then, for one Refractory had already done her day’s task - it was barely two o’clock - and was sitting behind it, with a head exactly matching it.)

‘A pretty Ouse this is, matron, ain’t it?’ said Refractory Two, ‘where a pleeseman’s called in, if a gal says a word!’

‘And wen you’re sent to prison for nothink or less!’ said the Chief, tugging at her oakum as if it were the matron’s hair. ‘But any place is better than this; that’s one thing, and be thankful!’

A laugh of Refractories led by Oakum Head with folded arms - who originated nothing, but who was in command of the skirmishers outside the conversation.

‘If any place is better than this,’ said my brisk guide, in the calmest manner, ‘it is a pity you left a good place when you had one.’

‘Ho, no, I didn’t, matron,’ returned the Chief, with another pull at her oakum, and a very expressive look at the enemy’s forehead. ‘Don’t say that, matron, cos it’s lies!’

Oakum Head brought up the skirmishers again, skirmished, and retired.

‘And I warn’t a going,’ exclaimed Refractory Two, ‘though I was in one place for as long as four year - I warn’t a going fur to stop in a place that warn’t fit for me - there! And where the family warn’t ’spectable characters - there! And where I fort’nately or hunfort’nately, found that the people warn’t what they pretended to make theirselves out to be - there! And where it wasn’t their faults, by chalks, if I warn’t made bad and ruinated - Hah!’

During this speech, Oakum Head had again made a diversion with the skirmishers, and had again withdrawn.

The Uncommercial Traveller ventured to remark that he supposed Chief Refractory and Number One, to be the two young women who had been taken before the magistrate?

‘Yes!’ said the Chief, ‘we har! and the wonder is, that a pleeseman an’t ’ad in now, and we took off agen. You can’t open your lips here, without a pleeseman.’

Number Two laughed (very uvularly), and the skirmishers followed suit.

‘I’m sure I’d be thankful,’ protested the Chief, looking sideways at the Uncommercial, ‘if I could be got into a place, or got abroad. I’m sick and tired of this precious Ouse, I am, with reason.’

So would be, and so was, Number Two. So would be, and so was, Oakum Head. So would be, and so were, Skirmishers.

The Uncommercial took the liberty of hinting that he hardly thought it probable that any lady or gentleman in want of a likely young domestic of retiring manners, would be tempted into the engagement of either of the two leading Refractories, on her own presentation of herself as per sample.

‘It ain’t no good being nothink else here,’ said the Chief.

The Uncommercial thought it might be worth trying.

‘Oh no, it ain’t,’ said the Chief.

‘Not a bit of good,’ said Number Two.

‘And I’m sure I’d be very thankful to be got into a place, or got abroad,’ said the Chief.

‘And so should I,’ said Number Two. ‘Truly thankful, I should.’

Oakum Head then rose, and announced as an entirely new idea, the mention of which profound novelty might be naturally expected to startle her unprepared hearers, that she would be very thankful to be got into a place, or got abroad. And, as if she had then said, ‘Chorus, ladies!’ all the Skirmishers struck up to the same purpose. We left them, thereupon, and began a long walk among the women who were simply old and infirm; but whenever, in the course of this same walk, I looked out of any high window that commanded the yard, I saw Oakum Head and all the other Refractories looking out at their low window for me, and never failing to catch me, the moment I showed my head.

In ten minutes I had ceased to believe in such fables of a golden time as youth, the prime of life, or a hale old age. In ten minutes, all the lights of womankind seemed to have been blown out, and nothing in that way to be left this vault to brag of, but the flickering and expiring snuffs.

And what was very curious, was, that these dim old women had one company notion which was the fashion of the place. Every old woman who became aware of a visitor and was not in bed hobbled over a form into her accustomed seat, and became one of a line of dim old women confronting another line of dim old women across a narrow table. There was no obligation whatever upon them to range themselves in this way; it was their manner of ‘receiving.’ As a rule, they made no attempt to talk to one another, or to look at the visitor, or to look at anything, but sat silently working their mouths, like a sort of poor old Cows. In some of these wards, it was good to see a few green plants; in others, an isolated Refractory acting as nurse, who did well enough in that capacity, when separated from her compeers; every one of these wards, day room, night room, or both combined, was scrupulously clean and fresh. I have seen as many such places as most travellers in my line, and I never saw one such, better kept.

Among the bedridden there was great patience, great reliance on the books under the pillow, great faith in GOD. All cared for sympathy, but none much cared to be encouraged with hope of recovery; on the whole, I should say, it was considered rather a distinction to have a complication of disorders, and to be in a worse way than the rest. From some of the windows, the river could be seen with all its life and movement; the day was bright, but I came upon no one who was looking out.

In one large ward, sitting by the fire in arm-chairs of distinction, like the President and Vice of the good company, were two old women, upwards of ninety years of age. The younger of the two, just turned ninety, was deaf, but not very, and could easily be made to hear. In her early time she had nursed a child, who was now another old woman, more infirm than herself, inhabiting the very same chamber. She perfectly understood this when the matron told it, and, with sundry nods and motions of her forefinger, pointed out the woman in question. The elder of this pair, ninety-three, seated before an illustrated newspaper (but not reading it), was a bright-eyed old soul, really not deaf, wonderfully preserved, and amazingly conversational. She had not long lost her husband, and had been in that place little more than a year. At Boston, in the State of Massachusetts, this poor creature would have been individually addressed, would have been tended in her own room, and would have had her life gently assimilated to a comfortable life out of doors. Would that be much to do in England for a woman who has kept herself out of a workhouse more than ninety rough long years? When Britain first, at Heaven’s command, arose, with a great deal of allegorical confusion, from out the azure main, did her guardian angels positively forbid it in the Charter which has been so much besung?

The object of my journey was accomplished when the nimble matron had no more to show me. As I shook hands with her at the gate, I told her that I thought Justice had not used her very well, and that the wise men of the East were not infallible.

Now, I reasoned with myself, as I made my journey home again, concerning those Foul wards. They ought not to exist; no person of common decency and humanity can see them and doubt it. But what is this Union to do? The necessary alteration would cost several thousands of pounds; it has already to support three workhouses; its inhabitants work hard for their bare lives, and are already rated for the relief of the Poor to the utmost extent of reasonable endurance. One poor parish in this very Union is rated to the amount of FIVE AND SIXPENCE in the pound, at the very same time when the rich parish of Saint George’s, Hanover-square, is rated at about SEVENPENCE in the pound, Paddington at about FOURPENCE, Saint James’s, Westminster, at about TENPENCE! It is only through the equalisation of Poor Rates that what is left undone in this wise, can be done. Much more is left undone, or is ill-done, than I have space to suggest in these notes of a single uncommercial journey; but, the wise men of the East, before they can reasonably hold forth about it, must look to the North and South and West; let them also, any morning before taking the seat of Solomon, look into the shops and dwellings all around the Temple, and first ask themselves ‘how much more can these poor people - many of whom keep themselves with difficulty enough out of the workhouse - bear?’

I had yet other matter for reflection as I journeyed home, inasmuch as, before I altogether departed from the neighbourhood of Mr. Baker’s trap, I had knocked at the gate of the workhouse of St. George’s-in-the-East, and had found it to be an establishment highly creditable to those parts, and thoroughly well administered by a most intelligent master. I remarked in it, an instance of the collateral harm that obstinate vanity and folly can do. ‘This was the Hall where those old paupers, male and female, whom I had just seen, met for the Church service, was it?’ - ‘Yes.’ - ‘Did they sing the Psalms to any instrument?’ - ‘They would like to, very much; they would have an extraordinary interest in doing so.’ - ‘And could none be got?’ - ‘Well, a piano could even have been got for nothing, but these unfortunate dissensions—’ Ah! better, far better, my Christian friend in the beautiful garment, to have let the singing boys alone, and left the multitude to sing for themselves! You should know better than I, but I think I have read that they did so, once upon a time, and that ‘when they had sung an hymn,’ Some one (not in a beautiful garment) went up unto the Mount of Olives.

It made my heart ache to think of this miserable trifling, in the streets of a city where every stone seemed to call to me, as I walked along, ‘Turn this way, man, and see what waits to be done!’ So I decoyed myself into another train of thought to ease my heart. But, I don’t know that I did it, for I was so full of paupers, that it was, after all, only a change to a single pauper, who took possession of my remembrance instead of a thousand.

‘I beg your pardon, sir,’ he had said, in a confidential manner, on another occasion, taking me aside; ‘but I have seen better days.’

‘I am very sorry to hear it.’

‘Sir, I have a complaint to make against the master.’

‘I have no power here, I assure you. And if I had—’

‘But, allow me, sir, to mention it, as between yourself and a man who has seen better days, sir. The master and myself are both masons, sir, and I make him the sign continually; but, because I am in this unfortunate position, sir, he won’t give me the countersign!’

A Small Star in the East

I had been looking, yesternight, through the famous ‘Dance of Death,’ and to-day the grim old woodcuts arose in my mind with the new significance of a ghastly monotony not to be found in the original. The weird skeleton rattled along the streets before me, and struck fiercely; but it was never at the pains of assuming a disguise. It played on no dulcimer here, was crowned with no flowers, waved no plume, minced in no flowing robe or train, lifted no winecup, sat at no feast, cast no dice, counted no gold. It was simply a bare, gaunt, famished skeleton, slaying his way along.

The borders of Ratcliff and Stepney, eastward of London, and giving on the impure river, were the scene of this uncompromising dance of death, upon a drizzling November day. A squalid maze of streets, courts, and alleys of miserable houses let out in single rooms. A wilderness of dirt, rags, and hunger. A mud-desert, chiefly inhabited by a tribe from whom employment has departed, or to whom it comes but fitfully and rarely. They are not skilled mechanics in any wise. They are but labourers, - dock-labourers, water-side labourers, coal-porters, ballast-heavers, such-like hewers of wood and drawers of water. But they have come into existence, and they propagate their wretched race.

One grisly joke alone, methought, the skeleton seemed to play off here. It had stuck election-bills on the walls, which the wind and rain had deteriorated into suitable rags. It had even summed up the state of the poll, in chalk, on the shutters of one ruined house. It adjured the free and independent starvers to vote for Thisman and vote for Thatman; not to plump, as they valued the state of parties and the national prosperity (both of great importance to them, I think); but, by returning Thisman and Thatman, each naught without the other, to compound a glorious and immortal whole. Surely the skeleton is nowhere more cruelly ironical in the original monkish idea!

Pondering in my mind the far-seeing schemes of Thisman and Thatman, and of the public blessing called Party, for staying the degeneracy, physical and moral, of many thousands (who shall say how many?) of the English race; for devising employment useful to the community for those who want but to work and live; for equalising rates, cultivating waste lands, facilitating emigration, and, above all things, saving and utilising the oncoming generations, and thereby changing ever-growing national weakness into strength: pondering in my mind, I say, these hopeful exertions, I turned down a narrow street to look into a house or two.

It was a dark street with a dead wall on one side. Nearly all the outer doors of the houses stood open. I took the first entry, and knocked at a parlour-door. Might I come in? I might, if I plased, sur.

The woman of the room (Irish) had picked up some long strips of wood, about some wharf or barge; and they had just now been thrust into the otherwise empty grate to make two iron pots boil. There was some fish in one, and there were some potatoes in the other. The flare of the burning wood enabled me to see a table, and a broken chair or so, and some old cheap crockery ornaments about the chimney-piece. It was not until I had spoken with the woman a few minutes, that I saw a horrible brown heap on the floor in the corner, which, but for previous experience in this dismal wise, I might not have suspected to be ‘the bed.’ There was something thrown upon it; and I asked what that was.

‘’Tis the poor craythur that stays here, sur; and ’tis very bad she is, and ’tis very bad she’s been this long time, and ’tis better she’ll never be, and ‘tis slape she does all day, and ’tis wake she does all night, and ’tis the lead, sur.’

‘The what?’

‘The lead, sur. Sure ‘tis the lead-mills, where the women gets took on at eighteen-pence a day, sur, when they makes application early enough, and is lucky and wanted; and ’tis lead-pisoned she is, sur, and some of them gets lead-pisoned soon, and some of them gets lead-pisoned later, and some, but not many, niver; and ‘tis all according to the constitooshun, sur, and some constitooshuns is strong, and some is weak, and her constitooshun is lead-pisoned, bad as can be, sur; and her brain is coming out at her ear, and it hurts her dreadful; and that’s what it is, and niver no more, and niver no less, sur.’

The sick young woman moaning here, the speaker bent over her, took a bandage from her head, and threw open a back door to let in the daylight upon it, from the smallest and most miserable back-yard I ever saw.

‘That’s what cooms from her, sur, being lead-pisoned; and it cooms from her night and day, the poor, sick craythur; and the pain of it is dreadful; and God he knows that my husband has walked the streets these four days, being a labourer, and is walking them now, and is ready to work, and no work for him, and no fire and no food but the bit in the pot, and no more than ten shillings in a fortnight; God be good to us! and it is poor we are, and dark it is and could it is indeed.’

Knowing that I could compensate myself thereafter for my self-denial, if I saw fit, I had resolved that I would give nothing in the course of these visits. I did this to try the people. I may state at once that my closest observation could not detect any indication whatever of an expectation that I would give money: they were grateful to be talked to about their miserable affairs, and sympathy was plainly a comfort to them; but they neither asked for money in any case, nor showed the least trace of surprise or disappointment or resentment at my giving none.

The woman’s married daughter had by this time come down from her room on the floor above, to join in the conversation. She herself had been to the lead-mills very early that morning to be ‘took on,’ but had not succeeded. She had four children; and her husband, also a water-side labourer, and then out seeking work, seemed in no better case as to finding it than her father. She was English, and by nature of a buxom figure and cheerful. Both in her poor dress and in her mother’s there was an effort to keep up some appearance of neatness. She knew all about the sufferings of the unfortunate invalid, and all about the lead-poisoning, and how the symptoms came on, and how they grew, - having often seen them. The very smell when you stood inside the door of the works was enough to knock you down, she said: yet she was going back again to get ‘took on:’ What could she do? Better be ulcerated and paralyzed for eighteen-pence a day, while it lasted, than see the children starve.

A dark and squalid cupboard in this room, touching the back door and all manner of offence, had been for some time the sleeping-place of the sick young woman. But the nights being now wintry, and the blankets and coverlets ‘gone to the leaving shop,’ she lay all night where she lay all day, and was lying then. The woman of the room, her husband, this most miserable patient, and two others, lay on the one brown heap together for warmth.

‘God bless you, sir, and thank you!’ were the parting words from these people, - gratefully spoken too, - with which I left this place.

Some streets away, I tapped at another parlour-door on another ground-floor. Looking in, I found a man, his wife, and four children, sitting at a washing-stool by way of table, at their dinner of bread and infused tea-leaves. There was a very scanty cinderous fire in the grate by which they sat; and there was a tent bedstead in the room with a bed upon it and a coverlet. The man did not rise when I went in, nor during my stay, but civilly inclined his head on my pulling off my hat, and, in answer to my inquiry whether I might ask him a question or two, said, ‘Certainly.’ There being a window at each end of this room, back and front, it might have been ventilated; but it was shut up tight, to keep the cold out, and was very sickening.

The wife, an intelligent, quick woman, rose and stood at her husband’s elbow; and he glanced up at her as if for help. It soon appeared that he was rather deaf. He was a slow, simple fellow of about thirty.

‘What was he by trade?’

‘Gentleman asks what are you by trade, John?’

‘I am a boilermaker;’ looking about him with an exceedingly perplexed air, as if for a boiler that had unaccountably vanished.

‘He ain’t a mechanic, you understand, sir,’ the wife put in: ‘he’s only a labourer.’

‘Are you in work?’

He looked up at his wife again. ‘Gentleman says are you in work, John?’

‘In work!’ cried this forlorn boilermaker, staring aghast at his wife, and then working his vision’s way very slowly round to me: ‘Lord no!’

‘Ah, he ain’t indeed!’ said the poor woman, shaking her head, as she looked at the four children in succession, and then at him.

‘Work!’ said the boilermaker, still seeking that evaporated boiler, first in my countenance, then in the air, and then in the features of his second son at his knee: ‘I wish I was in work! I haven’t had more than a day’s work to do this three weeks.’

‘How have you lived?’

A faint gleam of admiration lighted up the face of the would-be boilermaker, as he stretched out the short sleeve of his threadbare canvas jacket, and replied, pointing her out, ‘On the work of the wife.’

I forget where boilermaking had gone to, or where he supposed it had gone to; but he added some resigned information on that head, coupled with an expression of his belief that it was never coming back.

The cheery helpfulness of the wife was very remarkable. She did slopwork; made pea-jackets. She produced the pea-jacket then in hand, and spread it out upon the bed, - the only piece of furniture in the room on which to spread it. She showed how much of it she made, and how much was afterwards finished off by the machine. According to her calculation at the moment, deducting what her trimming cost her, she got for making a peajacket tenpence half-penny, and she could make one in something less than two days.

But, you see, it come to her through two hands, and of course it didn’t come through the second hand for nothing. Why did it come through the second hand at all? Why, this way. The second hand took the risk of the given-out work, you see. If she had money enough to pay the security deposit, - call it two pound, - she could get the work from the first hand, and so the second would not have to be deducted for. But, having no money at all, the second hand come in and took its profit, and so the whole worked down to tenpence half-penny. Having explained all this with great intelligence, even with some little pride, and without a whine or murmur, she folded her work again, sat down by her husband’s side at the washing-stool, and resumed her dinner of dry bread. Mean as the meal was, on the bare board, with its old gallipots for cups, and what not other sordid makeshifts: shabby as the woman was in dress, and toning down towards the Bosjesman colour, with want of nutriment and washing, - there was positively a dignity in her, as the family anchor just holding the poor shipwrecked boilermaker’s bark. When I left the room, the boilermaker’s eyes were slowly turned towards her, as if his last hope of ever again seeing that vanished boiler lay in her direction.

These people had never applied for parish relief but once; and that was when the husband met with a disabling accident at his work.

Not many doors from here, I went into a room on the first floor. The woman apologised for its being in ‘an untidy mess.’ The day was Saturday, and she was boiling the children’s clothes in a saucepan on the hearth. There was nothing else into which she could have put them. There was no crockery, or tinware, or tub, or bucket. There was an old gallipot or two, and there was a broken bottle or so, and there were some broken boxes for seats. The last small scraping of coals left was raked together in a corner of the floor. There were some rags in an open cupboard, also on the floor. In a corner of the room was a crazy old French bedstead, with a man lying on his back upon it in a ragged pilot jacket, and rough oil-skin fantail hat. The room was perfectly black. It was difficult to believe, at first, that it was not purposely coloured black, the walls were so begrimed.

As I stood opposite the woman boiling the children’s clothes, - she had not even a piece of soap to wash them with, - and apologising for her occupation, I could take in all these things without appearing to notice them, and could even correct my inventory. I had missed, at the first glance, some half a pound of bread in the otherwise empty safe, an old red ragged crinoline hanging on the handle of the door by which I had entered, and certain fragments of rusty iron scattered on the floor, which looked like broken tools and a piece of stove-pipe. A child stood looking on. On the box nearest to the fire sat two younger children; one a delicate and pretty little creature, whom the other sometimes kissed.

This woman, like the last, was woefully shabby, and was degenerating to the Bosjesman complexion. But her figure, and the ghost of a certain vivacity about her, and the spectre of a dimple in her cheek, carried my memory strangely back to the old days of the Adelphi Theatre, London, when Mrs. Fitzwilliam was the friend of Victorine.

‘May I ask you what your husband is?’

‘He’s a coal-porter, sir,’ - with a glance and a sigh towards the bed.

‘Is he out of work?’

‘Oh, yes, sir! and work’s at all times very, very scanty with him; and now he’s laid up.’

‘It’s my legs,’ said the man upon the bed. ‘I’ll unroll ’em.’ And immediately began.

‘Have you any older children?’

‘I have a daughter that does the needle-work, and I have a son that does what he can. She’s at her work now, and he’s trying for work.’

‘Do they live here?’

‘They sleep here. They can’t afford to pay more rent, and so they come here at night. The rent is very hard upon us. It’s rose upon us too, now, - sixpence a week, - on account of these new changes in the law, about the rates. We are a week behind; the landlord’s been shaking and rattling at that door frightfully; he says he’ll turn us out. I don’t know what’s to come of it.’

The man upon the bed ruefully interposed, ‘Here’s my legs. The skin’s broke, besides the swelling. I have had a many kicks, working, one way and another.’

He looked at his legs (which were much discoloured and misshapen) for a while, and then appearing to remember that they were not popular with his family, rolled them up again, as if they were something in the nature of maps or plans that were not wanted to be referred to, lay hopelessly down on his back once more with his fantail hat over his face, and stirred not.

‘Do your eldest son and daughter sleep in that cupboard?’

‘Yes,’ replied the woman.

‘With the children?’

‘Yes. We have to get together for warmth. We have little to cover us.’

‘Have you nothing by you to eat but the piece of bread I see there?’

‘Nothing. And we had the rest of the loaf for our breakfast, with water. I don’t know what’s to come of it.’

‘Have you no prospect of improvement?’

‘If my eldest son earns anything to-day, he’ll bring it home. Then we shall have something to eat to-night, and may be able to do something towards the rent. If not, I don’t know what’s to come of it.’

‘This is a sad state of things.’

‘Yes, sir; it’s a hard, hard life. Take care of the stairs as you go, sir - they’re broken, - and good day, sir!’

These people had a mortal dread of entering the workhouse, and received no out-of-door relief.

In another room, in still another tenement, I found a very decent woman with five children, - the last a baby, and she herself a patient of the parish doctor, - to whom, her husband being in the hospital, the Union allowed for the support of herself and family, four shillings a week and five loaves. I suppose when Thisman, M.P., and Thatman, M.P., and the Public-blessing Party, lay their heads together in course of time, and come to an equalisation of rating, she may go down to the dance of death to the tune of sixpence more.

I could enter no other houses for that one while, for I could not bear the contemplation of the children. Such heart as I had summoned to sustain me against the miseries of the adults failed me when I looked at the children. I saw how young they were, how hungry, how serious and still. I thought of them, sick and dying in those lairs. I think of them dead without anguish; but to think of them so suffering and so dying quite unmanned me.

Down by the river’s bank in Ratcliff, I was turning upward by a side street, therefore, to regain the railway, when my eyes rested on the inscription across the road, ‘East London Children’s Hospital.’ I could scarcely have seen an inscription better suited to my frame of mind; and I went across and went straight in.

I found the children’s hospital established in an old sail-loft or storehouse, of the roughest nature, and on the simplest means. There were trap-doors in the floors, where goods had been hoisted up and down; heavy feet and heavy weights had started every knot in the well-trodden planking: inconvenient bulks and beams and awkward staircases perplexed my passage through the wards. But I found it airy, sweet, and clean. In its seven and thirty beds I saw but little beauty; for starvation in the second or third generation takes a pinched look: but I saw the sufferings both of infancy and childhood tenderly assuaged; I heard the little patients answering to pet playful names, the light touch of a delicate lady laid bare the wasted sticks of arms for me to pity; and the claw-like little hands, as she did so, twined themselves lovingly around her wedding-ring.

One baby mite there was as pretty as any of Raphael’s angels. The tiny head was bandaged for water on the brain; and it was suffering with acute bronchitis too, and made from time to time a plaintive, though not impatient or complaining, little sound. The smooth curve of the cheeks and of the chin was faultless in its condensation of infantine beauty, and the large bright eyes were most lovely. It happened as I stopped at the foot of the bed, that these eyes rested upon mine with that wistful expression of wondering thoughtfulness which we all know sometimes in very little children. They remained fixed on mine, and never turned from me while I stood there. When the utterance of that plaintive sound shook the little form, the gaze still remained unchanged. I felt as though the child implored me to tell the story of the little hospital in which it was sheltered to any gentle heart I could address. Laying my world-worn hand upon the little unmarked clasped hand at the chin, I gave it a silent promise that I would do so.

A gentleman and lady, a young husband and wife, have bought and fitted up this building for its present noble use, and have quietly settled themselves in it as its medical officers and directors. Both have had considerable practical experience of medicine and surgery; he as housesurgeon of a great London hospital; she as a very earnest student, tested by severe examination, and also as a nurse of the sick poor during the prevalence of cholera.

With every qualification to lure them away, with youth and accomplishments and tastes and habits that can have no response in any breast near them close begirt by every repulsive circumstance inseparable from such a neighbourhood, there they dwell. They live in the hospital itself, and their rooms are on its first floor. Sitting at their dinner-table, they could hear the cry of one of the children in pain. The lady’s piano, drawing-materials, books, and other such evidences of refinement are as much a part of the rough place as the iron bedsteads of the little patients. They are put to shifts for room, like passengers on board ship. The dispenser of medicines (attracted to them not by self-interest, but by their own magnetism and that of their cause) sleeps in a recess in the diningroom, and has his washing apparatus in the sideboard.

Their contented manner of making the best of the things around them, I found so pleasantly inseparable from their usefulness! Their pride in this partition that we put up ourselves, or in that partition that we took down, or in that other partition that we moved, or in the stove that was given us for the waiting-room, or in our nightly conversion of the little consulting-room into a smoking-room! Their admiration of the situation, if we could only get rid of its one objectionable incident, the coal-yard at the back! ‘Our hospital carriage, presented by a friend, and very useful.’ That was my presentation to a perambulator, for which a coach-house had been discovered in a corner down-stairs, just large enough to hold it. Coloured prints, in all stages of preparation for being added to those already decorating the wards, were plentiful; a charming wooden phenomenon of a bird, with an impossible top-knot, who ducked his head when you set a counter weight going, had been inaugurated as a public statue that very morning; and trotting about among the beds, on familiar terms with all the patients, was a comical mongrel dog, called Poodles. This comical dog (quite a tonic in himself) was found characteristically starving at the door of the institution, and was taken in and fed, and has lived here ever since. An admirer of his mental endowments has presented him with a collar bearing the legend, ‘Judge not Poodles by external appearances.’ He was merrily wagging his tail on a boy’s pillow when he made this modest appeal to me.

When this hospital was first opened, in January of the present year, the people could not possibly conceive but that somebody paid for the services rendered there; and were disposed to claim them as a right, and to find fault if out of temper. They soon came to understand the case better, and have much increased in gratitude. The mothers of the patients avail themselves very freely of the visiting rules; the fathers often on Sundays. There is an unreasonable (but still, I think, touching and intelligible) tendency in the parents to take a child away to its wretched home, if on the point of death. One boy who had been thus carried off on a rainy night, when in a violent state of inflammation, and who had been afterwards brought back, had been recovered with exceeding difficulty; but he was a jolly boy, with a specially strong interest in his dinner, when I saw him.

Insufficient food and unwholesome living are the main causes of disease among these small patients. So nourishment, cleanliness, and ventilation are the main remedies. Discharged patients are looked after, and invited to come and dine now and then; so are certain famishing creatures who were never patients. Both the lady and the gentleman are well acquainted, not only with the histories of the patients and their families, but with the characters and circumstances of great numbers of their neighbours: of these they keep a register. It is their common experience, that people, sinking down by inches into deeper and deeper poverty, will conceal it, even from them, if possible, unto the very last extremity.

The nurses of this hospital are all young, - ranging, say, from nineteen to four and twenty. They have even within these narrow limits, what many well-endowed hospitals would not give them, a comfortable room of their own in which to take their meals. It is a beautiful truth, that interest in the children and sympathy with their sorrows bind these young women to their places far more strongly than any other consideration could. The best skilled of the nurses came originally from a kindred neighbourhood, almost as poor; and she knew how much the work was needed. She is a fair dressmaker. The hospital cannot pay her as many pounds in the year as there are months in it; and one day the lady regarded it as a duty to speak to her about her improving her prospects and following her trade. ‘No,’ she said: she could never be so useful or so happy elsewhere any more; she must stay among the children. And she stays. One of the nurses, as I passed her, was washing a baby-boy. Liking her pleasant face, I stopped to speak to her charge, - a common, bullet-headed, frowning charge enough, laying hold of his own nose with a slippery grasp, and staring very solemnly out of a blanket. The melting of the pleasant face into delighted smiles, as this young gentleman gave an unexpected kick, and laughed at me, was almost worth my previous pain.

An affecting play was acted in Paris years ago, called ‘The Children’s Doctor.’ As I parted from my children’s doctor, now in question, I saw in his easy black necktie, in his loose buttoned black frock-coat, in his pensive face, in the flow of his dark hair, in his eyelashes, in the very turn of his moustache, the exact realisation of the Paris artist’s ideal as it was presented on the stage. But no romancer that I know of has had the boldness to prefigure the life and home of this young husband and young wife in the Children’s Hospital in the east of London.

I came away from Ratcliff by the Stepney railway station to the terminus at Fenchurch Street. Any one who will reverse that route may retrace my steps.

On an Amateur Beat

It is one of my fancies, that even my idlest walk must always have its appointed destination. I set myself a task before I leave my lodging in Covent-garden on a street expedition, and should no more think of altering my route by the way, or turning back and leaving a part of it unachieved, than I should think of fraudulently violating an agreement entered into with somebody else. The other day, finding myself under this kind of obligation to proceed to Limehouse, I started punctually at noon, in compliance with the terms of the contract with myself to which my good faith was pledged.

On such an occasion, it is my habit to regard my walk as my beat, and myself as a higher sort of police-constable doing duty on the same. There is many a ruffian in the streets whom I mentally collar and clear out of them, who would see mighty little of London, I can tell him, if I could deal with him physically.

Issuing forth upon this very beat, and following with my eyes three hulking garrotters on their way home, - which home I could confidently swear to be within so many yards of Drury-lane, in such a narrow and restricted direction (though they live in their lodging quite as undisturbed as I in mine), - I went on duty with a consideration which I respectfully offer to the new Chief Commissioner, - in whom I thoroughly confide as a tried and efficient public servant. How often (thought I) have I been forced to swallow, in police-reports, the intolerable stereotyped pill of nonsense, how that the police-constable informed the worthy magistrate how that the associates of the prisoner did, at that present speaking, dwell in a street or court which no man dared go down, and how that the worthy magistrate had heard of the dark reputation of such street or court, and how that our readers would doubtless remember that it was always the same street or court which was thus edifyingly discoursed about, say once a fortnight.

Now, suppose that a Chief Commissioner sent round a circular to every division of police employed in London, requiring instantly the names in all districts of all such much-puffed streets or courts which no man durst go down; and suppose that in such circular he gave plain warning, ‘If those places really exist, they are a proof of police inefficiency which I mean to punish; and if they do not exist, but are a conventional fiction, then they are a proof of lazy tacit police connivance with professional crime, which I also mean to punish’ - what then? Fictions or realities, could they survive the touchstone of this atom of common sense? To tell us in open court, until it has become as trite a feature of news as the great gooseberry, that a costly police-system such as was never before heard of, has left in London, in the days of steam and gas and photographs of thieves and electric telegraphs, the sanctuaries and stews of the Stuarts! Why, a parity of practice, in all departments, would bring back the Plague in two summers, and the Druids in a century!

Walking faster under my share of this public injury, I overturned a wretched little creature, who, clutching at the rags of a pair of trousers with one of its claws, and at its ragged hair with the other, pattered with bare feet over the muddy stones. I stopped to raise and succour this poor weeping wretch, and fifty like it, but of both sexes, were about me in a moment, begging, tumbling, fighting, clamouring, yelling, shivering in their nakedness and hunger. The piece of money I had put into the claw of the child I had overturned was clawed out of it, and was again clawed out of that wolfish gripe, and again out of that, and soon I had no notion in what part of the obscene scuffle in the mud, of rags and legs and arms and dirt, the money might be. In raising the child, I had drawn it aside out of the main thoroughfare, and this took place among some wooden hoardings and barriers and ruins of demolished buildings, hard by Temple Bar.

Unexpectedly, from among them emerged a genuine police constable, before whom the dreadful brood dispersed in various directions, he making feints and darts in this direction and in that, and catching nothing. When all were frightened away, he took off his hat, pulled out a handkerchief from it, wiped his heated brow, and restored the handkerchief and hat to their places, with the air of a man who had discharged a great moral duty, - as indeed he had, in doing what was set down for him. I looked at him, and I looked about at the disorderly traces in the mud, and I thought of the drops of rain and the footprints of an extinct creature, hoary ages upon ages old, that geologists have identified on the face of a cliff; and this speculation came over me: If this mud could petrify at this moment, and could lie concealed here for ten thousand years, I wonder whether the race of men then to be our successors on the earth could, from these or any marks, by the utmost force of the human intellect, unassisted by tradition, deduce such an astounding inference as the existence of a polished state of society that bore with the public savagery of neglected children in the streets of its capital city, and was proud of its power by sea and land, and never used its power to seize and save them!

After this, when I came to the Old Bailey and glanced up it towards Newgate, I found that the prison had an inconsistent look. There seemed to be some unlucky inconsistency in the atmosphere that day; for though the proportions of St. Paul’s Cathedral are very beautiful, it had an air of being somewhat out of drawing, in my eyes. I felt as though the cross were too high up, and perched upon the intervening golden ball too far away.

Facing eastward, I left behind me Smithfield and Old Bailey, - fire and faggot, condemned hold, public hanging, whipping through the city at the cart-tail, pillory, branding-iron, and other beautiful ancestral landmarks, which rude hands have rooted up, without bringing the stars quite down upon us as yet, - and went my way upon my beat, noting how oddly characteristic neighbourhoods are divided from one another, hereabout, as though by an invisible line across the way. Here shall cease the bankers and the money-changers; here shall begin the shipping interest and the nautical-instrument shops; here shall follow a scarcely perceptible flavouring of groceries and drugs; here shall come a strong infusion of butchers; now, small hosiers shall be in the ascendant; henceforth, everything exposed for sale shall have its ticketed price attached. All this as if specially ordered and appointed.

A single stride at Houndsditch Church, no wider than sufficed to cross the kennel at the bottom of the Canongate, which the debtors in Holyrood sanctuary were wont to relieve their minds by skipping over, as Scott relates, and standing in delightful daring of catchpoles on the free side, - a single stride, and everything is entirely changed in grain and character. West of the stride, a table, or a chest of drawers on sale, shall be of mahogany and French-polished; east of the stride, it shall be of deal, smeared with a cheap counterfeit resembling lip-salve. West of the stride, a penny loaf or bun shall be compact and self-contained; east of the stride, it shall be of a sprawling and splay-footed character, as seeking to make more of itself for the money. My beat lying round by Whitechapel Church, and the adjacent sugar-refineries, - great buildings, tier upon tier, that have the appearance of being nearly related to the dock-warehouses at Liverpool, - I turned off to my right, and, passing round the awkward corner on my left, came suddenly on an apparition familiar to London streets afar off.

What London peripatetic of these times has not seen the woman who has fallen forward, double, through some affection of the spine, and whose head has of late taken a turn to one side, so that it now droops over the back of one of her arms at about the wrist? Who does not know her staff, and her shawl, and her basket, as she gropes her way along, capable of seeing nothing but the pavement, never begging, never stopping, for ever going somewhere on no business? How does she live, whence does she come, whither does she go, and why? I mind the time when her yellow arms were naught but bone and parchment. Slight changes steal over her; for there is a shadowy suggestion of human skin on them now. The Strand may be taken as the central point about which she revolves in a half-mile orbit. How comes she so far east as this? And coming back too! Having been how much farther? She is a rare spectacle in this neighbourhood. I receive intelligent information to this effect from a dog - a lop-sided mongrel with a foolish tail, plodding along with his tail up, and his ears pricked, and displaying an amiable interest in the ways of his fellow-men, - if I may be allowed the expression. After pausing at a pork-shop, he is jogging eastward like myself, with a benevolent countenance and a watery mouth, as though musing on the many excellences of pork, when he beholds this doubled-up bundle approaching. He is not so much astonished at the bundle (though amazed by that), as the circumstance that it has within itself the means of locomotion. He stops, pricks his ears higher, makes a slight point, stares, utters a short, low growl, and glistens at the nose, - as I conceive with terror. The bundle continuing to approach, he barks, turns tail, and is about to fly, when, arguing with himself that flight is not becoming in a dog, he turns, and once more faces the advancing heap of clothes. After much hesitation, it occurs to him that there may be a face in it somewhere. Desperately resolving to undertake the adventure, and pursue the inquiry, he goes slowly up to the bundle, goes slowly round it, and coming at length upon the human countenance down there where never human countenance should be, gives a yelp of horror, and flies for the East India Docks.

Being now in the Commercial Road district of my beat, and bethinking myself that Stepney Station is near, I quicken my pace that I may turn out of the road at that point, and see how my small eastern star is shining.

The Children’s Hospital, to which I gave that name, is in full force. All its beds are occupied. There is a new face on the bed where my pretty baby lay, and that sweet little child is now at rest for ever. Much kind sympathy has been here since my former visit, and it is good to see the walls profusely garnished with dolls. I wonder what Poodles may think of them, as they stretch out their arms above the beds, and stare, and display their splendid dresses. Poodles has a greater interest in the patients. I find him making the round of the beds, like a housesurgeon, attended by another dog, - a friend, - who appears to trot about with him in the character of his pupil dresser. Poodles is anxious to make me known to a pretty little girl looking wonderfully healthy, who had had a leg taken off for cancer of the knee. A difficult operation, Poodles intimates, wagging his tail on the counterpane, but perfectly successful, as you see, dear sir! The patient, patting Poodles, adds with a smile, ‘The leg was so much trouble to me, that I am glad it’s gone.’ I never saw anything in doggery finer than the deportment of Poodles, when another little girl opens her mouth to show a peculiar enlargement of the tongue. Poodles (at that time on a table, to be on a level with the occasion) looks at the tongue (with his own sympathetically out) so very gravely and knowingly, that I feel inclined to put my hand in my waistcoat-pocket, and give him a guinea, wrapped in paper.

On my beat again, and close to Limehouse Church, its termination, I found myself near to certain ‘Lead-Mills.’ Struck by the name, which was fresh in my memory, and finding, on inquiry, that these same lead-mills were identified with those same lead-mills of which I made mention when I first visited the East London Children’s Hospital and its neighbourhood as Uncommercial Traveller, I resolved to have a look at them.

Received by two very intelligent gentlemen, brothers, and partners with their father in the concern, and who testified every desire to show their works to me freely, I went over the lead-mills. The purport of such works is the conversion of pig-lead into white-lead. This conversion is brought about by the slow and gradual effecting of certain successive chemical changes in the lead itself. The processes are picturesque and interesting, - the most so, being the burying of the lead, at a certain stage of preparation, in pots, each pot containing a certain quantity of acid besides, and all the pots being buried in vast numbers, in layers, under tan, for some ten weeks.

Hopping up ladders, and across planks, and on elevated perches, until I was uncertain whether to liken myself to a bird or a bricklayer, I became conscious of standing on nothing particular, looking down into one of a series of large cocklofts, with the outer day peeping in through the chinks in the tiled roof above. A number of women were ascending to, and descending from, this cockloft, each carrying on the upward journey a pot of prepared lead and acid, for deposition under the smoking tan. When one layer of pots was completely filled, it was carefully covered in with planks, and those were carefully covered with tan again, and then another layer of pots was begun above; sufficient means of ventilation being preserved through wooden tubes. Going down into the cockloft then filling, I found the heat of the tan to be surprisingly great, and also the odour of the lead and acid to be not absolutely exquisite, though I believe not noxious at that stage. In other cocklofts, where the pots were being exhumed, the heat of the steaming tan was much greater, and the smell was penetrating and peculiar. There were cocklofts in all stages; full and empty, half filled and half emptied; strong, active women were clambering about them busily; and the whole thing had rather the air of the upper part of the house of some immensely rich old Turk, whose faithful seraglio were hiding his money because the sultan or the pasha was coming.

As is the case with most pulps or pigments, so in the instance of this white-lead, processes of stirring, separating, washing, grinding, rolling, and pressing succeed. Some of these are unquestionably inimical to health, the danger arising from inhalation of particles of lead, or from contact between the lead and the touch, or both. Against these dangers, I found good respirators provided (simply made of flannel and muslin, so as to be inexpensively renewed, and in some instances washed with scented soap), and gauntlet gloves, and loose gowns. Everywhere, there was as much fresh air as windows, well placed and opened, could possibly admit. And it was explained that the precaution of frequently changing the women employed in the worst parts of the work (a precaution originating in their own experience or apprehension of its ill effects) was found salutary. They had a mysterious and singular appearance, with the mouth and nose covered, and the loose gown on, and yet bore out the simile of the old Turk and the seraglio all the better for the disguise.

At last this vexed white-lead, having been buried and resuscitated, and heated and cooled and stirred, and separated and washed and ground, and rolled and pressed, is subjected to the action of intense fiery heat. A row of women, dressed as above described, stood, let us say, in a large stone bake-house, passing on the baking-dishes as they were given out by the cooks, from hand to hand, into the ovens. The oven, or stove, cold as yet, looked as high as an ordinary house, and was full of men and women on temporary footholds, briskly passing up and stowing away the dishes. The door of another oven, or stove, about to be cooled and emptied, was opened from above, for the uncommercial countenance to peer down into. The uncommercial countenance withdrew itself, with expedition and a sense of suffocation, from the dull-glowing heat and the overpowering smell. On the whole, perhaps the going into these stoves to work, when they are freshly opened, may be the worst part of the occupation.

But I made it out to be indubitable that the owners of these lead-mills honestly and sedulously try to reduce the dangers of the occupation to the lowest point.

A washing-place is provided for the women (I thought there might have been more towels), and a room in which they hang their clothes, and take their meals, and where they have a good fire-range and fire, and a female attendant to help them, and to watch that they do not neglect the cleansing of their hands before touching their food. An experienced medical attendant is provided for them, and any premonitory symptoms of lead-poisoning are carefully treated. Their teapots and such things were set out on tables ready for their afternoon meal, when I saw their room; and it had a homely look. It is found that they bear the work much better than men: some few of them have been at it for years, and the great majority of those I observed were strong and active. On the other hand, it should be remembered that most of them are very capricious and irregular in their attendance.

American inventiveness would seem to indicate that before very long white-lead may be made entirely by machinery. The sooner, the better. In the meantime, I parted from my two frank conductors over the mills, by telling them that they had nothing there to be concealed, and nothing to be blamed for. As to the rest, the philosophy of the matter of lead-poisoning and workpeople seems to me to have been pretty fairly summed up by the Irish-woman whom I quoted in my former paper: ‘Some of them gets lead-pisoned soon, and some of them gets lead-pisoned later, and some, but not many, niver; and ‘tis all according to the constitooshun, sur; and some constitooshuns is strong and some is weak.’

Retracing my footsteps over my beat, I went off duty.

Betting-Shops

In one sporting newspaper for Sunday, June the fourteenth, there are nine-and-twenty advertisements from Prophets, who have wonderful information to give - for a consideration ranging from one pound one, to two-and-sixpence - concerning every ‘event’ that is to come off upon the Turf. Each of these Prophets has an unrivalled and unchallengeable ‘Tip,’ founded on amazing intelligence communicated to him by illustrious unknowns (traitors of course, but that is nobody’s business) in all the racing stables. Each, is perfectly clear that his enlightened patrons and correspondents must win; and each, begs to guard a too-confiding world against relying on the other. They are all philanthropists. One Sage announces ‘that when he casts his practised eye on the broad surface of struggling society, and witnesses the slow and enduring perseverance of some, and the infatuous rush of the many who are grappling with a cloud, he is led with more intense desire to hold up the lamp of light to all.’ He is also much afflicted, because ‘not a day passes, without his witnessing the public squandering away their money on worthless rubbish.’ Another, heralds his re-appearance among the lesser stars of the firmament with the announcement, ‘Again the Conquering Prophet comes!’ Another moralist intermingles with his ‘Pick,’ and ‘Tip,’ the great Christian precept of the New Testament. Another, confesses to a small recent mistake which has made it ‘a disastrous meeting for us,’ but considers that excuses are unnecessary (after making them), for, ‘surely, after the unprecedented success of the proofs he has lately afforded of his capabilities in fishing out the most carefully-hidden turf secrets, he may readily be excused one blunder.’ All the Prophets write in a rapid manner, as receiving their inspiration on horseback, and noting it down, hot and hot, in the saddle, for the enlightenment of mankind and the restoration of the golden age.

This flourishing trade is a melancholy index to the round numbers of human donkeys who are everywhere browzing about. And it is worthy of remark that the great mass of disciples were, at first, undoubtedly to be found among those fast young gentlemen, who are so excruciatingly knowing that they are not by any means to be taken in by Shakespeare, or any sentimental gammon of that sort. To us, the idea of this would-be keen race being preyed upon by the whole Betting-Book of Prophets, is one of the most ludicrous pictures the mind can imagine; while there is a just and pleasant retribution in it which would awaken in us anything but animosity towards the Prophets, if the mischief ended here.

But, the mischief has the drawback that it does not end here. When there are so many Picks and Tips to be had, which will, of a surety, pick and tip their happy owners into the lap of Fortune, it becomes the duty of every butcher’s boy and errand lad who is sensible of what is due to himself, immediately to secure a Pick and Tip of the cheaper sort, and to go in and win. Having purchased the talisman from the Conquering Prophet, it is necessary that the noble sportsman should have a handy place provided for him, where lists of the running horses and of the latest state of the odds, are kept, and where he can lay out his money (or somebody else’s) on the happy animals at whom the Prophetic eye has cast a knowing wink. Presto! Betting-shops spring up in every street! There is a demand at all the brokers’ shops for old, fly-blown, coloured prints of race-horses, and for any odd folio volumes that have the appearance of Ledgers. Two such prints in any shop-window, and one such book on any shop-counter, will make a complete Betting-office, bank, and all.

The Betting-shop may be a Tobacconist’s, thus suddenly transformed; or it may be nothing but a Bettingshop. It may be got up cheaply, for the purposes of Pick and Tip investment, by the removal of the legitimate counter, and the erection of an official partition and desk in one corner; or, it may be wealthy in mahogany fittings, French polish, and office furniture. The presiding officer, in an advanced stage of shabbiness, may be accidentally beheld through the little window - whence from the inner mysteries of the Temple, he surveys the devotees before entering on business - drinking gin with an admiring client; or he may be a serenely condescending gentleman of Government Office appearance, who keeps the books of the establishment with his glass in his eye. The Institution may stoop to bets of single shillings, or may reject lower ventures than half-crowns, or may draw the line of demarcation between itself and the snobs at five shillings, or seven-and-sixpence, or half-a-sovereign, or even (but very rarely indeed), at a pound. Its note of the little transaction may be a miserable scrap of limp pasteboard with a wretchedly printed form, worse filled up; or, it may be a genteelly tinted card, addressed ‘To the Cashier of the Aristocratic Club,’ and authorising that important officer to pay the bearer two pounds fifteen shillings, if Greenhorn wins the Fortunatus’s Cup; and to be very particular to pay it the day after the race. But, whatever the Betting-shop be, it has only to be somewhere - anywhere, so people pass and repass - and the rapid youth of England, with its slang intelligence perpetually broad awake and its weather eye continually open, will walk in and deliver up its money, like the helpless Innocent that it is.

Pleased to the last, it thinks its wager won, And licks the hand by which it’s surely Done

We cannot represent the head quarters of Household Words as being situated peculiarly in the midst of these establishments, for, they pervade the whole of London and its suburbs. But, our neighbourhood yields an abundant crop of Betting-shops, and we have not to go far to know something about them. Passing the other day, through a dirty thoroughfare, much frequented, near Drury Lane Theatre, we found that a new Betting-shop had suddenly been added to the number under the auspices of Mr. Cheerful.

Mr. Cheerful’s small establishment was so very like that of the apothecary in Romeo and Juliet, unfurnished, and hastily adapted to the requirements of secure and profitable investment, that it attracted our particular notice. It burst into bloom, too, so very shortly before the Ascot Meeting, that we had our suspicions concerning the possibility of Mr. Cheerful having devised the ingenious speculation of getting what money he could, up to the day of the race, and then - if we may be allowed the harsh expression - bolting. We had no doubt that investments would be made with Mr. Cheerful, notwithstanding the very unpromising appearance of his establishment; for, even as we were considering its exterior from the opposite side of the way (it may have been opened that very morning), we saw two newsboys, an incipient baker, a clerk, and a young butcher, go in, and transact business with Mr. Cheerful in a most confiding manner.

We resolved to lay a bet with Mr. Cheerful, and see what came of it. So we stepped across the road into Mr. Cheerful’s Betting-shop, and, having glanced at the lists hanging up therein, while another noble sportsman (a boy with a blue bag) laid another bet with Mr. Cheerful, we expressed our desire to back Tophana for the Western Handicap, to the spirited amount of half-a-crown. In making this advance to Mr. Cheerful, we looked as knowing on the subject, both of Tophana and the Western Handicap, as it was in us to do: though, to confess the humiliating truth, we neither had, nor have, the least idea in connexion with those proper names, otherwise than as we suppose Tophana to be a horse, and the Western Handicap an aggregate of stakes. It being Mr. Cheerful’s business to be grave and ask no questions, he accepted our wager, booked it, and handed us over his railed desk the dirty scrap of pasteboard, in right of which we were to claim - the day after the race; we were to be very particular about that - seven-and-sixpence sterling, if Tophana won. Some demon whispering us that here was an opportunity of discovering whether Mr. Cheerful had a good bank of silver in the cash-box, we handed in a sovereign. Mr. Cheerful’s head immediately slipped down behind the partition, investigating imaginary drawers; and Mr. Cheerful’s voice was presently heard to remark, in a stifled manner, that all the silver had been changed for gold that morning. After which, Mr. Cheerful reappeared in the twinkling of an eye, called in from a parlour the sharpest small boy ever beheld by human vision, and dispatched him for change. We remarked to Mr. Cheerful that if he would obligingly produce half-a-sovereign (having so much gold by him) we would increase our bet, and save him trouble. But, Mr. Cheerful, sliding down behind the partition again, answered that the boy was gone, now - trust him for that; he had vanished the instant he was spoken to - and it was no trouble at all. Therefore, we remained until the boy came back, in the society of Mr. Cheerful, and of an inscrutable woman who stared out resolutely into the street, and was probably Mrs. Cheerful. When the boy returned, we thought we once saw him faintly twitch his nose while we received our change, as if he exulted over a victim; but, he was so miraculously sharp, that it was impossible to be certain.

The day after the race, arriving, we returned with our document to Mr. Cheerful’s establishment, and found it in great confusion. It was filled by a crowd of boys, mostly greasy, dirty, and dissipated; and all clamouring for Mr. Cheerful. Occupying Mr. Cheerful’s place, was the miraculous boy; all alone, and unsupported, but not at all disconcerted. Mr. Cheerful, he said, had gone out on ‘’tickler bizniz’ at ten o’clock in the morning, and wouldn’t be back till late at night. Mrs. Cheerful was gone out of town for her health, till the winter. Would Mr. Cheerful be back to-morrow? cried the crowd. ‘He won’t be here, to-morrow,’ said the miraculous boy. ‘Coz it’s Sunday, and he always goes to church, a’ Sunday.’ At this, even the losers laughed. ‘Will he be here a’ Monday, then?’ asked a desperate young green-grocer. ‘A’ Monday?’ said the miracle, reflecting. ‘No, I don’t think he’ll be here, a’ Monday, coz he’s going to a sale a’ Monday.’ At this, some of the boys taunted the unmoved miracle with meaning ‘a sell instead of a sale,’ and others swarmed over the whole place, and some laughed, and some swore, and one errand boy, discovering the book - the only thing Mr. Cheerful had left behind him - declared it to be a ‘stunning good ’un.’ We took the liberty of looking over it, and found it so. Mr. Cheerful had received about seventeen pounds, and, even if he had paid his losses, would have made a profit of between eleven and twelve pounds. It is scarcely necessary to add that Mr. Cheerful has been so long detained at the sale that he has never come back. The last time we loitered past his late establishment (over which is inscribed Boot and Shoe Manufactory), the dusk of evening was closing in, and a young gentleman from New Inn was making some rather particular enquiries after him of a dim and dusty man who held the door a very little way open, and knew nothing about anybody, and less than nothing (if possible) about Mr. Cheerful. The handle of the lower door-bell was most significantly pulled out to its utmost extent, and left so, like an Organ stop in full action. It is to be hoped that the poor gull who had so frantically rung for Mr. Cheerful, derived some gratification from that expenditure of emphasis. He will never get any other, for his money.

But the public in general are not to be left a prey to such fellows as Cheerful. O, dear no! We have better neighbours than that, in the Betting-shop way. Expressly for the correction of such evils, we have The Tradesmen’s Moral Associative Betting Club; the Prospectus of which Institution for the benefit of tradesmen (headed in the original with a racing woodcut), we here faithfully present without the alteration of a word.

‘The Projectors of the Tradesmen’s Moral Associative Betting Club, in announcing an addition to the number of Betting Houses in the Metropolis, beg most distinctly to state that they are not actuated by a feeling of rivalry towards old established and honourably conducted places of a similar nature, but in a spirit of fair competition, ask for the support of the public, guaranteeing to them more solid security for the investment of their monies, than has hitherto been offered.

‘The Tradesmen’s Moral Associative Betting Club is really what its name imports, viz., an Association of Tradesmen, persons in business, who witnessing the robberies hourly inflicted upon the humbler portion of the sporting public, by parties bankrupt alike in character and property, have come to the conclusion that the establishment of a club wherein their fellow-tradesmen, and the speculator of a few shillings, may invest their money with assured consciousness of a fair and honourable dealing, will be deemed worthy of public support.

‘The Directors of this establishment feel that much of the odium attached to Betting Houses (acting to the prejudice of those which have striven hard by honourable means to secure public confidence), has arisen from the circumstance, that many offices have been fitted up in a style of gaudy imitative magnificence, accompanied by an expense, which, if defrayed, is obviously out of keeping with the profits of a legitimate concern. Whilst, in singular contrast, others have presented such a poverty stricken appearance, that it is evident the design of the occupant was only to receive money of all, and terminate in paying none.

‘Avoiding these extremes of appearance, and with a determination never to be induced to speculate to an extent, that may render it even probable that we shall be unable “to pay the day after the race.”

‘The business of club will be carried on at the house of a highly respectable and well-known tradesman, situate in a central locality, the existence of an agreement with whom, on the part of the directors, forms the strongest possible guarantee of our intention to keep faith with the public.

‘The market odds will be laid on all events, and every ticket issued be signed by the director only, the monies being invested,’ &c. &c.

After this, Tradesmen are quite safe in laying out their money on their favourite horses. And their families, like the people in old fireside stories, will no doubt live happy ever afterwards!

Now, it is unquestionable that this evil has risen to a great height, and that it involves some very serious social considerations. But, with all respect for opinions which we do not hold, we think it a mistake to cry for legislative interference in such a case. In the first place, we do not think it wise to exhibit a legislature which has always cared so little for the amusements of the people, in repressive action only. If it had been an educational legislature, considerate of the popular enjoyments, and sincerely desirous to advance and extend them during as long a period as it has been exactly the reverse, the question might assume a different shape; though, even then, we should greatly doubt whether the same notion were not a shifting of the real responsibility. In the second place, although it is very edifying to have honorable members, and right honorable members, and honorable and learned members, and what not, holding forth in their places upon what is right, and what is wrong, and what is true, and what is false - among the people - we have that audacity in us that we do not admire the present Parliamentary standard and balance of such questions; and we believe that if those be not scrupulously just, Parliament cannot invest itself with much moral authority. Surely the whole country knows that certain chivalrous public Prophets have been, for a pretty long time past, advertising their Pick and Tip in all directions, pointing out the horse which was to make everybody’s fortune! Surely we all know, howsoever our political opinions may differ, that more than one of them ‘casting his practised eye,’ exactly like the Prophet in the sporting paper, ‘on the broad surface of struggling society,’ has been possessed by the same ‘intense desire to hold up the lamp of light to all,’ and has solemnly known by the lamp of light that Black was the winning horse - until his Pick and Tip was purchased; when he suddenly began to think it might be White, or even Brown, or very possibly Grey. Surely, we all know, however reluctant we may be to admit it, that this has tainted and confused political honesty; that the Elections before us, and the whole Government of the country, are at present a great reckless Betting-shop, where the Prophets have pocketed their own predictions after playing fast and loose with their patrons as long as they could; and where, casting their practised eyes over things in general, they are now backing anything and everything for a chance of winning!

No. If the legislature took the subject in hand it would make a virtuous demonstration, we have no doubt, but it would not present an edifying spectacle. Parents and employers must do more for themselves. Every man should know something of the habits and frequentings of those who are placed under him; and should know much, when a new class of temptation thus presents itself. Apprentices are, by the terms of their indentures, punishable for gaming; it would do a world of good, to get a few score of that class of noble sportsmen convicted before magistrates, and shut up in the House of Correction, to Pick a little oakum, and Tip a little gruel into their silly stomachs. Betting clerks, and betting servants of all grades, once detected after a grave warning, should be firmly dismissed. There are plenty of industrious and steady young men to supply their places. The police should receive instructions by no means to overlook any gentleman of established bad reputation - whether ‘wanted’ or not - who is to be found connected with a Betting-shop. It is our belief that several eminent characters could be so discovered. These precautions, always supposing parents and employers resolute to discharge their own duties instead of vaguely delegating them to a legislature they have no reliance on, would probably be sufficient. Some fools who are under no control, will always be found wandering away to ruin; but, the greater part of that extensive department of the commonalty are under some control, and the great need is, that it be better exercised.

Trading in Death

Several years have now elapsed since it began to be clear to the comprehension of most rational men, that the English people had fallen into a condition much to be regretted, in respect of their Funeral customs. A system of barbarous show and expense was found to have gradually erected itself above the grave, which, while it could possibly do no honor to the memory of the dead, did great dishonor to the living, as inducing them to associate the most solemn of human occasions with unmeaning mummeries, dishonest debt, profuse waste, and bad example in an utter oblivion of responsibility. The more the subject was examined, and the lower the investigation was carried, the more monstrous (as was natural) these usages appeared to be, both in themselves and in their consequences. No class of society escaped. The competition among the middle classes for superior gentility in Funerals - the gentility being estimated by the amount of ghastly folly in which the undertaker was permitted to run riot - descended even to the very poor: to whom the cost of funeral customs was so ruinous and so disproportionate to their means, that they formed Clubs among themselves to defray such charges. Many of these Clubs, conducted by designing villains who preyed upon the general infirmity, cheated and wronged the poor, most cruelly; others, by presenting a new class of temptations to the wickedest natures among them, led to a new class of mercenary murders, so abominable in their iniquity, that language cannot stigmatise them with sufficient severity. That nothing might be wanting to complete the general depravity, hollowness, and falsehood, of this state of things, the absurd fact came to light, that innumerable harpies assumed the titles of furnishers of Funerals, who possessed no Funeral furniture whatever, but who formed a long file of middlemen between the chief mourner and the real tradesman, and who hired out the trappings from one to another - passing them on like water-buckets at a fire - every one of them charging his enormous percentage on his share of the ‘black job.’ Add to all this, the demonstration, by the simplest and plainest practical science, of the terrible consequences to the living, inevitably resulting from the practice of burying the dead in the midst of crowded towns; and the exposition of a system of indecent horror, revolting to our nature and disgraceful to our age and nation, arising out of the confined limits of such burial-grounds, and the avarice of their proprietors; and the culminating point of this gigantic mockery is at last arrived at.

Out of such almost incredible degradation, saving that the proof of it is too easy, we are still very slowly and feebly emerging. There are now, we confidently hope, among the middle classes, many, who having made themselves acquainted with these evils through the parliamentary papers in which they are described, would be moved by no human consideration to perpetuate the old bad example; but who will leave it as their solemn injunction on their nearest and dearest survivors, that they shall not, in their death, be made the instruments of infecting, either the minds or the bodies of their fellow-creatures. Among persons of note, such examples have not been wanting. The late Duke of Sussex did a national service when he desired to be laid, in the equality of death, in the cemetery of Kensal Green, and not with the pageantry of a State Funeral in the Royal vault at Windsor. Sir Robert Peel requested to be buried at Drayton. The late Queen Dowager left a pattern to every rank in these touching and admirable words. ‘I die in all humility, knowing well that we are all alike before the Throne of God; and I request, therefore, that my mortal remains be conveyed to the grave without any pomp or state. They are to be removed to St. George’s Chapel, Windsor, where I request to have as private and quiet a funeral as possible. I particularly desire not to be laid out in state. I die in peace and wish to be carried to the tomb in peace, and free from the vanities and pomp of this world. I request not to be dissected or embalmed, and desire to give as little trouble as possible.’

With such precedents and such facts fresh in the general knowledge, and at this transition-time in so serious a chapter of our social history, the obsolete custom of a State Funeral has been revived, in miscalled ‘honor’ of the late Duke of Wellington. To whose glorious memory be all true honor while England lasts!

We earnestly submit to our readers that there is, and that there can be, no kind of honor in such a revival; that the more truly great the man, the more truly little the ceremony; and that it has been, from first to last, a pernicious instance and encouragement of the demoralising practice of trading in Death.

It is within the knowledge of the whole public, of all diversities of political opinion, whether or no any of the Powers that be, have traded in this Death - have saved it up, and petted it, and made the most of it, and reluctantly let it go. On that aspect of the question we offer no further remark.

But, of the general trading spirit which, in its inherent emptiness and want of consistency and reality, the longdeferred State Funeral has appropriately awakened, we will proceed to furnish a few instances all faithfully copied from the advertising columns of The Times.

First, of seats and refreshments. Passing over that desirable first-floor where a party could be accommodated with ‘the use of a piano’; and merely glancing at the decorous daily announcement of ‘The Duke of Wellington Funeral Wine,’ which was in such high demand that immediate orders were necessary; and also ‘The Duke of Wellington Funeral Cake,’ which ‘delicious article’ could only be had of such a baker; and likewise ‘The Funeral Life Preserver,’ which could only be had of such a tailor; and further ‘the celebrated lemon biscuits,’ at one and fourpence per pound, which were considered by the manufacturer as the only infallible assuagers of the national grief; let us pass in review some dozen of the more eligible opportunities the public had of profiting by the occasion.

LUDGATE HILL. - The fittings and arrangements for viewing this grand and solemnly imposing procession are now completed at this establishment, and those who are desirous of obtaining a fine and extensive view, combined with every personal convenience and comfort, will do well to make immediate inspection of the SEATS now remaining on hand.

FUNERAL, including Beds the night previous. - To be LET, a SECOND FLOOR, of three rooms, two windows, having a good view of the procession. Terms, including refreshment, 10 guineas. Single places, including bed and breakfast, from 15s.

THE DUKE’S FUNERAL. - A first-rate VIEW for 15 persons, also good clean beds and a sitting-room on reasonable terms.

SEATS and WINDOWS to be LET, in the best part of the Strand, a few doors from Coutts’s banking-house. First floor windows, £8 each; second floor, £5 10s. each; third floor, £3 10s. each; two plate-glass shop windows, £7 each.

SEATS to VIEW the DUKE of WELLINGTON’S FUNERAL. Best position of all the route, no obstruction to the view. Apply Old Bailey. N.B. From the above position you can nearly see to St. Paul’s and to Temple-bar.

FUNERAL of the late Duke of WELLINGTON. - To be LET, a SECOND FLOOR, two windows, firing and every convenience. Terms moderate for a party. Also a few seats in front, one guinea each. Commanding a view from Piccadilly to Pall-mall.

FUNERAL of the DUKE of WELLINGTON. - The FIRST and SECOND FLOORS to be LET, either by the room or window, suited to gentlemen’s families, for whom every comfort and accommodation will be provided, and commanding the very best view of this imposing spectacle. The ground floor is also fitted up with commodious seats, ranging in price from one guinea. Apply on the premises.

THE DUKE’S FUNERAL. - Terms very moderate. - TWO FIRST FLOOR ROOMS, with balcony and private entrance out of the Strand. The larger room capable of holding 15 persons. The small room to be let for eight guineas.

THE DUKE’S FUNERAL. - To be LET, a SHOP WINDOW, with seats erected for about 30, for 25 guineas. Also a Furnished First Floor, with two large windows. One of the best views in the whole range from Temple-bar to St. Paul’s. Price 35 guineas. A few single seats one guinea each.

THE FUNERAL PROCESSION of the DUKE of WELLINGTON. - Cockspur-street, Charing-cross, decidedly the best position in the whole route, a few SEATS still DISENGAGED, which will be offered at reasonable prices. An early application is requisite, as they are fast filling up. Also a few places on the roof. A most excellent view.

FUNERAL of the Late DUKE of WELLINGTON. - To be LET, in the best part of the Strand, a SECOND FLOOR, for £10; a Third Floor, £7 10s., containing two windows in each; front seats in shop, at one guinea.

THE DUKE’S FUNERAL. - To be LET, for 25 guineas to a genteel family, in one of the most commanding situations in the line of route, a FIRST FLOOR, with safe balcony, and ante-room. Will accommodate 20 persons, with an uninterrupted and extensive view for all. For a family of less number a reduction will be made. Every accommodation will be afforded.

But above all let us not forget the

NOTICE TO CLERGYMEN. - T.C. Fleet-street, has reserved for clergymen exclusively, upon condition only that they appear in their surplices, FOUR FRONT SEATS, at £1 each; four second tier, at 15s. each; four third tier, at 12s. 6d.; four fourth tier, at 10s.; four fifth tier, at 7s. 6d.; and four sixth tier, at 5s. All the other seats are respectively 40s., 30s., 20s., 15s., 10s.

The anxiety of this enterprising tradesman to get up a reverend tableau in his shop-window of four-and-twenty clergymen all on six rows, is particularly commendable, and appears to us to shed a remarkable grace on the solemnity.

These few specimens are collected at random from scores upon scores of such advertisements, mingled with descriptions of non-existent ranges of view, and with invitations to a few agreeable gentlemen who are wanted to complete a little assembly of kindred souls, who have laid in abundance of ‘refreshments, wines, spirits, provisions, fruit, plate, glass, china,’ and other light matters too numerous to mention, and who keep ‘good fires.’ On looking over them we are constantly startled by the words in large capitals, ‘WOULD TO GOD NIGHT OR BLUCHER WERE COME!’ which, referring to a work of art, are relieved by a legend setting forth how the lamented hero observed of it, ‘in his characteristic manner, “Very good; very good indeed.”’ O Art! You too trading in Death!

Then, autographs fall into their place in the State Funeral train. The sanctity of a seal, or the confidence of a letter, is a meaningless phrase that has no place in the vocabulary of the Traders in Death. Stop, trumpets, in the Dead March, and blow to the world how characteristic we autographs are!

WELLINGTON AUTOGRAPHS. - TWO consecutive LETTERS of the DUKE’S (1843) highly characteristic and authentic, with the Correspondence, &c. that elicited them, the whole forming quite a literary curiosity, for £15.

WELLINGTON AUTOGRAPHS. - To be DISPOSED OF, TWO AUTOGRAPH LETTERS of the DUKE of WELLINGTON, one dated Walmer Castle, 9th October, 1834, the other London, 17th May, 1843, with their post-marks and seals.

WELLINGTON. - THREE original NOTES, averaging 2¼ pages each, (not lithographs,) seal, and envelopes, to be SOLD. Supposed to be the most characteristic of his Grace yet published. The highest sum above £30 for the two, or £20 for the one, which is distinct, will be accepted.

TO BE DISPOSED OF, by a retired officer, FIVE LETTERS and NOTES of the late HERO - three when Sir A. Wellesley. Also a large Envelope. All with seals. Apply personally, or by letter.

THE DUKE’S LETTERS. - TWO highly interesting LETTERS, authentic, and relating to a most amusing and characteristic circumstance, to be SOLD.

THE DUKE of WELLINGTON. - AUTOGRAPH LETTER to a lady, with seal and envelope. This is quite in the Duke’s peculiar style, and will be parted with for the highest offer. Apply — where the letter can be seen.

F.M. the DUKE of WELLINGTON. - To be SOLD, by a member of the family, to whom it was written, an ORIGINAL AUTOGRAPH LETTER of the late Duke of Wellington, on military affairs, six pages long, in the best preservation. Price £30.

FIELD-MARSHAL the DUKE of WELLINGTON’S AUTOGRAPH. - A highly characteristic LETTER of the DUKE’S for DISPOSAL, wherein he alludes to his living 100 years, date 1847, with envelope. Seal, with crest perfect. £10 will be taken.

DUKE of WELLINGTON. - An AUTOGRAPH LETTER of the DUKE, written immediately after the death of the Duchess in 1831, is for SALE; also Two Autograph Envelopes franked and sealed.

DUKE of WELLINGTON. - AUTOGRAPH BUSINESS LETTER, envelope, seal, post-mark, &c. complete. Style courteous and highly characteristic. Will be shown by the party and at the place addressed. Price £15.

FIELD-MARSHAL the DUKE of WELLINGTON. - TWO AUTOGRAPH LETTERS of His Grace, one written in his 61st, the other in his 72d year, both firstrate specimens of his characteristic graphic style, and on an important subject, to be SOLD. Their genuineness can be fully proved.

THE DUKE of WELLINGTON. - A very curious DOCUMENT, partly printed, and the rest written by His Grace to a lady. This is well worthy of a place in the cabinet of the curious. There is nothing like it. Highest offer will be taken.

TO be SOLD, SIX AUTOGRAPH LETTERS from F. M. the Duke of WELLINGTON, with envelopes and seals, which have been most generously given to aid a lady in distressed circumstances.

THE DUKE of WELLINGTON. - A lady has in her possession a LETTER, written by his Grace on the 18th of June, in the present year, and will be happy to DISPOSE OF the same. The letter is rendered more valuable by its being written on the last anniversary which his Grace was spared to celebrate. The letter bears date from Apsley House, with perfect envelope and seal.

A CLERGYMAN has TWO LETTERS, with Envelopes, addressed to him by the late DUKE, and bearing striking testimony to the extent of his Grace’s private charities, to be DISPOSED OF at the highest offer (for one or both) received by the 18th instant. The offers may be contingent on further particulars being satisfactory.

THE DUKE of WELLINGTON. - A widow, in deep distress, has in her possession an AUTOGRAPH LETTER of his Grace the Duke of WELLINGTON, written in 1830, enclosed and directed in an envelope, and sealed with his ducal coronet, which she would be happy to PART WITH for a trifle.

VALUABLE AUTOGRAPH NOTE of the late Duke of WELLINGTON, dated March 27, 1850, to be SOLD, for £20, by the gentleman to whom it was addressed, together with envelope, perfect impression of Ducal seal, and Knightsbridge post-mark distinct. The whole in excellent preservation. A better specimen of the noble Duke’s handwriting and highly characteristic style cannot be seen.

ONE of the last LETTERS of the DUKE of WELLINGTON for DISPOSAL, dated from Walmer Castle within a day or two of his death, highly characteristic, with seal and post-marks distinct. This being probably the last letter written by the late Duke its interest as a relic must be greatly enhanced. The highest offer accepted. May be seen on application.

THE GREAT DUKE. - A LETTER of the GREAT HERO, dated March 27, 1851, to be SOLD. Also a beautiful Letter from Jenny Lind, dated June 20, 1852. The highest offer will be accepted. Address with offers of price.

Miss Lind’s autograph would appear to have lingered in the shade until the Funeral Train came by, when it modestly stepped into the procession and took a conspicuous place. We are in doubt which to admire most; the ingenuity of this little stroke of business; or the affecting delicacy that sells ‘probably the last letter written by the late Duke’ before the aged hand that wrote it under some manly sense of duty, is yet withered in its grave; or the piety of that excellent clergyman - did he appear in his surplice in the front row of T. C.’s shop-window? - who is so anxious to sell ‘striking testimony to the extent of His Grace’s private charities;’ or the generosity of that Good Samaritan who poured ‘six letters with envelopes and seals’ into the wounds of the lady in distressed circumstances.

Lastly come the relics - precious remembrances worn next to the bereaved heart, like Hardy’s miniature of Nelson, and never to be wrested from the advertisers but with ready money.

MEMENTO of the late DUKE of WELLINGTON. - To be DISPOSED OF, a LOCK of the late illustrious DUKE’S HAIR. Can be guaranteed. The highest offer will be accepted. Apply by letter prepaid.

THE DUKE of WELLINGTON. - A LOCK of HAIR of the late Duke of WELLINGTON to be DISPOSED OF, now in the possession of a widow lady. Cut off the morning the Queen was crowned. Apply by letter post paid.

VALUABLE RELIC of the late DUKE of WELLINGTON. - A lady, having in her possession a quantity of the late illustrious DUKE’S HAIR, cut in 1841, is willing to PART WITH a portion of the same for £25. Satisfactory proof will be given of its identity, and of how it came into the owner’s possession, on application by letter, pre-paid.

RELIC of the DUKE of WELLINGTON for SALE. - The son of the late well-known haircutter to his Grace the late Duke of Wellington, at Strathfieldsaye, has a small quantity of HAIR, that his father cut from the Duke’s head, which he is willing to DISPOSE OF. Any one desirous of possessing such a relic of England’s hero are requested to make their offer for the same, by letter.

RELICS of the late DUKE of WELLINGTON. - For SALE, a WAISTCOAT, in good preservation, worn by his Grace some years back, which can be well authenticated as such.

Next, a very choice article - quite unique - the value of which may be presumed to be considerably enhanced by the conclusive impossibility of its being doubted in the least degree by the most suspicious mind.

A MEMENTO of the DUKE of WELLINGTON. - La Mort de Napoleon. Ode d’Alexandre Manzoni, avec la Traduction en Français, par Edmond Angelini, de Venise. - A book, of which the above is the title, was torn up by the Duke and thrown by him from the carriage, in which he was riding, as he was passing through Kent: the pieces of the book were collected and put together by a person who saw the Duke tear it and throw the same away. Any person desirous of obtaining the above memento will be communicated with.

Finally, a literary production of astonishing brilliancy and spirit; without which, we are authorised to state, no nobleman’s or gentleman’s library can be considered complete.

DUKE of WELLINGTON and SIR R. PEEL. - A talented, interesting, and valuable WORK, on Political Economy and Free Trade, was published in 1830, and immediately bought up by the above statesmen, except one copy, which is now for DISPOSAL. Apply by letter only.

Here, for the reader’s sake, we terminate our quotations. They might easily have been extended through the whole of the present number of this Journal.

We believe that a State Funeral at this time of day - apart from the mischievously confusing effect it has on the general mind, as to the necessary union of funeral expense and pomp with funeral respect, and the consequent injury it may do to the cause of a great reform most necessary for the benefit of all classes of society - is, in itself, so plainly a pretence of being what it is not: is so unreal, such a substitution of the form for the substance: is so cut and dried, and stale: is such a palpably got up theatrical trick: that it puts the dread solemnity of death to flight, and encourages these shameless traders in their dealings on the very coffin-lid of departed greatness. That private letters and other memorials of the great Duke of Wellington would still have been advertised and sold, though he had been laid in his grave amid the silent respect of the whole country with the simple honors of a military commander, we do not doubt; but that, in that case, the traders would have been discouraged from holding anything like this Public Fair and Great Undertakers’ Jubilee over his remains, we doubt as little. It is idle to attempt to connect the frippery of the Lord Chamberlain’s Office and the Herald’s College, with the awful passing away of that vain shadow in which man walketh and disquieteth himself in vain. There is a great gulf set between the two which is set there by no mortal hands, and cannot by mortal hands be bridged across. Does any one believe that, otherwise, ‘the Senate’ would have been ‘mourning its hero’ (in the likeness of a French Field-Marshal) on Tuesday evening, and that the same Senate would have been in fits of laughter with Mr. Hume on Wednesday afternoon when the same hero was still in question and unburied?

The mechanical exigencies of this journal render it necessary for these remarks to be written on the evening of the State Funeral. We have already indicated in these pages that we consider the State Funeral a mistake, and we hope temperately to leave the question here for temperate consideration. It is easy to imagine how it may have done much harm, and it is hard to imagine how it can have done any good. It is only harder to suppose that it can have afforded a grain of satisfaction to the immediate descendants of the great Duke of Wellington, or that it can reflect the faintest ray of lustre on so bright a name. If it were assumed that such a ceremonial was the general desire of the English people, we would reply that that assumption was founded on a misconception of the popular character, and on a low estimate of the general sense; and that the sooner both were better appreciated in high places, the better it could not fail to be for us all. Taking for granted at this writing, what we hope may be assumed without any violence to the truth; namely, that the ceremonial was in all respects well conducted, and that the English people sustained throughout, the high character they have nobly earned, to the shame of their silly detractors among their own countrymen; we must yet express our hope that State Funerals in this land went down to their tomb, most fitly, in the tasteless and tawdry Car that nodded and shook through the streets of London on the eighteenth of November, eighteen hundred and fifty-two. And sure we are, with large consideration for opposite opinions, that when History shall rescue that very ugly machine - worthy to pass under decorated Temple Bar, as decorated Temple Bar was worthy to receive it - from the merciful shadows of obscurity, she will reflect with amazement - remembering his true, manly, modest, self-contained, and genuine character - that the man who, in making it the last monster of its race, rendered his last enduring service to the country he had loved and served so faithfully, was Arthur Duke of Wellington.

导读

弗吉尼亚·伍尔芙（Virginia Woolf，1882—1941），出生于英国伦敦肯辛顿，英国作家、文学批评家和文学理论家，意识流文学代表人物，被誉为二十世纪现代主义与女性主义的先锋。

伍尔芙的父亲莱斯利·斯蒂芬爵士（Leslie Stephen）是维多利亚时代出身于剑桥的著名文学评论家、学者和传记家。她成长于文化氛围浓厚的环境，在家中接受教育，阅读父亲的丰富藏书。从1906年起，伍尔芙的兄弟在剑桥结识的朋友们不断来家聚会，逐渐形成了一个文艺和学术的中心，即布卢姆茨伯里派（Bloomsbury Group），伍尔芙成为成员之一，其他成员包括了当时文化界的大批精英，对伍尔芙的文学创作产生了深远影响。

由于童年的不幸遭遇和父母先后离世，伍尔芙的精神遭到打击，几度崩溃，直至1941年投河自尽。有人这样形容伍尔芙：“她的记忆有着隐秘的两面—一面澄明，一面黑暗；一面寒冷，一面温热；一面是创造，一面是毁灭；一面铺洒着天堂之光，一面燃烧着地狱之火。”

拥有这样矛盾的气质的伍尔芙一生著述丰富，除了写下《达洛维夫人》（1925）、《到灯塔去》（1927）等著名小说外，还创作了多篇散文，在英国散文发展中占有重要地位。这本《空袭中的沉思》精心收录其中十篇。

“空袭中的沉思”发出了女权主义作家的呼喊。通过描述一场空袭，揭示出两性的不平等，思考女性的命运及其在人类社会中的巨大作用，主张女性的力量与男性相当甚至超过男性，认为女人可以“将男人从专制中解脱出来”，为帮助他们战胜内心的好战本能而“创造更多光荣的活动”。

“城市漫步”“牛津街浪潮”是对工业时代伦敦这座城市的观察与体验。文中既有明媚街景，又有晦暗角落，男女老少，高低贵贱，人景交织，现实与历史碰撞，在追求真实的自由的体验者眼中构建出光怪陆离的都市景象。

“工艺”对看似普通的文字的内在特质进行了探讨。文字不实用，但具有分辨真伪、表达真理的能力。文字含义变化多端，要恰当地运用文字，就要保留文字“表达多件事”的本性，不要禁锢其自由。这为阅读与写作提供了新的视角。

“传记艺术”是对传记文学的反思与质疑。二十世纪的传记已发生变化，传记不是史料的堆积，不该死气沉沉。作传者服从事实，但“有权利支配所有可供挑选的事实”，应更为主动、更富创造性，写出能引起读者共鸣的传记。

“对当代文学的印象”表现了伍尔芙的文学批评观，认为批评家必须站在读者的立场，从作者的视角理解与把握作品的文学性和精神世界，指出虽然处在一个杰作贫乏的时代，评论家应该“认真感受现在，观察过去和未来之间的联系，为即将到来的杰作作好准备”。

“为什么”对英国文学的教育模式发问，认为大学讲授文学的做法是过时的传统，学生“如果要通过英国文学考试，就要对英国文学进行相关写作，而这一切注定了埋葬英国文学的毁灭性结局”。人们应该聚在一起平等谈论文学，心灵相通。

“读者和报春花”探讨了作家与读者的关系。作家应知道自己是为谁而写，明智地挑选读者，为大众服务；理想的读者应具备一定的素质，帮助作家呵护写作之花。对读者的选择最为重要，文学的命运取决于读者和作家的结合。

“现代小说”被视为意识流小说创作的宣言，“生活是一圈闪耀的光晕，朦朦胧胧，从意识觉醒起就笼罩着我们，直到一切结束”；同时认为现代小说已不能生搬硬套传统小说观，指出了作家的使命，对小说写作技巧和选材等内容加以明确，提出小说创作是开放而非封闭的。

“应该如何阅读”对怎样读书的问题进行了回答，但强调这个回答并非给予他人的建议，而是伍尔芙主观的想法。她认为作为读者首先要消除成见，继而通过写作技巧更好地加强阅读技巧，广泛涉猎，运用想象力欣赏作品，对其进行评判，从中受益。阅读的乐趣就是阅读本身。

这些散文见解独到，娓娓道来，涵盖了女权主义、英国语言文学、作家与读者的关系、城市风景等多个主题，拓展了散文的范畴。开卷发人深省，相信读者细细品味后一定获益匪浅。

秦瑞宇

空袭中的沉思

昨天和前天连续两个晚上，德国人的飞机从这幢房子的上空掠过。此时此刻他们卷土重来。这种经历十分奇特：躺在黑暗之中，听着一只大黄蜂的嗡嗡声，而这只黄蜂随时可能蜇死人。这声音打断了对和平的冷静而连贯的思考，却比祷告和圣歌更能强迫人思考和平问题。如果我们不能把和平变为现实，我们—不单单是这张床上的这一个人，还有即将出生的千千万万的人—都将处于同样的黑暗之中，都将聆听同样的死亡悲鸣。枪声在山上砰砰响起，探照灯不时穿透云层，炸弹落在或近或远的地方。此时此刻我们正在思考，为了创造唯一有效的空袭避难所，我们能做什么事情。

英国和德国的年轻人正在头顶上空作战。保卫者是男人，进攻者也是男人。英国女人既没有武器退敌，也没有武器自卫。今晚她们只能手无寸铁地躺着。如果相信空中的战斗是德国人毁灭自由、英国人保卫自由之战，她们就必须尽自己所能为英国而战。然而手无寸铁的女人如何为自由而战呢？制造武器，纺织服装，或者烹饪食物。但是还有另外一个方法，无需武器却能为自由而战：我们可以用思想进行战斗。我们可以思考如何帮助那些正在空中击敌的英国年轻人。

但是为了达到此目的，我们必须快速决策并付诸实施。空中的黄蜂唤醒了思想上的黄蜂。今早《泰晤士报》上出现了嗡嗡声—刊登了一个女人的声音：“女人没有丝毫政治话语权。”内阁里没有女人，甚至任何重要职位都没有女人。制订有效计划的所有决策者都是男人。这种做法不仅限制了思维，还助长了不负责任的风气。为什么不堵上耳朵把头埋在枕头里，放弃思考这个徒劳的行为？因为不光办公室和会议室有思考的空间，别的地方也有。我们能因为看起来无用就放弃个人思考或遐想，从而失去可能对年轻的英国男人有价值的武器吗？仅仅因为我们的能力可能会让我们被辱骂、被蔑视，我们就强调自己无能吗？“我永远不会放弃精神斗争”，布莱克这样写道。精神斗争意味着反潮流思考，不随波逐流。

这股潮流借助广播和滔滔不绝的政治家快速而猛烈的传播。每天他们都说我们是自由的民族，我们为了保卫自由而战。这种思想回荡在年轻飞行员的脑海中，成为他们在云层间穿梭盘旋的动力。在地面上，我们头上是屋顶，手边是防毒面具。我们务必要揭开谎言的伪装，发现真相。真相是我们并不自由。今晚我们不论男女都是囚徒—男人全副武装，手边是枪；我们女人身处黑暗，手边是防毒面具。如果我们真的是自由的，我们应该在户外，跳舞、嬉戏，或是坐在窗边一起聊天。是什么让我们不能这样做？“希特勒！”喇叭里传来一声大叫。希特勒是谁？他是做什么的？他们的回答是侵略、暴政和对权力赤裸裸的疯狂追逐。消灭了希特勒，你们就会得到自由。

飞机嗡嗡飞过，听上去好像有人在头顶上锯木头。飞机盘旋不停而后飞过，房子正上方的木头也锯个不停。脑子里的声音也不停。埃斯特女士在今早的《泰晤士报》上说道：“男人潜意识中的希特勒主义压制了有能力的女人。”毫无疑问我们被压制了。今晚我们都是囚徒—英国男人被囚禁在飞机中，英国女人被囚禁在床上。但是如果他们停下来转而去思考，他们可能被杀死；我们也是一样。所以让我们替他们思考，让我们把压制我们的希特勒主义从潜意识里曳到意识中来。希特勒主义渴望侵略，渴望统治，渴望奴役。即使在黑暗中，这一切依然清晰可见。我们能看到耀眼的橱窗里茫然注视的女人，涂脂抹粉的女人，穿戴整齐的女人，涂着深红色口红和指甲油的女人。试图奴役别人的人，自己就是奴隶。如果我们可以将自己从奴役中解脱出来，我们应该也可以将男人从专制中解脱出来。奴隶成就了希特勒们。

一枚炸弹掉了下来。所有的窗户都吱吱作响。高射炮猛烈开火。山上还隐藏着一些火炮，上面覆盖了一张缠绕着模仿秋天落叶色调的绿色和棕色布条的网。现在这些火炮也都开火了。九点广播的时候我们将听到“晚间击落四十四架敌机，其中高射炮击落十架”。广播说解除武装是和平条件之一。意思是将来再也没有武器、陆军、海军和空军，再不会训练年轻人使用武器战斗。头脑中响起一个声音，好像阁楼上黄蜂的嗡嗡声，这声音来自一句引用：“与真正的敌人战斗，射击素不相识的陌生人，赢得不朽的荣誉和光辉，回家时胸前挂满了奖牌和勋章，这就是我最大的愿望……学习，训练，迄今为止我所做的一切都是为了实现这个愿望。”

这些话来自一位英国年轻人，他参加了上次战斗。面对这些，主流思想家还会认为仅仅在会议桌上签署“解除武装”的文件就完成了所有该做的事情吗？奥赛罗会失业，但他还是奥赛罗。在空中战斗的年轻飞行员的动力不仅是广播里的声音，还有他们内心的声音—人类古老的本能，教育和传统助长并推崇的本能。他们应该因为这些本能而备受责备吗？我们能听任政治家的调遣而收起母性吗？在和平条件中假设有这么一个命令：只有少数被特别挑选过的女人可以生育。我们会甘心服从吗？我们可能会说：“母性是女人的光辉之处。学习，训练，我一生所做的一切都是为了这份荣光。”但是，如果为了全人类的利益，为了世界和平，有必要限制生育和收起母性，女人将会努力接受。男人会帮助她们。他们会因女人拒绝生育而表彰她们，给予女人其他释放创造能力的机会。那也属于我们争取自由斗争的一部分。我们必须帮助年轻的英国男人从内心根除对奖牌和勋章的狂热。为了试图战胜内心好战本能和潜意识里的希特勒主义的年轻人，我们必须创造更为光荣高尚的活动。我们必须补偿失去武器的男人。

空中的嗡嗡声越来越响，所有的探照灯都直直射来，对准这屋顶正上方的一点，炸弹随时都会落在这幢房子上。一，二，三，四，五，六……时间一秒一秒流逝。炸弹尚未降落。但是在悬而未决的时间里所有的思考都停止了，所有的感觉都消失了，只剩下，隐隐的恐惧，像一枚钉子把整个人钉在了硬木板上。害怕和憎恶的情绪变得枯燥无味。一旦恐惧消除，思绪就跳脱出来，本能地尝试创造，慢慢恢复。房间一片漆黑，创造只能靠回忆。想到那些八月里的回忆—在白莱特听瓦格纳；在罗马的平原上行走；还有在伦敦的记忆。朋友的声音纷至沓来。诗歌的只言片语进入脑海。每一个想法，即使在回忆中，都远远比害怕和憎恶带来的恐惧来得积极乐观，充满活力，抚慰人心和富有创意。因此，如果我们将要对失去荣耀和武器的年轻人进行补偿，我们必须赋予他们创造性，我们必须营造幸福感，我们必须将他们从机械中解放出来，我们必须将他们从囚牢引领到一个自由天地。但是如果德国和意大利的年轻人还是奴隶，单单解放英国年轻人有什么用呢？

探照灯在公寓上方照来照去，现在停在了飞机身上。从这扇窗望出去，可以看到一只银色的小虫在光线里转来转去。枪声砰砰响了一阵，然后终于停火。攻击者可能在山后被击落了。之前有一天一个德国飞行员在附近安全着陆。他用流利的英语对逮捕他的人说：“不打仗了，我真高兴！”一个英国男人递给他一支烟，一个英国女人给他沏了一杯茶。从此可以看出，如果将男人从机械中解脱出来，和平的种子不会都落在石地上，它可以生根发芽。

终于完全停火了。所有的探照灯关闭，夏日夜晚回归了自然的漆黑一片，耳边再次响起村庄往常和平安详的声音。一个苹果扑通落地。猫头鹰一边咕咕叫着，一边扇着翅膀在林间飞来飞去。某位英国老作家的一句模糊不清的话突然映入了我的脑海：“美国的猎人们已站起身来……”让我们把这些信息片断传达给那些在美国的猎人，传达给那些还没有被枪炮声惊醒的男人和女人，相信他们一定会宽厚、仁慈地重新思考这些信息，也许将这些信息转化为有用的东西。不过现在，在处于黑夜的那一半世界，我们要睡了。

城市漫步

游历伦敦

可能没有人会对一支铅笔热情澎湃。但是总有些时候就是特别想拥有一支铅笔；有些时候我们一心想要获得某样东西，好找个借口在下午茶和晚饭的空当里漫步穿过半个伦敦。正如猎狐者打猎是为了保护狐狸族群，人们打高尔夫球是为了保护大片空地不叫开发商侵占，因此到街上走走的想法涌上心头时，铅笔就成了极好的托辞，我们站起身说：“真的，我得买支铅笔。”仿佛凭此借口我们可以尽情享受冬日城市的生活乐趣—在伦敦的街道上漫步。

时间应是晚上，季节应是冬天，因为冬天明亮的香槟色天空和热闹的街道令人心旷神怡。在夏天，喜欢树荫、独处和牧草场的清甜香气会被嘲笑，在冬天则不会这样。晚间的黑暗和灯光也让我们卸下责任。我们不再是自己。四点至六点之间的傍晚，天气美好，我们步出家门，不再是朋友们熟知的自己，变成了无名步行者共和大军中的一员，在一个人的房间独处之后，这真令人愉快。在自己的房间里我们被物品包围着，这些物品不仅折射出我们的奇怪秉性，还加深了对个人经历的记忆。比如说，在壁炉上挂着的那个碗，是一个大风天从曼图亚买来的。我们当时正要离开商店，一位带着邪气的老妇人猛地一下拉住我们的裙子，说她可能某天突然就饿死，但是大叫：“拿着它！”把一个蓝白相间的瓷碗塞到我们手中，仿佛连她自己都无法面对如此莫名其妙的慷慨大方。正因为如此，尽管怀疑被狠狠地骗了，我们还是内疚地把碗带回了小旅馆。回去的时候是午夜时分，旅馆老板正和他妻子激烈地争吵，我们都向院子探出身去看，却看到藤蔓缠满了柱子，星星在天上熠熠生辉。千万个瞬间悄悄溜走了，只有那一个被定格，像一枚硬币打上了不可磨灭的印记。在那里，那个忧郁的英国人在小铁桌边喝上几杯咖啡，站起身，暴露了内心的秘密—像一般旅客一样。所有这一切—意大利，刮风的清晨，缠绕在柱子上的藤蔓，英国人和他内心的秘密—都因壁炉上挂着的瓷碗而从记忆浮现出来。目光落到地面，看到的是地毯上一块棕色的污渍。这得怪劳埃德·乔治。“那人坏透了！”康明斯一边说一边把水壶放下，他本来要往茶壶里添水，结果在地毯上烫了一个褐色的圈儿。

但是一旦把门关上，所有这些都消失了。我们的灵魂形成一个硬壳裹住自己，让自己看起来与他人不同。现在这个硬壳碎了，形状粗糙的重重皱褶都碎了，剩下的如同牡蛎中间的肉，那么敏锐，好似一只巨大的眼睛。冬天的街道多美啊！有的地方明亮，有的地方昏暗。人们可以隐约看出笔直的大道两侧对称门窗的轮廓；路灯下晃动着浮岛一样的光圈，表情愉快的男男女女快步走过。和他们身上散发出的贫困窘迫的气息相比，脸上的表情看起来那样不真实，呈现出一种胜利的气息，好像他们给生活设了个圈套，然后得逞了，生活居然跌跌撞撞错过了他们。然而无论如何，我们都只是在做表面文章。眼睛不是矿工，不是潜水者，更不是地下珍宝的搜寻者。它只是带领我们顺流而下；眼睛看着的时候，大脑可能中断思考，停下来休息。

冬天的伦敦街道真美，灯光聚作一个个岛屿，黑暗连成长长的丛林。街的一边散落着几棵树和几片草丛，黑夜就地蜷起身子安然睡去。如果走过铁栅栏，可以听到树叶和树枝轻声颤动的噼啪声，猫头鹰咕咕叫着，远处山谷中火车辘辘驶过，更能感觉到四周的安静。但别忘了这是伦敦。光秃秃的树冠上高高挂着映出浓黄光线的椭圆框—那是窗户；如低悬的星星一样不间断亮着的光点—那是路灯；承载国家和国家和平的空地不过是伦敦的一个广场，周围环绕着办公室和住宅。那里现在正灯火通明，灯光照在地图、文件和办公桌上，书记员坐在桌前用沾湿的手指翻阅没完没了的书信；或是火光摇摆，灯光线直射进私人会客厅，照在舒适的椅子、纸张、瓷器、嵌入式的桌子和女子身上。她正精确计算要放几勺茶。她向门口望去，好像听到楼下门铃响起，有人问她在不在家。

但是我们必须在这里停下来。我们差点越过眼睛许可的范围，探究过深了；我们纠结于一些细枝末节而影响了一路顺流而下。随时，休眠的部队将会开始骚动，在我们心中唤醒千把小提琴和小号；人类会惊醒，显现所有的怪异、痛苦和卑劣。让我们多待一会儿，只满足于表面—公共汽车闪闪发亮，肉店里黄色的猪肋排和紫色的牛排肉色鲜亮，花店的玻璃橱窗里一束束蓝色和红色的鲜花争相怒放。

眼睛有奇特的属性：只为美而停留，就好像蝴蝶追求色彩，沉浸于温暖之中一样。在这样一个冬夜，大自然用尽全力装扮自己，在这样一个如同宝石构成的世界里，眼睛带回了如折断的小块祖母绿和红珊瑚一般最好的战利品。（非专业的普通）眼睛无法将这些战利品组合起来呈现出更晦涩的角度和关系。因此在细细地品味了这些纯粹简单、独立美好的视觉大餐之后，我们有点腻了。我们在鞋店门外徘徊，想了一些与真正原因毫无关联的小借口，不去看明媚的街景，而是退回到微暗的房间。在那里的高台上，我们顺从地抬起左脚，可能会问：“侏儒是什么样的？”

两位常人身高的女士护送她走进来。她们在她身旁看起来像是和蔼可亲的巨人。她们对着售货员微笑，看起来并不想突出她的缺陷，但让别人明白她处于她们的保护之中。残疾人脸上常出现的别扭但又歉疚的表情也出现在她脸上。她需要她们的体贴，但是她讨厌那样。护送她的女士把售货员叫过去，溺爱地笑着让售货员为“这位小姐”拿双鞋试试。售货员把小台子放到她面前，侏儒小姐猛地伸出脚，好像要吸引所有人的注意。她伸出脚好像在命令我们所有人—看啊！快看啊！这只脚形状、大小都与正常发育的女人无异。她的脚拱起，像个贵族。她看着自己放在地面上的脚，这一刻整个人的气质都变了。她看上去温和而满足，充满自信。她要了一只又一只，试了一双又一双。她站起身，在镜子前面踮起脚尖，看她自己穿着黄色鞋子，鹿皮鞋和蜥蜴皮鞋。她提起裙子，炫耀她纤细的双腿。她在想，无论如何，脚是一个人全身最重要的部位；她自言自语，女人会单单因为漂亮的脚得到爱情。只盯着脚看，她可能想的是身体其他的部分和这双美丽的脚比起来不值一提。她衣衫破旧，但准备在鞋上奢侈一下。这是唯一她不怕被人看反而积极地想要吸引注意的场合，她用尽所有手段拖延时间，慢慢地选择搭配。她这样走一步那样走一步，看起来就像在说，都来看我的脚。好脾气的售货员一定说了恭维话，因为她的脸突然洋溢起喜悦。可是，尽管护送她的女士和蔼可亲，但也有自己的事情要处理；她必须要作出决定，决定要哪双鞋。终于，她选定了一双鞋，晃着手指上的包装袋，她走到监护者中间。喜悦退去，理性回归，原有的别扭歉疚的表情又回到脸上。她重新回到街上，又变成了一个不过尔尔的侏儒。

但是她的心情变了；我们跟着她来到街上，她营造出了一种好像真的能让人变得驼背、畸形和残疾的气氛。两个留胡子的男人，兄弟俩，显然是全盲的，全身依靠用手撑住他们中间的小男孩的头，走过大道。他们走得坚强不屈却有点畏首畏尾，这给他们的行动增添了几分恐怖和宿命突然降临到他们身上的必然色彩。他们前进，笔直走着，这个小护卫队好像以独有的静穆，直行和灾难的气势在行人中间开了一条路。实际上，侏儒已经开始跳起踉踉跄跄的奇怪舞蹈，街上每个人都随她跳了起来；胖女士穿着紧身海豹皮外套；弱智的男孩吮吸着拐杖上的银色小球；老人蹲坐在门阶上，好像突然看到了什么人间奇观，他坐下来看—大家都和着侏儒蹒跚的节奏开始跳舞。

有人可能会问，这些跛足眼盲的残疾人生活在怎样的缝隙中？可能在霍尔本和苏活一带窄小老房子的高层。那里的人们来自五湖四海，名字千奇百怪，营生多种多样：打金子、给手风琴打褶、包纽扣，甚至还有更怪异的，买卖没有托的杯子、瓷伞柄、色彩鲜艳的殉道圣人像。人们居住在那里。看起来好像身穿海豹皮外套的女士可能觉得生活尚可忍受，与手风琴打褶人或是包纽扣的人打发时间；如此精彩的生活并不总是悲剧性的。我们沉思，他们并不嫉恨我们的幸福。突然，拐过转角，我们遇到一个有胡子的犹太人，他邋遢，极度饥饿，悲苦凄惨；或是路过素不相识的老妇人，她跛足，躺在公共场所台阶上，身上裹着一件斗篷，就像是谁匆匆忙忙盖在死去的马或驴身上一样。一看到这样的情景，后背上就一阵战栗，汗毛直立；突然之间眼中燃起熊熊怒火，问出一个从未被回答的问题。这些无家可归者通常不会选择待在剧院的周围，去听街头艺人的手摇风琴，也不会等到夜幕降临，去感受用餐者和舞者的光鲜亮丽和美丽身姿。他们靠近商店的橱窗。橱窗里现代商业向躺在门阶上的老妇人、盲人、跛足的侏儒展示颈部镀金的天鹅支撑的沙发，摆着一盘盘五颜六色水果的餐桌，铺满绿色大理石以便更好地承受野猪头重量的橱柜；因年代久远变得异常柔软，从淡红褪色成浅绿的地毯。

边走边看，一切都随意自然却奇迹般地散发出美丽的光芒，仿佛今晚牛津街上买卖的毫无例外全是宝贝。尽管没有购买的想法，眼睛却还是快活大方；它不停地创造；不停地装扮；不停地强化。站在街上，可以建起梦想中房子的所有房间并随心所欲地用沙发、桌子和地毯去装饰。这块地毯适合门厅，那只光洁雪白的碗应该放在窗台边雕花的桌子上，可以从那面圆圆的大镜子里看到我们的狂欢。但是，即使建造装饰了房子，也乐于没有必要去占有它；一眨眼就可以拆掉房子，再用别的椅子和玻璃建造装饰新房子。或纵情欣赏古董珠宝，徜徉在无数的指环和悬挂的项链中。比如，我们选那些珍珠，然后想象如果我们戴上，生活会有怎样的变化。转眼间就到凌晨两三点了；伦敦上流住宅区无人的街道上依旧灯火通明。这种时候只有汽车在外面，人感到空虚、激动和隐隐的快乐。戴着珍珠，穿着丝绸，步出房间，走上阳台，俯视沉睡中上流住宅区的花园。有些人的卧室还亮着灯，可能是刚从法院回家的大人物，可能是穿着入时的男仆，可能是与政治家牵手的贵妇。一只猫悄无声息地爬上花园的围墙。有人在绿窗帘后面的房间暗处私会，发出细微的诱人的声音。年老的首相似乎身处一块平台上，一边优雅地散步，一边为某位头发卷曲佩戴祖母绿的贵夫人解释历史上此处发生过的重大事件，仿佛英国的城郡都在平台之下沐浴阳光。我们像是攀上了最大轮船的最高桅杆的顶端；然而同时我们对此一无所知。爱不能得到证明，伟大的成就没有完成；所以我们与时间嬉戏，在其中轻轻地梳理羽毛。此刻我们站在阳台上，看着月光下的猫慢慢爬上玛丽公主家花园的围墙。

还能有什么更荒谬吗？实际上，现在是六点整；冬天的晚上；我们走路去斯特兰德街买铅笔。那么我们怎么会同时在六月份戴着珍珠待在阳台上呢？还能有什么更荒谬吗？但是这是自然的恶作剧，不是我们的。当她开始最伟大的杰作，创造人类时，她本该专心致志。她反而转过头去，与人格格不入的本能和欲望就偷偷潜入每个人心里，因此我们满是痕迹、斑驳不堪、混杂凌乱；所有的颜色都褪去了。到底是一月份站在人行道上的自己是真的，还是六月份在阳台上探身的自己是真的呢？我是在这里还是在那里？抑或这两个都不是真正的我，我既不在这里也不在那里，但是有些事富于变化并且漫无目的，只有当我们顺应心愿让它自由无阻地发展时，我们才是真正的自己？环境追求统一；方便起见，一个人就是一个整体。一位好公民，当他晚上打开家门，他一定是银行家，高尔夫爱好者，妻子的丈夫和孩子的父亲；而不是在沙漠中漂泊的流浪者，不是仰望星空的神秘主义者，不是流连在旧金山贫民窟的酒色之徒，不是领导革命的战士，更不是离群索居心存怀疑哀号悲鸣的贱民。当他打开家门，他会分开手指轻抚头发，然后和其他人一样把雨伞放在台上。

现在时间刚刚好，我们来到二手书店。这里是保守陈腐之物的避风港；我们看过了街道上的绚烂与悲惨，来到这里让内心得到平衡。书店老板娘坐在烧得很旺的炭火炉边，把脚放在炉围上，被门挡住，这情景让人平静又愉快。她从不读书，要看也是报纸；除了卖书，她最高兴谈论的就是帽子；她说她喜欢实用兼备美观的帽子。哦不，他们不在店里住，住在布里克斯顿；她得能看到一点绿色才行。夏天，她把自己花园长出的花放在大口瓶里，放在积满灰尘的东西上面，以便活跃书店气氛。到处都是书，使我们充满了历险的感觉。二手书是流浪者，无家可归；它们来路不同，却聚集在一起，带着一种图书馆里温顺的书无法比拟的魅力。除此之外，在这个杂乱无章的环境里，我们也许可以有幸接触到一些素不相识的陌生人，有可能成为生命中最好的朋友。当我们从上层书架上取出某本破旧不堪、无人问津的灰白的书，总有希望能够在此遇到一位一百年前横跨马背在中部地区和威尔士地区开拓羊毛市场的男人；或是一位不知名的旅行家，待在客栈里，大口喝酒，观察美丽的女孩和庄严的风俗习惯，费力顽强地将其全部记录下来，所有一切完全出自单纯的热爱（这本书由他自费出版）；书极其无聊，繁杂，平淡，不经意间流入了蜀葵和干草的气味，他却没注意到；他也画了一幅自画像，给他在思想炉边的温暖角落永远保留了一个位置。现在可能有人会花上十八便士买这本书。尽管书的标价是三先令六便士，但是书店老板娘考虑到封面破旧，以及从沙福克郡一位绅士的图书馆的拍卖会上买来这本书就一直待在那的情况，便会以十八便士的价格卖掉它。

然后，环顾书店，我们会和一些默默无闻的人和消失的人建立突如其来的友谊。他们仅存一点记录，比如，这本诗集，印刷精美，包装完好，附有作者画像。他是位诗人，因溺水而英年早逝，他的诗，如此温和谨慎，简洁精炼，发出脆弱的笛声，好像后街上穿着灯芯绒夹克的意大利手摇风琴手演奏出的声音。还有一些旅行者，就像不服输的老姑娘，还在求证他们经受过的苦难和维多利亚女王还是个小女孩时他们热爱的希腊的日落。去康瓦尔郡小煤矿参观被认为非常值得记录。人们顺着莱茵河一路向上，用印度墨水为彼此画像，坐在甲板上绳圈的旁边阅读；他们测量金字塔；多年来远离人类文明；在瘟疫横行的沼泽里教化黑人。他们整理行装，出发上路，大漠探寻，身染热病，在印度终其一生，甚至涉足中国然后返回埃德蒙顿过着单调的教区生活，在布满灰尘的地面上翻滚，英国是这样令人不安的海面，在家门口就能波浪惊天。旅行和探险的海水好像拍打着努力奋斗的小岛，终生事业也在地板上的印刷品中找到立足之地。这些深褐色的书籍背面刻着姓名首字母组合成的图案，可能是传播福音的神职人员；可能是用锤子和凿子在尤里披蒂斯和哀斯奇勒斯的古代文献上雕刻出声的学者。思考、注释、阐释以惊人的速度在我们周围及所有一切之间进行，像准时持久的海浪，拍打着古代文艺作品的海岸。无数著作告诉我们亚瑟有多么爱劳拉，他们分开的时候满怀忧郁，他们重逢之后幸福地生活在一起，就像维多利亚女王管理这些岛屿时那样。

世界上的书无穷无尽，只能大略浏览，颔首致意，浅谈几句，或是略微思考之后就换个话题，就好像在街上，总会偶然听到一些只言片语。他们在讨论一个叫凯特的女人：“昨晚我和她开门见山地说了……如果你觉得我连一张一便士的邮票也不如，我说……”但是谁是凯特，一便士的邮票对他们的友谊意味着什么严重问题，我们永远也不知道；就这样凯特在他们滔滔不绝中隐没了。在街角，生活翻开了新一页，可以看到两个男人站在路灯下商量事情。他们把最近新闻里来自纽马克特的电报一五一十地读出来。这时他们是不是在想有了钱就可以脱去褴褛衣衫，换上轻衣锦裘，挂上怀表，给原本无扣的衬衫别上钻石别针，不复以往的破旧？但是此刻行走的人群快速移动，以致我们无法提出这样的问题。在从工作到家的一小段路上，他们沉浸在令人陶醉的梦里，现在他们离开了办公室，迎面而来的是新鲜的空气。他们穿上了平时必须收起来的鲜亮外衣，充分利用余下的时间，然后他们变成了伟大的板球选手、著名演员和在危机时刻拯救国家的战士。在梦中，他们有时打着夸张的手势，有时大声地骂骂咧咧，穿过斯特兰德街，跨过滑铁卢大桥。在桥下乘火车前往巴恩斯和索比顿，火车辘辘作响。那里大厅中钟表的模样和地下室里晚餐的香气在梦里不断出现。

我们现在到达了斯特兰德街，我们在路边停下，手指长的小棒条拦住了快节奏的丰富多彩的生活。“真的，我必须—真的，我必须”—就是这棒条。思维丝毫不考虑需要，就向暴君般的习惯表示屈服。一个人必须，总是必须做点儿这做点儿那；一个人就是不被允许享受生活。前一段时间我们不就是为这个原因捏造理由，编出了要买东西的借口吗？我们要买什么来着？啊，想起来了，要买一支铅笔。那就让我们走去买铅笔吧。然而我们正要遵从指示，另一个自己跳出来反抗暴君的权威。于是又一场习以为常的争论开始了。躲在义务指挥棒的后面，我们慢慢走开，看到了开阔的泰晤士河—如此的宽广、忧郁和沉静。有人在夏天的夜晚斜倚着堤岸，对世界没有一丝留恋。我们借他的眼睛去看泰晤士河。我们先把买铅笔的事情放到一边；先去找这个人—马上发现一个再明显不过的事实，这个人就是我们自己。如果我们能站在六个月前曾驻足的地方，我们难道不能像当时那样冷静、淡定和满意吗？我们不妨再作尝试。不过河水比印象中更为汹涌阴沉。激流奔向大海。河水掀翻了一只拖船和两只驳船，船里的稻草紧紧地贴在防雨布的顶盖上。离我们很近的地方，有一对倚着栏杆的情侣，像所有情侣一样缺少自觉，仿佛他们正要开始的恋爱重要得很，可以理所当然地不顾对人类放纵堕落行为的任何质问。现在我们看到的景象和听到的声音和过去没有任何关联；我们也感受不到六个月前站在我们现在位置的那个人的沉着心境。他想到的是死亡的幸福；我们想到的是生活的不安定。他没有未来；然而未来正在侵袭我们内心的安宁。只有我们回顾过去，摘除其中的不确定因素，我们才能享受美好的平和。如果是这样，我们就必须返回去，我们必须再次去斯特兰德街，即使在这个时候，我们也必须找到能卖给我们铅笔的商店。

进入一个陌生的房间总是冒险的；因为房屋主人的生活和性格已经把他们的气息注入房间里，我们一走进去，就能呼吸到全新的感情律动。毫无疑问，在文具店里，人们刚刚在吵嘴。怒火点着了空气。双方都停了下来。老妇人—他们可能是丈夫和妻子—退到里屋去；老头儿额头圆圆的，瞪大了眼睛端详一些伊丽莎白时期手稿上的插画，留下来招呼我们。“铅笔，铅笔，”他重复着，“有，有。”他说话心不在焉，但是藏不住情绪的两颊又流露出热情。他打开一个又一个盒子，然后又合上。他说因为有这么多不同的种类，找起东西特别困难。他开始讲一个故事，故事是关于一位因妻子身陷泥潭的法律圈的绅士。他们相识多年；他说，他半个世纪都与教堂打交道，好像希望他妻子在后堂能够听到似的。他打翻了一盒橡皮圈。终于，他因为自己这样笨手笨脚有点生气了，把双开式弹簧门推开，粗鲁地喊起来：“你到底把铅笔放哪儿了？”好像他妻子有意把铅笔藏起来似的。老妇人走进来，谁也不看，她的手直直放在右边的盒子上。那里有铅笔。他怎么能离得了她呢？难道她对他来说不是必不可少的吗？为了让他们肩并肩站在那里，被迫平静下来，必须得挑剔地选铅笔；这个太软，那个太硬。两个人安静地对视。他们站的时间越长，就越冷静。气氛缓和了，愤怒消解了。现在，双方都没说话，但已言归于好。老头儿合上本·琼森的内封面，把盒子放回了适当的位置，向我们大大鞠躬道晚安，然后他们就回去了。她可能拿出了针线活儿；他也许在看报纸；金丝雀把种子平均分给两个人。争吵结束了。

鬼魂出来游荡了，争吵结束了，铅笔买了，街道重新变得空荡荡的。生活退回到顶楼，路灯亮起来。人行道干燥坚硬；马路闪着银光。穿过一片荒芜走回家，把侏儒、盲人、上流社交区别墅的晚会和文具店争吵的故事讲给自己听。虽然只是了解了这些人生活的点滴，却足以让人感觉想法不再单一，有那么几分钟可以进入别人的身体，想别人的事情。可以变成洗衣妇、酒店老板，或是街角的歌手。朋友们，有什么比脱离人格的直线轨道，沿着通向野蔷薇和茂密树丛的足迹，进入野兽栖居的森林深处更为快乐神奇呢？

毋庸置疑：逃离是最大的欢乐；冬天在街道上漫步是最伟大的探险。我们依然再次踏上门阶，感受着长久以来所拥有的东西及偏见包围着我们，抚慰着我们；还有停留在众多城市角落的自我，如飞蛾扑火一般的自我，躲避隐藏起来了。又看到了常见的门；椅子、瓷碗和地毯上的棕色污渍还保持着我们走时的模样。这—让我们温柔地查看，让我们满怀敬畏地抚摸—正是我们从城市的宝藏里获得的唯一战利品，一支铅笔。

牛津街浪潮

码头上的货物包装粗糙，体积庞大，种类多样，等运到牛津街就变得精美细致了许多。大桶潮湿的烟叶被银色的纸片卷成无数排列整齐的香烟。大捆的羊毛被纺成薄背心或柔软的长袜。厚厚的羊毛上的油脂被制成了芳香的护肤膏。买卖双方都同样经历了城市的变迁。穿着黑色外套步伐轻快，或穿着缎面长裙小步走，人类形态与动物制品一样适应新环境。人们不拉也不拽，熟练地打开抽屉，将绸缎在柜台上展平，用码尺量好之后用剪刀裁开。

不用多说，牛津街并不是伦敦最有名的大道。众所周知，卫道士对在牛津街购物的人表示蔑视，而他们居然还获得纨绔子弟的支持。时尚远离汉诺威广场，谨慎地退到邦德街的秘密领地，在那里举行更为庄重的仪式。牛津街有太多的讨价还价，太多的促销，太多上周还是两磅六便士现在就减价到一磅十一先令三便士的便宜货。这里的买卖十分喧嚣吵闹。日落时漫步—看到夕阳映射下的大理石拱门、人造灯光、成堆的绸缎和闪烁的公交车—牛津街好像一条长丝带，虽然起伏不定、俗艳耀眼，但是充满了魅力；又好像一张河床，铺满了被清泉冲刷过的卵石。一切都闪闪发亮。春天街上会出现许多手推车，上面盛满了精美包装的郁金香、紫罗兰和水仙，像是脆弱的小船在交通洪流中茫然打转。角落里，衣衫褴褛的魔术师正把彩色纸片放进大玻璃杯，然后把它们变成绚丽多彩的花丛，形成水下花园。另一角，乌龟在草丛里睡觉。它们行动最为缓慢，想法却最为深沉。乌龟总是一步两步地慢慢移动，小心翼翼地避开路过的行人。据此可以推断，人想拥有乌龟，就像飞蛾想拥有星星，这是人性中永恒不变的一部分。不过，能看到一位女士停下来把一只乌龟放到包裹上，也是难得一见的景象。

考虑到这一切—拍卖、手推车、便宜货、亮晶晶的小装饰—不足以概括牛津街的特色。这里是感官的温床和暖房。这里的人行道好像总是发生重大的惨剧，女演员离婚，百万富翁自杀之类的事件在此经常出现。居民区里的人行道则更为朴实无华。这里的新闻比伦敦其他地方更快更新。这里的人潮拥挤得好像要会吃掉海报上的墨水。这里比别处需要更多海报，需要比别处都快的最新信息。大脑变成一团吸附各种印象的黏稠物，牛津街就是一条卷上去的缎带，充斥着不断变化的景象、声音、动作。包裹撞来撞去，小公交车擦过路边，管乐队大吹大唱，音乐随着队伍远去慢慢变小。公交车、火车、汽车和手推车川流不息，就像拼图中的碎片；一只白色的手臂举起，拼图变厚、凝固、停止；白色的手臂放下，一切又开始、奔驰、扭曲、乱七八糟、毫无秩序。不管我们观望多久，拼图总也拼不起来。

富商在转弯过去的河岸修建了富丽堂皇的宅第，如同古代萨莫塞和诺森伯兰公爵，道赛特和索尔斯伯里伯爵在斯特兰德街上的豪宅一样。大企业的不同建筑见证了建造者的勇敢大胆和进取心，正如卡文迪什和珀西在边远郡里的大宅同样用来证明这些品质一样。我们的商人中一定会涌现出未来的卡文迪什和珀西。诚然，牛津街的伟人非常慷慨大方，和任何在家门口向穷人分发财物或面包的公爵或伯爵没有区别。只不过他们换了一种方式。他们的施舍援助体现在令人心跳的刺激、光彩夺目的展示、扣人心弦的娱乐、晚上灯火通明的窗户或是白天迎风飘扬的旗帜。他们不计回报，和我们分享最新的消息。在那里，会客厅里演奏的音乐是免费的。花不到一磅十一先令三便士就可以享受高大宽敞通风良好的房间；里面地板舒适，电梯豪华，墙壁干净，地毯整洁，银器闪亮。就连珀西和卡文迪什也没有这些。当然所有的装修都是为了能从我们口袋里拿到一先令十一便士；但是如果不为索取回报，珀西和卡文迪什决不会如此大方，要么要诗人的献诗，要么要农民的选票。当然，牛津街的新老贵族都为人们生活和娱乐增色不少。

但是不能否认的是牛津街的宅邸并不牢固—大概只能算得上是场地而非居住地。如果路过这里，看到木条安在铁制横梁上，就会意识到如此装饰华丽的外墙其实不堪一击。哪怕用雨伞尖用力一戳，都可能会对墙壁造成不可修复的破坏。伊丽莎白女王在位时为安置农场主和磨坊主修建了很多农舍。这些农舍虽然陈旧，但是墙壁以橡木为梁，紧密黏合在一起的砖块货真价实，经受得住外力冲击。除此之外农舍还安装了电力配套设施。这些农舍将会目睹所谓的豪宅化为乌有。也许有一天，当工人冒险爬上灰尘弥漫的屋顶，轻轻地敲打那些脆弱得好像是黄色硬纸板和糖霜的墙壁和外表，牛津街就会消失不见。

卫道士又开始对此表示不屑一顾。他们认为，如此脆弱不堪和易损的石头和砖块正是我们这个时代浮躁、虚荣、草率和不负责任的真实写照。不过大概他们也会被嘲笑，就好比是要求用铜去铸造百合，或是让雏菊长出不会腐坏的珐琅花瓣。现代伦敦的魅力就在于伦敦的建筑不是为了持久；而是为了消逝。透明玻璃，彩绘玻璃，彩色灰泥的波纹，汹涌而来的快乐与众不同。过去的建造者和赞助商以营造出永垂不朽的形象为骄傲，并认为那才是高贵典雅。我们则给出不同的定义。我们的骄傲在于可以随心所欲使用砖块石头，搭建临时建筑。我们的后代可能在云端或地下生活，我们不是为了他们而建造房屋，我们是为自己，更确切地说是自己的需要。我们按照自己的意愿拆除重建，在破坏中产生创造和生产的冲动。我们鼓励新发现，提倡新创造。

牛津街的宅子无视了希腊、伊丽莎白时期和十八世纪贵族建筑的长处；直到他们设计出能完美展示梳妆盒、巴黎洋装、廉价袜子和罐装浴盐的建筑，直到他们设计出宫殿、宅第、汽车，直到他们设计出装有留声机、无线电和电影的别墅，供克罗顿和索比顿的店员居住，他们才彻底意识到这一切都将会消逝。因此他们出乎意料地把石块展开，再以希腊、埃及、意大利和美式的狂野将它们压到一起，大胆尝试富丽奢华的风格，努力说服大众这种建筑其实美得无与伦比。这里总有新奇好玩的东西，价格低廉，轻松易得，好像一口看不到尽头的深井每天都冒出气泡。在牛津街，没有比考虑年龄、稳定和持久再奇怪的事情了。

因此，如果卫道士决定下午沿着这条奇特的大道走走，他应该做好准备听到一些古怪不协调的声音。在这里能听到有人在火车和公交车上狂欢高叫。卖乌龟的人说，天知道，我手臂疼；我几乎卖不出乌龟；但要振作！可能马上就有顾客来了；我今晚有没有地方睡觉可全指望它了；如果警察允许，我就推着乌龟沿牛津街走上一整天。做大买卖的商人说，说实话，我没想过要向大众普及高级美感；我绞尽脑汁才明白怎么能浪费最少，效果最好地展示我的商品；把绿龙雕在科林斯柱的顶端可能会有所帮助，让我们试试。中产阶级女士说，我认为，我总是闲逛，这看看那看看，拿东西换东西，讨价还价然后换来一篮又一篮的零料；我知道我两眼放光的样子并不得体，贪婪抢购的行为让人讨厌，但我丈夫不过是银行的小职员；我一年只有十五英镑的置装费；所以我到这里来，到处闲逛，看看我能不能打扮得像邻居那样。我是一个小偷，即使客人不注意的时候，从柜台上抢走手袋也需要很大的勇气；毕竟那里面可能只有眼镜和用过的公交车票。现在就去！

牛津街总是回荡着成千上万诸如此类的声音。一切都紧绷着，一切都是真实的，一切都来自被谋生压力所迫的人无法自抑的倾诉。他们要活着，要找个睡觉的地方，但却不得不无休止地在街上流浪。有人会设想，即使卫道士也要承认，这条俗气、吵闹、粗野的街道提醒我们生活就是战斗；所有的建筑都终会消失，所有的东西都是虚无。从此我们也许可以得出结论—除非聪明的店主心领神会，为孤独的思想者开设悬挂绿丝绒并且有萤火虫和骷髅飞蛾飞来飞去的房间，便于他们进行思考和反省，否则在牛津街任何追求结论的努力都将只是徒劳。

工艺

这个系列的主题是“无法用语言准确表达”，而这篇演讲题为“工艺”，因此，我们认为演讲者想要讨论文字运用技巧—作者的工艺。但是“工艺”这个词应用在文字上，多少有些矛盾和不和谐。平时，每当我们困惑不解时就求助英文词典，但是这次它却加深了我们的困惑。词典上说“craft”这个单词有两个含义：第一个含义是利用材料制作实物—比如，锅、椅子、桌子。第二个含义是诱骗、狡猾和欺诈。现在我们对文字知之甚少，知道的只是—虽然文字不能制造任何实物，但是它却可以分辨真伪。所以，讨论文字关联的技巧就要把两个相互矛盾的概念结合起来，这样大概就可以形成能被博物馆收藏在玻璃罩后面的珍奇宝贝一样的东西。因此，我们有必要更改演讲题目，也许可以换成另一个—文字漫谈。去掉题目的演讲，就好像被砍掉脑袋的母鸡，一直绕圈跑，直到最终死掉—人们把这种人称为母鸡杀手，把这种行为称为无起始演讲的过程或循环。然后让我们回到原点，文字无用。幸好这点众所周知，无须证明。举个例子，当我们去乘地铁，在月台等车，前方悬挂着一块亮灯的招牌，上面写着“经过罗素广场”。我们看到这些文字，自己不断重复，试着表达出脑海中真实的印象：下一列车将经过罗素广场。我们以“经过罗素广场，经过罗素广场”这样的速度一遍又一边地重复。然后一说出来，这些文字就混在一起开始变化。我们发现自己重复说着“一切都消失，消失……树叶枯萎凋落，雾气弥漫。有人出现……”突然清醒过来的时候，发现已经到了国王十字车站。

再举个例子。我们对面的车厢上写着“不要探身窗外”。开始，通过阅读可以了解实际的意思，也就是表面的意思；然而不久，我们坐下来，再读这些文字，发现它们开始混合变化。我们开始说“窗，是的，就是窗—在失掉了的仙域里引动窗扉[1]”。不知不觉，我们就已经探身窗外；去寻找在异邦的谷田里因想家而落泪的露丝[2]。这样做不是被罚二十磅就是脖子被折断。

如果非要证明，以上的两个例子已经证明了文字天生无用。如果我们坚持并强迫它们违背本性变得实用，将会付出代价。代价就是我们会被文字误导和愚弄，就好像脑袋被重重地打了一下。文字总是用这种方式愚弄我们，因为它们试图证明本性如此，不愿变得实用，只愿意表达一个简单的意思而非许许多多的不同含义—它们总是这样做。好在我们终于开始直面这个问题。我们开始创造另一种语言—一种可以完整优美地表达实用信息的语言，即符号语言。某位无名氏在米其林饮食指南中留下了对酒店的评价—不管这位无名氏是男是女，还是无人知晓的神秘力量—我们所有人都要感激他对符号语言的强大灵活的运用。如果他想告诉我们这家酒店一般，另一家不错，还有一家最好，他要怎么做呢？不需要文字；文字会立刻让人联想到灌木丛、撞球台、男男女女、缓缓升起的月亮和夏天海面上成片的水花—都是些美好的事物，但与主题无关。他选择用符号表达：一个三角，两个三角，三个三角。这就是他表达的，也是他需要表达的。贝德克尔借用了符号语言，并进一步使之成为一种高雅艺术。当他想表达一幅画很好，他给一颗星；如果非常好，两颗；如果对他来说是无与伦比的杰作，就会有三颗星在页面上闪闪发亮。符号语言就是这样。星星和匕首之类的符号简化了整个艺术批评和文学批评—当有人想进行简化的时候。但是这意味着作家需要在写作中同时使用两种语言；一种在现实中使用，一种在作品中使用。当自传家需要表述一个实用必要的事实，比如说，奥利弗·史密斯念大学，并在1892年获得第三名，他会在图五上画一个空心的圆圈。当小说家需要告诉我们约翰按响了门铃，不一会儿女仆打开了门，说“琼斯夫人不在家”，考虑到我们自身，他会更愿意运用符号而不是词语传达这个令人讨厌的信息—也就是说，在图三上写一个大写字母H。因此我们可以期待有那么一天我们的自传和小说都变得简洁有力。同时，用文字标注“不要探身窗外”的铁路公司会被处于不高于五磅的罚款，理由是没有选择正确的表达方式。

到那时，文字就会变得毫无用处。我们可以研究文字另一积极的特质，也就是表达真理的能力。通过查阅多部字典，我们发现至少有三种对真理的解释：上帝的绝对真理、学术真理和普遍真理（通常真实可信）。但是分别考虑三种真理要花费很长时间。那么就让我们把想法简单化，因为时间是检验真理的唯一标准，而语言最能经受时间变幻，所以语言是最真实的。建筑物会倒塌，甚至地球也终会毁灭。一切不过是沧海桑田，过眼云烟。但是如果运用恰当，文字好像可以永存。那么接下来，我们要问的是，应该如何恰当运用文字？我们说过，文字不表达实用信息，因为实用信息是只能表达一件事的信息。然而文字的本性就是表达多件事。以“经过罗素广场”这个被认为无用的简单句子为例，它除了表面含义，还包括了很多隐藏义。“经过”这个词暗示了事物的转瞬即逝，也就是时间的流逝和人事的变迁。“罗素”这个词暗示了树叶的沙沙声和光滑地面上的短裙，还有贝德福公爵宅第和英格兰一半的历史。最后，“广场”这个词让涂满石灰、轮廓分明的广场形象映入眼帘。因此，最简单的一句话也能唤醒想象、记忆、视觉和听觉—阅读的时候这一切都结合在一起。

然而，尽管它们结合在一起—哪怕这结合也是无意识的，一旦我们察觉到这些暗示，并加以强调，它们就变得不真实，我们也变得不真实了—我们变成了专家、文字游戏者、短句发现者，而不是读者。阅读的时候，我们要让隐藏义继续隐藏着、暗示着，不去挑明，任由它们游离，彼此沟通，好像河床上的芦苇。但是那句话里的词—经过罗素广场—毫无疑问都是非常基本的词。这些词不通过打字机而直接来自脑海。它们奇怪诡谲，充满力量，可以暗示出作者自身的一切，他的性格，他的外貌，他的妻子，他的家庭，他的房子—甚至壁炉前地毯上的猫。文字为什么要这样做，怎么做的，如何防止它们这样做？没有人知道。它们不以作者的意志为转移，总是和作者的意志相反。当然没有作家希望读者看穿自己的古怪秉性、个人隐私和怪癖。但是真的有作者，这里不是指打字员，可以做到完全客观吗？通常不可避免地，我们都会通过作品了解作者本人。文字具有如此强大的暗示作用，它们常常会把一本糟糕的书变成一个可爱的人，或是把一本好书变成一个我们很难原谅的人。即使是历史悠久的文字也具有这种能力；全新文字的暗示非常强烈，让我们感受不到作家的本意—而只是看到这些文字，听到这些文字。这是我们对在世作家的评价显得异常善变的原因之一。从某种程度上说，只有作家离世，他的文字才可以不受作家本身的影响，变得纯粹。

可以说，这种暗示的力量是文字最为神秘的属性之一。无论谁，哪怕只写过一句话，都会清楚或模糊意识到这一点。文字，或者说英语，自然而然地充满了回响、记忆和联想。多少世纪以来，它们出入于人们的唇齿之间，在住宅、街道和天地中穿梭。这也是今天书写文字的主要困难之一—它们包含了太多含义和记忆，缔结了许多著名婚姻。比如说，“殷红”这个词—谁会在用这个词的时候忘记随之而来的“一碧无垠的大海[3]”？当然，很久之前，当英文还是一门新的语言时，作家可以创造新词。现在创造新词也十分容易—每当我们看到新事物或者产生新的感受，新词就涌到唇边—可是我们不能这样做，因为文字有它的历史。不能在一门历史悠久的语言里使用完全新鲜的词，这一点显而易见却又有些神秘，因为词不是独立存在的个体，而是文字的一部分。如果不是句子的一部分，就不是一个真正的词。文字彼此相关，当然了，只有伟大的作家才会把“殷红”和“一碧无垠的大海”联系在一起。新词和老词的结合会对句子造成致命的打击。为了恰当运用新词，必须要创造一门新的文字；毫无疑问，我们将成功，但那不是当务之急。当务之急是我们能运用现在的英语做些什么。我们怎么把老词用新的顺序组合起来让它们重获新生，光彩再现，吐露真言，这才是问题所在。

如果谁能回答这个问题，他就有资格获得世上任何一顶荣誉的桂冠。试想，如果写作可教可学意味着什么？每本书每份报纸都说实话，创造美。然而，教授文字的过程中会出现一些障碍和困难。因为即使此刻有百余位教授在讲授过去的文学，千余位批评家在评论现在的文学，成千上万的年轻男女要参加学分最高的英语文学考试，事情并没有发生改变—四百年前没有授课、批评、教学，我们比那时写得更优美，读得更明白吗？我们现在所处的乔治时期的文学比维多利亚时期的文学好得多吗？事实如此，我们应该责备谁呢？不是教授，也不是评论家，更不是作家，而是文字。该责备的是文字。在所有事物中，文字最为不羁、自由、不受束缚、无法教授。当然，你可以捕捉文字，进行分类，并按照字典里的字母表排列顺序。然而文字不在字典里，在脑海中。如果你想证明这个，只要想想我们需要用文字表达情绪的时候总是找不到合适的表达就清楚了。虽然有字典，字母表中有大概五十万个词任凭我们使用，但是我们能灵活运用吗？答案是不能，因为文字不在字典里，而在脑海中。再看一遍字典。毋庸置疑，没有比《安东尼和克里奥佩特拉》更辉煌的戏剧；没有比《夜莺颂》更优美的诗歌；除了《傲慢与偏见》或是《大卫·科波菲尔》之外小说都是外行的粗糙拙劣的作品。秘诀就在于找到正确的词语，并将其恰当排列。但我们就是做不到，因为文字不在字典里，而在脑海中。怎么让它们进入脑海呢？就像千人千面，文字也多种多样，不一而终，有的大相径庭差别迥异，有的一见如故和谐融洽。文字的确不像我们总是被仪式和会议束缚。贵族文字可以和平民结合。只要英语愿意，它可以嫁给法语、德语、梵文和黑人语。实际上，为了保护“她”的名誉，不要去探究亲爱的英语“母亲”的过去。因为“她”实在经历了太多次结合。

这种文字的漂移无法改变，根本无法制定相关规则。我们所能规定的就是一些微不足道的语法和拼写原则。当我们在幽深漆黑偶有光亮的洞穴边缘向内窥探文字的住处—脑海—我们能说的就是它们喜欢人们在运用前先去思考和感受，但不是思考和感受它们，而是别的。文字高度敏感，极易感到不自在。它们不喜欢被别人讨论纯洁与否。如果有人想创造一个纯洁的英语社会，文字就会创造出一个不纯洁的英语社会来表示抗议—也就是现代英语中反常的语言暴力，这是对文字清教徒的反抗。它们还高度民主，相信每个词都有自己的优势，没学问的词和有学问的词一样好，粗俗的词和高雅的词一样好，在它们的社会里没有阶级或地位之分。文字不喜欢被用钢笔划出来，个别考察。它们结合起来形成句子、段落，或是整篇文章。它们讨厌变得实用功利，讨厌在公共场合发表演讲。简而言之，文字讨厌任何把它们和单一含义结合起来或运用它们表达单一含义的行为，因为其天性善变。

也许这才是文字最令人惊奇的地方—它们渴望变化。为了表达捕捉到的不同真实而变得多种多样，一会儿这样，一会儿那样。因此同一句话在这个人看来是这个意思，在那个人看来是那个意思；这代人觉得难以理解，另一代人觉得一清二楚。正因为这种复杂特殊性，文字才得以生存。我们这一代人中没有伟大的诗人、小说家，或是批评家，原因之一可能就是我们限制了文字的自由。我们只固定使用一个实用含义，这个含义可能会帮我们赶上火车，也可能会让我们通过考试。然而当文字被禁锢，它们就收起了翅膀，默默死去。最后，也是最重要的，像我们一样，文字需要隐私，从而自由自在地活着。当然文字喜欢我们在运用前思考和感受；但是它们更喜欢我们稍事休息，哪怕只是片刻的无意识。我们的无意识成就了文字的隐私；我们的黑暗就是文字的光明……我们的思考停下来，世界垂下黑暗的面纱，此时把文字温柔地召集起来，促成它和完美意象之间的闪婚，成为永不褪去的美好。但是，不—今晚不会发生。小家伙们闹脾气了，它们开始惹麻烦，不听话，装聋作哑。它们到底在低声说些什么呢？“时间到了！安静！”

传记艺术

1

传记艺术，虽然这样说—但是我们会立刻提出一个问题，传记是一门艺术吗？考虑到传记家曾带给我们的那些愉悦，这个问题显得有点愚蠢和狭隘。但是被如此频繁提及的问题背后肯定有些什么。不管何时打开一本崭新的传记，这个问题总会出现在书的每一页；难怪看上去有点死气沉沉，毕竟，传记里提到的人，有几个还尚在人世？

但是传记家认为，人们认为传记总是死气沉沉的原因在于传记与诗歌和小说这样的艺术相比还很稚嫩。对自己和别人感兴趣是人类头脑的最新发展。在英国，直到十八世纪，有关私人生活的描写才开始满足人们的好奇。直到十九世纪，传记才发展成熟，所获颇丰。如果真的只有三位伟大的传记家—约翰逊、伯斯威尔和洛克哈特—是因为时间太短；传记艺术形成发展的时间相对较短的说法已被教科书认可。不过究其原因—为什么散文作家的出现晚于诗人若干世纪，为什么乔叟在亨利·詹姆斯之前出现—最好先把这些无人问津的难题放到一边，让我们去研究传记为什么缺乏杰作。原因是在所有艺术中，传记艺术所受的限制最多。对此有现成的证据。史密斯曾经给琼斯写过传记，他在书的扉页上向曾借给他信件的老朋友和“最后也是最重要的”遗孀琼斯夫人表示感谢。因为如果“少了她的”帮助，他这样写道：“这本传记将无法完成。”他在前言中简单指出，现在的小说家，“书中的每个角色都是虚构的”。也就是说小说家可以自由发挥；传记家却被限制禁锢。

如果是这样，我们就进一步接近了那个不仅难以回答而且可能无法解决的问题：将传记归类为艺术作品意味着什么？无论如何，传记和小说相互区别—组成内容的不同可以证明这点。一个是借助朋友的帮忙完成的作品，内容来源于事实；另一个是不受限制的自由创作，艺术家酌情选择有利于自己的内容去发挥。因此区别是存在的；我们有充分理由相信过去的传记家也发现了这一点，因为这不仅是区别而且是非常重大的区别。

对于传记写作来说，遗孀和朋友其实是非常严厉的监工。试想，比如，那个聪明男人的道德败坏，脾气暴躁到把靴子扔到女仆的脸上。他的遗孀会说：“尽管这样我还是爱他—他是我孩子的父亲；决不能让热爱他作品的广大读者理想破灭。要不换个说法，要不就干脆不说。”传记家只能屈从。因此维多利亚时期传记中的大部分形象都非常僵硬刻板，像被殡葬队伍搬运然后保存在西敏寺的蜡像一样—只有外形和棺材里的死者极为相似。

之后，十九世纪末期传记艺术发生了转变。原因迄今不明，但是遗孀的思想变得更加开放，而大众的目光变得更加敏锐；蜡像一样的人物形象不再能够让人信服或满足人的好奇。自然而然地，传记家获得了相当的创作自由，表现在他至少可以暗示死者还有缺点和不足。弗洛德笔下的卡莱尔绝不是戴着玫瑰红色面具的刻板形象。弗洛德之后是埃德蒙高赛，他敢于承认他父亲也会犯错。紧接着埃德蒙高赛之后，就是在二十世纪初叶出现的利顿·斯特雷奇。

2

利顿·斯特雷奇作为传记史上非常重要的人物，值得我们稍作停顿仔细研究。他的三本名著—《伟大的维多利亚时代》《维多利亚女王》和《伊丽莎白女王》，高水平地展示了传记的取舍。同时也回答了一些问题，如传记是否是艺术，如果不是，为什么。

利顿·斯特雷奇作为一位作家实在是生逢其时。1918年，他出版了第一本传记，灵活自由的风格备受关注。对于像他这样对自己创作诗歌或剧本的能力存疑的作家来说，传记写作似乎是一个大有前途的选择。因为归根结底，如实记录逝者的生平总是能做到的。维多利亚时期盛产如同石膏雕塑一般的光辉形象，实际情况被严重扭曲。为了重现事实，呈现传记人物真实的模样，正需要和诗人或小说家同样的艺术天赋，而不用他自认缺少的原创能力。

事实证明传记写作非常值得一试。在《伟大的维多利亚时代》的创作过程中，他既饱受煎熬又兴致勃勃；这本书的成功可以证明他的笔触足以让曼宁、弗洛伦斯·南丁格尔、戈登和其他人重生，因为他们本就有血有肉。这些人多次成为舆论焦点。戈登酗酒是真事，或不过是杜撰而已？弗洛伦斯·南丁格尔是在卧室里还是客厅里接受勋章？尽管当时欧洲正处于硝烟战火之中，纷乱复杂，他依然激起大众的热情，去探寻名人生活的细枝末节。书中的描写痛苦和欢乐交织，十分精彩，因此他的书一版再版。

但是这些都是他创作的着重人物形象刻画的短小文章。他在描写伊丽莎白和维多利亚两位伟大女王的生活时进行了更为大胆的尝试。这是传记从未有过的展现其作为的好机会。现在机会就在眼前，他用所有自由灵活的创作赢得了这个机会。他的表现十分无畏，因为他已经证明了自己的才能非常卓越，完全能够胜任这项工作。结果是，传记的特性变得更加明显。有人在几次阅读之后还会质疑，难道两者相比，《维多利亚女王》获得巨大成功，而《伊丽莎白女王》则是惨败吗？其实如果我们这样比较，并不是利顿·斯特雷奇的失败，而是传记艺术的失败。在《维多利亚女王》中，他把传记当作一种技巧，甘受限制。在《伊丽莎白女王》中，他把传记当作一门艺术，打破束缚。

然而我们还要质疑这个结论的来源及其依据。首先，对于传记家来说，为两位女王写传的难点明显不同。维多利亚女王的一切都为人所知。她的所作所为，甚至她的所思所想都人尽皆知。没有谁的生平像维多利亚女王那样得到了清楚地验证。传记家无法进行原创，因为每时每刻手边的资料都会提醒他的写作和历史不同。因此，创作《维多利亚女王》的时候，利顿·斯特雷奇妥协了。他将传记家甄选和关联资料的能力发挥到极限，但是严格控制在事实范围内。保证每句话都有依据；每个事实都有来源。事实证明他对老女王的生活描述，就像伯斯威尔对字典创始人的描述一样。利顿·斯特雷奇笔下的维多利亚女王是为众人认可的维多利亚女王，正如伯斯威尔笔下的约翰逊是现在普遍接受的约翰逊博士一样。其他版本终会消失不见。无疑，在此之前他已经取得了巨大的成就，不过他渴望更进一步。所以才创作出这样真实可信有血有肉的维多利亚女王。然而不容置疑的是她的形象仍然存在局限。传记难道无法拥有诗歌一般的热烈，戏剧一般的激情？传记的特点难道只能是尊重事实和实际取材吗？

伊丽莎白女王似乎是一个非常适合进行大胆尝试的传记对象。人们对她的事迹不甚了解。她所生活的年代久远，那个时代人们的风俗、想法甚至行为十分奇特。“我们运用哪种艺术才能进入这些奇怪的思想，或是潜入更奇怪的部分中？我们越清楚怎么运用，就越偏离那个奇特的世界。”利顿·斯特雷奇在首页上写下这样的话。但是很明显，《伊丽莎白女王》是一段具有可塑性的悲剧历史，鲜为人知，所以惹人遐思。一切都非常适合写进书中，两个世界的优势集合在一起，赋予了艺术家极大的创作自由，并为创作提供事实依据—这本书不仅仅是一本传记，还是一部艺术作品。

尽管作家费尽心思，一切只是徒劳，因为事实和杜撰无法完美结合。伊丽莎白女王既不像维多利亚女王的形象那样真实，也不像克里奥佩特拉或孚斯塔夫那样富有戏剧性。原因似乎是，无人知晓—虽然他勇于创新，但是变得小有名气之后—他的创新却遇到了阻碍。因此女王身处一个位于事实和杜撰之间的模棱两可的世界。在那个既不抽象也不具体的世界，读者能感受到作家的茫然和努力，然而女王的形象十分中庸，毫不出彩，虽然没有任何批评，仍然算是失败。

如果判断正确，我们必须要承认传记自身存在问题：总是强加条件，条件就是必须要建立在事实基础上。我们说的传记里的事实是非艺术家也会认可的事实。如果像艺术家一样创作—不存在佐证无法对比的原创—并且试图将原创和事实结合起来，结果就是两败俱伤。

在《维多利亚女王》一书中，利顿·斯特雷奇似乎非常清楚地意识到这种条件的必要性，并且本能地屈从了。“女王的前四十二年，”他这样写道，“因为大量分门别类的官方信息而变得光辉夺目，直到阿尔伯特逝世，她才蒙上面纱。”随着阿尔伯特逝世，面纱落下，官方信息派不上用场，他意识到传记家必须依照前例。“我们乐于进行简短概括。”他这样写道，最后的几年被概括介绍。但是伊丽莎白女王的一生远比维多利亚女王的最后几年更为神秘。因此，他不再进行简短概括，而是开始写一本书，这本书包含了奇怪想法和由于可靠信息的缺失而变得更为奇怪的部分。以他当时的能力来说，这种大胆的尝试注定失败。

3

因此，每当传记家抱怨，说自己被朋友、信件和文件束缚时，其实不过是指出了传记创作不可避免的因素，当然也是不可避免的限制。因为原创人物生活在一个只有作家自己了解的世界里。在那个世界里，事实的真伪完全取决于作家的想法。和由其他人提供的真实信息创造出的世界相比，在作家自己想法支配下创造出的世界更为珍贵、热情和和谐。因为这样的差距，两个世界无法融合，如果妄图结合就会造成两败俱伤。我们似乎可以得出这样的结论：没有谁能同时在两个世界称雄；你必须作出选择，然后接受自己的选择。

尽管如此，《伊丽莎白女王》这本书并非毫无价值，它的失败开启了新的成功，因为这是传记家倾尽全力完成的大胆试验。利顿·斯特雷奇如果还在人世，也会十分确信是自己拓展了传记原创这条道路。事实也是这样，他为我们指出了后人前进的方向。传记家服从事实—应该这样。但是，即便如此，他也有权利支配所有可供挑选的事实。如果琼斯的确把靴子扔在女仆脸上，有一个情妇住在伊斯林顿，或是一夜风流之后醉倒在水沟里，那么传记家就有权利将这些事实写进书里—只要反诽谤法和人类情感允许的话。

但是这类事实和科学事实不同—科学事实一经发现，就保持不变。这类事实随想法变化而变化，想法则随时间变化而变化。现如今，通过心理学家举例说明，我们都知道关于罪恶的思考可能是种不幸；或是种好奇；或两者皆非，不过是不值一提毫不重要的琐碎之事。人们对性的想法也不断变化。这些变化使得大量消亡事物的毁灭模糊了人们的真实特征。过去经常出现的一些标题—大学生活、婚姻、事业—其实起得武断又造作。如今人们对书中主人公的生活的看法改变了。

因此传记家要走在我们这些人的前面，像矿工肩上的金丝雀一样，检测气氛，探寻虚伪、不真实和过时习惯的存在。传记家必须能活跃而谨慎地感受周围的事实。必须重申的是，因为我们生活的时代有众多来自报纸、信件和日记的摄像头，从不同角度关注每一个方面，传记家必须准备好认识同一张脸孔的矛盾两面。传记家的视线会对准奇怪的角落，从而扩大观察范围。如果事实的来源广泛，传记的内容就会十分丰富，不会杂乱无章令人困惑。因为很多不为人知的事情现在为人们所了解，我们不禁扪心自问，是否只有伟大人物的人生才应该被记录？难道不是每一个曾经活过，并留下生活记录的人都值得写传记吗—不管他是失败还是成功，卑微还是显赫？此外，究竟什么是伟大，什么是渺小？传记家必须修正我们关于美德的标准，树立新的值得崇拜的形象。

4

因此，传记的发展刚刚起步。我们可以肯定的是它还要面临漫长的积极的发展道路—途中会遇到困难，危险和艰苦。不管怎样，我们还可以肯定的是和诗歌小说的发展道路不同—传记的不那么紧张刺激。因此传记作品注定不会不朽，尽管每位作家都希望自己的作品永垂不朽。

已有事实证明传记的发展不会如作家所愿。伯斯威尔笔下的约翰逊博士不会像莎士比亚笔下的孚斯塔夫一样长久。我们也几乎可以确定米考伯[4]和贝茨小姐[5]会远远胜过沃尔特·斯科特爵士笔下的洛克哈特先生和利顿·斯特雷奇笔下的维多利亚女王。因为原创人物是用更为持久的要素构建起来的。丰富的想象力剥夺了易逝的事实的光彩；作家的创作素材本就优越，传记家却只能在字里行间写出这些终将消失的事实。几乎一切都要消失，只有个别得到留存。因此我们可以得出结论，传记家是工匠，不是艺术家；他的作品不是艺术品，而是模棱两可的中间产物。

如果浅谈传记，传记家的作品其实是无价之宝，我们表示再多的感谢也无法匹及。我们无法生活在尽是丰富想象的世界里。想象很快就会疲倦，需要休息和提神。但是，对疲倦的想象力来说，最好的补给不是劣俗的诗歌或不入流的小说—这些会让想象力变得迟钝和堕落—而是“严肃的事实”，正如利顿·斯特雷奇在优秀的传记作品中向我们展示的那样。一个真实的人生活过的时代和地方，他如何观察，他如何打扮，他的日常生活如何，他的亲戚朋友怎样，他的爱人怎样，他何时去世，去世时是不是像一个基督教徒一样躺在床上，等等。

传记家告诉我们这些真正的事实，从大事中发现细微，进行概括总结，这样我们就了解了全部。其实传记家比任何诗人或小说家更能启发想象力。因为很少有诗人和小说家可以承受向我们提供事实的巨大压力。但是几乎每一个传记家，如果他尊重事实，都能提供给我们很多事实，丰富我们的知识储备。传记家告诉我们一些事实，这些事实可以创新，可以发挥作用，可以提示和发展。对此有确切证据。就像读诗或读小说会产生共鸣一样，我们读完传记后将它搁置一旁，会发现一些场景还是非常鲜明，人物形象还在脑海深处栩栩如生，就好像我们回忆起往事。

对当代文学的印象

当代读者一定会对此印象深刻：同一时刻两位评论家坐在同一张桌子旁边，却对同一本书产生了截然相反的态度。一方面，这本书被认为是一本英文散文杰作；同时另一方面，如果火不会被它扑灭的话，它就是一厚叠理应被扔入火中的废纸。然而这两位评论家对弥尔顿和济慈持相同观点。他们如此表现是出于自身的敏锐感受和毋庸置疑的由衷热忱。只有当他们讨论当代作家的作品时，才会不可避免地起争执。引起他们争论的这本书不过出版了两个月左右，一位评论家认为它对英国文学的影响不仅立竿见影，而且很可能长期持续；另一位评论家则认为这本书不过是胡乱拼凑的无稽之谈。下面会解释为什么两者得出的结论不同。

此解释让人费解。读者和作家都一样为难；读者想在混乱的当代文学中找到方向；作家则自然而然地想了解自己在几乎一片漆黑中费尽心思创作出的作品是否有可能在英国文学名作中崭露头角，还是正相反，被人置之不理付之一炬。但是如果先将自己定义为读者，去探讨读者的困境，我们就不会感到这样迷惑。类似的事之前也经常发生。甚至从罗伯特·埃尔斯米尔[6]开始，平均一年两次，在春秋时分，我们都能听到学者们对新书的反对和对旧书的赞同。斯蒂芬·菲利普斯的书随处可见，然而即便这样，仍然有很多人并不喜欢。不过如果两位绅士观点一致，都认为布朗克的书是一本无可争议的杰作，我们就不得不面对一个抉择，是否要花上十先令六便士的书费去支持他们的观点，这的确更让人惊讶和心烦。这两位都是著名的评论家，哪怕是脱口而出甚至是不假思索的意见，都会作为对英美地区文学的评论，被收录进严肃的散文专栏。

固有的愤世嫉俗会让我们对当代的天才人物产生狭隘的不信任感，我们会不知不觉说出这样的话：如果评论家观点一致，那只是说明他们无事可做。当代文学根本不值得花钱，一张图书馆借书卡足矣。因为问题依然没有解决，让我们直接向评论家提问。如今的读者对已去世的作家毫无敬意，却被一个问题困扰，尊敬已去世的作家是否与理解在世的作家息息相关，于此难道没有任何相关指导吗？两位评论家快速调查后都遗憾地表示并没有这样的人。他们的评价为什么和新书相关呢？当然不是因为那十先令六便士的书费。他们丰富的经验告诉我们一些过去因鲁莽行为而造成严重后果的例子；如果他们评论去世的作家，却对在世的作家大加赞赏，就犯了评论界的众怒，会丢掉工作，毁掉声誉。他们提出的唯一建议就是尊重并无畏地追随自己的直觉，不要受任何在世的评论家或书评作者的影响，更不要反复阅读过去的著作质疑自己的直觉。

正是因为这些人，我们不得不表明事情不总是如此。尽管具体内容不为人知，我们相信曾有一条定律或规律约束着广大的读者群众。并不是说杰出的评论家—德莱顿、约翰逊、柯尔雷基和阿诺德—一定会对当代作品作出完美的判断，尽管他们的评语不会永久地印在书上，也不会省去读者自省的问题。但至少他们的存在会产生集中影响。他们随意给出一些书评，不难想象仅仅这样就能压制餐桌上人们的意见分歧，却让现在的学术权威费尽心机也不得其解。不同的学派会一如既往地热烈讨论，但是每个读者心里都会有这样的想法，至少有一个人会接近文学的主旨：如果你允许他有瞬间反常，他会凭一己之力与永恒接轨，无视赞美和责备，逆风向前。但是说到成为一个评论家，性格要大方，时机要成熟。当代社会分散的餐桌，构成社会的种种思潮的追逐和漩涡，只有涉猎极广的大人物才镇得住。值得我们期待的那个伟人到底在哪里？我们有书评作者但是没有评论家；我们有百万个能干正直的警察但是没有法官。有品位、有学识、有本领的人都在给年轻人讲学，都在为过去歌功颂德。但是他们灵活多产的笔触却总是让鲜活的文学组织干燥脱水变成小巧的骨骼。我们感受不到德莱顿那样的激情，也感受不到济慈那样温和天然的性情，或是他那样深远的洞察力和清晰的理智，或是柯尔雷基对诗歌的全身心投入，尤其是他作品中最常被人引用的伟大言论会在阅读时散发光热，正如书的灵魂一般。

对这一切，评论界也都慷慨大方地表示赞同。他们认为伟大的评论家极罕见。但是一旦他奇迹般地出现，我们如何支持，或者我们提供些什么？如果伟大的评论家本身不是伟大的诗人，那么他们一定得到了时代的哺育。有一些大评论家需要支持，有一些学派有待创立或毁灭，但是我们的时代已经到了贫乏的边缘，还没有谁一枝独秀技压群雄。没有什么大师，能够让年轻人骄傲自豪地成为他的学徒。很久之前哈代就淡出文坛；康拉德的才能带着一丝异国情调，这让他无法具有偶像般的影响力，虽然也被尊敬爱戴，但却有几分淡泊疏离。就其他人来说，尽管为数众多，极富热情，作品层出不穷，至今无人能对同时期的人产生影响，或是透过今天我们这个时代到达并不十分遥远的将来，成为我们津津乐道的不朽伟人。如果我们进行一个世纪测试，看看现在英国出版的书一百年后有多少还会存在，必须要说我们不光在哪本书这个问题上存在分歧，更令人质疑的是是否会有这么一本书。这是一个支离破碎的时代。几节诗，几页书，到处都是的章节，这部小说的开头，那部小说的结尾，对最好的时代或者作家来说都是一样的。但是我们能留给后代几打零散的书页，或让那时的读者从所有摆在他们面前的文学里大海捞针一般挑出少得可怜的华彩篇章吗？这些就是评论家可以堂堂正正放在桌面上，和作为同伴的小说家和诗人一起讨论的问题。

开始时，悲观主义似乎足以克服所有阻力占到上风。是的，我们再重复一遍，这是一个贫乏的时代，诸多方面都可以证实；但是，坦白地说，如果将两个世纪作比较，结果十分明显，我们被狠狠压倒。《韦弗利》、《远游》、《忽必烈汗》、《唐璜》、赫兹里特的散文、《傲慢与偏见》、《海伯利安》和《自由的普罗米修斯》都出版于1800到1821年。我们这个世纪不缺乏工业；但是如果说到杰作，不得不承认悲观主义者是正确的。似乎天才的时代之后是努力尝试的时代，再之后是喧嚣奢靡的时代。当然，这些放弃了不朽的机会而建筑井然有序的房屋的人们理应得到荣誉。但是如果我们说到杰作，何处可寻？我们知道有一些诗可以长存；济慈、戴维斯、德拉梅尔、劳伦斯，他们的诗当然拥有辉煌的瞬间，但是和长存不同。毕尔勃姆在他的领域是完美的，但那不是一个很大的领域。《遥远的过往》中的篇章无疑将会流芳百世。《尤利西斯》带来了值得纪念的伟大变动—十分大胆，变动剧烈。于是，我们挑挑选选，这样那样地摘出一些，拿出来展示，却感到被排斥或嘲笑，最后不得不同意评论家的反对意见，这的确是一个缺乏持之以恒的努力的时代，到处都是凌乱的碎片，根本无法与之前的那个时代相提并论。

这些说法盛行一时，我们也屈从于说话者的权威，然而却非常清楚有些时候我们连自己的话也无法相信。再重复一遍，这是一个贫乏枯竭的时代。我们不得不满怀嫉妒地回顾从前。但是同时，这也是初春晴朗的一天。生活总是不乏色彩。就连电话，总是打断严肃对话、缩短重要评论的电话，也别有一番情趣。虽然人们不经意的对话很难永垂不朽，但是在一个有灯，有街，有房子，有人们，或美丽或奇异的背景下倾吐心声，这一切交织在一起本就成为永恒。但这是生活；而我们谈论的是文学。我们必须试图将两者分开，反对悲观主义的优越合理，为乐观主义的鲁莽叛乱正名。

我们的乐观大体上说来自本能，来自晴朗的天气、美酒和畅谈，来自生活每日赐予的财富和最健谈的人也表达不出的启示。尽管我们尊敬爱戴死者，我们还是更喜欢生活本来的样子。就算我们可以选择生活在过去的任何时代，眼下也总有一些东西是我们不愿意交换的。当代文学尽管有不足和缺点，却还是那么富有魅力，那么吸引我们，就像一个我们每天都批评斥责却无法失去的亲人。它具有一种和蔼可亲的品质，这一点和我们自己，我们的作品以及我们生活的地方很相似。它并不居高临下，与我们保持距离，从外部审视，也没有像我们这代人如此强烈地怀念同时代。我们和先人被生生割裂开来。规模上的变化—几世纪以来一直保持原位的群体突然下跌—从上到下动摇了组织结构，把我们和过去割裂开来，可能使我们太过清楚地认识，到自身所处的现代。每天我们发现自己忙着，说着，或者想着对父辈来说不可能的事情。我们感觉到比起已经被完美诠释的相同点，不同点还没有引起足够多的关注。新书吸引我们去阅读，有几分希望能够反映我们重新变化的态度—这些场景、想法以及明显不和谐的偶然组合带来强烈的新奇感—并且，就像文学一样，回到我们的管辖范围，完整且便于理解。这的确是乐观主义的所有理由。我们这个时代拥有许多愿意表达将他们和过去割裂的不同点的作家，他们不愿表达将他们和过去连接的相同点，这些作家比任何其他时代的都更多。提起任何一位的名字都可能会惹人不快，但是即便是最肤浅的读者，只要对诗歌、小说或是传记稍有留意，就一定会对我们这个时代的勇气、真诚，简单地说，其广泛的原创性印象深刻。但是我们的快乐被莫名其妙地剥夺了。很多书都给我们一种承诺无法实现、知识贫乏、生活里被攫取的光彩没有转化为文学的感觉。当代作品中的佼佼者往往来自压力下的记录或潦草的速记，当人物在场景里出现，他们的行为和表情就会被以惊人的才华保留下来。但这些场景总是一闪而过，对此我们非常不满。快乐有多深，烦恼就有多重。

无论如何，我们回到了起点，在两端之间摇摆不定，这一刻还是狂热，下一刻就变成悲观，无法得出任何有关我们当代文学的结论。我们曾向评论家寻求帮助，但是他们觉得这件事不值一提。现在，正是通过咨询过去的杰作，接受他们的建议，修正这些极端的时候。我们感觉自己不得不这样做，不是被冷静的判断驱使，而是急切需要把我们的不稳定寄托在他们的稳定上。但是，说实话，今昔对比带来的震撼一开始令人不知所措。毋庸置疑，名著多少有些沉闷。华兹华斯、斯科特和奥斯汀的书中满是无所谓的平静，平静到让人想睡觉。他们忽略出现的机会，无视积聚的色彩和细节。他们看上去十分从容，不去满足被当代人快速刺激的感官：视觉、听觉、触觉—尤其是，人类自身的感觉，他的深度，想法的多样性，他的复杂性，他的困扰，等等，简言之，人本身。华兹华斯、斯科特和奥斯汀的书中对这些表现得很少。那些逐步产生、令人愉快，最后彻底地征服我们的安全感从何而来呢？这力量来自他们的信仰—加在我们身上的他们的信念。这一点在哲学诗人华兹华斯的身上体现得非常明显。闲适的斯科特也是一样，他总是在早餐之前草草几笔写出惊世之作。至于那位内向的未婚女士，则是在安静中单纯为了愉悦自己悄悄进行写作。这两位身上有一点相似，那就是都相信生活是平稳的。他们具有自己的行为判断。他们了解人和人之间以及人和世界之间的关系。他们可能都不会说出非常绝对的话，但是一切都依附其上。我们发现自己只是在表达信念，其他的一切都自行而来。举个简单的例子，我想起最近出版的《沃森一家》，一个美丽的女孩出于本能想去安慰一个在舞会上被冷落的男孩，只要你觉得这样绝对合理，你不仅会让一百年后的人们有同样的感觉，还会让他们感觉到文学。因为那种确定性是创作作品的条件。相信你的感觉能抓住一些对别人有益的东西，就可以从个人的限制束缚中解脱出来，像斯科特一样自由，充满热情地去发掘迷住我们的这个新奇浪漫的世界。这也是简·奥斯汀作为一个伟大作家所擅长的神秘加工过程的第一步。选择曾经的经历，深信不疑，把自己置之事外，然后准确地安排好位置；她非常自如地把这一切完成，使之成为文学的完整状态，整个过程不会向分析家泄露任何秘密。

当代作家让我们苦恼，因为他们没有信念。即使他们中最真诚的作家也只会告诉我们他自己身上发生了什么。他们无法创造一个世界，因为他们不能自如面对其他人。他们不会讲故事因为他们不相信故事是真实的。他们不会归纳。他们只依靠自己的感官和情感，尽管的确非常真实，而不愿依靠提供模糊信息的知识。他们被迫不去使用最具威力和技艺最精巧的武器。尽管坐拥英国文学的全部财富，他们却只是快速翻过一本又一本书。他们匆匆写下从外部观点选定的一个新鲜角度，热情地记下一闪而过的光芒，这点亮了什么？瞬息的光彩可能什么也不是。但是评论家在其中干涉，带着几分正义感。

如果这个描述站得住脚，如他们所言，并且不像可能的那样，完全依赖我们在桌边的位置和相当单纯像芥末瓶和花瓶一样的个人关系，那么评判当代文学的风险要比从前更大。如果他们的评论不着调也是情有可原的。就如马修·阿诺德建议的那样，从当今燃烧的区域退回到过去安全的平静更好。“我们进入一片燃烧的区域。”马修·阿诺德写道，“就在我们走近距离不远的那个时代的诗歌，拜伦、雪莱和华兹华斯的诗歌里面的价值评判不只是个人的，还是满怀热情的个人。”他们让我们想起，这些话写于1880年。他们提醒我们，注意观察放在显微镜下的每寸丝带，尽管它绵延不绝；如果我们毫无作为，事物就自己分类；节制和研究经典得到推崇。不仅如此，人生短暂；不久即将庆祝拜伦百年诞辰。此刻迫在眉睫的问题是，他到底有没有和他的妹妹结婚？总结一下，就是—如果的确任何一个结论都有可能的话，当每个人现在都说话，时间在不断流逝—对如今的作家而言，放弃创作杰作的希望似乎较为明智。他们的诗歌、喜剧、传记和小说不是书而是笔记。时间，好比一位优秀的老师，会手把手地教导，指出他们的缺点、草率和不足，把作品全都撕碎；但是他不会扔进废纸篓中。他会一直保留，因为别的学生会发现非常有用。未来的杰作出自今天的笔记。正如评论家刚才所说的，文学历史悠久，历经变革。尽管一些小争端可能搅得海面波涛汹涌，让小船不得安宁，但过分夸张它们的重要性则显得目光短浅心胸狭隘。狂风暴雨不过是表面现象，平和隽永才是本质。

对于评论家来说，他们的任务是评价当代的新书，我们承认这些评价会有几分艰涩难懂，常常令人心生不快。我们希望评论家们给当代文学予以鼓励，对那些花环花冠式的作品予以宽恕，它们偏离正道，易于消逝，还让戴花冠的对象在半年时间里着上去有点可笑。让评论家们更加自由，更加客观地对待当代文学和作者，置身其中，共同努力完成当代文学这座伟大的建筑，尽管可能个别工人的名字不详。希望他们重重关上门，尽管门的那一边温馨和谐，可以享受无数物美价廉的食物，哪怕只有一次，不再讨论那个令人兴奋的话题—拜伦是否和他的妹妹结婚—然后，离开我们坐着闲谈的桌子，哪怕离开一点，聊一些和文学本身有关的话题。如果他们要离去，我们要尽一切努力挽留，让他们想起那位瘦削的贵族女士，赫斯特·斯坦霍普夫人。她在马棚养了一匹乳白色的马，为的是有一天救世主能够骑上她的马在山顶鸟瞰世界，一览美景。虽然她等得心急如焚，但一直相信救世主总会出现，因此她从未放弃等待。评论家应该向她学习；认真感受现在，观察过去和未来之间的联系，为即将到来的杰作做好准备。

为什么

《吕西斯特拉忒》的第一期出版了，我承认十分失望。书的纸张质量上乘，印刷精美，看上去十分成功，尽善尽美。我一页页地翻着，感觉好像财富突然降临到萨默维尔。我本打算以消极的态度回应编辑的约稿请求，但值得欣慰的是，当我读到其中一位作者衣着简陋，另一位女作者毕业于实力和威望均很弱的大学时，我开始打起精神，许许多多迫切求解的问题涌上心头：“终于轮到我们了。”

和今天很多人一样，我也总是被许多问题困扰。我发现在街上很难不走走停停，有时可能就站在路中间，问为什么。教堂、酒吧、议会、商店、喇叭、汽车、空中飞机的嗡嗡声，和男男女女全都让我发问。然而，只向自己发问有什么意义呢？这些问题应该在公共场合公开提出。但是财富让公开提问变得非常困难。每个问题结尾处那个小小的弯曲的符号能让有钱人变得苦恼；权力和声望强烈反对它。因此，如果问题敏感、冲动或是有点可笑，则一定要仔细选择提问的场合。这样那样的问题被权力、荣华富贵和陈词滥调包围着慢慢枯萎。它们还没进入有影响力的新闻办公室，就在门口一批批死去。它们溜到了令人讨厌的不发达地区，那里的人们贫困潦倒，什么也给不了，无权无势，因此没什么可失去。一直困扰我让我想发问的问题，无论是对是错，如今都应该在《吕西斯特拉忒》中提出。问题们说：“我们从没指望你会在……提及我们。”这里它们说出了一些最体面的日报和周报的名字；“也不是……”这里它们说出了一些最受人崇拜的机构的名字。“但是，感谢上帝！”它们大声说，“女子大学的学生不是又穷又年轻吗？她们不是热爱创新勇于冒险吗？她们不是正要创造一个新的……”

“编辑不准写女性主义。”我严肃地打断它们。

“女性主义是什么？”它们异口同声地喊出来，因为我没有立刻回答，它们又抛给我一个新问题：“你不觉得是时候创造新的……”

但是我打断了它们的话，提醒它们我只能写两千字。如果字数超过了，文章就会被退回来，重新修改。最后我提出了一个请求，我可以采用其中最简单、温和、容易理解的一两个问题。比如，每当社团开始活动，或大学开学时频繁出现的问题—为什么讲课，为什么听讲？

为了好好提出这个问题，我会这样陈述，记忆会留住画面的鲜活，但正如伊丽莎白女王说过的那样，总有那么一个机会，虽然不常见但是永远不用过分悲伤，鉴于友情，或为获取法国大革命的相关信息，去听课是必要的。开始的时候，教室看上去让人摸不清头绪—既不让人休息，也不让吃东西。墙上可能挂着一张地图。当然讲台上会有一张桌子，还有几排又矮又硬很不舒服的小椅子。椅子上面陆陆续续坐满了人，有男有女。不光椅子看上去有点勉强，听课的人也是这样。有些人拿着笔记本，轻轻敲着钢笔；有些人空手而来瞪着牛蛙般的大眼沉默地望着天花板。大钟无精打采；时间一到，一个满脸无奈的男人大步走进教室。他脸上没有常人的表情，取而代之的是紧张、自负，或许还有压抑，仿佛这个艰难的任务令他变得没有一点正常人的样子。这时教室内一阵骚动。因为他写过书，而观察写过书的人是非常有趣的，所以每个人都盯着看他。他头顶光秃秃的，没有一根头发，嘴唇和下巴也与常人无异；总之，就算他写过书，也看不出和别人有什么不同。他清了清嗓子开始讲课。人的声音具有多种功能：它可以使人着迷让人得到安抚，也可以勾起怒火让人感到沮丧；但是在讲课过程中，只是让人心烦。他教授的内容其实非常合理，有学识，有论据，有推论，但是听着听着，注意力就涣散了。大钟看起来满脸惨白，指针也虚弱无力。莫非它们得了痛风，或是水肿？缓慢移动的动作让人想起一只三条腿的苍蝇痛苦地在冬天挣扎存活。平均有多少只苍蝇能活过英国的冬天？如果发现自己出现在讲授法国大革命的课堂上，这样一只昆虫会怎么想？这么想完全是白费功夫。已经溜号了—那一段已经讲过去了，没必要让老师重复。他讲得非常吃力但却很坚持自我。要找到法国大革命的源头—苍蝇的想法也要找到。千里以外也能运筹帷幄是这门课程的目的之一。“略过这段吧！”我们向他提出请求—没用；他没有略过。这简直就是一个笑话。然后老师的声音再次响起，窗户好像需要清洗，有女人打了一个喷嚏；老师的声音开始变快，马上到结论了，然后—感谢上帝！—终于下课了。

生命如此短暂，为什么要浪费时间来上课？好几世纪前就发明了印刷，为什么他不打印讲义非要自己讲课呢？这样，在冬天的炉火边，或是夏天的苹果树下，我们都可以阅读，反复思考，并且讨论讲义；我们还可以斟酌疑难问题，彼此争论。我们会学得更好更深刻。如果讲课的话，老师不得不降低难度，时不时活跃气氛，以便吸引各种各样听众的注意，否则他们很容易去研究鼻子啊下巴啊，要不就是打喷嚏的女人还有苍蝇的寿命，讲义则无须这样的内容重复和难度降低。

我要说的是，外行可能不清楚，大学里设置讲课是大学规章制度的重要组成部分。但是为什么—另一个问题冲上前线—如果讲课是教育的必要形式之一，不应该取消它的娱乐作用吗？总是等到每年春天，迎春花盛开，山榉树变红，英格兰、苏格兰和爱尔兰的所有大学里焦急的秘书才贴出如泉涌般的告示邀请这样那样的人莅临，讲授有关艺术、文学、政治或者伦理方面的课程—这是为什么呢？

过去，报纸稀缺，一份报纸要在办公大楼和教区住宅间小心地传阅。这种情况下努力复习和传播思想无疑是非常必要的。但是现在，桌子上每天都散落着文章和小册子，里面的思想各种各样，比口口相传更为简洁，为什么还要坚持过时的传统？不但浪费时间和力气，还助长了人性的阴暗面—自负、虚荣、逞强和改变宗教信仰的意愿。如果你的长辈们是再普通不过的男男女女，为什么非要让他们变成道学先生和先知？如果你只关注他们头发的颜色和苍蝇的寿命，为什么要让他们在讲台站上四十分钟？为什么不让他们和你平起平坐，亲切愉快地对话，或者倾听？为什么不创造一个建立在贫穷和平等基础上的新型社会？为什么不把人们都聚集在一起，不论年龄和性别，也不论名人还是平民，这样大家可以不用走上讲台，不用朗读论文，不用非得穿昂贵的衣服或是吃昂贵的食物，只是单纯的交谈？难道这样一个社会，这样一种教育模式，不比过去读过的所有艺术和文学的相关论文更为优越？为什么不消灭道学先生和先知？为什么不让人们心灵相通？为什么不试试？

我已经说够了“为什么”这个词，我要纵容自己想想过去、现在和将来的社会大体特征。突然看到特里尔夫人取悦约翰逊博士、荷兰夫人和马考雷勋爵开玩笑的有趣画面，一阵喧哗甚嚣尘上，我几乎听不到自己思考的声音。然后喧哗的原因渐渐清晰。因为愚蠢的我不小心用了“文学”这个词。如果说只有一个词能让人发问并造成混乱，这个词一定是“文学”。他们叫喊着，提出有关诗歌小说和批评的问题，每个都希望自己被听到，每个都觉得自己的问题才是那个唯一值得回答的问题。最后，他们破坏了我脑海中所有关于荷兰夫人和约翰逊博士的美好画面。其中一个坚持认为就算他有点愚蠢鲁莽也要胜于他人，所以他应该优先。他的问题是，如果能自己读书，为什么要在大学里学习英国文学？我要说的是，提出一个已经得到回答的问题是非常愚蠢的—我相信，大学已经在教授英国文学了。不仅如此，如果我们要开始就此进行讨论，我们至少要写二十本书，但是我们只剩下大概七百字了。鉴于他十分急切，我想我还是会问这个问题，尽我所能，在下面这个对话片段里插入这个问题，并且不夹杂任何我自己的观点。

有一天我去拜访我的一位朋友，她的工作是审稿。当我走进房间的时候，觉得有点暗。但是，窗户开着，正是春天里的好天气，那么应该是精神上有点暗淡—我内心的恐惧和忧伤影响了我。不过在那之后，她说的第一句话让我更加害怕：

“哎，可怜的孩子！”她大声说，绝望地把正读着的手稿扔在地上。我问，她的亲友是不是在驾驶或登山途中发生了什么意外？

“如果你觉得以伊丽莎白时期十四行诗发展为主题的三百页手稿是个意外，那么就是了。”她这样说道。

“就因为这个？”我如释重负地回答。

“就因为这个？”她反问，“这还不够吗？”然后，她一边在房间里走来走去一边大声说，“他从前是个聪明的男孩，值得一谈；从前他热爱英国文学。但是现在—”她耸耸肩好像无法用语言表达，悲愤和谩骂接踵而来。想到她每天读手稿的生活有多艰难，我就原谅了她，但是我没法和她一起讨论，我只知道这是一篇关于英国文学的文章。“如果你想教他们读英文，”她突然说，“教他们读希腊语。”—如果要通过英国文学考试，就要对英国文学进行相关写作，而这一切注定了埋葬英国文学的毁灭性结局。“这个墓碑，”她继续说，“一定是一本……”这时我打断了她的话，让她不要再说类似的废话。“那你告诉我，”她一边说着一边紧握拳头站在那儿看我，“他们写得更好了吗？是诗歌变好了，小说变好了，还是批评理论比他们曾经讲授如何阅读英国文学时更好了？”好像为了回答自己的问题，她拿起被扔在地上的手稿读出其中的一段。“和其他段落一模一样！”她低声抱怨，厌恶地把手中的和其他手稿一起放在架子上。

“但是想想他们必须知道的一切。”我尝试着反驳。

“知道？”她重复我的话。“知道？你说知道是什么意思？”要立刻回答这个问题有点难度，所以我把它放在一边，然后说：“好吧，无论如何他们能以此谋生，并且教育他人。”听我这样说，她生气了，抓起分析伊丽莎白时期十四行诗的作品，把它扔到了房间另一边。然后，这次拜访的其他时间都用于捡拾茶壶碎片了；那茶壶本是她外婆的东西。

当然现在还有很多其他问题叫嚷着要被提出；关于教堂、议会、酒吧、商店、喇叭和街上的男男女女；但是万幸的是结束了，一切归于宁静。

读者和报春花

年轻人开始写作的时候，一般会得到看似有理有据其实完全不切实际的建议，比如必须尽可能写得简短清楚，摒除杂念，只表达脑中的想法。但却没有人在此之上补充一条必要信息：“一定要选择正确的读者。”这是一切问题的本质，因为书总是写给读者阅读的。读者不仅是衣食父母，还在不知不觉间，十分微妙地引导作家，激发写作灵感，因此读者是否理想非常重要。

那么谁是理想的读者人选呢？是劝诱作家榨干大脑的精华，让作家写出最为强大多变的作品的人吗？时代不同，回答不同。大体上讲，伊丽莎白时期的作品是写给贵族和剧场大众的。十八世纪的读者包括咖啡店里的智者和格鲁布街书商。十九世纪，著名作家为卖半克朗的杂志和有闲阶级写作。回顾并赞叹这些不同组合的伟大结果，和我们所处的困境对比，看上去一清二楚，简单得令人羡慕—我们应该为谁写作？因为现如今市场空前繁荣，读者类型繁多，令人迷惘，包括日报、周报、月报的读者，英国大众和美国大众，喜欢热销书的大众和偏爱冷门书的大众，品位高雅的大众和思维活跃的大众。现在的读者自我意识强烈，才能显著，愿意通过不同的渠道表达他们的需求和喜好。因此当作家看到肯辛顿公园里开放的第一朵报春花，他就要在落笔之前从众多读者中选择最适合他的读者。“不管谁来读，只考虑描写报春花”这样的话毫无意义，因为写作本身就是一种沟通方式；如果没人分享报春花的美，它就不过是一株不完美的报春花。第一个或者最后一个人类可能会为自己而写作，不过那只是值得羡慕的特例，如果海鸥懂文学，他也会欢迎海鸥去读。

因此每个作家都应该为大众服务，高傲的人可能会说所谓的服务不过是向大众妥协，乖乖地接受别人的安排。道理似乎如此，却还是有很大风险。因为如果作家考虑到自己的读者，但却凌驾其上—这样的关系十分不幸且不和谐，塞缪尔·巴特勒、乔治·梅瑞迪斯和亨利·詹姆斯的作品就是证明。作家既不屑大众，又想讨好他们；如果自己的作品没有赢得一致的好评，他就把自己的失败归咎于大众；他越想越气，觉得他的读者既没有品位也不友好，一定要让他们为自己的卑微和矫饰付出代价。而真正的代价就是报春花备受折磨，虽然还是明艳照人，但却变得有点畸形，一面萎缩另一面狂长。接触一点阳光可能会让它们好起来。我们应该跑到相反的极端（如果只是假设）接受《泰晤士报》和《每日新闻报》编辑故意提出的谄媚提案吗？—“只需花二十磅即可订购专属你的报纸，它将于早上九点之前送达大不列颠的每个角落，并随刊附赠作者签名，像报春花一样在您的餐桌上准时绽放。”

但是单单一朵报春花就可以吗？它真的有可能美得如此炫目，以至于价格昂贵甚至还附带签名吗？显然媒体就是报春花的放大版。每年三月初黄色或紫色的报春花会在肯辛顿公园草坪中开放；如果我们仔细观察，不会觉得报纸上的文章和这些小巧的花朵有什么联系。但是正因为截然不同，在报纸上绽放的报春花更让人惊奇。它们充分利用空间，散发出金色的夺目光彩，不仅精致优美，还十分平易近人，令人如沐春风。没人会认为《泰晤士报》里“我们神奇的批评家”或《每日新闻报》的林德先生可以轻而易举写出众人喜爱的文字。也没有人会觉得让一百万人早上九点开动脑筋写出让两百万人感到身心愉快的文章是件卑鄙的事情。但是当夜幕降临，花朵全部枯萎；就像离开了大海的水波不再光辉闪烁，离开了舞台被困在电话亭中的女歌唱家的歌声也不再优美；只要失去了要素，再华丽的文章也不过如此。总而言之，如果内容陈旧迂腐，文章就会变得味如嚼蜡。

理想的读者群体能够帮助作家不让写作之花枯萎。然而，随着年龄变化，读者自身也产生变化；他既不能被浮夸的表面迷惑，也不能被花言巧语哄骗，而这需要绝对的正直和强烈的信念。真正的作家才能找到真正的读者；确定读者其实是在考验作家的判断力。因为知道为谁而写，才能明白怎么写。但是很多现代读者资质平庸。而现在，作家需要的明显是阅读习惯良好、不会三心二意的读者。同时，作家还要了解其他时代、其他民族的文学。不仅如此，我们所特有的劣势和当今的发展趋势还要求作家具备其他品质。比如，和伊丽莎白时期相比，当今文学的粗俗化更为严重，让我们十分苦恼。不过二十世纪的读者应该已经对此见怪不怪。读者应该能够正确判断，哪些是真正有好处的养料，哪些不过是虚张声势。他还要成为法官，不仅能够判断出对当代文学产生巨大影响的社会因素，还能区分有益的成熟观点和毫无用处的限制束缚。就算读者思绪万千情绪高涨，他往往只能一边强烈支持作家的多愁善感，一边害怕表白自己的想法。读者可能觉得不敢去想比想得太多还要糟糕。他也许还会进一步讨论语言，指出莎士比亚使用了多少词，或违反了多少语法。尽管我们故作优雅地翻阅钢琴上的黑色琴谱，依然无法改进《安东尼和克里奥佩特拉》。读者会说，如果你能连性别一起忘掉就更好了；作家没有性别之分。但是一切不过如此—简单却值得讨论。读者最大的优点就是和作家不同，他们运用简单的语言表达复杂的事物—气氛。读者要营造一种气氛，让报春花身处其中，备感重要；在这种情况下，对作品的误解是不可原谅的行为。读者要让作家产生这样的感觉：单单一朵真实的报春花就能让他感到满足；除了看书，他根本不想去听课，提升水平或了解自我；虽然有些歉意，他的要求还是让卡莱尔激动愤怒，让丁尼生悠闲自得，让罗斯金几近疯狂；他已经准备好接受作家的安排，隐姓埋名或是大出风头；读者不只是作家的衣食父母；二者其实是双胞胎，一损俱损，一荣俱荣；文学的命运取决于他们之间恰当的联盟，因为读者和作家的结合如此的完美—一切都会证明，正如我们在文章开始所提到的，选择读者最为重要。但是如何正确选择？怎么提高写作？这些都还是问题。

现代小说

在对现代小说的任何研究中，包括最自由灵活的研究，都会轻易得出现代艺术优于过去这样理所当然的结论。人们可能会说，虽然过去的工具简单，材料原始，菲尔丁也获得了成功，简·奥斯汀则更为成功，但是把他们的机会和我们的比比！他们著作简洁得确实不可思议。然而将文学与汽车制造之类的工序相比没有意义。人们怀疑，在过去的几个世纪中，尽管我们对机器制造了解很多，但是对于文学创作却知之甚少。我们的写作能力没有进步；我们所做的只能说是不断摸索，一会儿往这边，一会儿往那边；我们应该从制高点充分观察整个变化过程，找出其中的规律和趋势。不过没有必要立刻觉得我们失去了优势。平地之上，人群之中，被尘土半遮了眼，我们心中满是羡慕，回望那些战士；他们更为兴高采烈，战争的胜利，他们的成功带着平和的色彩；我们情不自禁地低语，相比起来，我们的战争更为激烈。就让文史学家为所有一切下结论，他们来判断现在是一个伟大的散文小说时代的开端，中期还是末尾，一般人则无法说清。我们只知道有些感谢和敌对情绪会激发我们；有些道路通向肥沃的土壤，有些则通向灰烬和沙漠；无论如何，这一切都值得一试。

我们不会和大作家起争执。如果我们说到威尔斯、贝内特和高尔斯华绥，在一定程度上他们本人存在的事实赋予他们的作品一些生活化的瑕疵，我们可以随意挑错。尽管他们的存在十分必要，我们还是更为看重哈代和康拉德，以及稍为逊色的著有《紫土》《绿色寓所》和《遥远的过往》的赫德逊。威尔斯、贝内特和高尔斯华绥曾经让许多满怀希望的人兴奋不已，却又让他们不断失望。因此我们的感谢主要是因为他们曾经让我们看到一种可能，虽然是他们并没完成的事情；然而这些事我们既做不来，也不想做。单独一个词不能表达我们对大量工作的控诉和不满，这些工作不仅数量浩大而且种类繁多，既让人赞叹又让人厌恶。如果我们试图用一个词来表达我们的想法，我们应该说这三位作家都是唯物论者。因为他们都不关注精神，而是关注物质，正是这一点让我们失望。我们觉得如果英国小说摒弃他们，哪怕走入沙漠也好，走得越快，对它的灵魂越有好处。自然，没有哪个词能直中三个独立目标的靶心。威尔斯明显没有射中靶心。他的例子暴露了他自身才能的缺点，那就是致命的想法和纯粹的创作激情混杂在一起。但是贝内特先生大概是三个里最过分的一个，因为迄今为止，他的写作手法最为娴熟。他的小说结构良好，有理有据，好像没有缝隙的窗框和没有裂痕的木板，就连最苛刻的批评家也挑不出什么缺点和纰漏。然而—如果生活不愿如此完美呢？这就是《老妇人的故事》的作者、乔治·卡农、埃德温·克雷汉格，以及其他一些人克服的难题。贝内特笔下的人物形象栩栩如生，类型丰富难以想象。但我们还是禁不住要问他们如何生活，他们为什么而活？这些人离开富人区豪华的别墅，在头等火车车厢里打发时间，那里有柔软的坐席，数不清的铃铛和按钮，触手可及十分方便。毫无疑问，这是一场奢侈的出行，就像在布莱顿那样的高级酒店寻欢作乐。我们说威尔斯是唯物论者不是因为他的作品结构精巧。他总想引起读者的心灵共鸣，以至于无法专注素材整合和结构架构。他之所以被称为唯物论者，纯粹是因为美好的心灵；他担负起本应由政府官员承担的责任，进行大量思考和构造，却没有时间去实现，或忽略了其重要性，使得人物形象十分粗糙。他笔下的琼和彼得会一直住在他造出的人间和天堂，有什么批评比这更糟糕呢？难道他们的人性缺点会让威尔斯特意描绘出的理想制度黯然失色吗？尽管我们对高尔斯华绥的正直和慈悲表示尊敬，我们能从他的书中找到我们的追求吗？

即使作家花费大量技巧和工程让转瞬即逝的细枝末节看起来真实持久，我们还是要为这些书别上唯物论者的标签，也就是说，这些书的内容并不重要。

我们不得不承认，我们非常苛刻挑剔，或者说，我们很难勉强解释或表达不满。每次我们都提出不同的问题。但每次读完一本书好像总是不断出现同样的深深叹气的画面—这本书值得读吗？有意思吗？人性不过偶尔出现小小偏差，贝尔特就全副武装，誓要捕捉生活里细微的错误，这样值得吗？这样的生活是不值得的，可能所有一切都不值得这样做。我承认用这样一个意象来说明自己的想法很模糊不清，但是像批评家那样只评判现实是无法改善情况的。既然承认思想的模糊性会干扰小说批评，我们就可以大胆猜测：此刻对于我们来说，小说形式更容易在流行潮流中迷失而非坚持自我追求。不管我们将之称为生活或精神，真理或事实，它已经开始消失或变化，不愿在我们的定义下继续发展。然而，我们却冥顽不灵，死不悔改，在完成越来越背离我们真正想法的计划之后，又继续构想了三十二章。花费如此大的精力来提高故事的合理性使之接近生活，不仅仅是白费工夫，更是南辕北辙。在错误的方向上即使再努力，写出的故事也不合理，毫无想法，看上去黯淡无光。作家不能随心所欲自我发挥，反而被一些权贵肆无忌惮地抑制，迫不得已构思一些情节，包括喜剧、悲剧、爱情故事，还有一种感觉—要让所有人将如此的完美铭记在心。如果他笔下的所有人物都活过来，他们会发现自己穿着当时的流行服饰，外套只系一个扣子。作家开始妥协，导致小说写作出现了变化。但是，随着时间流逝，每当我们进行习惯性的写作，偶尔会对此怀疑或是突然产生叛逆心理。生活是这样的吗？小说必须这样吗？

经过深入洞察，生活似乎并不是“这样的”。仔细观察一下普通日子里普通人的大脑。大脑接收的无数印象—不管平凡普通，与众不同，还是如钢铁般深深铭刻在心。它们像来自四面八方由无数原子构成的连绵不断的原子雨，无穷无尽连续不断地放射光芒；当它们接触地面，变成具体的星期一或星期二，重点也变得和从前不同；重要时刻既不是此刻也不是彼刻；因此，如果一位作家是自由人而非奴隶，如果他对创作具有选择权而非履行义务，如果他能将作品建立在自己的情感而非惯例之上，不再会有什么情节、喜剧、悲剧、爱情故事或是一般意义上的灾难性结局，大概也不会像庞德街的裁缝那样循规蹈矩地缝上每一个纽扣。生活不是一排被安排好的左右对称的马车车灯；生活是一圈闪耀的光晕，朦朦胧胧，从意识觉醒起就笼罩着我们，直到一切结束。不管生活表现出怎样的错综复杂，小说家的责任难道不就是用尽量熟悉的语言表达出时刻变化的既无法了解也无法限制的精神吗？我们不只是在为勇敢和真诚辩护；我们想表达的是，和惯例相比，小说的恰当取材更能让人信服。

无论如何，我们寻求类似方式来定义区分几位年轻作家的作品性质，比起前辈作家，詹姆斯·乔伊斯最为出众。这些年轻作家试图接近生活，更为诚实准确地保留生活中吸引和驱使他们的东西。为了达到目的，他们不惜摒弃小说家习以为常的惯例。无数的原子光束在他们的脑海里迸发，看上去可能有些支离破碎毫无逻辑。让我们按照先后顺序记录下来，描绘出它们的形态，这样每个场景或时间的记录都是意识的记录。我们不要理所当然地认为生活在大事上比在小事上体现得更充分。《青年艺术家的画像》和《尤利西斯》是乔伊斯的两部作品，后者更为小型文艺批评杂志称道。如果有人读过这两本书，可能会随意揣测乔伊斯的内心世界和想法。就我们来说，摆在面前的一份残稿，比起已经完结的小说更为充满刺激。不论作家的想法怎样，作为读者我们可能会认为艰涩难懂或不甚乐观，然而毫无疑问的是他满怀真诚，这才是最重要的。和我们称为唯物论者的人们相比，乔伊斯是精神化的；他关注大脑深处传递信息的噼啪作响的火焰，为了让它持续不断地燃烧，他鼓起全部勇气无视对他产生威胁的一切：这一切可能是统一集合，或是在摸不到也看不到的情况下，很多作家借助过的用来帮助读者进行想象的标志物，比如，坟墓的景象，灿烂、肃穆、混乱和突然意味深长地闪烁的光亮。毋庸置疑，无论如何我们都在初次阅读时被触动了，必须承认他的作品是杰作。如果我们探寻生活的本质，我们就一定会产生共鸣。的确，如果我们试图表达其他的想法，我们会发现自己的摸索十分笨拙。如果我们非要举有名的例子，因为某种原因，这样富有原创性的作品却无法与《青春》和《卡斯特桥市长》相提并论。失败的原因是作家相对贫瘠的思想，我们本可以这样简单概括，然后结束这个话题。但是我们还可以更深入一点，试想我们是否不应该把存在的感觉比作明亮却狭窄的房间，因为如果这样就意味着思想被关着，被限制着，并不是开阔自由的。这样想会抑制创新能力吗？这样想难道不会让我们感受不到快乐或宽容，从而只专注自身，不接受或创造自身以外或超过自身的事物吗？也许这样说有点说教意味，但是说教能影响乖僻孤立的事物吗？抑或是对现代人来说，无论怎样努力创新，比起指出已拥有的，感受所缺乏的更为简单？无论如何，不仔细观察“想法”是错误行为。如果我们是作家，所有的想法都是合理的，因为每一种想法都会正确表达出我们想要表达的思想；如果我们是读者，每一种想法都引领我们更靠近小说家。这样做的好处就是离我们口中的生活越来越近。阅读《尤利西斯》不意味着排斥或忽视了生活的主流，翻开《斯坦恩项狄传》或《潘丹尼斯》也不会感到冲击，这些书让人感到生活多种多样，丰富多彩。

然而，现在摆在小说家面前的问题，我们假设这个问题过去也存在，是怎么创造可以自由取舍的氛围。他必须有勇气说出吸引他的不是“这个”而是“那个”，他必须只用“那个”完成自己的作品。现代人看来“那个”，也就是兴趣点，非常可能隐藏在心底深处。因此，一旦重音变得略微不同，附加在某些事物上的强调就被忽视了。不同的形式纲要变得必要，而我们很难去把握，我们的前辈无法理解。现代人中，大概只有俄罗斯人，会觉得契诃夫写出的《古谢夫》的故事很有趣。故事描写一些俄国士兵乘轮船回国，在船上生病。我们通过他们的对话和内心活动的只字片语了解剧情：他们中间的某人死去并被运走；其他人的继续对话让我们知道古谢夫死了，他看起来“像胡萝卜或红萝卜”，然后被扔到船外。这部小说的重点在于出乎意料的场景。首先整个故事看起来好像没有重点，然后，就像当眼睛适应房间里微弱的光亮并认出物体的形状一样，我们逐渐意识到这个故事是多么的完整，伟大和真实，那正是契诃夫想要表达并描述的。把这样，那样，和其他的想法一起排列组成新的东西。但是我们不能说“这是喜剧”，或“那是悲剧”，我们也无法确定，因为我们知道的是短篇故事应该简洁，结局应该明确，如果不是这样，如果情节含糊不清，结局不明确，根本不能称之为短篇故事。

即使对现代英语小说做简单的评论，也无法跳过俄罗斯小说的影响。如果提到俄罗斯人，有人会觉得想要胜过他们完全是浪费时间。如果我们想理解灵魂和心灵，还有什么地方具有同样的深度呢？如果我们厌倦了自身的现实主义，俄罗斯最普通的小说家也对人文精神有着与生俱来的自然而然的敬意。“学着深入群众……但是别让这种同情留在脑中—尽管这样做很容易—留在心中，满怀爱意。”我们在每一位伟大的俄罗斯作家身上都可以找到圣人的特征，比如对他人苦难的同情，给予别人的爱，尽全力达到一些对道德要求极为苛刻的目标。他们中的圣人让我们对自身不虔诚的平庸感到惊慌，我们的著名小说也显得华而不实，故作玄虚。因此，俄罗斯作家的想法不可避免地成为对悲伤的极大理解和同情。的确，更确切地说，我们可以说是俄罗斯小说的未决性。这种感觉没有答案，如果被检视的生活变成一个又一个必须搁置从而不断发出回响的问题，故事以绝望的疑问结束，我们深深感受到令人厌恶的沮丧。也许他们才是正确的；毫无疑问，他们比我们看得更远，也没有我们严重的视力障碍。但是也有一种可能，我们会看到他们看不到的东西，不然为什么抗议的声音中夹杂着我们的忧郁？抗议的声音是另外一种来自远古文明的声音。远古文明赋予我们本能，去享受并且抗争，不去苦恼或理解。从史特恩到麦勒迪斯的英国小说都见证了我们与生俱来的才能，不管是幽默和喜剧，还是地球的美好，不管是智慧的活跃，还是身体的光彩。但是我们从两本小说的比较中得出的所有推论都远远比不上或胜过他们对我们造成的艺术影响。我们知道世界上没有限制，没有什么—没有“方法”，没有试验，甚至最为狂野的试验—会被禁止，除了虚伪和做作。“小说的合适选材”并不存在；一切都适合写成小说，每个感觉，每个想法，大脑的每项特质和振作的精神，任何知觉都不会出错。如果我们发挥自己的想象力，想到小说艺术有了生命，站在我们中间，毫无疑问的是她允许我们贬低恐吓，也会被我们推崇热爱，因为只有这样才能让她焕发生命力，确保独立。

应该如何阅读

首先，我想强调一下题目中的问题。即使我能回答这个问题，答案也是针对我而不是你。能给予他人的读书建议就是不要采纳任何建议，听从自己的直觉，运用自己的判断力，得出自己的结论。如果我们就此达成一致，我才能随心所欲提出一些观点和想法，因为你不会盲从或是束缚自己的独立思想。而独立思想对读者来说是最重要的品质。毕竟有什么条例可以规范书籍呢？滑铁卢战役的发生日期是可以确定的一天；但是作为一出戏剧，《哈姆莱特》好过《李尔王》吗？没有人可以下这样的结论。人人都必须自己回答这个问题。把穿着华贵毛皮外套和长袍的权威请到图书馆，让他们告诉我们如何阅读，阅读什么，如何评价我们所阅读的内容，就是在破坏自由精神，即这些圣洁场所的活力所在。在其他任何地方我们可能会被法律法规所限制—但在图书馆我们没有任何规定。

如果容许我老生常谈，我会说为了享受自由，我们当然不得不约束自己。我们不能无可奈何又不知不觉地滥用权力，就像不能喷湿了半个房子只为了浇灌一丛玫瑰花。我们必须在这个地方准确有力地训练权力。这应该是我们在图书馆首先遇到的难题之一。“这个地方”是哪里？令人充满了困惑。诗歌和小说，历史和回忆，字典和蓝皮书，这些书的作者是使用不同语言的男男女女，他们性格不同，种族不同，年龄不同。但是所有书都在书架上挤成一团。外面有阵阵驴叫，女人们在抽水机旁叽叽喳喳，小马驹在田野上飞驰而过。我们该从何开始？我们如何在众多繁杂混乱中建立秩序？如何从我们的阅读中获得最有深度、最广泛的快乐呢？

简单地说因为书可以按种类划分—小说、传记、诗歌—我们应该就此进行区分，以便可以分门别类获取它能给予我们的正确的东西。然而没有人会问书能给予我们什么。我们对于书总是迷迷糊糊懵懵懂懂，觉得小说真实，诗歌虚伪，传记阿谀谄媚，而历史书总是加深我们的偏见。如果我们能在阅读时消除这样的成见，那将会是一个美妙的开始。不要指挥作者，试着变成他们，或成为他的同事和伙伴。如果你开始犹豫畏缩，发表批评，你就失去了从阅读中获取可能最完整价值的机会。但是如果你尽可能地敞开心胸，首句的起承转合里那些几乎无法察觉的敏锐的标志和线索，会让你变得与众不同。沉浸其中，熟悉这些，很快你会发现作者在告诉你，或者正试图告诉你一些更确定的事情。一部小说里的三十章节—如果我们先考虑如何阅读一本小说—试图形成一些东西，这些东西像建筑一样被组合和限定，但是词语比砖块更为玄妙，阅读比观看的过程更为漫长，更为复杂。理解小说家工作要素的最快方法也许不是阅读，而是写作；自己做实验，了解运用词语的危险和困难。然后回想出一些给你留下深远印象的事情—可能在某个街角，你如何经过正在聊天的两个人。树枝轻摇，灯影晃动，步伐轻快，却也悲伤；整个场景，全部的概念，似乎都包含在那么一个瞬间。

但是当你试图用词语重建，会发现这个场景破碎成无数片相互矛盾的印象。一些含蓄温和，一些突出强调，在这个过程中你必须舍弃一些，可能是全部，去攫取感情本身。然后从自己含糊分散的书转向一些优秀小说家的率直的作品中—笛福、简·奥斯汀、哈代。现在你就会更好地欣赏他们的写作技巧。我们不只在别人面前—笛福、简·奥斯汀或托马斯·哈代—我们还生活在另一个世界。在《鲁宾逊漂流记》中，我们在平坦大路上跋涉，事情接踵而来，事实和其顺序令人应接不暇。但是如果户外和冒险对笛福很重要的话，它们对简·奥斯汀毫无价值。对她来说重要的是在会客厅里，人们谈天说地，他们的对话如镜子一般反映出各自的性格。当我们适应了会客厅和人们的反映，转头回去看哈代，就会立刻变得头晕目眩。周围是荒凉的原野，星星在头顶上闪闪发光。思想的另一面暴露出来—在孤独中浮现出的黑暗面，而不是在人群中表现出的阳光面。我们和其他人没有关系，而是和自然命运相关。然而尽管这些世界个个不同，每一个都坚持自我。每一个世界的创造者都从自己的角度仔细观察规律，不管他们对我们施加多大的压力，也不会像二流作家经常做的那样，在同一本书中引出两个不同类型的现实，让我们感到混乱。因此从一位杰出的小说家到另一位—从简·奥斯汀到哈代，从皮科尔到特洛勒普，从斯科特到米勒迪斯—不仅是断绝和背离，还陷入各式各样的困惑。阅读小说是困难复杂的艺术，你必须既有强烈的感受力，还有大胆的想象力，如果你要充分利用小说家—伟大的艺术家—所给予你的东西。

书架上的书种类繁多，稍微瞥一眼就知道没有几位“伟大的艺术家”；甚至书也根本不是艺术作品。比如，这些传记和自传，描述与世长辞并被人遗忘的伟大人物的生平，放在小说和诗歌的旁边，我们能因为他们不是“艺术”就不去读吗？或者我们可以用别的方式，抱着别的目的去读吗？有时在晚上，我们徘徊在房门前，那里灯火通明，窗帘紧闭，每一扇房门都向我们展示了人生的不同阶段，我们应该先为了满足心中的好奇去阅读吗？然后我们内心充满了对这些人生活的好奇—窃窃私语的仆侍、用餐的绅士、盛装打扮赶赴聚会的女孩，在窗边织个不停的老妇人。他们是谁，他们做什么，他们的名字、工作、想法和经历是什么？

传记和自传会回答这样的问题，点亮无数这样的房屋；他们向我们展示人们的日常生活，有辛苦，有失败，有成功，有吃喝，有爱有恨，直到死亡。有时我们看着，房屋渐渐消失，铁栅栏突然不见，我们变得一片茫然；我们打猎，航海，战斗；我们周围都是野蛮人和战士；我们参加伟大的游行。或者如果我们喜欢待在英国，就在伦敦这儿，场景还是会不断变化：街道变得狭窄；房屋变小，变窄，镶满了钻石却散发着臭气。我们看到一位诗人，多恩，从这样一栋房屋里被赶出来，墙壁太薄，孩子们的哭声穿过墙壁传了出来。我们跟着他穿过书页中的小径，到了特威克纳姆；到了贝德福夫人公园，那里是著名的贵族和诗人的汇集之处；然后我们移步到威尔顿，丘陵地下方的大房子，听西德尼为他的姐姐阅读《阿卡狄亚》；在沼泽附近徘徊，在那著名的浪漫之地欣赏苍鹭的英姿；然后偕同彭布鲁克夫人和安妮·克利福德，再次向北行，到达荒凉的野地，或繁华的城市，当看到加布里奥·哈维穿着黑色的天鹅绒套装和斯宾塞讨论诗歌时，克制我们的欢笑。没什么比在伊丽莎白时期伦敦的黑暗和光彩的交替中摸索探寻更为刺激。但是我们没有停留在那里。坦普尔一家和斯威夫特一家，哈利一家和圣约翰一家都在召唤。我们花了好长时间才从他们的争吵中解脱出来，从而解读他们的性格。当我们厌倦了这些，可以继续漫步，路过一位佩戴钻石的黑衣女士，去找塞缪尔·约翰逊和高登·斯密以及加里克；如果我们愿意，可以穿过海峡，去见伏尔泰、狄德罗和杜·德芳侯爵夫人；然后回到英国特威克纳姆—此地的一处公园曾归贝德福夫人所有，之后成为教皇的住所。然后去草莓山，到沃尔波府上拜访。但是沃尔波把好多新朋友介绍给我们，那里有太多的房屋可供参观，太多门铃要敲响，我们可能要好好地在贝利小姐的门阶等上一会儿，比如，当萨克雷到来的时候；他是沃尔波喜欢的女人的朋友。所以只是朋友到朋友，花园到花园，房屋到房屋的走访，我们就从英国文学的一端到另一端，突然发现自己现在在此，如果我们能够区分此刻和之前过去的那些片段。那么，这就是我们可以阅读这些生活和信件的一个方法；我们可以让他们点亮过去的窗户；我们可以从熟悉的住所和爱好观察故去的名人，有时我们离得非常近，会因为他们的秘密感到惊讶，有时我们拿出他们写过的一部戏剧或一首诗，看看它们是否和现在不同。但是这又引起了新的问题。我们必须自问，作者的生活到底能对他的书产生多大的影响呢？透过书中人物如何解读作家比较安全呢？我们应该如何坚持或放弃书中人物引起的同情和厌恶（词语如此敏感，作者的性格感受力如此强烈）？这些是阅读生活和信件时困扰我们的问题，我们必须问自己，因为没什么比被他人的偏好引导更糟糕了。

但是我们也可以带着其他目的阅读这样的书，不为了阐明文学，也不为了结识名人，只是为了恢复和运用我们的创造力。书架右手边没有打开的窗户吗？暂停阅读看看窗外的风景让人多么愉快！风景的无意识、疏离、永恒的运动—小马驹在原野上飞驰而过，妇人从井里提上满满一桶水，驴子摇头晃脑，发出悠长尖锐的声音—这一切多么鼓舞人心！图书馆更大的作用不是别的，正是这些对于男人、女人和驴子生命里转瞬即逝时刻的记录。每一段文学，随着慢慢变老，积攒了无数的废纸；这些废纸上记录着不复存在的瞬间和被人遗忘的生活，用一种已经消失的结巴微弱的口音讲述着。但是如果去阅读这些所谓的废纸，你会十分惊喜，可以说会被那些曾被遗弃而变得腐朽的人类生活遗迹所征服。可能是一封信—但是它展现了多么完整的画面！可能是几句话—但是它们暗示了多么美妙的景致！有时一个完整的故事和蕴含其中的美妙的幽默、哀伤完整结合在一起，就像一位伟大的小说家在工作，但它不过是一位老演员，泰特·威尔金森，想起了琼斯船长的诡异故事；不过是阿瑟·威尔斯利手下工作的年轻中尉，他爱上了里斯本的一个可爱女孩；不过是玛利亚·艾伦，她把针线活儿丢在了无人的客厅，自怨自艾，真希望她自己当时听从伯尼大夫的好建议，没有和她的利时私奔。这一切毫无价值，极其微不足道；然而当小马驹在原野上飞驰而过，妇人从井里提上满满一桶水，驴子高声大叫的时候，经常穿过废纸堆，在浩繁的过去中重新找到曾经被掩埋的指环、剪刀和撞坏的锥子，将它们缝到一起是多么有趣的事情啊！

但是我们终究还是厌倦了毫无意义的阅读。我们厌倦了不断寻找，以便能够使威尔金森、邦波利和玛利亚·艾伦写出的半成品变得完整真实。他们没有艺术家的控制力和取舍力。他们甚至无法讲述关于他们自己生活的真实；他们将原本可能非常美好的故事扭曲变形。他们能提供给我们的只有事实，但是事实只是小说非常低级的形式。因此我们心中产生了一个想法，希望能够去处理应对那些半真半假和似是而非；不用再去找出人类性格的细微形状，反而去享受更复杂的抽象，对于小说来说更纯粹的真实。因此我们创造出一种形式，集中概括，不拘泥于细节，但是在一些有规律反复出现的节拍上加重，这种形式一般被称为诗歌；当我们差不多可以写诗时，就是我们该读诗的时候了。

西风啊，你什么时候开始吹，

绵绵的细雨什么时候降下来？

啊，但愿我的爱人在我怀里，

让我们同床共枕重相爱！

诗歌的影响如此强烈直接，以至于现在除了诗本身之外，其他感觉都不存在。那么我们要探访多深—我们的沉溺是那么的突然和完全！没有什么可以被掌握，飞行中没有什么可以支撑我们。小说的幻想是逐步的，它的影响蓄势待发；但是当他们读这四行诗时，谁会问这诗是谁写的，或是脑海中浮现出道恩的房子或西德尼的秘书；或把他们和过去的复杂以及世代更替纠缠在一起？诗人总是我们同时代的人。我们此刻的存在既得到重视也得到压抑，正如个人情感的任何一次剧烈波动。然后，感观也的确开始大面积占领我们的思想，我们感受了更遥远的感觉，它们开始发声说话，我们听到了回音和反响。诗歌的集中性覆盖的情感范围很大。我们不得不去进行比较，欣赏这几句诗的力量和坦率：

我应该像树一样倒下，找到我的坟墓，

心中满是悲伤。

这几句诗的婉转：

时光如沙，分分秒秒在沙漏中溜走，

我们虚掷光阴，不知不觉迈向死亡，却无能为力；

恣意纵情的时刻总是在遗憾中结束，回归平静；

但是生活，已经厌倦了动荡，数着滑落的每一粒沙，

自怨自艾，直到最后的时刻来临，

草草了事，郁郁而终。

或是感受一下这几句诗的冷静理智：

不论年轻或年老，

我们的命运，我们的心和归属，

不受限制，就在那里，

只要有希望，只要希望不灭，

所有的努力，期待和心愿，

努力永远都会无限存在。

还有这几句诗的无与伦比的美感：

月亮慢慢升上天空，

一刻不停，

她轻轻地，轻轻地，变得越来越高，

周围闪烁着一两颗星—

或是这几句诗的自由奔放的想象力：

经常出没于森林，

他将会一直徘徊，

在那遥远的林中空地，

即使整个世界在燃烧，

火焰越来越高，

在他看来，

却像极了绽放中的报春花。

这让我们想起诗人的丰富多彩的艺术；他能让我们立刻成为演员和观众；他能亲手为人物注入活力，就好像一只手套，戴上就成了孚斯塔夫或李尔王；他能一直简化，夸大，或陈述事实。

“我们只能进行比较”—和那些已经公开的诗进行比较，阅读真正的复杂性得到了承认。第一阶段尽全力理解并获得印象，这只是整个阅读过程的一半而已；如果我们想从一本书中获得全部的快乐，我们需要完成另一半。我们要对众多印象进行评判；我们要为这些转瞬即逝的印象营造一个坚硬持久的形状。但是并不直接。等到阅读的尘埃落定，等到争执疑问渐渐消失，一边走一边聊，从玫瑰花上摘下枯萎的花瓣，或者沉入梦乡。然后突然地，不经我们命令，因为自然操作了这些转换，书回来了，变得有点不同。它会整个飘到思想的顶端。这本书被当作一个整体，不同于目前由一句句单独习语构成的书。现在细节都找到了合适的位置。我们看着那形状从开始到结束；可能是马厩，可能是猪圈，也可能是大教堂。现在我们能够像比较建筑那样比较书。但是这种比较的行为意味着我们的态度发生了变化；我们不再是作家的朋友，而是评审；正如作为朋友我们不能太过同情，作为评审我们也不能太过严厉。如果他们写出的书浪费我们的时间和同情，他们难道不是罪犯？如果他们写虚伪的充满腐朽堕落气息的书，他们难道不是全社会最狡猾的敌人，贪污腐败的人，亵渎神灵的人？那么让我们严格评判，让我们用每本书和同类最优秀的书作比较。他们萦绕在脑海中，读过的书因为我们下的评判而变得有形—《鲁宾逊漂流记》《爱玛》《野性的呼唤》。把小说和这些书作比较—当节奏不再令人陶醉，词语也不再绚丽多彩，幻想的形状就会出现，它应该和《李尔王》《菲德拉》《序曲》作比较；如果不和这些比较，也要和同类里最好的或者对我们来说最好的相比较。我们大概可以确定新诗和小说的新颖是它们最大的优势，我们只需要稍微修改一下，不必改写我们用以评判旧书的标准。

认为阅读的第二阶段，即评判和比较，和第一阶段一样简单—打开心胸，接受无数一转而过的印象—简直就是太愚蠢了。在你手头没有书的情况下也继续阅读，以一个幻影反对其他的幻影，广泛阅读，充分理解，进行生动富有启发性的比较—是非常困难的；“这本书既是这一类的，也是那一类的；这里失败了；那里成功了；这里不好；那里好。”说出这样的话更难。担负起读者这部分义务需要这样的想象力，洞察力，还要意识到有效接受任何想法都是非常难的；对最有自信的人来说，也不可能在自己身上发现更多这样的力量的根源。那么，放缓脚步阅读，让批评家，让图书馆里穿着华丽衣裳的权威人士为我们确定书籍的绝对价值吗？多么不可思议！我们可以强调同情的重要；阅读时我们可以试着忘记自我。但是我们知道我们不能完全地同情或者完全地投入；我们心中总有一个声音，低声说：“我憎恶那个，我喜爱这个，”我们无法让声音安静下来。事实上，我们的确是既憎恶又喜爱，我们与诗人、小说家的关系如此密切以至于我们无法容忍其他人的存在。即使结果相悖判断失误，我们的品位，在体内传达阵阵战栗的感官神经也仍然是我们的主要光源。我们通过感觉学习，不彻彻底底地感觉我们就无法表达自己的特质。但随着时间流逝，也许我们可以培养我们的品位；也许我们可以让它符合一些限制。当它贪婪奢侈地从各种书中吸取养分—诗歌、小说、历史、传记—然后不再继续阅读，寻找不同种类中间的巨大差异，人世间的不和谐，我们会发现它正一点点开始变化；它不再那么贪婪，它的想法更加成熟。它将带给我们的不只是对于书的评判，它还要告诉我们特定的一类书所共有的性质。听，它会这样说，我们管这个叫什么？它可能会给我们读《李尔王》或是《阿伽门农》，用来引出提到的共性。因此，品位带领着我们，越过单独的一本书，去寻找一类书的共性；我们会给它们命名，然后制定规则，让我们的想法变得条条有理。我们将从这种差异中获得更深层次更珍贵的快乐。规则总是在和书籍的关联中被不断打破推翻—没有比在真空中制定脱离事实的规则更简单愚蠢的事情了—终于现在，为了让自己在这项艰难的尝试中心神安宁，我们可能要向那些极少的将文学作为一种艺术启发人们的作家求助。柯尔雷基、德莱顿和约翰逊，这些诗人和小说家深思熟虑的批评和不假思索的发言总是有着惊人的联系；有些模糊的想法在我们的脑海迷雾中蹒跚而行，他们让这些想法变得清晰坚定。但是如果我们带着许多问题和意见去找他们，他们只能帮助我们在阅读过程中真实地面对自己。如果我们像躲在篱笆下的绵羊一样，屈服于他们的权威，那么他们对我们其实无能为力。只有当我们自己和他们有了不同，并且战胜了他们，我们才能理解他们的做法。

如果是这样，如果阅读需要想象力、洞察力和判断力这些珍贵的品质，你可能会得出这样的结论：文学是一种非常复杂的艺术，究其一生，我们可能也无法对文学批评作出任何贡献。我们只能做读者；我们无法得到那些少数能作出贡献的批评家能得到的荣誉。但是作为读者我们也有自己的责任和重要性。我们提出的标准和我们通过的评判不知不觉成为空气，成为作家工作时呼吸的一部分。即使这影响无法出版印刷，也仍然存在。如果这种影响被塑造成热情的、个人的、真诚的，可能在批评中止时产生巨大作用；接受审查的书籍就好像打靶场列队的动物，批评家只有一秒钟时间去装弹、瞄准、射击，如果他误把兔子当成老虎，把鹰当成家禽，或错过所有目标，把子弹浪费在远处田野上吃草的温顺奶牛身上，他们都会得到原谅。在出版社的枪林弹雨背后，作者感到有另外一种批评，人们因为喜欢阅读而去读书，阅读速度缓慢而且不太专业，心怀极大的同情和严厉的想法去评判，这样难道不能改进他的作品吗？如果通过我们的努力，书可能变得更强大、更丰富、更多元，那也是值得努力的。

然而谁会带着这个想法去阅读？是不是太理想了？难道没有我们实践的追求是因为它们本身就很好，从头到尾都很有乐趣吗？阅读不是其中之一吗？至少，有时我会幻想当世界末日来临，杰出的领袖、律师和政治家去领取他们的桂冠，并把他们的名字永久地刻在不朽的大理石上；上帝看到我们胳膊下夹着书向他走来，脸色平静，不无羡慕嫉妒之情，他会对天使彼得说：“看，这些人不需要回报。我们什么也给不了他们，因为他们喜欢阅读。”

Oxford Street Tide

Down in the docks one sees things in their crudity, their bulk, their enormity. Here in Oxford Street they have been refined and transformed. The huge barrels of damp tobacco have been rolled into innumerable neat cigarettes laid in silver paper. The corpulent bales of wool have been spun into thin vests and soft stockings. The grease of sheep's thick wool has become scented cream for delicate skins. And those who buy and those who sell have suffered the same city change. Tripping, mincing, in black coats, in satin dresses, the human form has adapted itself no less than the animal product. Instead of hauling and heaving, it deftly opens drawers, rolls out silk on counters, measures and snips with yard sticks and scissors.

Oxford Street, it goes without saying, is not London's most distinguished thoroughfare. Moralists have been known to point the finger of scorn at those who buy there, and they have the support of the dandies. Fashion has secret crannies off Hanover Square, round about Bond Street, to which it withdraws discreetly to perform its more sublime rites. In Oxford Street there are too many bargains, too many sales, too many goods marked down to one and eleven three that only last week cost two and six. The buying and selling is too blatant and raucous. But as one saunters towards the sunset and what with artificial light and mounds of silk and gleaming omnibuses, a perpetual sunset seems to brood over the Marble Arch the garishness and gaudiness of the great rolling ribbon of Oxford Street has its fascination. It is like the pebbly bed of a river whose stones are for ever washed by a bright stream. Everything glitters and twinkles. The first spring day brings out barrows frilled with tulips, violets, daffodils in brilliant layers. The frail vessels eddy vaguely across the stream of the traffic. At one corner seedy magicians are making slips of coloured paper expand in magic tumblers into bristling forests of splendidly tinted flora-a subaqueous flower garden. At another, tortoises repose on litters of grass. The slowest and most contemplative of creatures display their mild activities on a foot or two of pavement, jealously guarded from passing feet. One infers that the desire of man for the tortoise, like the desire of the moth for the star, is a constant element in human nature. Nevertheless, to see a woman stop and add a tortoise to her string of parcels is perhaps the rarest sight that human eyes can look upon.

Taking all this into account-the auctions, the barrows, the cheapness, the glitter-it cannot be said that the character of Oxford Street is refined. It is a breeding ground, a forcing house of sensation. The pavement seems to sprout horrid tragedies; the divorces of actresses, the suicides of millionaires occur here with a frequency that is unknown in the more austere pavements of the residential districts. News changes quicker than in any other part of London. The press of people passing seems to lick the ink off the placards and to consume more of them and to demand fresh supplies of later editions faster than elsewhere. The mind becomes a glutinous slab that takes impressions and Oxford Street rolls off upon it a perpetual ribbon of changing sights, sounds and movement. Parcels slap and hit; motor omnibuses graze the kerb; the blare of a whole brass band in full tongue dwindles to a thin reed of sound. Buses, vans, cars, barrows stream past like the fragments of a picture puzzle; a white arm rises; the puzzle runs thick, coagulates, stops; the white arm sinks, and away it streams again, streaked, twisted, higgledy-piggledy, in perpetual race and disorder. The puzzle never fits itself together, however long we look.

On the banks of this river of turning wheels our modern aristocrats have built palaces just as in ancient days the Dukes of Somerset and Northumberland, the Earls of Dorset and Salisbury lined the Strand with their stately mansions. The different houses of the great firms testify to the courage, initiative, the audacity of their creators much as the great houses of Cavendish and Percy testify to such qualities in some faraway shire. From the loins of our merchants will spring the Cavendishes and Percys of the future. Indeed, the great Lords of Oxford Street are as magnanimous as any Duke or Earl who scattered gold or doled out loaves to the poor at his gates. Only their largesse takes a different form. It takes the form of excitement, of display, of entertainment, of windows lit up by night, of banners flaunting by day. They give us the latest news for nothing. Music streams from their banqueting rooms free. You need not spend more than one and eleven three to enjoy all the shelter that high and airy halls provide; and the soft pile of carpets, and the luxury of lifts, and the glow of fabrics, and carpets and silver. Percy and Cavendish could give no more. These gifts of course have an object to entice the shilling and eleven pennies as freely from our pockets as possible; but the Percys and the Cavendishes were not munificent either without hope of some return, whether it was a dedication from a poet or a vote from a farmer. And both the old lords and the new added considerably to the decoration and entertainment of human life.

But it cannot be denied that these Oxford Street palaces are rather flimsy abodes-perhaps grounds rather than dwelling places. One is conscious that one is walking on a strip of wood laid upon steel girders, and that the outer wall, for all its florid stone ornamentation, is only thick enough to withstand the force of the wind. A vigorous prod with an umbrella point might well inflict irreparable damage upon the fabric. Many a country cottage built to house farmer or miller when Queen Elizabeth was on the throne will live to see these palaces fall into the dust. The old cottage walls, with their oak beams and their layers of honest brick soundly cemented together still put up a stout resistance to the drills and bores that attempt to introduce the modern blessing of electricity. But any day of the week one may sec Oxford Street vanishing at the tap of a workman's pick as he stands perilously balanced on a dusty pinnacle knocking down walls and facades as lightly as if they were made of yellow cardboard and sugar icing.

And again the moralists point the finger of scorn. For such thinness, such papery stone and powdery brick reflect, they say, the levity, the ostentation, the haste and irresponsibility of our age. Yet perhaps they are as much out in their scorn as we should be if we asked of the lily that it should be cast in bronze, or of the daisy that it should have petals of imperishable enamel. The charm of modern London is that it is not built to last; it is built to pass. Its glassiness, its transparency, its surging waves of coloured plaster give a different pleasure and achieve a different end from that which was desired and attempted by the old builders and their patrons, the nobility of England. Their pride required the illusion of permanence. Ours, on the contrary, seems to delight in proving that we can make stone and brick as transitory as our own desires. We do not build for our descendants, who may live up in the clouds or down in the earth, but for ourselves and our own needs. We knock down and rebuild as we expect to be knocked down and rebuilt. It is an impulse that makes for creation and fertility. Discovery is stimulated and invention on the alert.

The palaces of Oxford Street ignore what seemed good to the Greeks, to the Elizabethan, to the eighteenthcentury nobleman; they are overwhelmingly conscious that unless they can devise an architecture that shows off the dressing-case, the Paris frock, the cheap stockings, and the jar of bath salts to perfection, their palaces, their mansions and motor-cars and the little villas out at Croydon and Surbiton where their shop assistants live, not so badly after all, with a gramophone and wireless, and money to spend at the movies-all this will be swept to ruin. Hence they stretch stone fantastically; crush together in one wild confusion the styles of Greece, Egypt, Italy, America; and boldly attempt an air of lavishness, opulence, in their effort to persuade the multitude that here unending beauty, ever fresh, ever new, very cheap and within the reach of everybody, bubbles up every day of the week from an inexhaustible well. The mere thought of age, of solidity, of lasting for ever is abhorrent to Oxford Street.

Therefore if the moralist chooses to take his afternoon walk along this particular thoroughfare, he must tune his strain so that it receives into it some queer, incongruous voices. Above the racket of van and omnibus we can hear them crying. God knows, says the man who sells tortoises, that my arm aches; my chance of selling a tortoise is small; but courage! there may come along a buyer; my bed tonight depends on it; so on I must go, as slowly as the police allow, wheeling tortoises down Oxford Street from dawn till dusk. True, says the great merchant, I am not thinking of educating the mass to a higher standard of æsthetic sensibility. It taxes all my wits to think how I can display my goods with the minimum of waste and the maximum of effectiveness. Green dragons on the top of Corinthian columns may help; let us try. I grant, says the middle-class woman, that I linger and look and barter and cheapen and turn over basket after basket of remnants hour by hour. My eyes glisten unseemily I know, and I grab and pounce with disgusting greed. But my husband is a small clerk in a bank; I have only fifteen pounds a year to dress on; so here I come, to linger and loiter and look, if I can, as well dressed as my neighbours. I am a thief, says a woman of that persuasion, and a lady of easy virtue into the bargain. But it takes a good deal of pluck to snatch a bag from a counter when a customer is not looking; and it may contain only spectacles and old bus tickets after all. So here goes!

A thousand such voices are always crying aloud in Oxford Street. All are tense, all are real, all are urged out of their speakers by the pressure of making a living, finding a bed, somehow keeping afloat on the bounding, careless, remorseless tide of the street. And even a moralist, who is, one must suppose, since he can spend the afternoon dreaming, a man with a balance in the bank-even a moralist must allow that this gaudy, bustling, vulgar street reminds us that life is a struggle; that all building is perishable; that all display is vanity; from which we may conclude-but until some adroit shopkeeper has caught on to the idea and opened cells for solitary thinkers hung with green plush and provided with automatic glowworms and a sprinkling of genuine death's-head moths to induce thought and reflection, it is vain to try to come to a conclusion in Oxford Street.

How It Strikes a Contemporary

In the first place a contemporary can scarcely fail to be struck by the fact that two critics at the same table at the same moment will pronounce completely different opinions about the same book. Here, on the right, it is declared a masterpiece of English prose; on the left, simultaneously, a mere mass of waste-paper which, if the fire could survive it, should be thrown upon the flames. Yet both critics are in agreement about Milton and about Keats. They display an exquisite sensibility and have undoubtedly a genuine enthusiasm. It is only when they discuss the work of contemporary writers that they inevitably come to blows. The book in question, which is at once a lasting contribution to English literature and a mere farrago of pretentious mediocrity, was published about two months ago. That is the explanation; that is why they differ.

The explanation is a strange one. It is equally disconcerting to the reader who wishes to take his bearings in the chaos of contemporary literature and to the writer who has a natural desire to know whether his own work, produced with infinite pains and in almost utter darkness, is likely to burn for ever among the fixed luminaries of English letters or, on the contrary, to put out the fire. But if we identify ourselves with the reader and explore his dilemma first, our bewilderment is short-lived enough. The same thing has happened so often before. We have heard the doctors disagreeing about the new and agreeing about the old twice a year on the average, in spring and autumn, ever since Robert Elsmere, or was it Stephen Phillips, somehow pervaded the atmosphere, and there was the same disagreement among grown-up people about these books too. It would be much more marvellous, and indeed much more upsetting, if, for a wonder, both gentlemen agreed, pronounced Blank's book an undoubted masterpiece, and thus faced us with the necessity of deciding whether we should back their judgement to the extent of ten and sixpence. Both are critics of reputation; the opinions tumbled out so spontaneously here will be starched and stiffened into columns of sober prose which will uphold the dignity of letters in England and America.

It must be some innate cynicism, then, some ungenerous distrust of contemporary genius, which determines us automatically as the talk goes on that, were they to agree-which they show no signs of doing-half a guinea is altogether too large a sum to squander upon contemporary enthusiasms, and the case will be met quite adequately by a card to the library. Still the question remains, and let us put it boldly to the critics themselves. Is there no guidance nowadays for a reader who yields to none in reverence for the dead, but is tormented by the suspicion that reverence for the dead is vitally connected with understanding of the living? After a rapid survey both critics are agreed that there is unfortunately no such person. For what is their own judgement worth where new books are concerned? Certainly not ten and sixpence. And from the stores of their experience they proceed to bring forth terrible examples of past blunders; crimes of criticism which, if they had been committed against the dead and not against the living, would have lost them their jobs and imperilled their reputations. The only advice they can offer is to respect one's own instincts, to follow them fearlessly and, rather than submit them to the control of any critic or reviewer alive, to check them by reading and reading again the masterpieces of the past.

Thanking them humbly, we cannot help reflecting that it was not always so. Once upon a time, we must believe, there was a rule, a discipline, which controlled the great republic of readers in a way which is now unknown. That is not to say that the great critic-the Dryden, the Johnson, the Coleridge, the Arnold was an impeccable judge of contemporary work, whose verdicts stamped the book indelibly and saved the reader the trouble of reckoning the value for himself. The mistakes of these great men about their own contemporaries are too notorious to be worth recording. But the mere fact of their existence had a centralizing influence. That alone, it is not fantastic to suppose, would have controlled the disagreements of the dinner-table and given to random chatter about some book just out an authority now entirely to seek. The diverse schools would have debated as hotly as ever, but at the back of every reader's mind would have been the consciousness that there was at least one man who kept the main principles of literature closely in view: who, if you had taken to him some eccentricity of the moment, would have brought it into touch with permanence and tethered it by his own authority in the contrary blasts of praise and blame. But when it comes to the making of a critic, nature must be generous and society ripe. The scattered dinner-tables of the modem world, the chase and eddy of the various currents which compose the society of our time, could only be dominated by a giant of fabulous dimensions. And where is even the very tall man whom we have the right to expect? Reviewers we have but no critic; a million competent and incorruptible policemen but no judge. Men of taste and learning and ability are for ever lecturing the young and celebrating the dead. But the too frequent result of their able and industrious pens is a desiccation of the living tissues of literature into a network of little bones. Nowhere shall we find the downright vigour of a Dryden, or Keats with his fine and natural bearing, his profound insight and sanity, or Flaubert and the tremendous power of his fanaticism, or Coleridge, above all, brewing in his head the whole of poetry and letting issue now and then one of those profound general statements which are caught up by the mind when hot with the friction of reading as if they were of the soul of the book itself.

And to all this, too, the critics generously agree. A great critic, they say, is the rarest of beings. But should one miraculously appear, how should we maintain him, on what should we feed him? Great critics, if they are not themselves great poets, are bred from the profusion of the age. There is some great man to be vindicated, some school to be founded or destroyed. But our age is meagre to the verge of destitution. There is no name which dominates the rest. There is no master in whose workshop the young are proud to serve apprenticeship. Mr Hardy has long since withdrawn from the arena, and there is something exotic about the genius of Mr Conrad which makes him not so much an influence as an idol, honoured and admired, but aloof and apart. As for the rest, though they are many and vigorous and in the full flood of creative activity, there is none whose influence can seriously affect his contemporaries, or penetrate beyond our day to that not very distant future which it pleases us to call immortality. If we make a century our test, and ask how much of the work produced in these days in England will be in existence then, we shall have to answer not merely that we cannot agree upon the same book, but that we are more than doubtful whether such a book there is. It is an age of fragments. A few stanzas, a few pages, a chapter here and there, the beginning of this novel, the end of that, are equal to the best of any age or author. But can we go to posterity with a sheaf of loose pages, or ask the readers of those days, with the whole of literature before them, to sift our enormous rubbish heaps for our tiny pearls? Such are the questions which the critics might lawfully put to their companions at table, the novelists and poets.

At first the weight of pessimism seems sufficient to bear down all opposition. Yes, it is a lean age, we repeat, with much to justify its poverty; but, frankly, if we pit one century against another the comparison seems overwhelmingly against us. Waverley, The Excursion, Kubla Khan, Don Juan, Hazlitt's Essays, Pride and Prejudice, Hyperion, and Prometheus Unbound were all published between 1800 and 1821. Our century has not lacked industry; but if we ask for masterpieces it appears on the face of it that the pessimists are right. It seems as if an age of genius must be succeeded by an age of endeavour; riot and extravagance by cleanliness and hard work. All honour, of course, to those who have sacrificed their immortality to set the house in order. But if we ask for masterpieces, where are we to look? A little poetry, we may feel sure, will survive; a few poems by Mr Yeats, by Mr Davies, by Mr de la Mare. Mr Lawrence, of course, has moments of greatness, but hours of something very different. Mr Beerbohm, in his way, is perfect, but it is not a big way. Passages in Far Away and Long Ago will undoubtedly go to posterity entire. Ulysses was a memorable catastrophe-immense in daring, terrific in disaster. And so, picking and choosing, we select now this, now that, hold it up for display, hear it defended or derided, and finally have to meet the objection that even so we are only agreeing with the critics that it is an age incapable of sustained effort, littered with fragments, and not seriously to be compared with the age that went before.

But it is just when opinions universally prevail and we have added lip service to their authority that we become sometimes most keenly conscious that we do not believe a word that we are saying. It is a barren and exhausted age, we repeat; we must look back with envy to the past. Meanwhile it is one of the first fine days of spring. Life is not altogether lacking in colour. The telephone, which interrupts the most serious conversations and cuts short the most weighty observations, has a romance of its own. And the random talk of people who have no chance of immortality and thus can speak their minds out has a setting, often, of lights, streets, houses, human beings, beautiful or grotesque, which will weave itself into the moment for ever. But this is life; the talk is about literature. We must try to disentangle the two, and justify the rash revolt of optimism against the superior plausibility, the finer distinction, of pessimism.

Our optimism, then, is largely instinctive. It springs from the fine day and the wine and the talk; it springs from the fact that when life throws up such treasures daily, daily suggests more than the most voluble can express, much though we admire the dead, we prefer life as it is. There is something about the present which we would not exchange, though we were offered a choice of all past ages to live in. And modern literature, with all its imperfections, has the same hold on us and the same fascination. It is like a relation whom we snub and scarify daily, but, after all, cannot do without. It has the same endearing quality of being that which we are, that which we have made, that in which we live, instead of being something, however august, alien to ourselves and beheld from the outside. Nor has any generation more need than ours to cherish its contemporaries. We are sharply cut off from our predecessors. A shift in the scale-the sudden slip of masses held in position for ages-has shaken the fabric from top to bottom, alienated us from the past and made us perhaps too vividly conscious of the present. Every day we find ourselves doing, saying, or thinking things that would have been impossible to our fathers. And we feel the differences which have not been noted far more keenly than the resemblances which have been very perfectly expressed. New books lure us to read them partly in the hope that they will reflect this re-arrangement of our attitude these scenes, thoughts, and apparently fortuitous groupings of incongruous things which impinge upon us with so keen a sense of novelty-and, as literature does, give it back into our keeping, whole and comprehended. Here indeed there is every reason for optimism. No age can have been more rich than ours in writers determined to give expression to the differences which separate them from the past and not to the resemblances which connect them with it. It would be invidious to mention names, but the most casual reader dipping into poetry, into fiction, into biography can hardly fail to be impressed by the courage, the sincerity, in a word, by the widespread originality of our time. But our exhilaration is strangely curtailed. Book after book leaves us with the same sense of promise unachieved, of intellectual poverty, of brilliance which has been snatched from life but not transmuted into literature. Much of what is best in contemporary work has the appearance of being noted under pressure, taken down in a bleak shorthand which preserves with astonishing brilliance the movements and expressions of the figures as they pass across the screen. But the flash is soon over, and there remains with us a profound dissatisfaction. The irritation is as acute as the pleasure was intense.

After all, then, we are back at the beginning, vacillating from extreme to extreme, at one moment enthusiastic, at the next pessimistic, unable to come to any conclusion about our contemporaries. We have asked the critics to help us, but they have deprecated the task. Now, then, is the time to accept their advice and correct these extremes by consulting the masterpieces of the past. We feel ourselves indeed driven to them, impelled not by calm judgement but by some imperious need to anchor our instability upon their security. But, honestly, the shock of the comparison between past and present is at first disconcerting. Undoubtedly there is a dullness in great books. There is an unabashed tranquillity in page after page of Wordsworth and Scott and Miss Austen which is sedative to the verge of somnolence. Opportunities occur and they neglect them. Shades and subtleties accumulate and they ignore them. They seem deliberately to refuse to gratify those senses which are stimulated so briskly by the moderns; the senses of sight, of sound, of touch above all, the sense of the human being, his depth and the variety of his perceptions, his complexity, his confusion, his self, in short. There is little of all this in the works of Wordsworth and Scott and Jane Austen. From what, then, arises that sense of security which gradually, delightfully, and completely overcomes us? It is the power of their belief-their conviction, that imposes itself upon us. In Wordsworth, the philosophic poet, this is obvious enough. But it is equally true of the careless Scott, who scribbled masterpieces to build castles before breakfast, and of the modest maiden lady who wrote furtively and quietly simply to give pleasure. In both there is the same natural conviction that life is of a certain quality. They have their judgement of conduct. They know the relations of human beings towards each other and towards the universe. Neither of them probably has a word to say about the matter outright, but everything depends on it. Only believe, we find ourselves saying, and all the rest will come of itself. Only believe, to take a very simple instance which the recent publication of The Walsons brings to mind, that a nice girl will instinctively try to soothe the feelings of a boy who has been snubbed at a dance, and then, if you believe it implicitly and unquestioningly, you will not only make people a hundred years later feel the same thing, but you will make them feel it as literature. For certainty of that kind is the condition which makes it possible to write. To believe that your impressions hold good for others is to be released from the cramp and confinement of personality. It is to be free, as Scott was free, to explore with a vigour which still holds us spellbound the whole world of adventure and romance. It is also the first step in that mysterious process in which Jane Austen was so great an adept. The little grain of experience once selected, believed in, and set outside herself, could he put precisely in its place, and she was then free to make it, by a process which never yields its secrets to the analyst, into that complete statement which is literature.

So then our contemporaries afflict us because they have ceased to believe. The most sincere of them will only tell us what it is that happens to himself. They cannot make a world, because they are not free of other human beings. They cannot tell stories because they do not believe that stories are true. They cannot generalise. They depend on their senses and emotions, whose testimony is trustworthy, rather than on their intellects whose message is obscure. And they have perforce to deny themselves the use of some of the most powerful and some of the most exquisite of the weapons of their craft. With the whole wealth of the English language at the back of them, they timidly pass about from hand to hand and book to book only the meanest copper coins. Set down at a fresh angle of the eternal prospect they can only whip out their notebooks and record with agonised intensity the flying gleams, which light on what? And the transitory splendours, which may, perhaps, compose nothing whatever. But here the critics interpose, and with some show of justice.

If this description holds good, they say, and is not, as it may well be, entirely dependent upon our position at the table and certain purely personal relationships to mustard pots and flower vases, then the risks of judging contemporary work are greater than ever before. There is every excuse for them if they are wide of the mark; and no doubt it would be better to retreat, as Matthew Arnold advised, from the burning ground of the present to the safe tranquillity of the past. 'We enter on burning ground,' wrote Matthew Arnold, 'as we approach the poetry of times so near to us, poetry like that of Byron, Shelley, and Wordsworth, of which the estimates are so often not only personal, but personal with passion,' and this, they remind us, was written in the year 1880. Beware, they say, of putting under the microscope one inch of a ribbon which runs many miles; things sort themselves out if you wait; moderation, and a study of the classics are to be recommended. Moreover, life is short; the Byron centenary is at hand; and the burning question of the moment is, did he, or did he not, marry his sister? To sum up, then-if indeed any conclusion is possible when everybody is talking at once and it is time to be going it seems that it would be wise for the writers of the present to renounce the hope of creating masterpieces, Their poems, plays, biographies, novels are not books but notebooks, and Time, like a good schoolmaster, will take them in his hands, point to their blots and scrawls and erasions, and tear them across; but he will not throw them into the waste-paper basket. He will keep them because other students will find them very useful. It is from the notebooks of the present that the masterpieces of the future are made. Literature, as the critics were saying just now, has lasted long, has undergone many changes, and it is only a short sight and a parochial mind that will exaggerate the importance of these squalls, however they may agitate the little boats now tossing out at sea. The storm and the drenching are on the surface; continuity and calm are in the depths.

As for the critics whose task it is to pass judgement upon the books of the moment, whose work, let us admit, is difficult, dangerous, and often distasteful, let us ask them to be generous of encouragement, but sparing of those wreaths and coronets which are so apt to get awry, and fade, and make the wearers, in six months time, look a little ridiculous. Let them take a wider, a less personal view of modern literature, and look indeed upon the writers as if they were engaged upon some vast building, which being built by common effort, the separate workmen may well remain anonymous. Let them slam the door upon the cosy company where sugar is cheap and butter plentiful, give over, for a time at least, the discussion of that fascinating topic-whether Byron married his sister and, withdrawing, perhaps, a handsbreadth from the table where we sit chattering, say something interesting about literature itself. Let us buttonhole them as they leave, and recall to their memory that gaunt aristocrat, Lady Hester Stanhope, who kept a milk-white horse in her stable in readiness for the Messiah and was for ever scanning the mountain tops, impatiently but with confidence, for signs of his approach, and ask them to follow her example; scan the horizon; see the past in relation to the future; and so prepare the way for masterpieces to come.

The Patron and the Crocus

Young men and women beginning to write are generally given the plausible but utterly impracticable advice to write what they have to write as shortly as possible, as clearly as possible, and without other thought in their minds except to say exactly what is in them. Nobody ever adds on these occasions the one thing needful: 'And be sure you choose your patron wisely', though that is the gist of the whole matter. For a book is always written for somebody to read, and, since the patron is not merely the paymaster, but also in a very subtle and insidious way the instigator and inspirer of what is written, it is of the utmost importance that he should be a desirable man.

But who, then, is the desirable man-the patron who will cajole the best out of the writer's brain and bring to birth the most varied and vigorous progeny of which he is capable? Different ages have answered the question differently. The Elizabethans, to speak roughly, chose the aristocracy to write for and the playhouse public. The eighteenth-century patron was a combination of coffee-house wit and Grub Street bookseller. In the nineteenth century the great writers wrote for the halfcrown magazines and the leisured classes. And looking back and applauding the splendid results of these different alliances, it all seems enviably simple, and plain as a pikestaff compared with our own predicament-for whom should we write? For the present supply of patrons is of unexampled and bewildering variety. There is the daily Press, the weekly Press, the monthly Press; the English public and the American public; the bestseller public and the worst-seller public; the high-brow public and the red-blood public; all now organized self-conscious entities capable through their various mouthpieces of making their needs known and their approval or displeasure felt. Thus the writer who has been moved by the sight of the first crocus in Kensington Gardens has, before he sets pen to paper, to choose from a crowd of competitors the particular patron who suits him best. It is futile to say, 'Dismiss them all; think only of your crocus', because writing is a method of communication; and the crocus is an imperfect crocus until it has been shared. The first man or the last may write for himself alone, but he is an exception and an unenviable one at that, and the gulls are welcome to his works if the gulls can read them.

Granted, then, that every writer has some public or other at the end of his pen, the high-minded will say that it should be a submissive public, accepting obediently whatever he likes to give it. Plausible as the theory stands, great risks are attached to it. For in that case the writer remains conscious of his public, yet is superior to it-an uncomfortable and unfortunate combination, as the works of Samuel Butler, George Meredith, and Henry James may be taken to prove. Each despised the public; each desired a public; each failed to attain a public; and each wreaked his failure upon the public by a succession, gradually increasing in intensity, of angularities, obscurities, and affectations which no writer whose patron was his equal and friend would have thought it necessary to inflict. Their crocuses, in consequence, are tortured plants, beautiful and bright, but with something wry-necked about them, malformed, shrivelled on the one side, overblown on the other. A touch of the sun would have done them a world of good. Shall we then rush to the opposite extreme and accept (if in fancy alone) the flattering proposals which the editors of The Times and the Daily News may be supposed to make us-'Twenty pounds down for your crocus in precisely fifteen hundred words, which shall blossom upon every breakfast table from John o' Groats to the Land's End before nine o'clock to-morrow morning with the writer's name attached'?

But will one crocus be enough, and must it not be a very brilliant yellow to shine so far, to cost so much, and to have one's name attached to it? The Press is undoubtedly a great multiplier of crocuses. But if we look at some of these plants, we shall find that they are only very distantly related to the original little yellow or purple flower which pokes up through the grass in Kensington Gardens early in March every year. The newspaper crocus is an amazing but still a very different plant. It fills precisely the space allotted to it. It radiates a golden glow. It is genial, affable, warm-hearted. It is beautifully finished, too, for let nobody think that the art of'our dramatic critic' of The Times or of Mr Lynd of the Daily News is an easy one. It is no despicable feat to start a million brains running at nine o'clock in the morning, to give two million eyes something bright and brisk and amusing to look at. But the night comes and these flowers fade. So little bits of glass lose their lustre if you take them out of the sea; great prima donnas howl like hyenas if you shut them up in telephone boxes; and the most brilliant of articles when removed from its element is dust and sand and the husks of straw. Journalism embalmed in a book is unreadable.

The patron we want, then, is one who will help us to preserve our flowers from decay. But as his qualities change from age to age, and it needs considerable integrity and conviction not to be dazzled by the pretensions or bamboozled by the persuasions of the competing crowd, this business of patron-finding is one of the tests and trials of authorship. To know whom to write for is to know how to write. Some of the modern patron's qualities are, however, fairly plain. The writer will require at this moment, it is obvious, a patron with the book-reading habit rather than the play-going habit. Nowadays, too, he must be instructed in the literature of other times and races. But there are other qualities which our special weaknesses and tendencies demand in him. There is the question of indecency, for instance, which plagues us and puzzles us much more than it did the Elizabethans. The twentieth-century patron must be immune from shock. He must distinguish infallibly between the little clod of manure which sticks to the crocus of necessity, and that which is plastered to it out of bravado. He must be a judge, too, of those social influences which inevitably play so large a part in modern literature, and able to say which matures and fortifies, which inhibits and makes sterile. Further, there is emotion for him to pronounce on, and in no department can he do more useful work than in bracing a writer against sentimentality on the one hand and a craven fear of expressing his feeling on the other. It is worse, he will say, and perhaps more common, to be afraid of feeling than to feel too much. He will add, perhaps, something about language, and point out how many words Shakespeare used and how much grammar Shakespeare violated, while we, though we keep our fingers so demurely to the black notes on the piano, have not appreciably improved upon Antony and Cleopatra. And if you can forget your sex altogether, he will say, so much the better; a writer has none. But all this is by the way-elementary and disputable. The patron's prime quality is something different, only to be expressed perhaps by the use of that convenient word which cloaks so much-atmosphere. It is necessary that the patron should shed and envelop the crocus in an atmosphere which makes it appear a plant of the very highest importance, so that to misrepresent it is the one outrage not to be forgiven this side of the grave. He must make us feel that a single crocus, if it be a real crocus, is enough for him; that he does not want to be lectured, elevated, instructed, or improved; that he is sorry that he bullied Carlyle into vociferation, Tennyson into idyllics, and Ruskin into insanity; that he is now ready to efface himself or assert himself as his writers require; that he is bound to them by a more than maternal tie; that they are twins indeed, one dying if the other dies, one flourishing if the other flourishes; that the fate of literature depends upon their happy alliance-all of which proves, as we began by saying, that the choice of a patron is of the highest importance. But how to choose rightly? How to write well? Those are the questions.

How Should One Read a Book?

In the first place, I want to emphasize the note of interrogation at the end of my title. Even if I could answer the question for myself, the answer would apply only to me and not to you. The only advice, indeed, that one person can give another about reading is to take no advice, to follow your own instincts, to use your own reason, to come to your own conclusions. If this is agreed between us, then I feel at liberty to put forward a few ideas and suggestions because you will not allow them to fetter that independence which is the most important quality that a reader can possess. After all, what laws can be laid down about books? The battle of Waterloo was certainly fought on a certain day; but is Hamlet a better play than Lear? Nobody can say. Each must decide that question for himself. To admit authorities, however heavily furred and gowned, into our libraries and let them tell us how to read, what to read, what value to place upon what we read, is to destroy the spirit of freedom which is the breath of those sanctuaries. Everywhere else we may be bound by laws and conventions-there we have none.

But to enjoy freedom, if the platitude is pardonable, we have of course to control ourselves. We must not squander our powers, helplessly and ignorantly, squirting half the house in order to water a single rose-bush; we must train them, exactly and powerfully, here on the very spot. This, it may be, is one of the first difficulties that faces us in a library. What is 'the very spot'? There may well seem to be nothing but a conglomeration and huddle of confusion. Poems and novels, histories and memories, dictionaries and blue-books; books written in all languages by men and women of all tempers, races, and ages jostle each other on the shelf. And outside the donkey brays, the women gossip at the pump, the colts gallop across the fields. Where are we to begin? How are we to bring order into this multitudinous chaos and so get the deepest and widest pleasure from what we read?

It is simple enough to say that since books have classes-fiction, biography, poetry-we should separate them and take from each what it is right that each should give us. Yet few people ask from books what books can give us. Most commonly we come to books with blurred and divided minds, asking of fiction that it shall be true, of poetry that it shall be false, of biography that it shall he flattering, of history that it shall enforce our own prejudices. If we could banish all such preconceptions when we read, that would be an admirable beginning. Do not dictate to your author; try to become him. Be his fellow-worker and accomplice. If you hang back, and reserve and criticize at first, you are preventing yourself from getting the fullest possible value from what you read. But if you open your mind as widely as possible, then signs and hints of almost imperceptible fineness, from the twist and turn of the first sentences, will bring you into the presence of a human being unlike any other. Steep yourself in this, acquaint yourself with this, and soon you will find that your author is giving you, or attempting to give you, something far more definite. The thirty chapters of a novel if we consider how to read a novel first are an attempt to make something as formed and controlled as a building: but words are more impalpable than bricks; reading is a longer and more complicated process than seeing. Perhaps the quickest way to understand the elements of what a novelist is doing is not to read, but to write; to make your own experiment with the dangers and difficulties of words. Recall, then, some event that has left a distinct impression on you-how at the corner of the street, perhaps, you passed two people talking. A tree shook; an electric light danced; the tone of the talk was comic, but also tragic; a whole vision, an entire conception, seemed contained in that moment.

But when you attempt to reconstruct it in words, you will find that it breaks into a thousand conflicting impressions. Some must be subdued; others emphasized; in the process you will lose, probably, all grasp upon the emotion itself. Then turn from your blurred and littered pages to the opening pages of some great novelist-Defoe, Jane Austen, Hardy. Now you will be better able to appreciate their mastery. It is not merely that we are in the presence of a different person-Defoe, Jane Austen, or Thomas Hardy-but that we are living in a different world. Here, in Robinson Crusoe, we are trudging a plain high road: one thing happens after another; the fact and the order of the fact is enough. But if the open air and adventure mean everything to Defoe they mean nothing to Jane Austen. Hers is the drawing-room, and people talking, and by the many mirrors of their talk revealing their characters. And if, when we have accustomed ourselves to the drawing-room and its reflections, we turn to Hardy, we are once more spun round. The moors are round us and the stars are above our heads. The other side of the mind is now exposed-the dark side that comes uppermost in solitude, not the light side that shows in company. Our relations are not towards people, but towards Nature and destiny. Yet different as these worlds are, each is consistent with itself. The maker of each is careful to observe the laws of his own perspective, and however great a strain they may put upon us they will never confuse us, as lesser writers so frequently do, by introducing two different kinds of reality into the same book Thus to go from one great novelist to another-from Jane Austen to Hardy, from Peacock to Trollope, from Scott to Meredith is to be wrenched and uprooted; to be thrown this way and then that. To read a novel is a difficult and complex art. You must be capable not only of great fineness of perception, but of great boldness of imagination if you are going to make use of all that the novelist-the great artist-gives you.

But a glance at the heterogeneous company on the shelf will show you that writers are very seldom 'great artists'; far more often a book makes no claim to be a work of art at all. These biographies and autobiographies, for example, lives of great men, of men long dead and forgotten, that stand check by jowl with the novels and poems, are we to refuse to read them because they are not 'art'? Or shall we read them, but read them in a different way, with a different aim? Shall we read them in the first place to satisfy that curiosity which possesses us sometimes when in the evening we linger in front of a house where the lights are lit and the blinds not yet drawn, and each floor of the house shows us a different section of human life in being? Then we are consumed with curiosity about the lives of these people-the servants gossiping, the gentlemen dining, the girl dressing for a party, the old woman at the window with her knitting. Who are they, what are they, what are their names, their occupations, theirthoughts, and adventures?

Biographies and memoirs answer such questions, light up innumerable such houses; they show us people going about their daily affairs, toiling, failing, succeeding, eating, hating, loving, until they die. And sometimes as we watch, the house fades and the iron railings vanish and we are out at sea; we are hunting, sailing, fighting; we are among savages and soldiers; we are taking part in great campaigns. Or if we like to stay here in England, in London, still the scene changes; the street narrows; the house becomes small, cramped, diamond-paned, and malodorous. We see a poet, Donne, driven from such a house because the walls were so thin that when the children cried their voices cut through them. We can follow him, through the paths that lie in the pages of books, to Twickenham; to Lady Bedford's Park, a famous meeting-ground for nobles and poets; and then turn our steps to Wilton, the great house under the downs, and hear Sidney read the Arcadia to his sister; and ramble among the very marshes and see the very herons that figure in that famous romance; and then again travel north with that other Lady Pembroke, Anne Clifford, to her wild moors, or plunge into the city and control our merriment at the sight of Gabriel Harvey in his black velvet suit arguing about poetry with Spenser. Nothing is more fascinating than to grope and stumble in the alternate darkness and splendour of Elizabethan London. But there is no staying there. The Temples and the Swifts, the Harleys and the St Johns beckon us on; hour upon hour can be spent disentangling their quarrels and deciphering their characters; and when we tire of them we can stroll on, past a lady in black wearing diamonds, to Samuel Johnson and Goldsmith and Garrick; or cross the channel, if we like, and meet Voltaire and Diderot, Madame du Deffand; and so back to England and Twickenham-how certain places repeat themselves and certain names!-where Lady Bedford had her Park once and Pope lived later, to Walpole's home at Strawberry Hill. But Walpole introduces us to such a swarm of new acquaintances, there are so many houses to visit and bells to ring that we may well hesitate for a moment, on the Miss Berrys' doorstep, for example, when behold, up comes Thackeray; he is the friend of the woman whom Walpole loved; so that merely by going from friend to friend, from garden to garden, from house to house, we have passed from one end of English literature to another and wake to find ourselves here again in the present, if we can so differentiate this moment from all that have gone before. This, then, is one of the ways in which we can read these lives and letters; we can make them light up the many windows of the past; we can watch the famous dead in their familiar habits and fancy sometimes that we are very close and can surprise their secrets, and sometimes we may pull out a play or a poem that they have written and see whether it reads differently in the presence of the author. But this again rouses other questions. How far, we must ask ourselves, is a book influenced by its writer's life-how far is it safe to let the man interpret the writer? How far shall we resist or give way to the sympathies and antipathies that the man himself rouses in us-so sensitive are words, so receptive of the character of the author? These are questions that press upon us when we read lives and letters, and we must answer them for ourselves, for nothing can be more fatal than to be guided by the preferences of others in a matter so personal.

But also we can read such books with another aim, not to throw light on literature, not to become familiar with famous people, but to refresh and exercise our own creative powers. Is there not an open window on the right hand of the bookcase? How delightful to stop reading and look out! How stimulating the scene is, in its unconsciousness, its irrelevance, its perpetual movement-the colts galloping round the field, the woman filling her pail at the well, the donkey throwing back his head and emitting his long, acrid moan. The greater part of any library is nothing but the record of such fleeting moments in the lives of men, women, and donkeys. Every literature, as it grows old, has its rubbish-heap, its record of vanished moments and forgotten lives told in faltering and feeble accents that have perished. But if you give yourself up to the delight of rubbish-reading you will be surprised, indeed you will be overcome, by the relics of human life that have been cast out to moulder. It may be one letter-but what a vision it gives! It may be a few sentences but what vistas they suggest! Sometimes a whole story will come together with such beautiful humour and pathos and completeness that it seems as if a great novelist had been at work, yet it is only an old actor, Tate Wilkinson, remembering the strange story of Captain Jones; it is only a young subaltern serving under Arthur Wellesley and falling in love with a pretty girl at Lisbon; it is only Maria Allen letting fall her sewing in the empty drawing-room and sighing how she wishes she had taken Dr Burney's good advice and had never eloped with her Rishy. None of this has any value; it is negligible in the extreme; yet how absorbing it is now and again to go through the rubbishheaps and find rings and scissors and broken noses buried in the huge past and try to piece them together while the colt gallops round the field, the woman fills her pail at the well, and the donkey brays.

But we tire of rubbish-reading in the long run. We tire of searching for what is needed to complete the half-truth which is all that the Wilkinsons, the Bunburys and the Maria Aliens are able to offer us. They had not the artist's power of mastering and eliminating; they could not tell the whole truth even about their own lives; they have disfigured the story that might have been so shapely. Facts are all that they can offer us, and facts are a very inferior form of fiction. Thus the desire grows upon us to have done with half-statements and approximations; to cease from searching out the minute shades of human character, to enjoy the greater abstractness, the purer truth of fiction. Thus we create the mood, intense and generalized, unaware of detail, but stressed by some regular, recurrent beat, whose natural expression is poetry; and that is the time to read poetry when we are almost able to write it.

Western wind, when wilt thou blow?
The small rain down can rain.
Christ, if my love were in my arms,
And I in my bed again!

The impact of poetry is so hard and direct that for the moment there is no other sensation except that of the poem itself. What profound depths we visit then-how sudden and complete is our immersion! There is nothing here to catch hold of; nothing to stay us in our flight. The illusion of fiction is gradual; its effects are prepared; but who when they read these four lines stops to ask who wrote them, or conjures up the thought of Donne's house or Sidney's secretary; or enmeshes them in the intricacy of the past and the succession of generations? The poet is always our contemporary. Our being for the moment is centred and constricted, as in any violent shock of personal emotion. Afterwards, it is true, the sensation begins to spread in wider rings through our minds; remoter senses are reached; these begin to sound and to comment and we are aware of echoes and reflections. The intensity of poetry covers an immense range of emotion. We have only to compare the force and directness of

I shall fall like a tree, and find my grave,
Only remembering that I grieve.

with the wavering modulation of

Minutes are numbered by the fall of sands,
As by an hour glass; the span of time
Doth waste us to our graves, and we look on it;
An age of pleasure, revelled out, comes home
At last, and ends in sorrow; but the life,
Weary of riot, numbers every sand,
Wailing in sighs, until the last drop down,
So to conclude calamity in rest.

or place the meditative calm of

whether we be young or old,
Our destiny, our being's heart and home,
Is with infinitude, and only there;
With hope it is, hope that can never die,
Effort, and expectation, and desire,
And effort evermore about to be,

beside the complete and inexhaustible loveliness of

The moving Moon went up the sky,
And nowhere did abide:
Softly she was going up,
And a star or two beside-

or the splendid fantasy of

And the woodland haunter
Shall not cease to saunter
When, far down some glade,
Of the great world's burning,
One soft flame upturning
Seems, to his discerning,
Crocus in the shade,

to bethink us of the varied art of the poet; his power to make us at once actors and spectators; his power to run his hand into characters as if it were a glove, and be Falstaff or Lear; his power to condense, to widen, to state, once and for ever.

'We have only to compare'-with those words the cat is out of the bag, and the true complexity of reading is admitted. The first process, to receive impressions with the utmost understanding, is only half the process of reading; it must be completed, if we are to get the whole pleasure from a book, by another. We must pass judgment upon these multitudinous impressions; we must make of these fleeting shapes one that is hard and lasting. But not directly. Wait for the dust of reading to settle; for the conflict and the questioning to die down; walk, talk, pull the dead petals from a rose, or fall asleep. Then suddenly without our willing it, for it is thus that Nature undertakes these transitions, the book will return, but differently. It will float to the top of the mind as a whole. And the book as a whole is different from the book received currently in separate phrases. Details now fit themselves into their places. We see the shape from start to finish; it is a barn, a pig-sty, or a cathedral. Now then we can compare book with book as we compare building with building. But this act of comparison means that our attitude has changed; we are no longer the friends of the writer, but his judges; and just as we cannot be too sympathetic as friends, so as judges we cannot be too severe. Are they not criminals, books that have wasted our time and sympathy; are they not the most insidious enemies of society, corrupters, defilers, the writers of false books, faked books, books that fill the air with decay and disease? Let us then be severe in our judgments; let us compare each book with the greatest of its kind. There they hang in the mind the shapes of the books we have read solidified by the judgments we have passed on them-Robinson Crusoe, Emma, The Return of the Native. Compare the novels with these-even the latest and least of novels has a right to be judged with the best. And so with poetry when the intoxication of rhythm has died down and the splendour of words has faded, a visionary shape will return to us and this must be compared with Lear, with Phedre, with The Prelude; or if not with these, with whatever is the best or seems to us to be the best in its own kind. And we may be sure that the newness of new poetry and fiction is its most superficial quality and that we have only to alter slightly, not to recast, the standards by which we have judged the old.

It would be foolish, then, to pretend that the second part of reading, to judge, to compare, is as simple as the first-to open the mind wide to the fast flocking of innumerable impressions. To continue reading without the book before you, to hold one shadow-shape against another, to have read widely enough and with enough understanding to make such comparisons alive and illuminating that is difficult; it is still more difficult to press further and to say, 'Not only is the book of this sort, but it is of this value; here it fails; here it succeeds; this is bad; that is good'. To carry out this part of a reader's duty needs such imagination, insight, and learning that it is hard to conceive any one mind sufficiently endowed; impossible for the most self-confident to find more than the seeds of such powers in himself. Would it not be wiser, then, to remit this part of reading and to allow the critics, the gowned and furred authorities of the library, to decide the question of the book's absolute value for us? Yet how impossible! We may stress the value of sympathy; we may try to sink our own identity as we read. But we know that we cannot sympathize wholly or immerse ourselves wholly; there is always a demon in us who whispers, 'I hate, I love', and we cannot silence him. Indeed, it is precisely because we hate and we love that our relation with the poets and novelists is so intimate that we find the presence of another person intolerable. And even if the results are abhorrent and our judgments are wrong, still our taste, the nerve of sensation that sends shocks through us, is our chief illuminant; we learn through feeling; we cannot suppress our own idiosyncrasy without impoverishing it. But as time goes on perhaps we can train our taste; perhaps we can make it submit to some control. When it has fed greedily and lavishly upon books of all sorts-poetry, fiction, history, biography and has stopped reading and looked for long spaces upon the variety, the incongruity of the living world, we shall find that it is changing a little; it is not so greedy, it is more reflective. It will begin to bring us not merely judgments on particular books, but it will tell us that there is a quality common to certain books. Listen, it will say, what shall we call this? And it will read us perhaps Lear and then perhaps the Agamemnon in order to bring out that common quality. Thus, with our taste to guide us, we shall venture beyond the particular book in search of qualities that group books together; we shall give them names and thus frame a rule that brings order into our perceptions. We shall gain a further and a rarer pleasure from that discrimination. But as a rule only lives when it is perpetually broken by contact with the books themselves-nothing is easier and more stultifying than to make rules which exist out of touch with facts, in a vacuum now at last, in order to steady ourselves in this difficult attempt, it may be well to turn to the very rare writers who are able to enlighten us upon literature as an art. Coleridge and Dryden and Johnson, in their considered criticism, the poets and novelists themselves in their unconsidered sayings, are often surprisingly relevant; they light up and solidify the vague ideas that have been tumbling in the misty depths of our minds. But they are only able to help us if we come to them laden with questions and suggestions won honestly in the course of our own reading. They can do nothing for us if we herd ourselves under their authority and lie down like sheep in the shade of a hedge. We can only understand their ruling when it comes in conflict with our own and vanquishes it.

If this is so, if to read a book as it should be read calls for the rarest qualities of imagination, insight, and judgment, and you may perhaps conclude that literature is a very complex art and that it is unlikely that we shall be able, even after a lifetime of reading, to make any valuable contribution to its criticism. We must remain readers; we shall not put on the further glory that belongs to those rare beings who are also critics. But still we have our responsibilities as readers and even our importance. The standards we raise and the judgments we pass steal into the air and become part of the atmosphere which writers breathe as they work. An influence is created which tells upon them even if it never finds its way into print. And that influence, if it were well instructed, vigorous and individual and sincere, might be of great value now when criticism is necessarily in abeyance; when books pass in review like the procession of animals in a shooting gallery, and the critic has only one second in which to load and aim and shoot and may well be pardoned if he mistakes rabbits for tigers, eagles for barndoor fowls, or misses altogether and wastes his shot upon some peaceful cow grazing in a further field. If behind the erratic gunfire of the press the author felt that there was another kind of criticism, the opinion of people reading for the love of reading, slowly and unprofessionally, and judging with great sympathy and yet with great severity, might this not improve the quality of his work? And if by our means books were to become stronger, richer, and more varied, that would be an end worth reaching.

Yet who reads to bring about an end, however desirable? Are there not some pursuits that we practise because they are good in themselves, and some pleasures that are final? And is not this among them? I have sometimes dreamt, at least, that when the Day of Judgment dawns and the great conquerors and lawyers and statesmen come to receive their rewards-their crowns, their laurels, their names carved indelibly upon imperishable marble-the Almighty will turn to Peter and will say, not without a certain envy when He sees us coming with our books under our arms, 'Look, these need no reward. We have nothing to give them here. They have loved reading.'

译者导读

贾科莫·莱奥帕尔迪（Giacomo Leopardi，1798—1837）是意大利著名的悲观主义诗人和哲学家，被誉为“继彼得拉克之后最伟大的抒情诗人”。他在短暂的一生创作了很多诗歌和散文。其中，诗歌《致意大利》《但丁纪念碑》《致席尔维娅》《无限》等均为传世之作。散文有《道德小品集》《杂记》等。这些散文往往借用具有象征意义的历史人物或虚构人物，来阐发哲学观点。《时尚与死亡的对话》是其中杰出的代表作之一。

《时尚与死亡的对话》实为一部有关哲学思考的对话录。莱奥帕尔迪采用了十一则对话的方式，就人类的永恒话题如死亡、人性、幸福、自然等方面，进行了哲学剖析和冥想。根据记载，莱奥帕尔迪自小体弱多病，因此，他对痛苦的感知似乎要比普通人更为强烈，也更为持久。来自疾病的折磨如影随形，使他无处遁形，也无从解脱。死神似乎随时都会前来叩击门环。他总是一次又一次如此近距离地接触死亡这个终极的归宿，但又极为侥幸地多次逃脱。在反反复复的较量中，宿敌竟然演变为最熟悉的人之一。

书中直接涉及死亡对话一共有两则。第一则对话发生于时尚与死亡之间。莱奥帕尔迪用谈笑的口吻，辛辣而又深刻地揭示了时尚之于人类健康的损害，而人类仍不顾生命安危、乐此不疲地追求时尚的矛盾行为，反映了人类思维中的非理性和盲目性的这一可悲可叹的致命弱点。在另一则死亡对话中，他想象木乃伊们暂时复活，以便向他们请教濒死时的体验。他从人在生理上对疼痛的正常感知入手，通过抽丝剥茧般的层层推理，分析并还原了濒死体验的真正可能性。同时，也嘲讽了人们一贯以来对死亡的极度恐惧和不实夸大。在莱奥帕尔迪看来，死亡的消耗远远低于生命的消耗。

另一则颇有一番见地的话题是有关幸福的探讨，莱奥帕尔迪将悲观主义精神发挥到极致。他认为纵使走遍天涯海角，人类也不可能找到真正的幸福。一个人无论做到怎样的无害、远离尘嚣、与世无争，幸福仍然遥不可及。自然赐予我们一切，却单单忘记了给予我们幸福感。人类具有欢笑的能力，却并不真正拥有快乐。反而，那些小鸟总是欢快地鸣叫，人类中只有儿童才能展现出如小鸟般的那种快乐情绪。回想生命中所经历的时段，似乎只有在清晨和青春时期才能够感受到片刻幸福，痛苦总是纷至沓来，让人无力挣扎，生命瞬间枯竭和凋零。

莱奥帕尔迪还用极为冷静、近乎残忍的方式揭示了人性中的恶。人类不仅相互倾轧，更有甚者，互相戕害，例如，父亲会杀死妻儿并烹饪其肉而食之，在原始社会中如此，在文明社会中亦是如此。父亲开枪自杀前先将自己的幼子杀死。这些都是在别的动物或物种中不曾发生过的恶劣行径。以上种种迹象表明，人类远非传统上认为那样，是最优秀的物种。莱奥帕尔迪对此传统观念深感怀疑并流露出极度不屑。人类可以是智力最高的物种，但绝对不是最高贵的物种。

本书余篇还探讨了有关自然的思考。即便是人类赖以生存的地球本身，也不过是茫茫宇宙中最微不足道的一员，是供神祇消遣的玩具，也是时时刻刻都会被外力摧毁的存在。因此，无论是地球还是其他生命体，都是永恒的时间长河中的区区一粒尘埃。

贯彻全书始末的是写实性的理性分析和严密的逻辑论证，笔锋犀利且不乏幽默，既有伤口撕裂时带来的痛楚，也有心智得以启迪时的一片明朗。总之，这是一本不得不读的好书。

海格立斯和阿特拉斯的对话

海格立斯　阿特拉斯（Atlas）前辈，朱庇特（Jove）派我前来向您问候。他说万一您厌倦了肩上的重担，就让我接替您几个小时，如同我上回所做的那样。不过因这期间时隔数个世纪，现今竟忘得干净。这样您就可以喘口气，休息一会儿了。

阿特拉斯　谢谢你，我的小海格立斯（Hercules），尤其感谢朱庇特陛下。好在地球已经变得很轻了，我甚至感到身上用来遮挡雨雪的斗篷越发沉重。倘若不是朱庇特命令我站在这里一动不动，以便使我背上的那个小球保持平衡，我早就把它挟在腋下，或装在口袋里，或让它悬挂在我的一根胡须上了。如此，我就可以去料理自己的事情了。

海格立斯　地球怎么会变轻呢？我倒是注意到它确实有所变化，其状如同面包卷，已不再似从前那般圆浑饱满。回想昔日，为了和阿耳戈（Argonauts）一道出海寻觅金羊毛，我还曾研修过宇宙学呢。纵使如此，我还是纳罕地球怎么会较之前轻了呢？

阿特拉斯　我也不甚明白个中原因，但是，倘若你把它放在手中掂量一二，就会知晓它有多轻！

海格立斯　上苍！若非亲自感受，确实令人难以置信。我到底是发现了什么新状况？记得上一次扛负它时，它在我的背上有力地跳动，宛如动物们跳动的心脏，并且发出阵阵如马蜂巢般的经久不息的嗡嗡声。可眼下，地球就像断了弹簧的手表般嘀嗒着，没有一丝声响。

阿特拉斯　对此我也无法作出解释。据我所知，在很早之前，地球就失去任何活动和声音的迹象了。故而，依我拙见，我严重怀疑它已经死了。每日，我都在担心会闻到它尸体上散发出的恶臭。于是，我思量着如何将它安葬，葬在何处，以及在它的坟头刻什么样的碑文，然而，后来，我看到地球并没有朽败掉，我又由此判断它已经从最初的动物状态变成某种植物了，正如达芙妮（Daphne）化作桂树，以及其他许多同类情况一样。这就是它不呼吸也不活动的原因吧。时至此刻，我都在担心它会随时在我的肩膀上生根发芽。

海格立斯　我倒还是宁愿相信它是睡着了。这种睡眠就如同埃庇米尼得斯（Epimenides）的睡眠一样，一觉就长达半个多世纪之久；也可能是像赫尔摩底谟（Hermotimus）式的睡眠。有传言说，他的灵魂常常随意游离于身体之外且多年不回归本体。他的灵魂在幸福地游历完各国之后，才会回家——直至他的朋友们焚毁了他的身体，这种荒唐才算结束。后来，当他的灵魂远游归来准备回家时，却发现他的家已经被烧掉了。试想他的灵魂若想安顿下来，就必须租用一具身体或借居在旅店之内。当然，为了保证地球不会永久长眠，或者保证它不会被某个误认为地球已死的朋友或好心人烧毁，我建议我们应当尽力唤醒地球。

阿特拉斯　很好。可怎么做呢？

海格立斯　我本来打算让它好好吃我一顿棍子，可又担心会把它彻底拍成煎饼。也许我应该像敲鸡蛋一样把它敲碎，毕竟它的壳掂上去分量很轻，因此也应该很薄才对。不过，我不敢确定的是，如果让一个习惯赤手空拳与狮子搏斗的人现在去跟跳蚤打架，他会不会因为这一击的失重而晕厥。看来最好的办法是，我扔掉球棒，你脱掉斗篷，接下来，我们就用这个小小的地球一起玩球。有些抱歉，我没有带来和墨丘利（Mercury）玩球时用的长手套和球拍，我和他总在朱庇特的房子里或后院里玩耍。不过，我们有拳头就足够了。

阿特拉斯　好主意！可万一被你父亲撞见，他也想加入我们的游戏并且把他的一个火球扔给我们，把我们绊倒——天知道何时何地会发生——让我们就像法厄同（Phaethon）一般一头栽进波河（the Po），那可怎么办？

海格立斯　不错。假如像法厄同一样，我只是一个诗人的儿子而不是他的儿子；假如没有这样的出身，我就不能如此妄为——诗人可以用里拉琴的琴声吸引城里挤满人群——而我则可以用球棒的砰砰声将天上和地上所有的人驱走。只轻轻一脚，我就可以把他的火球踢到天庭（the Empyrean）的最后一块天花板上。你不必担心。即便我突发奇想，想摘下五六颗星星来玩榛子游戏，或者用一颗彗星来练习打靶并抓住它的尾巴当秋千荡，甚至是拿太阳本身来玩掷铁饼游戏，我父亲也会假装视而不见的。再者，我们玩这个游戏的初衷是造福世界，自然有别于法厄同之流。他不过是为了在时间侍女们面前显示他的敏捷。侍女们在他登上车子后曾一度约束了他的步伐。他还妄图在安德洛墨达公主（Andromeda）和卡利斯托（Callisto）以及其他众多美丽群星面前赢得优秀御者的声誉。我们听说他在路过时，曾向她们撒下了不少光芒花束和光亮蜜饯球。事实上，他是为了在众神的舞会上显摆自己。如你所知，那天恰巧是个节日。因此，你大可安心，我父亲是不会发怒的。无论如何，我答应你我会赔偿你的损失。现在，我们开始吧。请你脱掉斗篷发球吧。

阿特拉斯　不管是否喜欢，我最好还是依你之言。你又强壮又有武器，而我呢，又老又没武器。不过，我们要小心别把它摔坏了。别再让它生出肿块、瘀青、裂缝，就像西西里岛从意大利、非洲从西班牙断裂出去那样，或者掀掉一小块——可能是个省也可能是个王国——由此极易触发战争。

海格立斯　别担心。

阿特拉斯　轮到你发球了。你难道不觉得它有些瘪，因为它已经变形了？

海格立斯　来吧，使点劲儿。你的球都没发到我这儿来。

阿特拉斯　不是发球的事儿。是风，这里的风总是从西南方向刮来，球被风带偏了——球太轻了。

海格立斯　又是老一套，总是随风追逐。

阿特拉斯　说实话，给它充点气也不是个坏主意。因为在击球时，它就像个没弹性的瓜。

海格立斯　又一个新缺点。在古时，它像一只山羊般能弹能跳。

阿特拉斯　快跑！快！快！我说，别让它掉了。该死的，怎么让它掉了？

海格立斯　你发给我的球太糟了，太低了。纵使我以折断脖子的速度奔跑也是接不住的。噢，可怜的家伙，你怎么样啦，是受伤了吗？我听不到一丝人类的呼吸声，看不到任何人在活动，他们仍然在沉睡吧。

阿特拉斯　还是把它还给我吧，看在冥河的份上，这样我就能重新把它放回到肩上了。你捡起你的球棒，赶紧回天庭吧。请为此代我向朱庇特道歉，尽管这都是你的错。

海格立斯　我马上照办。记得数百年前，有位名为贺拉斯（Horace）的诗人曾应邀到我父亲府上做客。他是由奥古斯都（Augustus）推荐来做宫廷诗人的。之前，考虑到罗马人的实力，朱庇特就让奥古斯都入了仙籍。这位诗人不停地吟诵他的诗词。其中在一首诗里，他写到即使世界坍塌，一个正义的人也不会动摇。我想现在世上所有的人都是正义的，你看，尽管世界坍塌了，却没有一个人动一动。

阿特拉斯　有谁会怀疑人的公正性？请不要浪费时间了。赶紧回你父亲那里为我洗刷罪名。我在担心随时随地都可能有霹雳打过来，把我从阿特拉斯变为埃特纳火山。

时尚和死亡的对话

时尚　死亡夫人，死亡夫人。

死亡　请你依序等待，届时无须召唤我也会来的。

时尚　死亡夫人。

死亡　见鬼。我会在你意料之外时找上门的。

时尚　仿佛我不是永生似的。

死亡　永生？

“自永生时代起，已经过去一千多年了。”

时尚　哦，连我们的死亡夫人也口吐彼特拉克（Petrarch）的诗句，似是一位十六世纪或说是十九世纪的意大利诗人。

死亡　我钟爱彼特拉克的诗文，因为诗里能找到我的胜利且几乎处处提及我的存在。不过，现在别来妨碍我。

时尚　好啦。以你对七宗罪的爱的名义，请先停一下，看看我。

死亡　我正在看着。

时尚　你难道看不出我是谁吗？

死亡　你应该晓得我的视力有些差。况且，我没法带眼镜儿，因为英国人没能造出一副合适我的眼镜儿。当然，即使他们造得出来，我也不知道怎么个戴法儿。

时尚　我是时尚呀，你的姊妹。

死亡　我的姊妹？

时尚　是啊。你不记得我们都是衰老（Caducity）的女儿了吗？

死亡　我怎么可能记得？我是记忆最大的敌人。

时尚　可我记得格外清楚。我记得我们两人一道不断地摧毁并改变下面尘世间的所有，尽管你我使用的方式不尽相同。

死亡　如果你不是在喃喃自语，或者是和你嗓子眼里的人说话，就请大声一点并注意你的措辞。如果你继续用你细若游丝的嗓音嘀嘀咕咕的话，我可听不见。因为你早该知道，我的听力不比视力好。

时尚　但是，这么做有失礼仪——在法国，人们可不是为了听见而说话的——既然我们是姐妹，也就不顾及这些繁文缛节了，我就如你所愿。我想说的是我们两个的本质和习惯就是去不断地革新世界。只不过从伊始，你就关注人与鲜血；而我则一般专注于胡子、头发、服饰、家具、建筑之类。诚然，我从未曾——今后也不会克制自己——不去玩那些和你一样的把戏，如穿耳洞、唇孔、鼻孔，我会在上面挂满能将其撕裂的小饰物；用火辣辣的烙印烧焦男人们的皮肤，我让他们做这些是出于美的缘故；用绷带或什么束带把婴儿的头部弄变形，让全国上下把拥有相同的头型变为一种习俗，我在美国和亚洲就是这么干的；穿紧憋的鞋子把人们弄瘸；或穿紧身胸衣导致其呼吸困难、眼睛外凸，以及其他上百种类似的法子。事实上，一般来说，我会劝导并迫使所有的文人雅士每天忍耐数千种艰难和数千种不适和伴随而来的常规性的疼痛和折磨，我甚至让一些人为了爱我的缘故而光荣死去。我不会告诉你为了追从我，有多少人患了头疼、感冒、各种炎症，以及一天一次、三天一次或四天一次的发烧；他们顺从我的意志，用羊毛护肩、布片遮胸，由此在寒风里冻得哆嗦或者在炎热里窒息。他们愿意按照我的意志去做任何事情，不管会对他们造成多大伤害。

死亡　这么说来，我相信你确实是我的姊妹。如你所愿，我会比相信死亡更加相信这个事实——你甚至不用拿出教区出生证来证明。如果这么一直不动的话，我可能会晕倒。以此，你若愿意和我并肩而奔，请不要抱怨我跑得太快。我们在奔跑的同时，还可以聊聊你的业务。抑或，考虑到我们的血缘关系，我承诺在我死后会把一切留给你。你可以带着我最美好的祝福待在你想待的地方。

时尚　假如我们一起参加帕里奥赛马，还不知道谁会跑赢呢。虽然你跑得快，可我却可以飞驰；你一旦在某个地方驻足就会晕倒，而我只不过是变得衰弱。因此，让我们再次开始奔跑吧。就像你说的，我们可以边跑边谈公务。

死亡　那我们继续。既然你也是我母亲生的孩子，你要帮我做一些杂事才好。

时尚　在过去，我做的这类杂事要比你想象的多得多。首先，尽管我屡屡消除和歪曲其他的习俗，但在任何一个地方，我从未曾允许过死亡习俗的停止。正因如此，你才可以看到在各地，从世界之初到如今，死亡一直在进行。

死亡　真是奇迹啊——你没有去尝试你力所不能及的事情。

时尚　什么叫力所不能及？你是什么意思？很明显，你似乎并不了解时尚的力量。

死亡　够了，够了！一旦有不死的习俗来临，我们总会有大把的时间讨论这一点。不过现在，我希望你能像个好姊妹一样帮帮我，协助我比之前更迅速更轻松地完成与不死习俗截然相反的目标。

时尚　我已经告诉过你我的部分作为，它们对你都是有极大助益的。不过，这些相较我现在要告诉你的事情就只是些琐屑了。以往，为了帮助你，我一步步地让人们忽视和放弃那些有益于身体的活动和运动，同时，我又引进了无数让人们趋之若鹜的各种损害身体和缩短寿命的法子。其次，我在这个世界里建立了这般的秩序和习俗：即生命本身，无论是肉体还是灵魂，都生不如死，以至于这个世纪可以被名副其实地冠以死亡世纪之称谓。在古代，你所拥有的财产不过是些水渠和山洞，别无他物——你在黑暗中播种骨头与尘埃，那是不会结果的种子——而如今，你拥有阳光下的土地，以及那些用双脚移动和行走的人们。可以这么说，甚至不需要收割就完全属于你——实际上，他们从出生的那一刻起就属于你。况且，如果说在过去，你总是被人们憎恨和责骂的话，那么现在，归功于我的所作所为，情况已经大为改观。任何有点智商的人都视你为珍宝并对你称颂有佳，爱你胜过生命，爱你到常常呼唤你，并把你看作生命中最大的希望。最后，我看到很多人吹嘘他们将会永生，就是说，他们不会完全死去，因为他们生命的很大一部分不会落入你手。我知道这种说法荒谬之极。倘若那些人或任何人能活在人们的记忆中的话，他们的生命就会成为一个笑话。他们享受盛名的程度不会比在坟墓里遭受阴冷潮湿的程度更甚——总之，鉴于这种永生刺痛了你，因为它似乎损害了你的荣誉和名声——我已经废除了这种追求永生以及将其赐予值得拥有它的人的习俗了。因此，现在如果一个人死了，你可以确信他身上的每一个部分都死掉了。他最好赶紧完整地去地下，就像一条一口被吞下头和身子的鱼。以上这些事情既非少见也非微不足道。是我为了你的缘故而做——因为我一心想帮你在地球上开疆辟土，一如之前所发生的那般。为此，我准备日后的每一天都继续这么做甚至更多。这个，就是我到处寻找你的缘由。我认为我们最好从现在开始就待在一起。这样的话，我们就可以好好商量事情，作出最好的决定，并将其实施。

死亡　你太正确了。就依你之言。

地球和月亮的对话

地球　亲爱的月亮，我知道您能言辞能作对答，因为您是人类，我常常听到诗人们如是说。另外，我的孩子们也提及，您实际上就像他们一样有嘴巴、鼻子、眼睛，这些都是他们亲眼所见。要知道在他们的这个年龄，视力自然是极好的。至于我，毫无疑问您该知道我同样也是人类。尤其是年轻时，我生有诸多子嗣。因此，假如您听到我讲话，请不要惊讶。好吧，我甜美的月亮，尽管连我也记不清多少个世纪与您为邻，可时至今日，我从未曾与您有所交流。大抵因为我总在忙于活计，一直无暇闲聊。而今，我的事情已无关紧要。实际上，我可以说任它们顺其自然发展。我不知道生活何以为续，无聊之极。我打算今后时常找您聊聊，顺带关注下你的事情——若是我没有给您添太多麻烦的话。

月亮　这点请勿担心。我倒是希望命运带给我的麻烦如同您带给我的那样少。你若是想和我说说话，就敬请畅所欲言。恐怕您也知道我不善言辞，但是，我乐意倾听，也很乐意答您所问，如果能对您有所帮助的话。

地球　您听到那美妙的音乐了吗？就是天体移动时发出的乐声？

月亮　说实话，我什么也没有听见。

地球　我也没听到任何声音。除却呼啸的风声从极地刮向赤道又从赤道刮回极地——它听着似乎一点也不像音乐，然而，毕达哥拉斯（Pythagoras）说天球之间会产生一种音乐，非常美妙也非常神奇，而且您本身就是其中的一分子，因为您算是这个宇宙里拉琴的第八根琴弦。我听不到大约是因为我的耳朵已经被那个音乐声震聋了。

月亮　那我的耳朵也一定被震聋了。因为如我所言，我没听到，更不知道自己是根琴弦。

地球　那么，我们还是换个话题吧。请您告诉我，月球上真的有人居住吗？如此众多的现代及古代哲学家，从俄耳甫斯（Orpheus）到拉朗德（De La Lande）都对此深信不疑。尽管我像个大蜗牛般地尽量伸长自己的触角，人们将这些触角称之为山脉和峰顶，并且按照人们的提示去努力望向你。可是，我却始终没在您那里看到一个居民——然而，我听说过有一个叫大卫·法布里奇乌斯（David Fabrius）的人，他的视力甚至赛过林克斯（Linceus）本人，他曾一度发现有人在太阳上晾晒衣物。

月亮　至于您的触角，我倒是不清楚。事实是我这里的确有居民。

地球　您那里的人是什么肤色？

月亮　什么人？

地球　就是那些居住在您上面的人呀。您刚才不是说过您那里住有居民吗？

月亮　是啊，那又如何？

地球　那么，您的居民们不可能全是动物。

月亮　他们既不是动物也不是人类，我不确定他们究竟是何种生物——或是其中哪一个。实际上，对于被您唤作人类的生物，我竟是一无所知呢。

地球　但是，您那里住的是哪种人呢？

月亮　有很多，类型各异。您对他们不了解就如同我不了解你们地球上的人类一样。

地球　在我看来很是奇怪。若不是听到您本人这么说，我无论如何也不敢相信啊。您难道没有曾经被您的居民征服过吗？

月亮　据我所知从来没有过。怎么征服？为什么征服？

地球　因为野心，或因为嫉妒别人的财产而通过政治手段或者诉诸武力占为己有。

月亮　我不知道您所谓的武力、野心、政治是什么。简言之，我不知道您在说些什么。

地球　那么，即使您不懂什么是武器，那一定知道什么是战争吧。因为前不久，我们一位科学家借助天文望远镜——就是一种能够帮助您看得很远的工具——发现在月球上有个巨大工事，其周边筑有各种堡垒。这些迹象说明您那里的人至少知道围攻和互战。

月亮　请您原谅，地球夫人，我本是您的奴仆和臣下，但是请您允许我逾越我的身份来答复您的问题。实话实说，假如您理所当然地认为世界每一个地区的每一样东西都和您那里的一模一样，您带给我的印象是您过于自负，似乎大自然在做任何事时都在复制您一样。我曾说过我有居民，您竟然由此断言我的居民一定是人类。我告诉您不是这样。尽管您承认他们是不同的生物这一事实，可是您却假设他们具有和您那里的人一样的品质且生活在同一环境下。您还提到某位科学家的望远镜及其他，但是，假如这架望远镜在其他情况下看得并不比这次更清楚，我只能认为它的视力应该和您孩子们的视力相差无几。您的孩子们看到我有眼睛、嘴和鼻子——可这些连我自己都不知道呢。

地球　如此说来，所谓您的行省里有宽敞的马路以及耕种的田地都不是真的了？——这些从地球上的德国地区通过望远镜就可以看到。

月亮　如果我被耕种过，我怎么对此一无所知；至于马路，我更是从未见过。

地球　我亲爱的月亮，您知道我有些愚钝和迟缓，所以才易于被人蒙骗，但是我要告诉您的是，即便您那里的人从未想过征服您，您也并不安全。一直以来，地球上的很多人苦心琢磨怎么征服您。他们还为此做了大量的计划和准备工作。尽管他们爬到最高点，踮起脚尖，伸长胳膊还是够不到您。况且，多年来我发现人类仔细地研究您的每一部分，测绘您的地理图形，测量您山脉的高度，甚至还为之起了名字。我觉得出于对您的感情和考虑，我该告诉您这些，以便您能应付紧急情况。现在，请允许我问您几个问题。当狗冲着您吠叫时您会感觉多烦躁？您对于那些指着水井里您的倒影的人有什么看法？您是男性还是女性？在古代人们不太确信。阿卡狄亚人（Arcadians）是否早于您来到这个世界？您那里的女人们——我不知应该如何称呼她们——都是卵生的？她们是否曾在这遗落过一枚卵子？还有，您是否如现代科学家认为的那样像念经珠般在中心穿孔？您是否像英国人说的那样是由绿奶酪做成的？在某天，或某个晚上，穆罕默德（Mohammed）把您像西瓜似的切成两半，您的大半个身体滑进他了的袖筒里？坐在光塔的顶端您感觉多幸福？您对拜兰节（Bairam）的宴席怎么看？

月亮　请继续。您这么滔滔不绝地侃侃而谈，我都不需要回答您也无需打破我一贯的沉默。您若是找不到别的话题只喜欢在这些废话上浪费时间的话，与其找我这样不能理解您的人，不如找别人为您另造一个星球，依照您的喜好和居住方式而建，并围着您旋转。除了人、狗以及其他类似的事情，您不会谈论别的。而对此我又知之甚少。我仅仅知道我们的太阳是围绕人们所说的大太阳旋转的。

地球　的确如此。与您交谈时，我越是想尽量避免提及自己的事情，就越是失败。不过从现在起，我会倍加小心。请告诉我，您是不是那个享受吸引地球上的潮汐涨落的人？

月亮　也许吧。即便我有这么做，或者对您做了其他什么事，我压根没有注意过。就像您不大会注意到您对我的影响，您对我的影响要远远大于我对您的影响，毕竟您的体积更大也更强壮些。

地球　实际上，就我所知我唯一能影响到您的事情就是，每隔一阵子我会遮蔽太阳照向您的光芒。我自身也会吸收您的光芒。我还知道在您的夜间时段，我的光线会将您照得很明亮，这个我会不时地看到。不过，我好像忘掉了一些至关重要的事情。我想知道，是否真的如同阿里奥斯托（Ariosto）写的那样，人丢失的每样东西——如青春、美貌、健康，以及用在求学、追名逐利，用在依照良好的行为规范教养孩子长大成人，用在建立和推广有用机构等事物中所消耗的的体力和金钱——这一切都流向并聚集在您那上面，以至人类的一切都可以在您那里找到，只有愚蠢不在此列，因为愚蠢从未离开过人类。如果上述所言为真，我设想您一定被占满了，没有剩余空间。尤其是考虑到人类在近代丢失了许多东西（如爱国主义、美德、宽容、诚实），不是像以往似的只丢了部分或几个，而是整个的全部丢失了。当然，如果这些东西不在您处，我也不知其所踪。故而，我想同您签份协议。您现在开始把这些东西退还给我，日后一有机会，您仍旧坚持这么做下去。毕竟，我想丢掉这些您也会很开心，尤其是常识，据我所知总是占据极大的空间。我会设法每年都让人类支付给您一大笔钱的。

月亮　啊，您又谈及人类了。尽管正如您所说，愚蠢从未离开过您的领地，您寻找人类的智慧，却妄图把我的智慧夺走。我不知道它们在哪儿，也许它们正在消失，也许它们藏在世界的某个角落；我只知道在我这儿找不到它们，您刚才提到的其他东西也都不在这里。

地球　至少您可以告诉我您上边的人们是否知晓恶习、犯罪、灾难、痛苦、衰老，简言之，就是各种邪恶？您明白这些词的意思吗？

月亮　哦，当然。我当然明白。我不仅知道它们的意思更知道它们所谓何指。我完全明白这些，因为我这里充满了这些东西——而不是您刚刚提到的那些东西。

地球　在您那里的人们中什么更普遍，美德还是邪恶？

月亮　截止目前，是邪恶。

地球　什么更多些，善还恶？

月亮　无须比较，是恶。

地球　那么，一般来说，您的居民们是幸福的还是不幸福的？

月亮　非常不幸福。我甚至都不愿和他们中最幸福的人交换位置。

地球　和我这边情况相同。以至于我很惊讶您我在这一点上如此相似，当然您在其他地方又如此不同。

月亮　再有，我与您形状相似，运动模式相似，同样接受太阳的照射。没有什么值得大惊小怪的，因为邪恶是这个宇宙里所有星球所共有的，至少在这个太阳系中如此——正如我刚才提及的圆球形状以及其他条件一样。假如您提高嗓门大声说话，就会被天王星（Uranus）和土星（Saturn）听到，或者被我们世界中的其他星球听到。您问他们那里有无幸福的存在，或者善和恶哪个更多些，他们每个都会像我一样回答您。之所以这么说，是因为我已经问过金星（Venus）和水星（Mercury）同样的问题，因为通常我总觉得比起您来，我离他们更近些。就同样的问题我还问过路过的流星，他们的答案和我一模一样。我认为太阳自己也好，每颗星星也好，都会给出同一个答案。

地球　尽管如此，我仍怀抱希望。尤其是现今，人类许诺于我在未来会有莫大的幸福。

月亮　您可以肆意希望下去。我确信您可以永久地希望下去。

地球　您知道发生什么啦？那些人和动物们开始活动且发出声响了。我跟您谈话那一面是夜晚，正如您所见，不，您根本看不到；所以他们还在睡觉，不过，我们谈话时发出的巨大响动已经把他们惊醒。

月亮　可是，您看我这上边，依然是白天呢。

地球　我不想吓坏我的人们或者惊扰他们的美梦，睡眠是他们最大的福分了。好吧，我们下次再谈吧。那么，再见。日安。

月亮　再见，晚安。

普罗米修斯的赌注

在朱庇特治下833275年，缪斯学院下令印刷一些海报并在哈勃纳菲勒斯城（Hypernephenlus）城内及城郊的各个公共场所内张贴。海报上面力邀众神，不论大神还是小神，以及该城的其他居民，任何一位近期或之前有过有价值的发明的人士参加展示比赛。赛事要求参赛者以本人、模型或描述方式在由该学院指定的评委面前展示其发明。与此同时，该学院遗憾地表示鉴于学院的一贯清贫，他们无法随心所欲地慷慨，但是他们承诺，作为奖品，那个被评为最漂亮也是最有用的发明其发明者将会获得一顶桂冠，并被授予特权日夜佩戴它，无论是在公共场合还是私人场合，无论是在城内还是城外。同时，还允许他头戴桂冠的样子被绘制成画、被塑像、被雕刻、被塑形，以及以任何材料和任何方式进行展示。

很多神祇都参与其中，但也仅仅是把它看作一种消遣。对于哈勃纳菲勒斯城的居民来说，如同和其他城镇的居民一样，这个比赛属于可有可无——至少他们没有兴趣赢得那顶桂冠，它的价值甚至比不过一顶纯棉的睡帽。至于说到荣誉，假如人类自己——他们现在都是哲学家了——都鄙夷它，可想而知在诸神心中它会是什么地位，更别提神要远远比人聪明[事实上，据毕达哥拉斯和柏拉图（Plato）所言，神才是真正的聪明]。因此，这一赛事成为独一无二的特例，在此之前的同类赛事中闻所未闻，即在奖项评审时，没有任何徇私徇情之扰，没有私下的承诺和阴谋。最后，总共有三位获奖者：酒的发明者巴克斯（Bacchus）；护肤油类的发明者米涅瓦（Minerva），其发明对于众神每日的沐浴无比重要；节能铜锅的发明者伏尔甘（Vulcan），该锅能够省火省时地烹饪任何食物。如此一来，奖品不得不分成三份，结果是每人能获得一小截桂树枝，但是这三位都拒绝领取该奖品，不论是部分奖品还是全部奖品。伏尔甘说他的大部分时间都花在锻冶炉前工作和流汗，头上戴着这个东西将会成为一个大麻烦——更别说将会置他于险地，一旦碰巧有火星喷溅到干树枝上，就有可能着火，从而将他烧伤或灼伤。米纳瓦说既然她的头上需要戴一顶一次能遮盖住一百个城池军队的帽子，如荷马（Homer）描述的那样，那么在她的头上增加任何重量都是不明智之举。巴克斯说他不想换帽子，他不愿意把头上的葡萄藤叶桂冠换成桂树桂冠，当然如果允许的话，他还是乐意把桂树枝挂在他的酒馆前面做招牌，然而，缪斯们最终拒绝了他的要求，因此奖品仍然留在他们的宝库里。

其他竞争者们一点也不嫉妒这三位胜出却又拒绝领奖的仙家，也没有人抱怨评委或质疑他们的裁定。只有一个人例外：普罗米修斯。他参加了比赛，他的作品是他在造人时用泥捏的第一个人，并附上了对其功能及品德的介绍，人类种族始于普罗米修斯之手。对于最终结果普罗米修斯大为光火。虽然其他所有人，不管是赢家还是输家都觉得这个比赛不过是个游戏而已。针对普罗米修斯的这种愤愤不平的背后原因大家做了一番调查，原来他最想要的不是这份荣誉而是获胜者能够享有的特权。有些人猜测他可能想用这顶帽子来保护头部不受暴风雨的肆虐，就像台比留（Tiberius）一样，传言他一听到雷声就立刻带上桂冠，因为他相信桂冠不易受雷电侵袭。可是，哈勃纳菲勒斯城里既没有雷也没有闪电；还有些人，更是言之凿凿，他们说普罗米修斯的年龄慢慢大了，已经开始脱发了——对这种不幸，他和很多人一样对其深恶痛疾——再加上他又未曾读过辛奈西斯（Synesius）所著的秃顶颂，或者更可能的是，他并没有被其言论说服。于是，他宁愿把他的秃顶像尤里乌斯·凯撒那样藏在王冠底下。

还是回到我们的故事中来。有一天，普罗米修斯正和莫摩斯（Momus）交谈，他悲切地抱怨道：酒、油和锅被赋予比人类更多的优先权。他宣称人类才是神族给予世界的最好作品。他感觉到莫摩斯没有被他说服，尽管他提出了很多悖论进行论证。于是，普罗米修斯建议他们一同飞往地球，并随意降落在五大洲中的第一个有人烟的地方；不过，首先他们先相互下了赌注——普罗米修斯打赌在所有这五个洲里，或在其中的大部分地区，他们都能找到正面证据，以证明人类确实是宇宙中最完美的生物。莫摩斯表示同意。就赌金数额达成一致后，他们立即起身下界。他们首先奔向新世界。既是出于其名字的原因，也是出于还没有任何仙家到过该地区的考虑，因此他们对此地区特别好奇。他们的第一站停在波波牙国（Popaián）北部地区，距考卡河（Cauca）不远。此处有种种人类居住的迹象——乡间有耕种的痕迹，无数小路纵横交错，其中多数路段已被堵死；树木被砍倒横在地面上；尤其是那些看上去像坟墓的地方，周遭到处扔着人骨头。尽管如此，两位神仙还是没能看到一个活人的影子或听到人的声音，且不论他们如何努力地竖起耳朵睁大眼睛。他们继续前行，飞一阵儿，走一阵儿。又往前走了数英里，翻过山岭跨过河流，每到一处都能找到相同的迹象和孤寂。“这些地方为何如此荒凉？”莫摩斯向普罗米修斯发问，“明明是有人居住过的样子。”普罗米修斯辩称也许是受到潮汐、地震、飓风或大雨影响。据他所知这些在热带地区是常见的。确实，就在此时，他们听到附近森林里随着风刮过，树枝上的雨不停地被拂落到地上的声音，但是，莫摩斯还是无法理解此地怎么会受到潮汐的影响——大海明明离得很远，远到根本看不见嘛。更让他费解的是，如果地震、飓风、大雨毁灭了该国度里所有的人，那么，那些随处可见的美洲虎、猴子、狐狸、食蚁兽、老鹰、鹦鹉及其他数百种飞行爬行的动物又是怎样得以逃生的呢？最终，他们降临在一个巨大的山谷里。在那儿，他们发现了似乎是一小堆房子，准确地说是类似小木屋的东西，上面覆盖着棕榈树叶子——每幢房子四周都围着木头栅栏。在其中的一处房子前面聚集着很多人，有些人站着，有些人坐着，他们正围在一个悬挂在篝火上面的瓦罐四周。两位仙家幻化作人形，走近人群。普罗米修斯极有礼貌地向在场的每个人问好，然后，他转向一位貌似酋长的人并询问他们在做什么。

野人　我们在吃东西，你不是看见了嘛。

普罗米修斯　在吃什么好东西呢？

野人　吃这块肉。

普罗米修斯　是家畜肉还是野味？

野人　家养的，实际上，是我儿子的肉。

普罗米修斯　你是把公牛当儿子吗，就和帕西法厄（Pasiphae）似的？

野人　不是公牛，是人。是和其他人一模一样的人。

普罗米修斯　此话当真？你在吃自己的骨肉？

野人　不是我自己的骨肉，但确实是我儿子的骨和肉。我照顾他、养育他、把他带到这个世界来的唯一目的就是为此。

普罗米修斯　仅仅是为了吃掉他吗？

野人　这有什么奇怪吗？再有，他妈妈也是一样的。既然她已经不可能再生孩子了，我打算最近吃掉她。

莫摩斯　这就好比你吃完鸡蛋再吃掉母鸡一个道理。

野人　我的其他女人们也一样……她们一旦没有生孩子的用处了……我就打算吃了她们。还有你看到的在这里的奴隶们……要不是隔一阵我就能吃几个他们生的孩子们，我干嘛要养活他们？不过，要是他们老了，也会被我吃掉，一次一个——倘若我能活那么久的话。

普罗米修斯　告诉我，这些奴隶——他们是属于你的部落还是别的部落的？

野人　别的部落。

普罗米修斯　是离这儿很远的一个部落吗？

野人　非常远。远到在他们与我们的房子之间甚至隔着一条小溪。

接着，他指向一处矮山头又补充道：“就在那边，那是他们以前一直居住的地方，但已经被我们的人毁掉了。”此时此刻，普罗米修斯觉察到许多野人们正向他频抛媚眼，那种爱慕的眼神就如同一只猫看见老鼠似的。故而，以防被同类吃掉，他快速飞起，莫摩斯也一样。他们俩起飞时都有些慌张，以至于他们离开时带起的尘土弄脏了野人们的食物。那些尘土一如当年哈耳皮埃（Harpies）出于妒忌撒在特洛伊人（Trojans）餐桌上的尘土一样。不过，野人们已经很饿了，况且也不像埃涅阿斯（Aeneas）的伙伴们那般挑剔，因此，他们仍继续大快朵颐。

普罗米修斯　对新世界颇感失望。于是，他立即赶往最古老的世界，也就是亚洲。几乎是在瞬间，他们两人就从新印度飞到了旧印度并降落在阿格拉城（Agra）附近的一处田间地头。那边聚集了浩浩荡荡的人群。他们都围拢在一条堆满柴火的沟渠边上——在沟渠的一头他们看到一些男人手持点燃的火把，准备随时点燃火堆；在沟渠的另一头，有一个平台，上面有一个年轻女子衣着极为华美，浑身佩戴着各色原始饰物，正在载歌载舞，脸上似乎露出极为开心的模样。看到这一幕，普罗米修斯想象着一个新卢克丽斯（Lucretus）或者一个新弗吉尼亚（Virginia）诞生了。她是一位类似埃瑞克修斯（Erechthetia）的女儿们式的人物，又和伊芙琴尼亚（Iphigenia）、科德拉斯（Codrus）、孟子（Mencius）、柯歇斯（Curtius），德西厄斯（Decius）类似，她遵循神谕，为了祖国而甘愿牺牲自己。不久之后，他却听说她只是在给亡夫殉葬。于是，他揣度她跟阿尔刻提斯（Alcestis）没什么两样，都愿意用自己的生命换取丈夫的性命，然而，他进而了解到她愿意被活活烧死的原因不过是为了遵循当地的寡妇的风俗，而她一直恨自己的丈夫，并且当时她喝醉了。那个死去的丈夫，不是要复活，而是将在同一把火里被烧掉。普罗米修斯马上不再理会这场景而是转身向欧洲出发。在路上，他和莫摩斯有如下对话：

莫摩斯　你可曾想过，当年你历经重重险阻盗取天庭的火种送给人类，而有些人却用它把同类放进锅里蒸煮食用，还有些人情愿把自己烧死？

普罗米修斯　当然没有，但是，亲爱的莫摩斯，请别忘记，我们目前见到的都是些野人。人类的本性不是由野人而是由文明人来衡量的。现在我们就在去找他们的路上。我坚信在他们中间我们不仅将会看到听到值得称颂的事情，也会让你充满惊讶。

莫摩斯　假设人类是世上最完美的生物，我不明白为什么他们需要被文明教化才能不去自焚或食用自己的子嗣。其他动物都是野生的，然而它们从未刻意烧死自己。当然凤凰除外，不过这种生物从未有人目睹过。吞食自己同类的动物也极为罕见，更别说食用自己子嗣的动物了——只有在极特殊情况下才会有个别例外，但也断断不会是为了食用而繁衍子嗣的。请你注意，在地球的五个洲中，到目前为止只有最小的那个，况且也不是整个这个洲，再加上其他地区的极少区域里，才被赋予你所宣称的那种高度文明。我不认为你自己会坚持这种文明已经几近完美，巴黎人也好，费城人也好，已经取得人类种族可能取得的那种完美程度。现在，人类需要工作和努力多久才能达到一个并不算完美的文明程度？大概从人类诞生的第一天算起直至今日这么多年的时间了吧。况且，几乎所有有利于或者是获取文明所必备的方法，并非源于刻意的构想而是源于机缘凑巧。也就是说，人类文明更像意外的结果而绝非自然发展的产物；假如这些偶然不存在，人类依旧还是野人，尽管他们刚好和文明人同龄。因此，我断定，如果野人们在诸多方面都逊色于其他动物的话；如果文明，作为野蛮的对立面，时至今日仍只是极少数人的特权的话；再者，如果这极少数人在耗费了数个世纪之后，依赖偶然事件而非其他渠道才达到目前的文明状态的话；最后，如果目前的文明状态仍然远远不够完美的话——那么，我认为假如你用下面的简短方式表达，你对人类的判断也许会更准确些，即，承认人类确实如你所想的那样优于其他物种，不是在完美方面而是在不完美方面——尽管人类在说话或评判时，总是不停混淆这两个概念。他们最擅长从自己设定的前提，或从自以为正确的真理中推导结论。可以确定的是，其他物种从初始起就很完美，每一类都能遵循自己的本性。虽然与其他物种相较，尚不清楚野人为什么会是最糟糕的物种。令我费解的是，既然人类的本质是如此的残缺，正如人类看上去那样，却又为何被认为是比其他物种更为文明的物种？再补充一点，人类文明不仅难以获得，也许也没有完成的可能性，况且也没有稳定到不会被分化，实际上，在已然获得高度文明的各色人类中，文明曾经无数次坍塌。简言之，我持下列观点，假如是你的兄弟厄庇墨透斯（Epimetheus）展示给评委们他创造第一只毛驴或第一只青蛙所用的模型，他很可能赢得你无法赢得的奖项，但是，如果你断定人类的完美是如同普罗提诺（Plotinus）贡献于世界的那种完美，普罗提诺声称其贡献绝对优质而完美，那么，我同意你的说法。所谓完美，是要求这个世界，在所有事物中，也包含所有可能的邪恶。因为，实际上在现今世界里我们发现邪恶几乎无处不在。在这层意义上，我可能赞同莱布尼兹（Leibniz）的观点，当今世界已经是可能的最好的世界了。

毫无疑问，普罗米修斯已经有了现成的答案——简洁、明了并且合乎逻辑——以迎合前述论点，但同样可以确定的是，他并没有说出来。因为就在那时，他们发现已经飞到伦敦上空了。他们降落下来，看到某处私人住宅门前聚集了一大批人群。他们加入到人群中进入屋内。屋里，他们看到一个人面朝天躺在床上，手握着枪，已经死去了，胸部留有伤口。在他身边躺着两个小孩，也已经死去。几个仆人站在屋子里，正在接受治安官们的盘问，书记员一边做着笔录。

普罗米修斯　这些可怜的人是谁？

仆人　是我的主人和他的孩子们。

普罗米修斯　谁杀了他们？

仆人　我的主人，三个都杀了。

普罗米修斯　你的意思是，他杀了自己和自己的孩子们？

仆人　对的。

普罗米修斯　难以置信。他一定遇到了极可怕的事情。

仆人　据我所知应该没有。

普罗米修斯　但是，也许因为他太穷，受人鄙视，或者失恋了，或者仕途不如意。

仆人　恰恰相反。他非常富有，我想所有人都尊重他。对于爱情他是毫不在意的。况且，他很受朝廷欢迎。

普罗米修斯　那他怎么如此绝望？

仆人　因为对生活的厌倦，正如他自己写的那样。

普罗米修斯　那些治安官们——他们在干吗？

仆人　他们在盘问我的主人是否精神失常。要是他没疯，他的资产将归皇室所有。的确这种可能无法避免。

普罗米修斯　但是请告诉我，他没有亲人和朋友可以托付这两个孩子了吗，为什么一定要杀死他们俩个？

仆人　是的，当然有的。有一个和他关系特别好的朋友，他把他的狗托付给他了。

莫摩斯　正准备向普罗米修斯祝贺文明的良好作用，以及它带给人类生命的福音。他还打算提醒他除了人类以外，没有任何其他动物会因为绝望而杀死自己以及自己的孩子们，但是普罗米修斯已经先他一步，付给他赌金了。他已经没有兴趣再去世界的其他两个区域看看了。

自然和冰岛人的对话

一位冰岛人，曾经游历了大半个世界并访问了很多国家。有一次，他在非洲内陆地区游荡时，穿过赤道进入到一片未曾被人探索过的地域。在那里，他经历了一番与瓦斯科·达·伽马（Vasco da Gama）类似的奇遇。当他绕过好望角区域以及好望角的这个角时，把守奥斯（Austral）海域的好望角，化作一个巨人走至他面前，劝阻他不要进入海图上未载明的水域。冰岛人看到远处有一个巨大的半身像。起初，他以为是石头雕像，类似于他多年前在复活节岛上见过的那些巨型石像，但是，走近之后，他发现原来是一个巨大的女人的身体。她端坐在地上，上身挺直，她的背部和手臂靠着身后的大山。她不是什么石像，而是一个大活人——她的脸既美丽又令人生畏，她的眼睛和头发像渡鸦一样漆黑。她默默地凝视了他一会儿，最终开口。

自然　你是谁？到这片地域来干什么？你的同类们目前还尚未涉足这里。

冰岛人　我是个可怜的冰岛人。我一直在逃离自然。基本上我的一生都在逃开她，我已经逃离过地球上的一百多个地区，现在我在设法逃离这个地方的自然。

自然　小松鼠也是这么逃离响尾蛇的，直到它最终落入蛇口。我就是你要逃离的自然。

冰岛人　自然？

自然　正是我。

冰岛人　真是万分遗憾啊。我深感再没有什么比这更大的灾难降临到我身上了。

自然　你应该很清楚在这些地区特别容易找到我的。在这儿，你也知道我的能量要远远大于在别处。究竟是什么促使你躲避我呢？

冰岛人　我来告诉你。自儿时起，在经历一些事情之后，我意识到并确信人生的虚浮以及人类的冥顽不化。为了不会快乐的快乐，为了没有用处的物资，他们彼此间争斗不休；他们忍耐并施予彼此无尽的焦虑和无尽的烦恼，这些都会带来真正的骚扰和伤害。由此，他们越是追求幸福，幸福就会离他们越远。因为受到这些观点的影响，我抛开所有的抱负，下定决心过一种默默无闻的宁静生活，不去打扰别人，不去费心钻研，也不与世人你争我夺。同时，我也不曾期待幸福——这是个与我们种族绝缘的东西——我只为自己设定了一个目标，就是脱离痛苦。这样的决定，并不意味着我打算放弃工作和体力劳动，况且你也知道，在劳作与痛苦之间，平静生活与懒散生活之间还是有区别的。我刚刚把我的决心付诸实践，便从中体会到以下的想法真是大错特错。比如，与人生活在一起，假如你认为你不伤害别人，别人就不会伤害你；再比如，如果你能自觉地隐退并满足于最少的物质，这样你就被允许留有一小点地方并且你的这一小点不会被夺走。但是，我还是很轻松地把自己从同类的敌意中解放出来了，比如我远离人类社会，闭门不出——这一切在我的家乡很容易办到。就这样毫无乐趣地生活了一段时间之后，我依然不能毫无痛苦地活着，因为漫长的冬天异常寒冷，而夏天又是出奇得炎热，两者属于典型的当地气候，这样的天气一直在折磨着我。还有炉火，因为我不得不大部分时间待在火边，我的皮肤被烤干，眼睛被烟火熏坏。因此，不论在室内还是室外我都无法感到丝毫舒适。更遑论那种获得我全身心渴望的宁静生活的可能。因为陆地上以及海上经常爆发可怕的风暴，海克拉火山的威胁和隆隆声，对火灾的恐惧，火灾在我们居住的木制房子里十分常见。所有这些始终在困扰着我。在这个一成不变的生活里，摆脱了所有的欲望、希望和几乎所有的烦恼，只留有平静安宁，上述那些不舒适就显得比平时更为尖锐，更让人难以忍受，因为在平时，我们的脑子总是被社会交际生活以及来自他人的敌意占得满满的。因此，我发现我越是像过去那样退隐，越是尽力把自己缩起来，以避免妨碍或伤害到世上的其他生物，我就越容易被那些事情所烦恼和折磨。于是，我开始尝试不同的地理位置和气候，企图寻找地球上是否有那么一块地方，在那里，我不冒犯别人，别人也不会冒犯我。在那里，没有快乐，但也不会有痛苦。尤其是想到下面这一点，我就更加坚定了自己的决心：也许你注定人类只能适应一种气候（正如你对其他动植物的规定那样），或只能适应某个特定区域，在该范围之外人类就无法兴盛，也无法舒适而毫无痛苦地活着；一旦他们不屑一顾或突破你所规定的适合人类居住的规则，那么由此招致的艰难和痛苦只能归罪于他们自己，而并非你的责任。我几乎找遍了整个世界，足迹踏遍了每个国家，但是我的初衷未改，即不带给任何人麻烦，并过宁静生活。可是，我曾在热带被热浪灼伤；在极地被寒冷冻僵；在温带饱受不稳定的气候的折磨；每到一处我都会被自然灾难所扰。我看到在很多地方，几乎没有一天没有暴雨，也就是说你每天都要袭击或悉心准备一场战争给那些从未伤害过你的居民们。在其他地区，宁静的天空下却总是伴随频繁的地震、频频发作的剧烈火山喷发，以及整个区域地表下的沸腾和颤抖。在狂风与飓风肆虐的地区和季节里不再有其他的天气灾难。有时，我会感觉到房顶向我的头顶压下来，因为上面有太多积雪；有时，因为倾盆暴雨，地面会裂开并在脚下下沉；有时，我不得不拼命地从河边逃离，那些河水在我身后紧紧追赶如同要找我算账一般。很多我从来没有一丝一毫地冒犯过的野兽却想一口吃掉我；很多毒蛇想毒死我；很多地方有不少飞虫把我吸得只剩骨头。我更不愿意提及的是那些天天发生的、无数一直在威胁着人类的危险。这些危险多到一位古代哲学家认为不仅没有克服恐惧的办法，相反的，实际上每件事都是令人恐惧的。不仅如此，我也没有被免于病痛的侵扰，尽管从过去到现在，我在肉体享乐上不仅一贯节制，甚至是克己的。我不得不惊叹，一想到你注入我们体内如此强烈却又无法满足的对快乐的渴望，没有这种快乐，或剥夺这种自然的渴求，我们的生命便不再完美。然而，你又规定沉溺于这种快乐，是在所有有关人类的事情里最为有害身心健康的，对每个人都具有毁灭性质，是寿命延续的大敌。纵然，一直以来我基本完全杜绝了所有的享乐，可是我仍然被诸多的各式病症所折磨。一些疾病差点让我丧命；一些几乎让我失去肢体；一些永久性地让我的生活比过去悲惨。所有这些都长达数天乃至数月，以一千种匮乏和一千种痛苦煎熬着我的身心。尽管在生病时，我们每一个人都体验到未曾经历的痛苦和比平日里更多的不幸福（似乎生活本身还不够痛苦），而你却没有因此而补偿人类。比如让他有一段时间精力充沛、有更胜于平时的健康，带给他质量和数量上的双重快乐。在某些国家里，常年冰雪覆盖，我的眼睛几乎变瞎了，就像拉普兰德（Lapland）国的居民常常有的状况。太阳与空气，二者于我们的生存息息相关，所以无从回避，但它们也在时时折磨着我们——我们四周空气里含有的湿度、气候的严峻、天气的各种突变，太阳的热度、光线自身，以至于人类只要暴露于其下就必定会感觉不舒服或受伤。确实，我记不得自己生命中哪一天是不用遭受痛苦的，而同时那些快乐的日子屈指可数。我意识到我们命中注定痛苦之多与快乐之少是等同的。获得任何一种平静生活的可能性与争斗的生活中没有磨难的可能性一样微乎其微。这样，我被迫得出结论，你才是人类、其他动物以及你所创造的生物的最鲜明的敌人。时而，你让我们落入陷阱；时而，你威胁我们；时而，你袭击我们；时而，你又螫伤我们；时而，你击打我们；时而，你撕碎我们。永远地，你总在冒犯我们、迫害我们。不论是出于习惯或受规则约束，可以说，你是你自己家庭、子女、亲骨肉的刽子手。故而，我不抱任何希望。我知道人类最终会停止迫害那些一心要躲开和逃避他们的人，而你则永远不会对我们停手，直到把我们击垮为止。如今，我已经几近步入痛苦而毫无希望的老年时期了。年迈是真正而明确的邪恶，实际上也是最具压迫性的邪恶和痛苦的集合。它不是偶然而来，而是你的法则赋予所有有生命的生物的邪恶。从孩童时代我们就知晓它的存在。从二十五岁生日之后，迹象越来越明显，那种令人无比悲伤的不幸的腐化的过程。如是，人类生命的三分之一是用来成长的，仅仅有短短的瞬间是成熟和完美期，其余的就是衰老以及随之而来的各种不适。

自然　你是否碰巧想过这世界难道只是为你而造的吗？好吧，让我来告诉你，除了极个别情况之外，在我的工作、法则和操作中，我的目的在过去乃至现在都不是为了人类的幸福或不幸福。不论我在何时以何种方式伤害了你，我都未曾注意到，当然除却极少数例外情形。正如在一般情况下，我并不知晓我是取悦了你们还是帮助了你们。我并没有如你所想的那样，曾经做过这些，或者现在做这些去取悦你、帮助你。最后，即便我不经意间毁灭了你们整个种族，我也从未留意过。

冰岛人　让我们来假设一下，如果有人主动且强烈地邀请我拜访他的别墅。为了使他高兴，我接受了邀请。然而，在应邀前往贵宅之后，我被安置在一间年久失修的破败小室里，潮湿、恶臭、走风漏雨，还时刻会有把我砸扁的可能。主人不仅没有花费心思招待我，让我过得舒适；相反，他甚至没有提供维持我生存的足够供给。他还允许他的孩子以及其他家庭成员对我进行辱骂、嘲笑、威胁乃至殴打。假如我向他抱怨这样的待遇，他会回答：“难道你觉得我的别墅是为你造的吗？我养活我的孩子和佣人就是为了帮助你吗？除了招待你，为你花钱，我还有很多事情需要考虑呢。”对此我的回答是：“你看，我的朋友，你的别墅的确不是为我而建，你有权决定是否邀请我来此做客，但是，既然你主动邀请我住在这里，难道你不觉得你应该做些安排，至少从你那方面来说，让我不受折磨和危险，安心住在这里？”这些就是我现在要说的话。我知道你创造这个世界并非为了让它服务于人类。我更愿意相信你的初衷是为了折磨人类。现在，我来问你，我是否恳求你让我来到这个世界，还是我使用暴力手段或未经你允许闯入这个世界的？事实上，是你自己一厢情愿、亲手安排我来到这里，既没有征得我的同意，也不让我有反抗或反对它的选择。在此情形下，难道，即便你没有义务让我在你的国度里感到快乐与满足，你不应该至少保证我不会备受折磨并且生活在这里不会有害于我吗？我所说的不仅仅是我自己，更是关乎整个人类种族，其他动物乃至其他所有生物。

自然　很显然，你没有考虑到在这个宇宙里生命是生产与毁灭的永恒循环——两者紧紧相连，相互作用，才有世界现实状况。一旦任何一方停止作用，世界将不复存在。因此，若是任何事物没有痛苦便是有害于这个世界的。

冰岛人　这恰恰是那些哲学家们说的。既然被毁灭的要受难，毁灭者也没有体验到快乐，况且他本身也即将被毁灭，请告诉我哲学家不能回答的：有谁能在这个世界最悲惨的生活里找到一丝快乐和任何优点？它的存在依仗受难与死亡，而这两者恰恰又是生命的组成部分？

我们得到消息说在他们进行这样或类似讨论的时候，碰巧有两头狮子出现了，它们是如此疲惫和饥饿，以至于它们只有刚刚好的力气吃掉这个冰岛人。于是它们就吃了，并有了足够的能量再多活一天。有人不相信这个版本的故事，他们坚持说在冰岛人说话时，突然狂风骤起，风把他掀翻在地，接着又把他卷起扔进一个巨大的沙子坟墓里，在那下面，他的身体被完美地脱水并变成了一具漂亮的干尸。后来，他被旅行者发现了，并被带回来陈列在欧洲某城的一个博物馆里。

弗瑞德里克·鲁谢和木乃伊们的对话

木乃伊们在弗瑞德里克·鲁谢的书房合唱

每一个创造物

孤零零地在这世上，走向永恒，

我们最原始的本性

在你，死亡中，得到安息；

不是快乐，而是不再遭受

世世代代的痛苦。

沉沉夜幕

在我们混乱的头脑中

遮蔽了我们坟墓中的思索；

感觉到希望、渴望、枯萎的灵魂

它的力量渐渐远去；

由此，不再遭受痛苦，不再感觉恐惧

那些漫长的空虚岁月

逝去时不再无聊。

我们活着；如同

一个受到惊吓的鬼魂的混乱记忆

如同大汗淋漓的梦魇

在婴儿的灵魂里游荡，

因此，记忆仍在我们中间徘徊

生前的记忆：摆脱恐惧的

是我们的记忆。我们曾经是谁？

生命曾经的意义何在？

如今，生命之于我们的头脑

仍然是巨大的谜团

对于生者的头脑，也是如此

无名的死亡迫近。活着时

要逃离死亡，而现在

要逃离生命之火

我们的原始本元

不快乐但是很安全

因为幸福

既没有被命运赋予凡人也没有赋予死者。

鲁谢　（站在书房外面，从门缝里窥探书房）怎么回事，谁教这些死人唱歌？他们的歌声就像公鸡在半夜打鸣似的。我被惊出了一身冷汗，几乎吓死。我没有期待它们活过来，我只是为它们做了防腐处理。好吧，不管我有多少理论，我还是从头到脚哆嗦个不停。那个让我把这些人带回家的混蛋真该死。我都不知道该怎么办。如果我继续把他们锁在里面，他们也许会破门而出，他们也许会从锁眼里冒出来，在我熟睡时抓住我。可若是大声呼救说我害怕这些死人，似乎也不太体面。好吧，鼓起勇气，让我先吓唬一下他们。

（进入书房）嗯，孩子们，在玩什么游戏呢？难道不记得你们已经死了吗？你们在这里吵闹什么？是不是因为沙皇的拜访你们就有些得意忘形？还是你们以为不需要像过去一样接受法律约束？我想你们仅仅是在开玩笑，对不对？假如你们活过来了，我得向你们祝贺；不过，我没那么富有，可以像保存死人一样养活你们。因此，你们必须离开。假如有关吸血鬼的传言是真的，你们就是吸血鬼，那么你们必须得找点别人的血喝喝。我可不打算让你们喝我的血，不管之前我可以多么慷慨地往你们的血管里注入人工血。简言之，如果你们还能像先前一样保持安静和沉默，我们就能和平共处。在我的家里你们可以自便。否则，我就插上门把你们都杀掉。

木乃伊　请别生气。我向您保证我们还会像从前一样了无声息，您完全没有必要杀死我们。

鲁谢　那么，这个唱歌是怎么回事？

木乃伊　不久前，就在午夜时分，古人们曾多次提及的大数学年第一次结束了。这也是第一次死者能开口讲话的时候。不单单是我们，所有公墓里的、坟墓里的，甚至是埋在海底、埋在积雪和沙子下面、或者暴露在空气中的死者，不论其身处何地，在这个午夜时分，所有的死者就像我们一样，唱那首你刚刚听到的歌。

鲁谢　那么他们将会唱多久或说多久啊？

木乃伊　至于唱歌，他们已经唱完了。至于说话，他们每个人被允许说一刻钟。之后，他们就回归沉默直到下一个同样年份的来临。

鲁谢　如果这是真的，我觉得你们不会再吵醒我睡觉了。你们随心所欲地说吧，我会好奇地站在一边，很高兴听你们交谈而不去打扰。

木乃伊　我们只能靠回答活人的问题说话。唱歌结束后，那些不需要回答活人问题的就保持安静。

鲁谢　真是太遗憾了。本来我觉得如果你们能讲话，听你们之间谈什么会非常有趣。

木乃伊　即便我们能行，你也什么都听不到。因为我们彼此间没有可交流的。

鲁谢　我可以想出一千个问题问你。不过，既然时间紧迫，没有选择余地，就请你言简意赅地告诉我在死亡的瞬间，你的身体和思想都经历了什么样的感觉？

木乃伊　我没注意到死亡的瞬间。

其他木乃伊我们也没有。

鲁谢　你们怎么可能没有注意到呢？

木乃伊　就像你不会注意到你入睡的瞬间一样，不管你为之多么注意。

鲁谢　可是，入睡是一个自然的过程。

木乃伊　难道你不觉得死亡也是一个自然的过程吗？你任意找一个不会死的人、动物或植物给我看看？

鲁谢　要是你没有意识到你已经死了，我一点也不惊讶你会继续唱歌和说话。

丝毫未察觉到这个打击，他继续前行

依然在挣扎，尽管已经死去。

一位意大利诗人如是写道。我想关于死亡的问题，你们这些已经死去的人会比活人更有发言权。还是回到我们的主题上来，在死亡的瞬间，你们没有感到疼痛吗？

木乃伊　如果感觉死亡的那个人根本没有意识到，又怎么有疼痛呢？

鲁谢　不管怎样，所有人都认为死亡的感觉是极度痛苦的。

木乃伊　仿佛死亡是一种强烈的感觉而不是恰恰相反。

鲁谢　可是，就灵魂的本质来讲，无论是倾向于伊壁鸠鲁（Epicurean）观点的人，还是持有传统观点的人，他们所有人，或者其中绝大部分人都同意我的说法，认为死亡就其本质上来说，是一种无可比拟的极度的痛。

木乃伊　好吧，请您谨代表我们向他们俩提一个问题：假如人类没有能力意识到他们的主要器官，或多或少地因为睡眠、昏睡、晕厥或其他原因而暂停运作，他又如何能意识到那些功能完全停止工作的那一瞬间，不是暂时地而是永久性地停止？再者，一种活着的感觉怎么能存在于死亡之中呢？实际上，就死亡本身的特质来说怎么可能是一种活着的感觉呢？当知觉不仅变得虚弱而稀少，而且被削弱到最低程度以至于知觉停止或被取消，你认为此时人还会有那么强烈的感觉吗？事实上，难道你认为这种感知的消亡本身会是一种强烈的感觉吗？你可以观察到，当死亡来临时，即便是那些迟早会死于剧烈且痛苦疾病的病人，在他们断气前，也会趋于平静安宁。于是乎，我们看到在减少到很少量时，他们所剩无几的生命不足以感觉疼痛。因而，疼痛比生命更早结束。请你代表我们把这一点告诉那些认为生命快终结时会因疼痛而死的人。

鲁谢　对于伊壁鸠鲁的支持者来说这些原因已经足够，但是，对于其他人来说却不尽然，他们根据灵魂的实质来判断。在过去我作过很多这方面的研究，将来也会继续作更多，尤其是听到死者说话和唱歌之后。他们相信死亡是一种灵魂从身体的剥离，所以，他们不明白的是，既然二者结合在一起，可以说二者如此粘合为一体最终共同组成一个完整的人，那么，在二者分开时，怎么会不遭受暴力以及难言的苦楚呢？

木乃伊　请你告诉我，灵魂是恰巧附着在身体的神经上，还是黏在肌肉上或是黏膜上了？所以灵魂离开时，必须把它撕开？抑或，它原本是身体的一部分，必须通过暴力才能将其扯开或断开？你难道不知道灵魂离开身体，仅仅因为它不被允许待在那里了？那里已经没有它的位置了，而不是因为有一种力量把它拽开或连根拔起？再请你告诉我，当灵魂进入身体时，它是否感到被粘在，或被紧紧系在，或如你所说粘合在身体上？那么，当它离开那具身体时，灵魂又怎能感到被分开，换言之，经历一种被暴力撕开的感觉？请相信灵魂进入和离开身体都是同样安静、容易和温柔的。

鲁谢　那么，如果死亡不是痛苦又会是什么？

木乃伊　是快乐而非其他。你要知道垂死好比入睡，不是瞬间发生而是循序渐进的。诚然，死亡的原因及类别不同，其过程自然或多或少，或大或小，不一而论。在最后时刻，死亡带来的既不是快乐也不是痛苦，至少不会比睡眠有更多的感觉。在死亡的前一刻，它不再产生疼痛，因为疼痛是生的感觉。那一刻，也就是死亡开始之初，人的感官是濒死的，就像最大程度上被弱化一样。它有可能是快乐的缘由，因为快乐并不是生的感受。事实上，人类很多快乐源于某种倦怠，因此即便是接近死亡，人的感觉依然感受到快乐，因为倦怠本身常常就是快乐，尤其是它解除你的痛苦。你很清楚，所有痛苦和不舒适的停止本身就是快乐。故而，由死亡产生的倦怠应该受到欢迎，因为它让人摆脱更大的折磨。就个人而言，在行将就木的时间里，我并没有关注自己是怎么感觉的，因为医生命令我不要消耗脑力。不过我依然记得我所经历的那种感觉，与人入睡时由倦怠产生的快乐类似。

其他木乃伊我们也似乎记得这些。

鲁谢　就依你们所言。不过，以前几乎所有曾和我讨论这个话题的人都持有完全不同的观点。不过呢，据我所知，他们毕竟没有亲身经历。现在请告诉我，在死亡时，在感受到快乐的同时，你想到你快要死了吗？这种快乐只是死亡的礼遇，或者你在想着别的什么事？

木乃伊　只要我还没死掉，我从未想过我不能避开这个危险。至少在我依然有思考能力的最后时间里，我一直期望我依然能再多活一到两个小时。我想很多人死的时候也这样想的。

其他木乃伊我们也经历了同样的事情。

鲁谢　的确。西塞罗曾说过没有人虚弱到他认为不能至少再多活一年。你怎么注意到灵魂最终离开身体了？请告诉我，你怎么知道你已经死了？他们不回答了。孩子们，能听到我说话吗？一刻钟应该已经到了。让我来摸一下他们的脉搏。他们又死掉了。他们没有机会再吓到我了。我还是回去睡觉吧。

克里斯托弗·哥伦布和佩德罗·古铁雷斯的对话

哥伦布　多美的夜晚，我的朋友。

古铁雷斯　确实美丽。不过，若是从陆地上看会更加美丽。

哥伦布　是的。这么说你也厌倦航行了啊。

古铁雷斯　不单单是航行。这次出海要远远比我预期的漫长，感觉有些吃不消了。虽说如此，请别以为我会像别人一样埋怨你。相反，无论此次航行你作什么决定，我都会一如既往地支持你。既然谈到了这个话题，我希望你能开诚布公、清晰无误地告诉我，你是否一如最初时那般坚定？你仍旧认为我们真的可以在世界的这边找到陆地和人类？抑或，这许多年里经历过无数次徒劳往返之后，你也开始产生怀疑？

哥伦布　坦白地讲，就像朋友之间吐露心迹那样，我承认我现在感觉有点不太确定。尤其本次航海中，多种迹象曾给我带来巨大的希望，但又最终化为失望——比如：在离开哥麦那岛（Gomera）起航后的几天里，有飞鸟从西方掠过我们的头顶。我一度认为这是附近有陆地的征兆。还有，日复一日，我逐渐发现，实际情况和我在出海前的设想与预测完全不同。原先设想的航海中可能遇到的各种事情均未发生。于是，我开始思考，是否那些预测误导了我——尽管它们看上去几乎无懈可击——也有可能，这其中最大的假设，即我们能在海洋的另一端找到陆地，也可能最终落空。诚然，该假设确实持之有故，言之有理。倘若一旦被推翻，那么，似乎除了依靠我们亲眼所见与亲耳所听到的东西，我们再不能相信人类的任何判断了。但另一方面，我还意识到，常常或大多数时候，理论往往与现实相悖。我质问自己，你如何能断定地球的每一部分都如出一辙呢？仅仅因为东半球是一半陆地一半水域，所以西半球也必须如此吗？你怎么肯定它就不可能是一片汪洋呢？或者排除全是陆地，以及陆地和海洋结合的可能性，也有可能是其他元素构成的？假使它和另一半一模一样，都有陆地和海洋，也有可能它那里根本就没有人烟？甚至根本无法居住？假定它像我们的半球一样住满了居民，你又如何能确定那里的居民是和我们一样是有理智的生物呢？即便这些存在，你也不能确定他们是人还是其他有智力的动物？即便是人类，也有可能和我们熟悉的人类并不一样。比如说，他们体型硕大，更加强壮、灵活，并拥有更高的与生俱来的智商和智慧，抑或拥有更为发达的文明以及人文与科学？我在反复问自己这些。毕竟，自然完全具备此项能力，她的成果如此不同，如此众多，以至于我们无法确定，在我们世界毫不知晓的远方，自然做过什么，又正在做什么，我们也应该质疑用后者为前者辩论是否是个严重的错误？设想未知世界中可能存在的事物——也许是部分也许是全部——是不为我们熟知且令人惊叹的，这并不会有悖于真理的概率。此刻，我们亲眼看到在这片水域，指南针偏离北极星且似乎指向西方——这是海员们以前从未见过的情形。不管我思索了多久，都无法得出满意的答案。尽管如此，我的言下之意不是说我们要相信古代人关于未知世界和未知水域的种种奇迹的传说。例如，汉诺（Hanno）寓言描述某些国家的夜晚充满了火焰，还有流入大海的烈焰之河。其实在本次航海中，我们的船员体会到，对遭遇的可怕奇观和令人忐忑的新事物的恐惧是多么苍白无力——当看到大片大片遮挡航线的、看上去像草地的海草时，他们曾自以为已经到达了可行驶海域的尽头。不过，为了回答你的问题，我的意思是我的假设只是基于最具可能性的推断。不仅我的判断如此，且如你所知，我还就此问题请教了诸多来自西班牙、意大利，还有葡萄牙的著名地理学家、天文学家、航海家，他们一致认为如此。当然，也有碰巧是错误的可能。因为，我反复说过，许多基于最好推理所推导出的结论并不能经得起实践的检验。尤其是涉及我们并不清楚的事情时，这种状况尤为常见。

古铁雷斯　那么，实际上，你是为了一个完全是猜测性的假设，拿自己以及同伴的生命做赌注？

哥伦布　确实如此。我不否认这点，但是，暂且不考虑这样的事实。如果每天都有人为了很小的缘由或毫无价值可言的事情去冒险——甚至都未经过思量——设想以下情况：假如你我以及我们的同伴不是身在大海中央的船只上，周遭一片未知的荒凉，置身于能想象的到的危险与不安定之地的话，那么我们会过什么样的生活？我们怎样打发时日？也许会更快乐？或者是相反，也许我们正陷于某种焦虑或困苦——或者感觉了无生趣？假如即便没有不安和危险又如何？如果只是安逸和快乐也就罢了，但如果是被烦恼痛苦缠绕，我倒觉得还不如作其他选择呢。不用我提醒，一旦我们的航行圆满结束，我们将获得多少荣耀和利益，而我们的希望也将得以实现。即便我们没有从中获益，在我看来仍然是极为有益的。它至少保证我们不再感觉无聊之极，让我们珍惜生命，让很多我们平时习以为常的事情变得珍贵。古人写道——你也许曾经读过或听过——那些失恋的人儿，从圣毛拉（Santa Maura）崖[过去曾被称作卢克迪亚（Leucadian）岩]纵身跳入大海，若侥幸不死，就会得到阿波罗（Apollo）的恩惠而不再受情爱所困。我不知道我们是否应该相信他们是因此而被治愈了，但是我很清楚地知道从这样的危险中逃脱之后，他们会暂时珍视以前觉得可憎的生命，即便未受到阿波罗的恩惠。或者，无论如何他们一定会比以前更加珍爱生命。根据我的判断，每次出海航行就好似卢克迪亚岩的一跳，它会产生大致相同的影响，且更持久。从这个层面上来讲，海上航行更优越些。一般人认为海员和士兵由于时常处于危险之中，所以他们往往不如普通人那般珍惜生命，但是我却认为，正是因为这个原因很少有人会比海员和士兵更爱惜自己的性命。正因为拥有才使得我们身在福中不知福。很多稀松平常的事情对于海员来说却异常珍贵，因为他们失去了这一切。有谁会把能够站在一小块陆地上当作一种福音？除了海员，尤其是我们的海员们，因为无法预料这次航行的结果，没有人会把发现一小块陆地当作最大的心愿。这个心愿在我们早晨醒来时就占据我们的头脑，到晚上入睡时仍萦绕在心头。如果我们碰巧看到远处山脉的一角、一片森林或类似的事物，我们都无法掩饰自己的喜悦。能够双脚踏上陆地，仅仅一想到我们又可以站在坚实的土地上，能够随意行走，都会让我们幸福上好几天。

古铁雷斯　你所言极是。假如你的猜想性假设如同你的实践所依靠的判断一样正确的话，毫无疑问，总有一天，我们会品尝到这种幸福的滋味。

哥伦布　尽管我也不敢保证它的确如此，但就我看来，我希望我们很快能享受到它。这几天，如你所知，测深线已经碰触到海底，它带上海面的信息于我是个好兆头。临近傍晚时，围绕在太阳周围的云层颜色和形状都与过去有些不同。还有空气，你也能感觉到似乎比过去和煦温暖。风也不再猛烈地、横冲直撞地刮个不停。相反，风向飘忽不定，似乎被什么东西阻隔了。还有，海面上飘来的芦苇很明显是不久前被割断的，上面还带着新鲜的红色果实。接下来，一群群的飞鸟……它们曾经误导过我，但是现在出现如此众多的迹象，并且日益愈增，我感觉我们可以相信这一次，尤其是很多鸟类看上去并不像海鸟。总之，我已经尽力克制自己，但是这些迹象确实让我有巨大的美好期许。

古铁雷斯　这次上帝让它变成现实吧。

雀之礼赞

在春天里的一个早晨，阿弥里斯（Amelius），一位独处的哲人，坐在他乡下房子的阴凉处，正捧着书阅读。他被四处里鸟儿的鸣叫声吸引，于是，开始慢慢倾听和思考，放下了手中的书。最后，他提笔坐下写下了下面的文字。

鸟儿生来就是这世上最快乐的生灵。之所以这么说，不是因为每当你听到看到鸟儿时，鸟儿所带来的快乐，而是因为鸟儿们本身就比其他动物更容易感受到快乐和欢悦。其他动物一般神色肃穆沉重，甚至很多看上去郁郁寡欢。它们极少会流露出快乐的表情。即便偶尔为之，也难以察觉、转瞬即逝。在多数高兴和享乐的时候，它们都不会显露出兴奋以及丝毫快乐的迹象。即使它们在享受着绿色田野，享受着广阔而美丽的景色，享受着明媚的阳光以及清澈甜美的空气，它们也毫不形之于色——只有野兔例外。据说在月光明亮的夜晚，尤其是月圆之夜，野兔们一起蹦跳玩耍，因这明亮而欢喜，色诺芬（Xenophone）如是写道。通常情况下，鸟儿们的动作和神情里总是表达出极大的欢悦。它们的存在之所以带给我们欢悦，是源于它们自身的体态和行为，是源于它们与生俱来的那种展示快乐和欢悦的特殊能力和性情——是一副看上去既不空洞也不具欺骗性的模样。它们会为经历过的每一次快乐和满足而歌唱。越是快乐和满足，越是唱得努力而投入。鉴于多数时间里它们都在歌唱，我们断定在正常情况下它们是快乐的、是享受生活的。也有人观察到鸟儿们在恋爱时期要比平时唱的更动听、更持久、也更频繁，但不能因此说除了恋爱，就没有其他驱使它们唱歌的快乐和满足的动因。我们能够清楚地观察到，鸟儿们在明媚且风平浪静的天气里远远比在阴暗且多变的天气里唱得更多。当暴风雨袭来时，它们保持沉默，如同任何受到惊吓时的反应那般。暴风雨结束后，它们会飞入空中唱歌，与同伴嬉戏。同样地，我们还观察到，每个清晨，它们总是醒来就歌唱。部分原因是新的一天所带来的欢快，部分原因是与别的动物一样，一晚的休息之后精力充沛所致。同理，鸟儿们嗜好青翠的草木、葱茏的峡谷、清澈透明的溪水和美丽的风景。有个现象非常有趣，凡是我们人类觉得美丽和谐的事物，鸟儿们也有相同的感受——从捕猎丛及类似地点里安置的捕鸟网、粘鸟胶到吸引鸟类的诱饵就可以确定这一点。乡间那些鸟儿们经常光顾、歌唱的地方，也可以体现这一点。与之相比，也许除去那些被人类驯服且与人类生活很久的动物，再没有其他动物，即便有也是极少数，能和人类共享这种地理上适宜和美丽的概念。无需惊奇，因为鸟类只有在自然中才能找到快乐。而现在的这些，许多被我们称之为自然的地方，实际上是人工的。诸如：耕种的田地，经过修剪整理的树木和其他植物，被河岸死死禁锢、只能流向固定方向的河流，以及其他许多事物都不具备在自然状态下的样子与特征。从而，每一处世代相传的、居住着文明人类的乡间——且不说人类密集而居的城镇，大体都是人工的，因而在很大程度上有别于自然应有的状态。关于这个问题，有人认为我们区域的鸟鸣声要远比原始野人时期的好听，声音更柔和，调奏更协调。于是乎他们得出结论，即便像鸟儿们那般自由自在无拘无束的动物，也会因为常常光顾人类的居住场所而习得了些许文明。

暂且不论他们是否说了真话，就自然能同时赋予鸟类歌唱与飞翔的先决条件就很神奇了。有些人的工作就是依靠声音取悦其同类。一般来说他们要站在高处，如是，声音才会传得更远，才会有更多的人听到。因而，空气作为传递声音的元素，应该驻有有乐感会唱歌的生物。我们的确从鸟儿的鸣叫中——依我之见，我们人类并不强于其他动物——获得了极大的安慰与快乐。我想这种快乐的感受，不是源于鸟儿们甜美的声音，不管其鸣叫多么婉转动听、千变万化、此唱彼和、相互呼应，而是源于歌曲中通常会自然而然地含有的欢快，尤其是存在于鸟类的鸣叫中的那种欢快。正可谓，好似鸟类感到愉悦和舒适时发出的一种笑声。

如是，在某些方面，鸟儿和人类共享欢笑的能力——这是其他动物所不具备的特权。实则，有人认为既然人被定义为聪慧善思的动物，也可将人充分地描绘为会笑的动物，因为他们认为笑是一个并不比理智更逊色的人类标记。这一点确实令人咋舌。虽然人类本是所有生灵中最受折磨、最痛苦的生物，却独独拥有笑的能力，而别的生物却不具备此项能力。另外值得称奇的是我们使用这项特权的方式。比如：有些人遭遇严重的事故，有些人悲恸欲绝，有些人觉得生活了无生趣，他们坚信自己没有任何优点，也无力享受一点快乐，感到万念俱灰——然而，我们发现他们会笑。其实，人们越是知道世事的浮华，越是理解生命终归是不幸福的，其期望值就会越低，也就越发不能适应对快乐的享受。越是如此，人类反而越是易于发笑。然而，笑的普遍本质以及它的内在原则和模式，以及其在头脑中所占据的部分，是很难被定义和限定的——除非承认笑是某种暂时疯狂的表现，是某种胡言乱语、神志不清的行为。因为人类从来不会感到满足，也不曾在任何事物中找到真正的快乐，所以人类并不具备一个合理的、正当的发笑的原因。研究人类如何或在何种条件下首次使用这个特权一定会很有趣。毫无疑问，在原始时代，人类和其他动物一样，通常十分严肃，甚至看上去郁郁寡欢。对此，我的观点是，这个世界里的笑出现于哭之后——这个问题是毫无争议的——不过，在第一次发现和体验笑之前一定有一段漫长的时光。在此期间，母亲不会冲着婴儿微笑，婴儿也不会回应母亲一个微笑——如维吉尔（Virgil）所言。因为时至今日，至少在有人类文明的地区，人出生后不久就会笑，多半是因为他周围的人在笑的缘故。我倾向于认为人类首次发笑的原因和时机可能是源于醉酒——这一点是人类种族的遗传特征。醉酒早在人类取得任何文明进步之前就已经产生了。实际上，我们知道很难找到一种原始人类没有酒，没有其他把自己灌醉的方式方法，没有无节制喝酒的习惯。切勿惊讶，因为人类远远比其他动物不快乐，因此人类比其他任何动物都热衷于在思想麻木中找到快乐，转而在忘掉自我中，或者说在生活的某个中断里找到快乐。是故，通过停止或者削减自身对痛苦的认识和感知，他们从中获得极大裨益。谈到笑这个问题，我们观察到，人类虽然在其他时段里多数神情严肃而悲伤，但在醉酒之后，却会频频发笑——不停地说话、唱歌、有悖于他们平日的习性。这些问题我会放在我即将撰写的笑的历史中去详加讨论。在完成笑的起源之后，我打算再写笑的经历、变迁和直至如今的命运——在现代，笑拥有过去所无法比拟的尊重和影响力，并在文明国度之中占据一席之地。笑所扮演的功能，在某种意义上取代了美德、正义、荣誉以及其他以往所扮演的角色，从多个方面限制，甚至是吓退人类的不良企图。现在，就鸟儿们的歌唱作一番归纳。我认为我们通常会因为看到或得知别人的快乐而感同身受——妒忌的情况除外——自然很明智地设定鸟儿的歌唱是一种欢悦与笑声的表达，因此人人喜爱；但是人类的歌唱和笑声，则要考虑到其他人的感受，应该不干扰他人。自然很聪明地确保地面上和空中挤满了能够发出响亮和严肃声响的动物，似乎是在咏唱宇宙之生命的赞歌，激励其他动物随之欢欣鼓舞，由此而营造出不间断，却是虚假的一派众生和乐的景致。

鸟儿们之所以比别的动物更快乐或更能够展示快乐不是没有深层原因的。正如我最初所示，自然确实使鸟类更加适合享受快乐和幸福。鸟儿们不会遭受无聊之扰。每一刻它们都在变换位置，从一个区域换到另一个区域，不管其间的距离多远。从最低点飞到空中的最高点，也不过是在瞬间内就能轻松自如地完成的事情。在其生命历程中，它们看到并体验到的事情数量众多且类型各异。它们时时刻刻在锻炼身体，并有充足的户外运动。所有其他动物在吃饱喝足之后，总是安静而懒散地躺着。没有任何一种动物，除去鱼类和一些飞虫，会单单因为愉悦而撒欢奔跑。同理，原始人——只要每日能喂饱自己就不会多走一步，他所需做的工作通常简短且简单。除了暴风雨来临，或者被野兽追逐或其他类似状况之外——原始人大多喜欢安逸和无动于衷。他整日无声无息地、无所事事地呆坐在破旧的小茅草屋里打发时间，要么待在户外、石缝里、悬崖上或岩石的洞穴里。与之相反，鸟儿们很少长时间地停留在一个地方。它们不停地飞来飞去不是因为需要什么，而是为了快乐而飞翔。有时，它们从自己居住的海边飞上几百英里，在傍晚时分又飞回原地。即便是在一个地方作短暂停留，你也不会看见它们安静地坐着。它们总是左转右转，一会儿踱步，一会儿弯腰，一会儿伸伸脖子，一会儿摇一摇，活泼敏捷地振翅，动作迅疾无以言状。总之，鸟儿从破壳而出的那一刻直至死亡，除去中间的睡眠时间，它不会停息一分钟。以上观察的结果是，很明显，从本质上来讲，其他动物包括人类的正常状态是休息，而鸟类则是运动。

与上述品质及外在条件相呼应的是内在条件，即：头脑条件——这点促使它们比别的动物更加适合感受幸福。它们的听力极为敏锐，它们的视力是我们难以想象的发达和完美。具备了这些能力，它们便可以整天享受层出不穷、千变万化的景象：从高高的云霄里，它们能一眼看到大片开阔的区域，并同时能用眼睛清晰地区分出不同地方。这一点也是人类难以理解的。从此现象中，我们推测它们一定拥有强大的力量、活力和无限的想象力。鸟儿们的这种想象力不属于那种深沉、热烈、疾风暴雨，如但丁（Dante）和塔索（Tasso）那般的想象力——后者如同一个致命的礼物，是最糟糕的永恒痛苦与焦虑的根源——鸟儿们拥有的是一种丰富的、变化的、轻盈的、不稳定的、如孩童般的想象力，是愉快和快乐思想的取之不竭的源泉，是自然赋予生物的最慷慨的、最伟大的、最有用处的礼物。正因如此，鸟儿们拥有无限的之于精神愉悦息息相关的能力，并同时缺少有毒害的、痛苦的东西。由于它们的外在生活异常丰富，带动其内在生活也非常丰富，由此产生的优势和快乐非常类似于孩童的那般——绝非是成人一般会有的拙劣和痛苦。因为鸟儿们的活泼和外在的好动性明显展露出与儿童类似的一面，所以我们可以合理地假设它们与儿童的内心也很相似。假如孩童般的幸福可以出现在其他年龄段里，而其他年龄段里的疾病不会比儿童时期的疾病更严重，也许人类就有理由慢慢忍受生命的种种了。

依我之见，从某些方面看，鸟类本质的完美性超越其他动物。譬如，当我们考虑到鸟类在视力以及听力方面都远远超越其他动物，根据生物的自然法则，这两项属于主要感官。于是，可以得出这样的结论：鸟类的本性比其他生物的本性更完美。此外，正如我们所见，其他动物自然而然地倾向于休息，而鸟类则倾向于运动——运动要比休息更富有活力。生命实际上是由运动构成的，而鸟类比别的动物具有更多的户外活动——另外，如果视力和听力优于其他动物，这两项也是鸟类们最突出的能力，是否当作生物最典型的特征？因为这两项能力本身就很鲜明且动性强，并且其带给动物的习惯以及内外在效果都很显著。考虑到上述一些情况，结论是鸟类比其他动物拥有更多的外在和内在生命。现在，假如生命的完美多于不完美——至少在生物里如此——假如生命越有活力就是完美的话，那么，结论就是鸟儿的本性更完美。在这一点上，我们不要忘了鸟儿同样能忍耐极度的寒冷和炎热，穿梭在两者之间甚至不用太多时间过渡一下。事实上，我们常常看到，几乎是在瞬间，他们已然从地面冲向凌霄，几乎相当于是在极寒的地区，并且它们能在很短的时间里穿越多种气候。

阿克那里翁（Anacreon）曾许愿他愿意变成一面镜子，这样他的爱人就可以天天看他；他愿意变成一件裙子，这样就可以穿在她身上；他愿意变成油膏擦拭她的身体；他愿意变成水供她沐浴；他愿意变成胸带，这样她就可以把他紧紧抱在胸前；他愿意变成一串项链挂在她脖子上；他愿意变成鞋子，至少她会用脚挤压他——同样地，我也希望可以有一会儿变成一只飞鸟，这样我就可以体验到它们生命中的满足与快乐。

伟大的野公鸡之歌

某些希伯来学者和作家们声称在天与地之间，或者确切地说是一半在空中，一半在地面，生活着一只野公鸡。它脚踏地面，喙与鸡冠顶着天空。你可以在那些作家的作品里读到对它这些特征的描述，此外，这个体形庞大的公鸡还具备思考的能力。否则，诚然，便无异于鹦鹉，说着不知被谁教会的人类的语言。实则，有一首歌名为Scir detarnegòl bara letzafra，即：伟大的野公鸡之晨歌，其原版为希伯来文。这首歌的用语混合了秘术家用语、塔古姆用语、犹太教法学博士语言、犹太教神秘哲学语言以及犹太法典语言，它被写在了一块旧羊皮纸上。我尽力理解并翻译成下列我们所使用的文字。在此期间，我为之付出了艰辛的劳动并同时请教了若干犹太教祭司、犹太教神秘哲学者、神学家、法理学家及犹太哲学家。目前我尚不确定的是，这只公鸡是时不时地吟唱这首歌还是在每日清晨吟唱，抑或仅唱过一次？有谁经常听到这首歌或曾经听到过这歌声？歌词语言是否属于公鸡语言？这首歌是否是从另一种语言翻译过来的？就目前的版本，我已经穷尽一切可能使之忠实于原文，我认为最好使用散文体而不是诗体，尽管事实上它是一首诗。其行文中有不连贯之处，偶尔也会有浮夸语体，但这些不该由我负责，因为译本首先是忠于原文的。在此处，需要符合东方语言的习惯，尤其是要符合他们的诗人标准。

起来吧，凡人，苏醒！新的一天又开始了。真理回归世界，虚假的影像离去。起来，重拾生活之重担，从虚假之国回归真理世界。

在这一刻，每个人都在头脑里回顾并审视他生命中的全部想法，回想他的计划、努力、需要处理的事情，并自行想象一下在新的一天里可能会遇到的快乐与痛苦。每个人都会在此时更加强烈地渴望找到快乐的期望和愉悦的思想。当然没什么人真的实现了上述愿望。因为苏醒对于每个人来说是不幸的。可怜的人儿刚刚醒来，马上就落入各自不幸福的手中。最甜蜜的事情是睡眠，由快乐与希望相结合带来的睡眠——这种状态会安然无恙地一直持续到天明，之后，它们就会消失不见。

如果凡人的睡眠是永恒的，是与生命等同的话；如果在启明星照耀下，所有活物在地球各处以最无声的方式憔悴着，没有任何活动痕迹：草地上没有牛儿在哞哞地叫，森林里没有野兽在咆哮，天空中没有鸟儿在歌唱，乡间没有蝴蝶在低语、蜜蜂在嗡嗡叫；没有任何声音，没有任何活动的迹象，除了水涨起、风刮起和暴风雨袭来；那么，这个宇宙也就真的毫无用处了。那时是否比会比现在痛苦更多，幸福更少？我问你，哦，太阳，白日的主宰和我们清醒时的保护者，到目前为止你所历经的多少个世纪里，在升起又落下之间，你是否曾见到过一个生物曾经幸福地生活过？截至目前你所见到的凡人无数的成就里，你是否认为至少有一个人实现了他的目标：满足感，即他从他的成功中获得了持久或暂时的满足？你现在是否看见，或者说你曾看见这四海之内可有幸福的存在？幸福到底居住在哪块田野，哪片森林，哪座山峰，哪条峡谷，是在有人居住的地方还是在不毛之地，还是它藏在你的光芒所能照射到并赋予温暖的众多星球中的某个上面？也许，幸福躲在你的视线之外，藏在幽深的洞穴里，也许在地心或海底深处？什么样的活物有幸知道幸福是什么？哪种植物，或其他任何被你赋予生命的生物体，有哪些被赐予幸福，有哪些被剥夺了幸福，又有哪些植物或动物知晓幸福？还有你自己，就像一个不知疲倦的巨人，从不睡觉和休息，日夜急速行进在你的既定行程上，你是幸福的还是不幸福的？

凡人快醒来！你还在受生的束缚。迟早会有一天，无论是外界力量，还是内在力量，都无法把你从沉睡中唤醒。彼时，你将永远地、尽情地安息。你尚未被允许死去。仅仅是间或，你被允许暂时诈死一小会儿。因为若非时不时暂停一会儿，生命就难以为续。倘若过度渴求这种本来就短暂易逝的浅眠，其本身就是致命的，将会招致永久长眠。生活就是如此，为了能够忍受生活的种种，我们必须时不时地放下它，获得一点喘息的机会，用死亡的滋味或几乎是少许死亡让我们重新振作起来。

事物最本质的一面似乎是以死亡为真正且唯一的目的。一切存在源于虚无，因为不存在就不会有死亡。可以确定的是存在的最终目的不是幸福，因为没有什么是幸福的。诚然，活着的生物每做一项工作都是以此为目的的，但是没有一项能带给他们幸福。在他们整个的生命历程里，他们奋斗、克己、遭受痛苦，无一不是在苦苦追索自然制定的这个唯一的目标：死亡。

正常情况下，一天里的清晨是生物们最容易忍受的时段。在苏醒的一刻里，很少有人头脑里充斥着快乐愉悦的思想。但是很快，几乎人人会产生和形成某些快乐的思想。因为在那个时段里，人的头脑总是极易高兴的，即便没有任何特定或特殊的原因，它会比一天内其他时段都更适于忍受生活的不幸。因此，当一个人入睡时充满了绝望，在第二天醒来时他又重新找到了希望，即便这种希望来得毫无缘由。很多不幸和个人困扰、很多恐惧和悲痛的根源会在此时显得要比头天晚上渺小许多。甚至，前一天的煎熬会在今天被嘲笑，会被斥之为幻想和空想的结果。夜晚被比作老年，而早晨被比作青年，总是从容而自信；夜晚则是悲伤的、沮丧的、充满了各种不幸的先兆。但是正如人的青春那般短暂，凡人每天所体验的早晨时光也是极为短促且转瞬即逝，很快白天也会变得年迈不堪。

尽管是生命中的最好部分，我们的盛年依旧是痛苦的。实际上，哪怕仅仅是这丁点幸运也会在短时间内消失殆尽，以致人们很快发现诸多逐渐衰老的迹象。他还未曾体验到生命的完美，还未曾感受到和知晓生命的力量，就已经开始减弱。但凡世间的生灵，他们的绝大部分生命是在慢慢枯萎中度过。自然在其所有的创造里都毫不掩饰地指向了死亡：这正是为什么衰老如此显著、如此清晰、如此长久、如此普遍的原因。宇宙的每一部分都在不知疲倦地奔向死亡，速度迅猛且毫不迟疑。似乎只有宇宙本身不受衰败和凋萎的侵蚀。因为假如在秋天和冬天里，它的生命变得虚弱和衰老；那么，到春天时就一定又青春焕发。当然，就如凡人每天清晨都会感觉年轻一些，尽管实际上每天都在变老，直至吐出最后一口气。宇宙也一样，每年年初重新变得年轻，尽管它其实在不断衰老。总有一天宇宙和自然本身也将不复存在。就好似曾经无比伟大的人类王国和帝国，以及该时代的不朽成就，虽然辉煌一时，但终究会被遗忘。这整个世界也如是这般，所有生命体经历无数变迁和灾难之后，最终不会留下一丝痕迹。取而代之的将是无边的沉寂和深邃的静谧。如此一来，宇宙生命所带来的惊人的、令人不安的秘密，会在它被宣布和了解之前就已经消失得无影无踪了。

哥白尼的任务

第一幕

第一时辰和太阳

第一时辰　早上好，阁下。

太阳　早上好，或者该说，晚上好。

第一时辰　马车为您备好了。

太阳　好的。

第一时辰　启明星已经升起一段时间了。

太阳　她想来就来，想走就走。

第一时辰　您这是什么意思呢，阁下？

太阳　我的意思是你别来烦我。

第一时辰　可是，阁下，夜晚已经持续了很久，不能再拖延下去了。倘若再行耽搁，阁下，就会有奇怪的事情发生。

太阳　无论发生什么，我都不打算动一下。

第一时辰　哦，阁下，这是怎么啦？您感觉不舒服吗？

太阳　不，没有，我没有感觉不舒服。我就是不想动。你呢，去忙自己的事吧。

第一时辰　要是您不配合的话，我怎么忙呢？我是白日的第一个时辰，要是阁下您不能发发慈悲像往常一样出来的话，这一天会变成什么样子？

太阳　如果不能属于白天，那你还是归属夜晚吧——要不就让夜晚时辰加一次班，你和你的白日伙伴们就可以休息了。因为，你知道吗？我已经厌倦了每天不停地旋转只为照亮那些生活在一小撮泥土上的小生物们——他们才那么一丁点儿，我这么好的视力几乎都看不到呢。今晚，我决定不再因为这点小事麻烦了。假如人类需要光线的话，他们可以生火照明或找些其他途径解决。

第一时辰　但是，阁下，您让那些可怜的人儿们怎么找呢？若是他们的灯笼和那么多蜡烛整日点燃着，可是非常昂贵的花销啊。假如他们已经找到某种非常便宜的气体，可以用来烧火、照明街道、点亮房间、商店、阁楼和其他地方的话，那么我会觉得事情还不算太糟糕，但是，实际情况是，距人们发现这种气体之前还有差不多三百年的时间呢。在此期间，他们会耗尽燃油、蜡烛、树脂和动物脂。最后，他们就没有什么可供燃烧的东西了。

太阳　他们可以去抓些萤火虫和发光虫用来照明。

第一时辰　那他们怎样御寒呢？若是没有阁下您的襄助，森林中的所有树木都不足以保证他们取暖。他们还会被饿死，因为地球不再结果子了。在短短几年内，那些可怜的动物种族将会消失。接下来的一段时间里，他们在地球上的一片黑暗中四处摸索着，找寻可以吃的食物和取暖之用。最终，没有任何可以吞咽的食物，最后一星火焰熄灭，那时他们所有人就会在黑暗中死去，就像冻僵的岩水晶一样。

太阳　我为什么要管这些？我，难道说，是人类种族的奶妈吗，还是负责给他们准备及烹饪食物的厨子？我为什么要关心那些几百万英里之外的我根本看不到的小东西们，就因为没有我的光芒他们看不见，也不能取暖吗？那么，如果说，我必须成为供他们取暖的加热器或火炉的话，合理的状况是他们一家人想取暖就应该自己到火炉边来，而不是火炉围着他们的房子旋转。因此，如果地球需要我的光芒，就请她自己围着我转或者想些办法得到它。就我个人而言，我不需要地球的任何东西，也不需要去照看她。

第一时辰　阁下您的意思是说，假如我理解无误的话，现在地球应该做您以前一直在做的事情？

太阳　是的，现在，从现在开始到永远。

第一时辰　阁下您说的无疑很有道理。况且，您可以随意而为，不过，还是请您考虑一下，如果您建立新的世界秩序的话，会有多少美丽的事物因此而毁于一旦？白天再也没有美丽的金色战车，也没有那些美丽的战马，它们通常会在大海里沐浴。更别提及其他的细枝末节了。就连我们这些时辰们也不会在天上拥有一席之地了，我们会从天庭侍女变成陆地女子。根据我的预测，除非我们变成青烟才得以重返天庭。即便如此，问题是如何说服地球开始转动呢？想必会很难，因为她尚不习惯这么做。她会觉得这么不停地跑下去、这么浪费力气很奇怪，以前她可从未曾离开她的位置半步。假如阁下您好像都冒出了偷懒的念头，我听说地球并没有比过去勤快一丁点儿啊。

太阳　在这种情况下，需求会激励她，会逼迫她不得不去跑去跳。最快速也是最确定的方法就是找到一位诗人或自然哲学家，去劝说地球移动。万一劝说失败，也可以强行迫使她移动。从长远来看，这种事情主要由诗人们和自然哲学家们负责。实际上，他们几乎能胜任任何事情。过去，那些诗人们（那时，我年轻尚且听话），他们用美丽的颂歌诱导我——我这么又肥又大的一个人——心甘情愿地去做那项围着一小堆儿沙子拼命疯跑的极度愚蠢的工作，并把它当作一种运动或一种高尚的锻炼。现在我的年纪大些了，我开始转向信仰哲学。做每件事时，我要看它是否有用而不是漂不漂亮。诗人们的伤感情怀，不是让我作呕，就是让我忍俊不禁地大笑。在做每件事前，我总要三思而后行。我发现劳神劳力的生活并不比舒适悠闲的生活更可取——因为这样的生活并不会产生值得你费神费力的成果（在这个世界上，成果一文不值）——我下定决心把劳累和不舒适留给别人。至于我，就安静地留在家里无所事事。我的观念之所以发生了转变，除了部分出于年龄的原因，还如我之前所说的是由于哲学家们而改变的——这些人目前已经开始得势，并且有如日中天的趋势。假如我希望地球能够移动并取代我奔跑的话，诗人在某一方面会比自然哲学家、甚至科学家更能胜任。诗人们，通过讲一两个故事，就能让人们相信世界上的事情真的有价值、很重要，是美丽和愉快的。他们创造出一千种愉快的希望，借此劝诱人们努力和拼命工作。反之，哲学家则会起到劝阻作用。既然哲学家已经占据上风，我担心现在地球也会像我一样不会任诗人摆布。假如没有人听诗人的话，他自然就束手无策了。因此，我认为最好还是请自然哲学家或科学家来帮忙。尽管哲学家们通常不适合也不愿意劝说他人工作，不过在这个极端情况下，他们也许会尽力作些意料之外的努力——除非地球决定与其如此大费周章还不如直接毁灭合适——在那种情况下，我也不能说她做错了。够了，让我们静观其变吧。现在，去做这个：到地球上去，或者派你的一个姊妹，或任何一个你觉得合适的人跑一趟。如果她发现任何一位自然哲学家，站在屋外新鲜的空气里，正在研究天空和星体——因为我们可以很合理地推断她一定会找到这么一位，因为夜已经太长了——不要耽搁，把他带上来，扛在肩上，火速带来见我。我会说服他去做该做的事情。你明白了吗?

第一时辰　是。阁下。我马上照办。

第二幕

（站在阳台上，用一个小纸筒观察东方的天空——因为彼时还没有发明天文望远镜）

哥白尼　真是难以置信。莫不是所有的钟表都坏了？否则太阳早在一小时之前就应该升起来了。可是东方仍看不到一丝光亮，尽管天空如镜面般清澈透明。所有的星星在闪烁着，似乎仍在夜里。现在，赶紧去查阅《天文学大成》和萨克罗博斯科（Sacrobosco）的相关书籍，问问他们是否能就此现象解释一番。我常听人说朱庇特会在夜间和底比斯王的妻子幽会。我还记得我最近读过的一本由一位西班牙人撰写的现代书。书里提及秘鲁人说在古时候，他们的国家曾经有一个特别漫长的夜晚，实际上，是一个永远不会结束的夜。最后，太阳从一个叫作的的喀喀（Titicaca）湖里出来了。此前，我一直以为这是一派胡言。像所有有理性的人一样，我确信它的确如此。现在，我意识到科学和理智根本一文不值嘛。我决定相信那些传言以及类似的东西很有可能完全是真实的。实际上，我正准备去我能找到的所有湖泊，还有沼泽看一看，看我是否能碰巧把太阳捞上来，但是，我听到这震耳欲聋的声响是什么——似乎是一只巨鸟拍打翅膀的声音？

第三幕

最后时辰和哥白尼

最后时辰哥白尼，我是最后时辰。

哥白尼　最后时辰？好吧，我也无能为力。假如，如果可能的话，请留给我足够的时间写遗嘱以及安排身后的事宜——在我死之前。

最后时辰你是什么意思，“死”吗？我不是生命的最后时辰。

哥白尼　那你是谁，是每日祈祷时间的最后时辰吗？最后时辰我敢确定较其他时段你更喜欢最后时辰——当你在唱诗班里时。

哥白尼　不过，你怎么知道我是一位咏礼司铎？你怎么认识我的？你刚才在呼唤我的名字。

最后时辰我刚刚从前面的街上打听到你的信息。总之，我是白天的最后时辰。

哥白尼　啊，我明白了。第一个时辰病了，所以我们看不到白天。

最后时辰请允许我说下去。白天再也不会来了——不仅是今天，还有明天，永远不会再来了，倘若您不打算做些什么的话。

哥白尼　真有意思！似乎我的工作就是造白天似的！

最后时辰我会告诉您怎么做。但是首先您必须立即跟我去我的主人太阳的府邸。路上我会详细解释。我们到达后，太阳阁下将会亲自跟您解释一下。

哥白尼　好吧。但如果我没理解错的话，这趟旅行会很漫长。我怎么才能带够充足的食物，以保证我在到达前的几年内不会被饿死？况且，我不认为太阳阁下的土地会生产什么能供吃一餐的东西。

最后时辰别担心这些。您不会在太阳府邸待太久。这趟旅行也仅仅是瞬间的事——因为，恐怕您还不知道，我是个精灵。

哥白尼　可我只是个凡胎肉体。

最后时辰好吧。您完全不需要担心这些事情，您又不是一位玄学哲学家。来吧，坐在我肩上，看我的。

哥白尼　好的。出发……不知道事情最后会是什么样。

第四幕

哥白尼和太阳

哥白尼　您好，最明亮先生。

太阳　请你见谅，哥白尼，我没法请你坐下，因为我们没有椅子。我们的谈话很快就会结束。从我的仆人那里，你一定听说你此行所为何事了。我个人认为——以及我从侍女们那里了解到的你的能力——我想你完全能胜任这项工作。

哥白尼　先生，我觉得这份工作困难重重。

太阳　困难不会吓跑你这类人的。事实上，人们常说困难只会增加勇敢者的勇气。那么，有什么困难呢？

哥白尼　首先，不论自然哲学和科学的力量有多么强大，我不能确定它们可以强大到足够说服地球去运转而不是舒舒服服地坐着，或是说服地球去工作和劳累而不是悠闲地待着。尤其考虑到我们这个时代并不是一个英雄主义时代。

太阳　那么，如果不能说服她的话，就强迫她。

哥白尼　我很乐意一试，我的光明先生。假如我是海格立斯或者是罗兰（Roland），而不是一个从沃尔姆斯（Worms）来的小小咏礼司铎的话。

太阳　这两者又有什么关系？听说你们中有一位古算术家过去曾说，只要他能站在世界之外，毫无疑问他就能移动天空和地球？现在，你不需要移动天空，你现在站在地球之外，因此，如果你不比那位先贤更笨的话，你就能移动地球，不用管她乐不乐意。

哥白尼　我亲爱的先生，我可以这么做。但是我需要一个撬棍。这支撬棍会很长，长到不仅是我，就连您自己，不论您有多么富有，都没有能力支付所消耗的材料及人工的费用。另一个更严重的困难是下列问题：事实上，这个问题更像是一团乱麻。截至目前为止，地球一直占据宇宙第一的位置，也就是，中心位置。您也知道，她一直是一动不动地坐着，除了环视一下宇宙的其他星球，基本无事可做。其他或大或小，或明亮或暗淡的星球，从她头顶、身边或脚下转过，每个都行色匆匆，如此紧张，如此激烈，以至于我们即便想上一想都会觉得头晕目眩。如此，一切似乎都是为她服务的。宇宙看上去好像一个皇庭，地球似乎端坐在宝座上，其他星球围在她周围，像朝臣、护卫、仆人，各自忙着自己的活计。正因如此，地球一直认为自己是宇宙的女王。实际上，假如情况仍同过去一样的话，我们不能说她的想法是毫无道理的。事实上，我不能否认她的这一想法是建立在良好的基础之上的。那么，我再告诉您人类又会有什么反应。我们认为，并将永远认为，我们自己才是地球所有生灵中第一个同时也是最重要的生物。我们每一个人，即便衣衫褴褛，即便只啃着一小块干面包，无一不觉得自己如国王般重要。这个国王不是君士坦丁堡的君主，德国的君主，或半个地球的君主——例如过去的罗马皇帝——而是整个宇宙的君主，太阳的君主，所有行星的君主，也是所有看得见的、看不见的恒星们的君主。他还是万物之源，是所有恒星、行星，还有阁下您及一切的最终渊源。但是现在，假如我们要求地球放弃现在的中心位置，让她奔跑、转动，不停地忙碌，去做那些到目前为止只有其他星球才做的事情；最后，她会变为其他星球中的一员——这就意味着逼迫地球陛下以及人类的皇帝陛下们禅位，并放弃王国——他们只剩下司空常见的破衣烂衫和凄楚悲凉。

太阳　你到底在说什么呀？我亲爱的尼古拉（Nicholas）神父，也许你是害怕这个行为会招致叛国罪？

哥白尼　不是这样的，最明亮先生。要是我没有记错的话，没有任何一部法典、法律精要、公法丛书、帝国法、民法、自然法中曾提及过此类叛国罪。我的意思是说我们的这项任务不像乍看上去那样，是简单的物质层面的事情。它的后果不单单显示在物理层面上，因为它将会颠覆尊卑秩序阶梯上的所有阶层以及事物的现存秩序。它将会扭转生物们的目标，由此将会引起玄学中前所未有的巨大变革，并波及其他任何涉及思辨方面知识的领域。因此，如果人类有能力并且愿意进行理性思考的话，他们会发现自己和之前的自己完全不同，并且和他们之前自己对自我的认识也完全不一样。

太阳　孩子，这些事都不会吓倒我。因为我既尊重玄学也尊重物理学，同样也尊重化学——或者如果你愿意还有通灵术。人类应该对他们现有的样子感到满足。假使他们不喜欢现在的样子，那就让他们继续进行他们颠三倒四的推理，继续反驳事实性证据，毕竟在这些方面他们都得心应手。如是，他们还会继续把自己假想成想象中的样子——男爵、公爵、皇帝或其他什么他们喜欢的样子。虽然这些会带给他们安慰，但是他们的评判不会对我有丝毫影响。

哥白尼　好的。我们先不谈人类和地球。但是，请考虑一下，我的最明亮先生，我们试想一下其他星球会怎样。当他们看到地球变成他们中的一员，做着和他们同样的事，他们不会愿意再这么光秃秃和灰扑扑的，像以前一样荒凉和凄惨——凭什么地球可以有这么多装饰？他们也同样想拥有河流、海洋、山脉、植被以及动物和居民，因为他们看不到自己为什么要低于地球的级别？宇宙也将会发生一个巨大变革：每一处都会有无数新家庭像雨后春笋般冒出来。

太阳　那你就让他们冒出来呗。让他们自由发展。我的光和热已经足够他们所有人使用——不会增加多余的费用。宇宙有足够的储备供他们吃饭、穿衣、居住，并慷慨地善待他们而不会因此而负债。

哥白尼　但是，最明亮先生，请再仔细考虑一下。您将会看到另外一个混乱局面。那些星星们，当他们看到你坐着，不是坐在板凳上而是坐在御座上，四周围绕着这么美丽的朝廷和众多的行星——他们，也同样地，不会满足于要求坐下休息，还会要求上位。为了统治需要，必须有臣民。因此，他们会要求像您一样——每人都有自己的行星。这些新的行星也同样需要像地球一样被装饰和被居住。此处，我不再向您提及可怜的人类了——与当前世界相比他们已经无足轻重。无以计数的世界蜂拥而出，连银河里最小的星星都拥有了行星，未来将会变成什么？即便我们只考虑您的得失，让我来说到目前为止，您的位置至少是第二位的，仅次于地球——没有人能和您匹敌，因为其他星星绝没有胆量和您相提并论，但是，在这个新宇宙世界里，您有很多同级，因为它们也有自己的世界。请慎之又慎，以确保您所做的这种改变不会损伤你的尊严。

太阳　你难道不记得你们的凯撒大帝曾说过，在他穿越阿尔卑斯（Alps）山脉时，他碰巧路过一些可怜的野人的茅草屋——他说他宁愿做那个茅草屋的第一人也不愿做罗马的第二人？同理，我宁愿做我的世界里的第一人，也不愿意做宇宙的第二名。我改变现状的初衷不是野心，而仅仅是对安宁的热爱。更确切地说，是对懒散的热爱。因此，我不在乎有没有同级，也不在乎是在第一位还是最后一位。我和西塞罗（Cicero）不同，我感兴趣的是悠闲而不是尊严。

哥白尼　最明亮先生，只要我力所能及，我会尽全力助您实现您的悠闲，不过，恐怕即便我帮您实现这个愿望，它也不会持久。首先，我几乎可以肯定用不了多少年，您就得被迫和水井里的滑轮一样，或像石磨一样转个不休——尽管您没有移动位置。进而，我怀疑最终，也就是迟早，您会发现您不得不再次奔跑。我不是说绕着地球跑。不过，您又不会在乎这些？也许您的自转就是您再次奔跑的原因。好了，即使如此，不管困难如何、如何筹措，如果您还是坚持先前的决定，我将会鼎力相助。如若本次方案最终无果，您要相信我确实能力欠佳——而别说我并不是个果敢的人。

太阳　好的，我的哥白尼，请试一下。

哥白尼　只剩下一个困难了。

太阳　告诉我，是什么？

哥白尼　我不想因为这件事，而把自己像凤凰那样活活烧死。如果真的发生了，我感觉我肯定不可能像那只鸟似的从灰烬中重生。因此，从现在起我不会再出现在阁下您面前了。

太阳　听着，哥白尼，你知道在你们的哲学家和科学家还未出生的时候——我的意思是说——当诗人占据主导位置的时候——我曾经是个预言家。现在请你让我最后一次预测未来，根据我古代的记忆，我希望你能相信我。从而，我会告诉你之后发生了什么。即使那些支持你的人被烧焦了或遭遇类似情况，但是你自己，如我能看到的，不会因此而受苦。假如你想更安全一些的话，遵循这个建议：请你把这本你撰写的书献给教皇。这样，我保证你甚至不会失去你的祭司位置。

年历小贩和一名路人的对话

小贩　年历，新年历。新日历，您需要年历吗，先生？

路人　新年年历？

小贩　是的，先生。

路人　你觉得这个新年会很快乐吗？

小贩　当然，先生，肯定的。

路人　跟去年一样？

小贩　比去年好，好很多呢。

路人　会和前年一样吗？

小贩　比前年好，先生，好很多呢。

路人　但是，新年会像哪一年呢？你不希望新年像以往的某一年一样吗？

小贩　不，先生，我不想。

路人　你是多少年前开始卖年历的？

小贩　肯定是二十年前了，先生。

路人　你希望今年的新年像过去二十年中的哪一个？

小贩　我？我不知道。

路人　你难道不记得某个感觉特别幸福的新年吗？

小贩　说真的，我不知道，先生。

路人　但是生活是美丽的，不是吗？

小贩　这个大家都知道的。

路人　你难道不想把这二十年重新再过一遍吗，从你出生那天开始，过去所有的年月？

小贩　嗯，我亲爱的先生，我祈求上帝可以让我这样。

路人　但是，假如是让你过和以前一模一样的生活怎么样——经历它所有的痛苦和欢乐？

小贩　我可不希望这样。

路人　那么，你希望重新过什么样的生活呢，是我这样的生活，或者是一个王子的生活，还是别的什么人的生活？你是否想过，无论是我、王子，还是其他人，都会给出和你一样的回答？假如能够重新把以前的生活再过一遍，没有人会乐意这么做？

小贩　我也这么想的。

路人　你不愿意再回去，除非换另一种生活？

小贩　对，先生，我真的不愿意。

路人　不过，你希望过哪种生活呢？

小贩　任何一种，上帝给我哪种都可以，只要没有附加条件就行。

路人　随便哪一种。事先也不知道，就像我们不知道新年会是什么样似的？

小贩　完全正确。

路人　如果我能够重新生活，我也会这么选择。每个人大抵都会如此吧？但是这意味着截至今年年底，命运对每个人都未加以善待啊。很明显，每个人都认为分给自己的不幸多于，或大于幸运——如果要把以前的生活再过一遍，重新经历它所有的好与恶，没有人愿意重生。美丽的人生不是我们已知的人生，而是未知的人生，它不是过去的人生，而是将来的人生。这个新年，命运将会善待你、我和所有人，幸福的人生即将开始。不是吗？

小贩　希望如此吧。

路人　那好，让我看一下你最漂亮的年历。

小贩　给您，先生，一共三十分。

路人　这是三十分。

小贩　谢谢您，先生，再见。年历，新年历，新日历。

Dialogue Between Hercules and Atlas

hercules. Father Atlas, Jove sends me and wants me to bring you his greetings, and in case you are tired of that burden, he wants me to take it on my shoulders for a few hours, as I did I don't remember how many centuries ago, so that you can catch your breath and rest a little.

atlas. I thank you, my little Hercules; I also feel much obliged to His Majesty Jove. But the world has become so light that this cloak I wear to protect myself from the snow is much heavier. And if it weren't that Jove forces me to stand still here, balancing this little ball on my back, I'd put it under my arm or in my pocket, or I'd let it dangle from a hair of my beard, and then I'd go about my business.

hercules. How has it gotten so light? I can see that it has changed shape and that it has become like a bread roll, and it's no longer round as it was when I studied cosmography for that enormous voyage with the Argonauts, but still, I don't understand why it should weigh less than it used to.

atlas. I don't know the reason either. But you can verify its lightness yourself if you take it in your hand for a moment and feel its weight.

hercules. By Hercules, if I hadn't felt it myself, I could never have believed it. But what kind of novelty is this that I discover? The last time I carried it, it throbbed strongly on my back, like the heart of an animal, and it made a continuous buzzing roar that sounded like a hornet's nest. But now, it ticks like a watch with a broken spring; and it doesn't make the slightest buzz of any kind.

atlas. I can't explain this either except that a long time ago the world stopped giving signs of any motion and noise; and, personally, I had a very strong suspicion that it was dead, and from day to day I expected to be infected with its stench. So I was trying to figure out how and where I could bury it and the kind of inscription I should put over its grave. But when I saw that it didn't rot, I concluded that from the animal that it was at first it had turned into a plant, like Daphne and many others, and that this was the reason it didn't stir or breathe. And even now I am afraid that it will soon put down roots and plant them into my shoulders.

hercules. I rather believe that it is asleep and that this sleep is of the same kind as that of Epimenides, which lasted more than half a century; or that of Hermotimus, whose soul, they say, used to leave his body whenever it wanted to and remain absent for many years, happily wandering about various countries and then coming back – until his friends, to put an end to such pranks, burned the body. And so when the spirit returned to get back into its home, it found it destroyed, and if it wanted a lodging, it had either to rent another one or to go to an inn. But to make sure that the world will not sleep forever and that some friend or benefactor won't set it on ffire, thinking that it is dead, I say that we should try to wake it up.

atlas. Good. But how?

hercules. I'd let it have a good whack of my club; but I am afraid I'd thoroughly flatten it into a pancake; or perhaps I'd crack it like an egg since its shell feels so light that it must have become quite thin. And I'm not so sure that men, who used to fight lions with their bare hands, and now fight fleas, wouldn't all faint away from the blow. The best thing is for me to get rid of my club and for you to take off your cloak and then for us to play ball with this tiny globe. I'm sorry I haven't brought the gauntlets or rackets Mercury and I use when we play in Jove's house or his back yard, but our fists should be enough.

atlas. Good idea! And what if your father, seeing us play, feels like joining us in the game and throws one of his fireballs and makes us tumble – who knows where – just like Phaethon into the Po?

hercules. True, if, like Phaethon, I were a poet's son and not his and if I weren't such that – while poets peopled the cities by the sounds of their lyres – I could unpeople heaven and earth by the sound of my club. And with a kick I would send his fireball flying all the way to the last ceiling of the Empyrean. But you can be sure that even if I got it into my head to unnail five or six stars for a game of cobnuts or to do target shooting with a comet and use it as a sling by holding it by the tail or even to use the sun itself in discus throwing, my father would pretend not to see. Then, in this game our intention is to do good to the world, and it is not like that of Phaethon, who wanted to show off his agility to the hours, who held his stepping block when he climbed into the cart and who also wanted to gain the reputation of being a good charioteer with Andromeda and Callisto and with the other fair constellations, to whom, as we are told, he flung in passing bouquets of rays and candied little balls of light. In fact, he wanted to make a show of himself before the gods during their promenade that day, which, as you know, was a holiday. So don't worry about my father's being angry; in any case, I promise that I will pay you the damages. Now let's get going. Take off your cloak and throw the ball.

atlas. Like it or not, I'd better do as you say; you're strong and armed, and I'm old and without weapons. At least be careful not to let it fall so that it doesn't get any more bumps and doesn't get bruised or cracked, as when Sicily broke off from Italy and Africa from Spain; or a splinter may tear off – like a province or a kingdom – and there may be a war as a result.

hercules. Don't worry.

atlas. Your turn to serve. Don't you see that it's limping because it's out of shape?

hercules. Come on. Hit it harder; your serves don't reach me.

atlas. It's not the hitting; the wind comes from the southwest, as is usual here, and the ball is carried by the wind – it's so light.

hercules. It's the same old story; always chasing after the wind.

atlas. Actually, it wouldn't be a bad idea to inflate it, for it doesn't bounce off the ffist any more than a melon does.

hercules. This is a new flaw, for in ancient times it bounced and jumped like a mountain goat.

atlas. Run! Quick! Quick! I say. Don't let it fall; damn the moment you came here!

hercules. You served it to me so badly and so low that I couldn't have caught it even if I'd broken my neck running. Oh, poor thing, how are you? Did you hurt yourself? I can't hear anyone breathing; I can't see a soul stirring; they're all still asleep.

atlas. Let me have it, by all the horns of the Styx, so that I may settle it again on my shoulders. And you pick up your club, and go back to heaven as fast as you can, and apologize for me to Jove for this accident, which was all your fault.

hercules. I'll do so. For many centuries a certain poet by the name of Horace has been a guest in my father's house, where he was admitted as court poet upon the recommendation of Augustus, who had been deified by Jove out of consideration for the power of the Romans. This poet keeps singing certain songs of his; in one of them he says that a just man remains unmoved even if the world falls. I must think that now all men are just, for the world has fallen and no one has moved.

atlas. Who ever doubted the justice of men? But stop wasting time; run and hurry to clear me with your father; for I am afraid that at any moment a thunder-bolt will turn me from Atlas into Etna.

Dialogue Between Fashion and Death

fashion. Madam Death, Madam Death.

death. Wait for your time, and I'll come without your calling me.

fashion. Madam Death.

death. Go to hell. I'll come when you don't want me.

fashion. As if I weren't immortal.

death. Immortal?

‘More than a thousand years have passed’since the time of the immortals.

fashion. Oh, our Madam spews Petrarch too, just like a sixteenth- or nineteenth-century Italian poet.

death. I love Petrarch's poetry because there I find my Triumph and because it mentions me almost everywhere. But now get out of my way.

fashion. Come, in the name of your love for the seven deadly sins, stop a moment and look at me.

death. I'm looking.

fashion. Don't you recognize me?

death. You should know that I don't see very well and that I can't wear glasses because the English don't make any that fit me, and even if they did, I wouldn't know how to keep them on.

fashion. I'm Fashion, your sister.

death. My sister?

fashion. Yes. Don't you remember that we are both Caducity's daughters?

death. What can I remember, I who am memory's greatest enemy?

fashion. But I remember well; and I know that you and I together keep undoing and changing things down here on earth although you go about it one way and I another.

death. If you are not talking to yourself or to someone who is inside your throat, raise your voice and chisel your words better; if you keep mumbling between your teeth with that spider-web voice of yours, I'll never hear you, for if you don't know it already, my hearing is no better than my eyesight.

fashion. Even if it isn't good manners – and in France people don't speak in order to be heard – and since we are sisters and don't have to stand on ceremony, I'll speak as you want. I'm saying that it is our nature and our custom to keep renovating the world. But right from the start you threw yourself on people and on blood, whereas I'm generally satisfied with beards, hair, clothes, furnishings, buildings, and the like. It is quite true, however, that I haven't refrained – nor am I refraining now – from playing many games comparable with yours, such as, for instance, piercing ears, lips, or noses with holes and causing them to be torn by the trinkets I hang in those holes; charring the flesh of men with red-hot brands, as I make them do for beauty's sake; misshaping the heads of babies with bandages and other trappings, making it a custom for all the men of a country to have their heads in the same shape, as I have done in America and in Asia; crippling people with tight shoes; cutting off their breath and making their eyes pop out because of their tight corsets; and a hundred other such things. As a matter of fact and generally speaking, I persuade and force all genteel men to endure daily a thousand hardships and a thousand discomforts and often pain and torment and I even get some of them to die gloriously for love of me. I won't tell you about the headaches, the colds, the inflamations of all kinds, the quotidian, tertian, or quartan fevers that men catch to obey me, agreeing to shiver in the cold or to stifle in the heat according to my wishes, by protecting their shoulders with wool and their chests with cloth, and by doing everything my way, no matter how much it hurts them.

death. Then I believe that indeed you are my sister and, if you want me to, I'll hold it more certain than death itself – without your having to prove it with a parish birth certificate. But if I keep this still, I'll faint. So, if you feel like running next to me, be sure you don't croak, for I go fast; and as we run, you can tell me about your business. Or else, in view of our family ties, I promise you that upon my death I'll leave you everything I have, and you can stay where you are with my best wishes.

fashion. If we were to run the Palio together, I don't know which one of us would win the race, for whereas you can run, I can go faster than a gallop; and whereas you faint by standing still in one place, I waste away. So let's start running again, and, as you say, as we run, we'll talk about our affairs.

death. Let's get on with it. And since you were born from my mother's womb, it would be good if you would help me in some way with my chores.

fashion. I have done that in the past more often than you think. First of all, though I continuously cancel and distort all the other customs, I've never in any place allowed the practice of dying to stop; and because of this, you can see it going on everywhere from the very beginning of the world until today.

death. Some miracle – that you didn't do what you couldn't.

fashion. What do you mean I couldn't? Obviously you don't seem to know the power of fashion.

death. All right, all right! We'll have plenty of time to talk about that when the custom of not dying has come. But for the moment I would like you, as a good sister, to help me obtain the opposite goal more easily and more speedily than I have done so far.

fashion. I have already told you about some of my doings that are of great assistance to you. But they are trifles in comparison with what I am going to tell you now. A little at a time, but mostly during these past years, to help you out, I have caused the neglect and the elimination of the exertion and those exercises which favor physical well-being, and I have introduced innumerable others that weaken the body in a thousand ways and shorten life and have caused them to be valued highly. In addition to this, I have put in the world such orders and such customs that life itself, both of the body and of the soul, is more dead than alive, so much so that this century can truly be called the century of death. And while in ancient times you had no other property except ditches and caves – where you sowed bones and dust in the darkness, which are seeds that bear no fruit – now you have land in the sun; and the people who move and walk about with their own feet are, so to speak, entirely yours even without harvesting them – as a matter of fact from the very moment they are born. Furthermore, if in the past you were generally hated and reviled, nowadays, because of my doings, things have come to such a point that whoever has any intelligence values and praises you, preferring you to life, and loves you so much as to call you constantly and to look to you as their greatest hope. Finally, I saw many boasting that they would become immortal, that is to say, they would not die completely because a good part of them would not fall into your hands. Although I knew that this was nonsense and that if those or any other people lived in the memory of mankind, their life would become a joke and they wouldn't enjoy their fame any more than they would suffer from the humidity of their tombs – in any case, seeing that this business of immortality stung you, because it seemed to injure your honor and your reputation – I have done away with this custom of seeking immortality and also of bestowing it on anyone who might deserve it. So now if someone dies, you can rest assured that there isn't a particle of him that isn't dead, and he'd better go right underground in his entirety, just like a fish who's swallowed up head and bones in a mouthful. These things are neither few nor slight, and I have done them for your sake – as I wanted to advance your domain on earth, as has happened. For this purpose I am ready to do the same, and more, each day; and for this reason I looked for you. And I think it desirable that from now on we should always stay together, for in this manner we'll be able to talk things over and reach the best decisions, as well as carry them out.

death. You are quite right. Let's do as you say.

Dialogue Between the Earth and the Moon

earth. My dear Moon, I know that you can speak and answer questions because you are a person, as I have often heard from the poets. Also, our children say that you, in fact, have a mouth, nose, and eyes, just like their own, and this they can see with their very eyes, which, at their age, must naturally be extremely sharp. As for me, I have no doubt that you know that I am no less a person, so much so that when I was younger, I had many children, so you will not be surprised if you hear me speak. Well then, my sweet Moon, although I have been your neighbor for so many more centuries than I can remember, I never said a word to you until now, for I was so busy with my chores that I did not have any time left for a chat. But now my affairs are of very little consequence; as a matter of fact, I can state that they take care of themselves. I don't know what to do, and I'm bored to death. So I plan to talk to you often in the future and to take an interest in your affairs – if I don't trouble you too much.

moon. Don't worry about that. I wish Fortune would give me as little trouble as I am certain you will give me. If you feel like talking to me, talk as much as you want, for although I am a friend of silence, as I think you know, I shall listen to you and shall be happy to answer your questions if that can be of help to you.

earth. Do you hear this delightful music, which the heavenly bodies make with their movements?

moon. To tell you the truth, I don't hear anything.

earth. I don't hear anything either, except the roar of the wind rushing from my poles to the equator and from the equator to my poles – and it doesn't seem anything like music. Yet Pythagoras says that the celestial spheres make a certain music, so sweet that it is indeed wondrous and that you yourself have a part in it, for you are the eighth string of this universal lyre, which I don't hear because I am deafened by that very music.

moon. Then I must surely be deafened too, for, as I said, I don't hear it; and I didn't know I was a string.

earth. Then let's change the subject. Tell me, are you really inhabited, as so many philosophers, ancient and modern, from Orpheus to De La Lande, state and swear? Though, like a big snail, I try to stretch these horns of mine, which men call mountains and peaks and with whose tips I keep staring at you, I have never been able to discover a single inhabitant on you – and yet I hear that one David Fabricius, whose eyesight was keener than that of Linceus himself, once discovered a number of them as they were hanging their laundry in the sun.

moon. As to your horns, I don't know anything. The fact is that I'm inhabited.

earth. What color are those men of yours?

moon. What men?

earth. Those who inhabit you. Didn't you say you are inhabited?

moon. Yes. And so?

earth. And so, your inhabitants cannot all be animals.

moon. Neither animals nor men, though I don't know what kind of creatures they are – either of them. As a matter of fact, I haven't been able to understand an iota of what you have been saying about men, as I think you call them.

earth. But what kind of people are yours?

moon. Very many and different kinds; you don't know them just as I don't know yours.

earth. That is very strange to me, so much so that if I hadn't heard it from you yourself, I could not believe it for anything in the world. Have you ever been conquered by any of your inhabitants?

moon. Not that I know of. And how? And why?

earth. Through ambition, through greed for other people's possessions, by means of politics, by force of arms.

moon. I do not know what you mean by arms, ambition, politics; in short, I don't know what you are talking about.

earth. But if you don't know about arms, you certainly know about war, for not long ago, one of our scientists with the help of a telescope – which is an instrument made to see very far – discovered a great fortress up there with regular and straight bastions, which is a sign that your people are at least acquainted with sieges and mural combats.

moon. Excuse me, Madame Earth, if I answer you a little more freely than becomes one of your subjects or servants, as I am. But really, you strike me as rather vain if you think that all things in every part of the world are like your own; as if Nature were only intent on reproducing you in everything she did. I say that I am inhabited, and from this you conclude that my inhabitants must be men. I inform you that they are not; and although you accept the fact that they are different creatures, you assume that they have the same qualities and live under the same conditions as your people; and you bring up the telescope of some scientist or other. But if this telescope doesn't see more clearly in other cases than in this one, I must believe that its eyesight is as good as your children's, who discover in me eyes, mouth, nose – which I don't know anything about.

earth. Then it isn't true that in your provinces there are broad-paved roads and that you are cultivated – as can be clearly seen from the German regions with a telescope.

moon. If I am cultivated, I don't know anything about it. And as to my roads, I do not see them.

earth. My dear Moon, you must know that I am somewhat dense and slow, and no wonder men fool me so easily. But I can tell you that even if your own people have never tried to conquer you, nonetheless, you weren't always free from danger; for at various times many people down here got it into their heads to conquer you themselves, and for that purpose they made plans and preparations. But even though they climbed to the highest points and raised themselves on their tiptoes and stretched out their arms, they could not reach you. Moreover, I have seen for many years men minutely scrutinize every part of you, drawing maps of your regions, and measuring the height of your mountains, which we even know by name. I thought I should tell you these things out of my affection and consideration for you so that you'd be prepared for any emergency. Now, let me ask you a couple of questions. How annoyed are you by the dogs barking at you? What do you think of those who point you out in wells? Are you male or female? In ancient times people were not quite sure. Is it true that the Arcadians came into the world before you? That your women – or whatever I should call them – are oviparous, and that one of their eggs fell down here some time ago? And that you are pierced in the middle like rosary beads, as a modern scientist believes? That you are made of green cheese, as the English say? That one day, or perhaps one night, Mohammed cut you in half, just like a watermelon, and that a large chunk of your body slipped into his sleeve? How happy are you to sit on the tops of minarets? How do you feel about the feast of Bairam?

moon. Go right ahead. When you go on like this, I don't need to answer you and break my usual silence. If you like to spend your time with such nonsense and cannot find anything else to talk about, instead of turning to me who cannot understand you, you'd do better to get men to build you another planet, made and inhabited the way you like, to whirl around you. You can't talk of anything else but men, dogs, and other such things, about which I know no more than about that gigantic sun, around which they say our own sun revolves.

earth. Truly, as I talk to you, the more I resolve to avoid speaking about my own things, the less I succeed. But from now on, I'll try to be more careful. Tell me, are you the one who enjoys making the water of my seas rise and then enjoys letting it fall?

moon. Maybe. But supposing I do to you this or anything else, I don't notice it at all, as in the same way you probably don't notice your influence up here, which must be much greater than mine on you, as you are greater in size and strength.

earth. Actually, the only thing I know about the influence I have on you is that every once in a while I take away the light of the sun from you, and I take away your own light from myself. I also know that during your nights I shine very brightly on you, as I myself can see at times. But I was forgetting something that is more important than anything else. I would like to know if really, as Ariosto writes, everything that man loses – such as youth, beauty, health, the labors and the expenses invested in learning and in gaining fame, in bringing up children according to the norms of good behavior, in founding or promoting useful institutions – everything goes and collects up there so that all human things can be found in you, except folly, which never leaves mankind. If this is true, I suppose you must be so full that you have no room to spare, especially if we consider that in recent times men have lost a great many things (such as patriotism, virtue, magnanimity, integrity), not only in part and not only a few of them, as happened in the past, but all together and completely. And certainly, if those things are not up there, I don't know in what other place they could be found. Therefore, I would like to make a pact with you. You'll start returning all these things to me now, and then you'll keep doing so as the opportunity arises. After all, I think that you yourself would be glad to be rid of them, especially common sense, which, as I understand, takes a tremendous amount of space. I would see to it that every year men would pay you a substantial sum of money.

moon. And there you speak of men again. Although, as you state, folly does not leave your regions, you seek men's wits while you try to take my own away from me. I don't know where they are, if they are disappearing or if they remain in any part of the world; all I know is that they cannot be found here, just as one cannot find any of the other things you have been asking about.

earth. At least you can tell me if up there people are acquainted with vice, crime, calamity, pain, old age, in short, evils. Do you understand these words?

moon. Oh yes. I surely understand them. And not only the words but the things they mean; I know them perfectly well, for I am filled with them – rather than with the other things you mentioned.

earth. What are more prevalent among your people, virtues or vices?

moon. Vices, by far.

earth. What is more abundant, good or evil?

moon. Evil, without comparison.

earth. And, in general, your inhabitants are happy or unhappy?

moon. So unhappy that I wouldn't change places with the most fortunate of them.

earth. It's the same here. So much so that it is a great surprise how similar you are to me in this, whereas you are so different in everything else.

moon. I am also similar to you in form, and in movement, and in receiving light from the sun, and this is no less surprising than the rest because evil is something common to all the planets of the universe or at least of this solar system – just as much as roundness and the other conditions I have mentioned. If you could raise your voice so high that it could be heard by Uranus or Saturn, or by any other planet of our world, and if you could ask them whether unhappiness exists on them and whether good or evil prevails among them, each would answer in the same way I have. I say this because I have already asked Venus and Mercury about the same things, for now and then I find myself closer to them than you. I have also asked some of the comets that have passed by me. All have answered in the same way as I have. And I believe that the sun himself, and every star, would give the same answer.

earth. In spite of all this, I am still hopeful, especially nowadays, when men are promising me great future happiness.

moon. Hope as much as you like; I assure you that you can hope forever.

earth. Do you know what's going on? These men and these animals are beginning to stir and make noise. On the side from which I'm talking to you, it is night, as you can see, or rather, as you can't see; and so they were all asleep, and at the commotion that we are making while we talk, they are waking up with great fear.

moon. But up here, as you can see, it is daytime.

earth. I don't want to frighten my people or to shatter their sleep, which is the greatest blessing they have. So we'll talk again some other time. Goodbye, then; and good day.

moon. Goodbye; and good night.

The Wager of Prometheus

In the year eight hundred thirty-three thousand two hundred and seventy-five of the reign of Jove, the College of the Muses ordered that certain posters be printed and affixed in the public places of the city and suburbs of Hypernephelus, by which all the gods, great and small, as well as the other inhabitants of the city, who recently or in former times might have made some valuable discovery, were invited to present it, either in person or in the form of a model or a description, to the judges appointed by said College. At the same time, regretting that because of their well-known poverty they could not be as generous as they would have liked, they promised, as a prize to the competitor whose invention would be judged the most beautiful and the most useful, a laurel crown with the privilege of wearing it day and night, in public and in private, within and without the city, along with the right to be painted, sculpted, engraved, molded, that is, represented in any manner and material, with such a laurel crown on the head.

Many of the gods competed for this prize, just as a pastime, something no less necessary to the inhabitants of Hypernephelus than to those of other cities – not that they had any desire for that crown, which was not worth a cotton nightcap; and as for glory, if men themselves, now that they have become philosophers, despise it, we can imagine in what kind of esteem it is held by the gods, who are so much wiser than men (as a matter of fact, according to Pythagoras and Plato, they are the only ones to be really wise). Therefore – and it was a unique ex ample, until then unheard of for similar cases of awards offered to the most deserving – this prize was adjudged without the intrusion of solicitations or favors, of secret promises or intrigues. Three competitors won: Bacchus for the discovery of wine; Minerva for the discovery of oil, which is so necessary to the gods for daily anointing after their baths; and Vulcan for having invented an economical copper pot, by which any food can be cooked quickly and with little fire. So the prize had to be divided into three parts, with the result that each one got a small laurel branch; and all three of them refused it, either in part or in whole. Vulcan declared that as most of his time was spent working and sweating before the fire of his forge, that thing on his forehead would be a great nuisance – not to mention that it would expose him to the danger of being burned or scorched if a spark should by chance fall upon those dry leaves and set them on fire. Minerva said that since she had to hold on her head a helmet large enough to cover at once the armies of a hundred cities, as Homer writes, it was not advisable for her to increase that weight in any way. Bacchus said that he didn't want to change his hat and his crown of vine leaves for a laurel crown, although he would happily accept it if he were allowed to use it as a sign in front of his tavern. But the Muses refused to grant it to him for this purpose so that it remained in their treasury.

The other competitors did not envy the three deities who had won and had rejected the prize, nor did they complain about the judges or blame their decision, except one, Prometheus, who had entered the competition by sending in the clay model which he had used in forming the first men, adding to it a description of the qualities and functions of the human race, which he had invented. No little astonishment was caused by Prometheus's dissatisfaction in this matter, which all the others, winners and losers alike, had taken as no more than a game. But as the reason for such dissatisfaction was investigated, it was learned that he strongly desired not the honor itself but the privilege he would have enjoyed had he been the winner. Some think that he wanted to avail himself of the laurel to protect his head against the storms, as we are told of Tiberius, who, whenever he heard thunder, put on his crown, for he believed that laurel was not susceptible to lightning. But in the city of Hypernephelus there is neither thunder nor lightning. Others, more plausibly, state that Prometheus, who was getting on in years, was beginning to lose his hair – a misfortune which he, like many others, did not like at all – and since he had not read Synesius's work in praise of baldness or, as is more likely, since he had not been convinced by it, he wanted to conceal the bareness of his head under the diadem, just as Julius Caesar did.

But to go back to our story. One day, as he was talking to Momus, Prometheus bitterly complained that wine, oil, and pots had been given preference over the human race, which he pronounced the best work the immortals had brought to the world. And since he thought that Momus was not convinced, for he advanced all kinds of arguments to the contrary, Prometheus suggested that both of them fly down to earth together and in each of its five parts stop at random in the first place they discovered to be inhabited by men; but first they made this mutual wager – with Prometheus betting that in all of the five places, or in the majority of them, they would find positive proof that man is the most perfect creature in the universe. This was acceptable to Momus, and having agreed on the amount of the wager, they immediately began their descent toward the earth. They first directed themselves to the New World, for owing to its very name and owing to the fact that no one of the immortals had ever been there, it especially excited their curiosity. They made their first stop in the northern area of the country of Popaián, not far from the river Cauca, in a place where there appeared many signs of human habitation – traces of cultivation in the countryside, numerous trails, al -though often interrupted and mostly obstructed, trees felled and stretched out on the ground, and particularly what looked like graves, with some human bones here and there. But for all that, the two celestial creatures could neither hear a man's voice nor see a live man's shadow no matter how much they sharpened their ears or their eyes. They went on, partly walking, partly flying, for many miles, passing over mountains and rivers, and everywhere they found the same signs and the same solitude.‘How is it these places are so deserted,’said Momus to Prometheus,‘when they clearly show that they were inhabited?’Prometheus mentioned tidal waves, earthquakes, hurricanes, heavy rains, which he knew to be common in tropical regions; and, indeed, at that very time they heard in all the nearby forests rain constantly falling from the tree branches as they were shaken by the wind. But Momus could not possibly understand how that area could be subject to tidal waves – the sea being so far away that it could nowhere be seen; and he could understand still less how it had happened that earthquakes, hurricanes, and heavy rains had destroyed all the men of that country while they had spared jaguars, monkeys, foxes, anteaters, eagles, parrots, and a hundred other kinds of animals of the earth and of the air, which were visible in the area. Finally, as they descended into an immense valley, they discovered, as it were, a small heap of houses, or rather of wooden huts, covered with palm leaves – each one surrounded by a wooden fence. In front of one of them there were many people, some standing, some sitting around an earthen pot suspended over a large fire. The two celestial beings, having taken human form, approached the group. Prometheus courteously greeted everybody and then turned to the one who appeared to be the chief and asked him what they were doing.

savage. We're eating, as you can see.

prometheus. Do you have something good to eat?

savage. Only this meat.

prometheus. Is it meat from a domestic or from a wild animal?

savage. Domestic; as a matter of fact, from my own son.

prometheus. Did you have a steer for a son, like Pasiphae?

savage. Not a steer but a man, such as all other people have.

prometheus. Do you really mean it? Do you eat your own flesh?

savage. Not my own but certainly his, for it was only for this purpose that I brought him into the world, and I cared for him and nurtured him.

prometheus. Just for the purpose of eating him?

savage. What's so strange? And his mother too! Since she is not likely to bear any more children, I'm planning to eat her soon.

momus. Just as you eat the hen after having eaten the eggs.

savage. And so the other women I have ... as they become useless for childbearing ... I'll eat them too. And these slaves you see here ... do you think I'd keep them alive if every once in a while I didn't get some of their children to eat? But as they get old, I'll eat them too, one at a time – if I live long enough.

prometheus. Tell me, those slaves – do they belong to your own people or to another?

savage. To another.

prometheus. To one very far from here?

savage. Very far, so much so that between their houses and ours there was a little stream.

Then he pointed at a low hill and added:‘There, that's where they used to live, but our people destroyed them.’At this point Prometheus noticed that many of the savages were ogling him with the kind of loving look that a cat gives a mouse. Thus, so as not to be eaten by his own creatures, he quickly took off in flight; and so did Momus with him. Both of them were so scared that as they departed, they contaminated the barbarians' food with the same kind of dirt that the Harpies out of envy showered on the tables of the Trojans. But the savages, more hungry and less squeamish than Aeneas's companions, continued their meal.

Prometheus, quite disappointed with the New World, immediately directed his course toward the oldest world, that is to say, toward Asia; and having covered in not much more than an instant the distance between the new and the ancient Indies, both of them made their descent near Agra, in a field overflowing with a vast multitude of people gathered on the edge of a trench crammed with wood – on whose brim you could see on one side some men with lighted torches, ready to set the wood afire, and on the other, on a platform, a young woman wearing extremely sumptuous clothes and all kinds of barbaric ornaments, who was dancing and shouting and showing signs of the most extravagant joyfulness. As he saw this, Prometheus imagined a new Lucretia or a new Virginia, or an emulator of Erechtheus's daughters, of Iphigenia, of Codrus, of Menecius, of Curtius, and of Decius, who, following the command of some oracle, would voluntarily offer herself up in sacrifice for her country. When he later learned that the woman was sacrificing herself because of her husband's death, he thought that she, not unlike Alcestis, wanted to buy back her husband's life at the price of her own. But having further ascertained that she was preparing herself to be burned alive only because this was the custom among the widows of her group, that she had always hated her husband, that she was drunk, and that the dead man, rather than coming back to life, was to be burned in that very same fire, Prometheus immediately turned his back on that spectacle and headed for Europe. On the way, he held this conversation with his companion.

momus. Would you ever have thought, when with enormous risk you stole fire from heaven to give it to men, that some of them would use it to cook one another in pots and some others to burn themselves voluntarily to death?

prometheus. Certainly not. But don't forget, dear Momus, that those we have seen so far are barbarians and that the nature of men should not be judged from barbarians but from civilized people toward whom we are now traveling. I'm firmly convinced that among them we'll see and hear things that not only will seem worthy of praise but will also fill you with astonishment.

momus. If men are the most perfect species in the universe, I don't see why they need to be civilized in order not to burn themselves to death or not to eat their own children. The other animals are all barbarians, and yet they don't deliberately burn themselves, except the phoenix, who has never been seen by anyone; those who eat any of their own kind are extremely rare, and still rarer are those who feed on their own offspring – and then only because of some strange accident and not because they've brought them into the world for this purpose. Note also that of the five parts of the world, only one, by far the smallest and not even all of it, plus some minimal areas of another part, are endowed with that civilization that you acclaim. And I don't think that you yourself will maintain that this civilization is so complete that nowadays the men of Paris or of Philadelphia have reached all the perfection of which their species is capable. Now, how long did those people have to work and suffer to reach a state of civilization which is not yet perfect? As many years as those that can be counted from the origin of man to our day. And almost all the inventions that were either most necessary or most conducive to the attainment of a civilized state have had their origins not in design but in chance so that human civilization is more the work of accident than of natural development; and where those accidents have not occurred, the people are still barbarians, although they are just as old as the civilized ones. Therefore, I conclude, if barbarians show themselves in many ways inferior to any other animal; if civilization, which is the opposite of barbarism, is even today the prerogative of a small part of the human race; and if, additionally, this small part has been able to reach the present civilized condition only after innumerable centuries, and mostly by accident rather than by any other cause; and finally, if this condition is far from being perfect – I wonder if you would consider that your judgment of the human race might be more correct if you shortened it in this manner, that is to say, by stating that the human race is indeed supreme among all the others, as you think, but supreme in imperfection rather than in perfection – although men, in speaking and in judging, continually mistake one for the other, for they draw their conclusions from premises which they have themselves devised and which they hold to be tangible truths. It is certain that the other species of creatures have been totally perfect from the very beginning, each according to its own nature. And even if it weren't clear that a savage, considered in relation to the other animals, is the worst of all, I fail to understand why being extremely imperfect in one's own nature, as man appears to be, should be valued as a greater condition of perfection than that of all other creatures. We should add that human civilization, which is so difficult to attain, and perhaps impossible to bring to completion, is not so stable that it cannot disintegrate, as has, in fact, happened many times and among various people who had acquired a good measure of it. In short, I am of the opinion that if your brother Epimetheus had brought before the judges the model he must have used when he formed the first donkey or the first frog, he would have perhaps won the prize you couldn't get. However, I'll be happy to concede that man is a most perfect creature if you decide to say that his perfection is like the one Plotinus attributed to the world, which, said Plotinus, is excellent and perfect in absolute; but to be perfect, the world must contain, among other things, all possible evils as well; for, in fact, we can find in it as much evil as it can possibly hold. And in this sense, I would probably also concede to Leibniz that the present world is the best of all possible worlds.

There is no doubt that Prometheus had a ready answer – clear, precise, and logical – to all these arguments; but it is equally certain that he did not produce it; for at that very moment they found themselves over the city of London. They descended and saw a great multitude of people gathering by the door of a private house. They joined the crowd and entered the house; there they found a man lying on his back in a bed with a pistol in his hand; he was dead, a wound in his chest; and next to him lay two small children, also dead. Several members of the house staff were also in the room, as well as some magistrates, who were questioning them, while a clerk wrote down their answers.

prometheus. Who are these wretched people?

a servant. My master and his children.

prometheus. Who killed them?

servant. My master, all three of them.

prometheus. You mean to say, his children and himself?

servant. Yes!

prometheus. Incredible! Something really terrible must have happened to him.

servant. Not to my knowledge.

prometheus. But perhaps he was poor, despised by everyone, disappointed in love, or in disfavor with the Court.

servant. On the contrary! He was very rich, and I think everyone held him in high esteem; to love he was indifferent, and he was very much in favor with the Court.

prometheus. Then, how did he get so desperate?

servant. Because of the tedium of life, as he has declared in writing.

prometheus. And these magistrates – what are they doing?

servant. They are inquiring whether my master had lost his mind or not; for if he hadn't, his property goes to the Crown; and indeed there is no way to avoid that.

prometheus. But tell me, had he no friend or relative to whom he could entrust these small children instead of killing them?

servant. Yes, he did, and, among others, one to whom he was especially close and to whom he has entrusted his dog.

Momus was about to congratulate Prometheus on the good effects of civilization and on the happiness which it seemed to bring to men's lives; he also wanted to remind him that no other animal, except man, kills himself voluntarily or takes the lives of his own children out of sheer desperation. But Prometheus was ahead of him and, without caring about seeing the two remaining parts of the world, paid him the wager.

Dialogue Between Nature and an Icelander

An Icelander, who had traveled most of the world and had visited many different countries, was once wandering in the interior of Africa when he crossed the equator into a region never before explored by man. There he met with an adventure similar to the one encountered by Vasco da Gama, when he doubled the Cape of Good Hope and the Cape itself, which stands guard over the Austral seas, came toward him in the form of a giant to dissuade him from entering those uncharted waters. The Icelander saw an enormous bust far away in the distance. At first he imagined it to be made of stone, like those colossal figures he had seen on Easter Island many years before. But as he drew nearer, he discovered that it was the huge body of a woman, seated on the ground, her bust erect and her back and her elbow resting against a mountain. And she was not a statue, but alive – her face at once beautiful and awesome, her eyes and her hair raven black. She looked at him fixedly for some time, without speaking. Finally she said:

nature. Who are you? What are you looking for in these regions, where so far your species has been unknown?

icelander. I'm a poor Icelander and am fleeing Nature. I have fled her nearly all my life in a hundred areas of the earth, and now I'm fleeing her in this area.

nature. So flees the squirrel from the rattlesnake until he finally falls into its jaws. I am she from whom you're fleeing.

icelander. Nature?

nature. No one else.

icelander. I regret it to the depths of my soul, for I firmly believe that no greater misfortune could happen to me.

nature. You should have known that I would be found especially around these parts, where, as you know, my power is more evident than elsewhere. But what prompted you to run away from me?

icelander. Let me tell you that since my early youth and after a little experience, I became aware and convinced of the vanity of life and of the stupidity of men, who fight one another continually for pleasures that don't please and for goods that don't help; they endure and inflict on one another innumerable worries and innumerable troubles, which actually harass and injure; and thus the more they seek happiness, the farther away they get from it. As a result of these perceptions, I abandoned all other desires and resolved to lead an obscure and quiet life, without bothering anyone, without trying to advance myself in any way, without competing with anyone for any good in the world. And without hoping for any kind of pleasure – which is something that's denied our species – I did not set for myself any other goal than to stay away from suffering. With this I don't mean to say that I intended to abstain from work and physical labor, for, as you well know, there is a difference between labor and discomfort and between a quiet and an idle life. As soon as I began to carry out this resolution, I learned by experience how vain it is to think that if you live among men and you don't hurt anyone, you may also avoid being hurt by others; and that if you spontaneously withdraw and are satisifed with the minimum, you may be allowed a little place somewhere, and this minimum may not be taken away from you. But I easily freed myself from the hostility of men by removing myself from their society and by retiring into solitude – which in my native island can be accomplished without difficulty. After doing this and living almost without any trace of pleasure, I still could not exist without suffering because the intense cold of the long winters and the extreme heat of the summers, which are typical of that region, tormented me continually; and the fire, next to which I was forced to spend much of my time, dried up my flesh and tortured my eyes with smoke so that neither inside my house nor in the open air could I save myself from perpetual discomfort. Nor could I lead that quiet life to which I especially turned all my aspirations, for the frightening storms on land and sea, the rumblings and the threats of Mount Hekla, the fear of fires, which are extremely frequent in wooden houses such as ours, never ceased to disturb me. In a constantly uniform life, divested of all desires and hopes and of almost all worry but that of being in peace and quiet, such discomforts as these assume no little weight and are far more serious than they usually appear to be when most of the mind is occupied by thoughts of social and civil life and by the adversities produced by men. Thus, when I found that the more I withdrew and almost contracted myself, as it were, within myself so as not to disturb or harm anything in the world, the less could I avoid being troubled and tormented by other things, I began to change regions and climates to see if there was any part of the earth where, offending no one, I might escape being offended and where, not enjoying pleasure, I might escape suffering. I was further moved to this resolution by the thought that perhaps you had destined the human race to only one climate of the earth (as you had done with each of the other species of animals and plants) and to certain specific areas outside of which men could neither prosper nor live without difficulty and misery; so that if they should scoff at and exceed the limits that your laws had prescribed for human dwellings, such difficulty and misery were to be blamed on them, and not on you. I have searched almost the entire world and have explored almost every country, always keeping my resolution of causing other creatures the least possible trouble and of seeking only a quiet life. But I was burned by heat in the tropics, stiffened by cold near the poles, afflicted by the instability of the weather in the temperate zones, plagued everywhere by the convulsions of the elements. I have seen many places where not a day passes without a storm, which is like saying that every day you attack and give deliberate battle to those inhabitants who have never done you any harm. In other regions the usual serenity of the sky is balanced by the frequency of earthquakes, by the multitude and the fury of volcanoes, by the subterranean boiling and rumbling of the entire country. Winds and furious tornadoes prevail in the regions and the seasons that are free from the other furies of the weather. There were times when I felt the roof cave in over my head because of the great weight of the snow; other times, because of the torrential rain, the earth itself cracked and gave away under my feet. At times I had to flee as fast as I could from rivers that pursued me as if I had done them some wrong. Many wild beasts I had never provoked with the slightest offense tried to devour me; many snakes tried to poison me; in various places flying insects almost consumed me to the bone. I won't speak of the infinite number of daily dangers, which are always threatening man, so much so that an ancient philosopher could not find any cure for fear other than the fact that everything is to be feared. Nor was I spared by illnesses although I was, and still am, not only temperate but self-denying in the pleasures of the flesh. I greatly marvel when I consider that you have instilled in us such a strong and insatiable craving for pleasure that without this pleasure and deprived of what it naturally desires, our life is most imperfect; and yet you have ordered that the indulgence in this pleasure shall be, of all things human, the most harmful to the strength and the health of the body, the most calamitous to everyone, and the most contrary to the duration of life itself. Nevertheless, although I have almost always and completely abstained from all pleasures, I could not avoid suffering many and diverse illnesses, some of which brought me to the brink of death; others threatened me with the loss of a limb or with perpetually leading a more miserable life than in the past; and all of them oppressed my body and mind for days and months with a thousand privations and a thousand sufferings. Although in times of illness each of us experiences new and unfamiliar pains and greater unhappiness than normal (as if human life were not sufficiently miserable as it is), you certainly have not compensated man for this by giving him periods of exuberant and unusually good health, which could bring him some extraordinary pleasure both in quality and in quantity. In countries that are generally covered with snow, I was nearly blinded, as regularly happens to the people of Lapland. The sun and the air, which are vital and necessary to our life and therefore, inescapable, continuously abuse us – the air with its humidity, its rigor, and its other whims, the sun with its heat and with light itself, so much so that man can never be exposed to either one of them without some degree of discomfort or harm. Indeed, I can't remember spending one single day of my life without suffering, whereas I cannot even count those days that I have passed without the shadow of a pleasure. I realize that suffering is as much our inevitable fate as is lack of pleasure and that it is as impossible to lead a quiet life of any kind as it is to lead a restless one without misery; thus, I am bound to conclude that you are a manifest enemy of men, and of the other animals, and of all your own creatures. Now you ensnare us, now you threaten us, now you attack us, now you sting us, now you strike us, now you rend us, and always you offend or persecute us. Either by habit or by rule, you are the slaughterer of your own family and of your own children and, as it were, of your own flesh and blood. Therefore, I have no more hope. I have understood that men finally stop persecuting those who flee or hide from them with the firm resolution of fleeing and hiding, but you never stop harrowing us until you finally crush us. And I am already close to the bitter and gloomy time of old age, a true and manifest evil, in fact an accumulation of the most oppressive evils and miseries, an evil which is not accidental but destined by your laws to all kinds of living creatures, foreknown by each of us from childhood, and continuously apparent in us from our twenty-fifth birthday on, with a sad and unfortunate process of unmerited decay. So that one-third of man's life is assigned to growth, only a few instants to maturity and perfection, and the rest to decline, with all the resulting discomforts.

nature. Did you think by any chance that the world was made for you alone? Now let me tell you that in my works, laws, and operations, except for very few of them, my purpose was not, and is not, the happiness or unhappiness of men. When I harm you in any way and with whatever means, I don't notice it, except very rarely; just as I ordinarily don't know whether I please or help you; nor have I done those things, nor do I do those actions, as you believe, to please or to help you. Finally, even if I happened to wipe out your entire species, I wouldn't notice it.

icelander. Let us suppose that someone of his own initiative invited me and strongly urged me to visit his villa, that to please him I accepted, and that once there, I was to be lodged in a dilapidated and ruined cell, humid, fetid, and exposed to the wind and the rain, where I was in constant danger of being crushed. And that not only did he not take the trouble to entertain me with some recreation or provide me with some comfort, but he barely furnished me with enough to keep alive, and he also let me be reviled, scorned, threatened, and beaten by his children and by the rest of his family. And if I complained to him of such treatment, he answered:‘Do you think that I built this villa for you or that I keep these children and these servants of mine just to assist you? I have many things to think about other than entertaining you and spending money for your support.’To this I would reply:‘See, my friend, as you did not build this villa for me, so it was your privilege not to invite me here. But since you asked me of your own initiative to come and stay here, don't you think you should arrange it so that, as far as possible on your part, I should be able to live here without suffering and without danger?’This is what I am saying now. I know very well that you did not create the world for the service of men; I could more easily believe that you created it for the express purpose of torturing them. Now I ask you, did I ever beg you to put me in this universe? Did I intrude into it violently and against your will? Indeed, you yourself have placed me here with your own hands and of your own will and without my knowledge and in such a way that I could neither resist nor oppose it. Then is it not your duty, if not to keep me happy and satisfied in this kingdom of yours, at least to see to it that I am not tormented and tortured and that living in it is not harmful to me? And what I am saying about myself, I am also saying about the entire human race, about the other animals, and about all living creatures.

nature. Evidently, you have not considered that in this universe life is a perpetual cycle of production and destruction – both functions being so closely bound together that one is continuously working toward the other, thus bringing about the conservation of the world, which, if either one of them were to cease, would likewise dissolve. Therefore, were anything free from suffering, it would be harmful to the world.

icelander. That is just what all philosophers say. But since what is destroyed suffers and what destroys does not experience pleasure and is itself soon also destroyed, tell me what no philosopher can: who finds any pleasure or who finds any advantage in this most miserable life of the universe, which is preserved by means of the suffering and the death of the very things that compose it?

We are told that while they were engaged in these and similar discussions, there happened to appear two lions who were so worn out and starved that they barely had enough strength to eat up the Icelander, which they did and thus managed to get enough nourishment to survive for the rest of that day. But there are some who deny this story and maintain that while the Icelander was speaking, an extremely fierce wind arose, threw him down to the ground, and raised over him a majestic mausoleum of sand, under which, perfectly desiccated and turned into a beautiful mummy, he was later discovered by some travelers and placed in the museum of a European city.

Dialogue Between Frederick Ruysch and His Mummies

Chorus of Mummies in Frederick Ruysch's Study

Alone in the world, eternal, toward whom does move
Every created thing,
In you, Death, finds rest
Our naked nature;
Not joyous, but secure
From ancient suffering. Profound
Night in our confused mind
Obscures our grave thought;
Towards hope, desire, the shriveled spirit
Feels its strength wane;
Thus from affliction and from fear is freed
And the empty slow years
Unbored whiles away.
We lived; and as the confused memory
Of a frightening ghost
And of a sweating dream
Wanders in the souls of infants,
So in us remembrance lingers
Of our lives: but far from fear
Is our remembering. What were we?
What was the bitter point called life?
Stupendous mystery is today
Life to our minds, and such
As to the minds of the living
Unknown death appears. As when living
From death it fled, now flees
From vital flame
Our naked nature
Not joyous but secure;
For to be happy
Is denied to mortals and denied the dead by Fate.

ruysch. (Outside his study, looking through the chinks of the door) What's going on? Who taught music to these dead? They sing like roosters in the middle of the night. I'm in a cold sweat and am almost more dead than they are. I didn't expect them to come back to life simply because I preserved them from decomposition. Well, for all my philosophy I'm shaking from head to foot. Damn that devil who made me bring these people into my house. I don't know what to do. If I keep them locked up here, they might break the door down, or they might get out through the keyhole and come and get me in my bed. To call for help because I'm afraid of dead people doesn't look good. All right, a little courage, and let me try to scare them instead.

(Entering) Eh, children, what kind of game is this? Don't you remember that you are dead? What's this racket you are making? Have you gotten cocky because of the Czar's visit, and do you think you're no longer subject to the same laws as in the past? I suppose you meant all this in jest, and no more. If you've come back to life, I congratulate you; but I'm not rich enough to support the living the same way I support the dead; therefore, you'll have to go. If what they say about vampires is true, and you are vampires, you'll have to look for some other blood to drink; for I'm not going to let you suck mine, no matter how generous I've been with the artificial blood I've put into your veins. In short, if you want to keep quiet and silent, as you have so far, we'll remain on good terms, and in my house you won't go without anything you need; otherwise, I'm going to get the door bar and kill you all.

mummy. Don't be upset; I promise you that we'll all stay as dead as before, without your having to kill us.

ruysch. Then what's this idea of singing?

mummy. A short time ago, at exactly midnight, for the first time that great mathematical year has ended of which the ancients write so much; and this is also the first time the dead speak. And not only us but in every cemetery, in every tomb, down at the bottom of the sea, under snow or sand, in the open air, or in whatever place they are, at midnight, all the dead sang, like ourselves, that little song you heard.

ruysch. And how long will they go on singing or talking?

mummy. As for singing, they have already finished. For talking, they'll be allowed a quarter of an hour. Then they'll return to silence until that same year is again completed.

ruysch. If that's true, I don't think you'll break my sleep again. Talk together freely. I'll stand aside and gladly listen to you out of curiosity without disturbing you.

mummy. We can only talk by answering some living person. After the song is finished, those who don't have to answer the living remain quiet.

ruysch. I'm really sorry, for I think it would be great fun to hear what you'd say among yourselves if you could talk together.

mummy. Even if we could, you wouldn't hear anything; for we wouldn't have anything to say to one another.

ruysch. I can think of a thousand questions to put to you. But since time is short and leaves no choice, let me know in brief what kind of sensations of body and mind you experienced at the point of death.

mummy. I didn't notice the actual point of death.

the other mummies. We didn't either.

ruysch. How come you didn't notice it?

mummy. Just as you never notice the moment you begin to sleep, no matter how much attention you pay.

ruysch. But to fall asleep is natural.

mummy. And don't you think that dying is natural? Show me a man, or an animal, or a plant that doesn't die.

ruysch. I'm no longer surprised that you go on singing and talking if you didn't notice when you died.

Unwitting of the blow, he went ahead,
Combatting still, and yet already dead,

writes an Italian poet. I thought that on this question of death, those like you would know something more than the living. But going back to our subject, at the point of death didn't you feel any pain?

mummy. What kind of pain can it be if one who feels it doesn't notice it?

ruysch. At any rate, all are convinced that the sensation of death is extremely painful.

mummy. As if death were a sensation and not the opposite.

ruysch. Yet in regard to the nature of the soul, both those who incline to the opinion of the Epicureans and those who hold the common belief, all, or most of them, agree with what I am saying, that is, in believing that death is by its very nature and beyond all comparison an extremely acute pain.

mummy. Well, just ask both of them on our behalf: if man has no power to notice the point when his vital operations, to a greater or lesser extent, remain only interrupted by sleep, lethargy, syncope, or by whatever cause, how will he notice the point when those same operations cease altogether, and not for a short space of time but forever? And moreover, how can it be that a living sensation exists in death? As a matter of fact, how can it be that death itself is by its very nature a living sensation? When the power of feeling is not only weak and scanty but reduced to such a minimum that it fails and is abolished, do you think that a person is capable of a strong sensation? In fact, do you believe this very extinction of the power of feeling to be in itself a very great sensation? You can observe that as death approaches, even those who die of acute and painful diseases sooner or later, before they expire, become calm and rest so that we can perceive how, being reduced to a small quantity, their life is no longer sufficient for pain, and as a result pain ceases sooner than life itself. This you may tell on our behalf to whoever thinks he'll die of pain at the point of death.

ruysch. Those reasons might be enough for the Epicureans. But not for those who judge otherwise of the substance of the soul, as I have done in the past and will do much more in the future, having heard the dead speak and sing. For believing that death consists in a separation of the soul from the body, they will not understand how these two things, conjoined and, as it were, conglutinated together in such a way that they both form only one person, can be separated without very great violence and unspeakable suffering.

mummy. Tell me, is the spirit by any chance attached to the body by some nerve or by some muscle or membrane, which must necessarily be torn when the spirit goes? Or is it by any chance part of the body, from which it must be violently snatched or severed? Don't you see that the soul leaves the body only because it is not allowed to remain and has no place there any longer and not because of any force that tears it and uproots it? Tell me also, when the soul enters the body, does it by any chance feel stuck and vigorously fastened or, as you say, conglutinated to it? Why then, when it leaves that body should the soul feel itself being detached or, in other words, experience a most violent sensation? Rest assured that the entry and the exit of the soul are equally quiet, easy, and soft.

ruysch. Then what's death if it's not pain?

mummy. Pleasure rather than anything else. You should know that dying, like falling asleep, does not take place in an instant but by degrees. True, these degrees are more or less and greater or smaller according to the variety of the causes and to the kinds of death. In the last moment death brings neither pain nor pleasure, no more than does sleep. In the preceding moments it cannot produce pain because pain is something alive, and, at that time, that is, after the beginning of death, man's senses are moribund, which is like saying weakened in the extreme. It may well be a cause of pleasure, for pleasure is not always something alive; in fact, most human pleasures consist in some sort of languor, so that man's senses are capable of pleasure even when they are near extinction since very often languor itself is pleasure, especially when it frees you from suffering; for, as you well know, the cessation of any pain or discomfort is in itself pleasure. So, the languor of death ought to be the more welcome as it frees man from greater suffering. Personally, although in the hour of death I didn't pay much attention to what I was feeling because the doctors had ordered me not to tire my brain, I nevertheless remember that the sensation I experienced was not much unlike the pleasure produced in men by the languor they feel while they are falling asleep.

the other mummies. We also seem to remember that.

ruysch. Be it as you say, although all those with whom I have had the chance of discussing this matter had an altogether different opinion; but then, so far as I can remember, they didn't bring up their own personal experience. Now tell me, at the time of death, while you felt that pleasure, did you think you were dying and that that pleasure was a courtesy of death, or did you imagine something else?

mummy. So long as I wasn't dead, I never thought I wouldn't escape that danger; and at least up to the last moment that I had the power to think, I kept hoping that I would still have an hour or two of life, as I think happens to many when they die.

the other mummies. The same thing happened to us.

ruysch. Indeed, Cicero says that no one is so decrepit that he doesn't expect to live at least another year. But how did you notice at last that the spirit had left the body? Tell me, how did you know that you were dead? They don't answer. Children, don't you hear me? The quarter of an hour must be over. Let me feel their pulse. They're dead again all right; there is no danger of their scaring me another time. So let's go back to bed.

Dialogue Between Christopher Columbus and Pedro Gutierrez

columbus. A beautiful night, my friend.

gutierrez. Beautiful indeed; but I think it would be more beautiful seen from land.

columbus. Good. So you're tired of sailing too.

gutierrez. Not just of sailing; but this sailing is turning out to go on much longer than I thought, and it's beginning to get to me. Even so, you shouldn't think that I'm complaining about you, as the others do. Rather, you can be sure that whatever you may decide in regard to this voyage, I'll always be on your side, as in the past, as much as I can. But since we're on the subject, I would like you to tell me clearly, in all honesty, if you still feel as sure as in the beginning that you will find land and people in this part of the world, or if, after so much time and experience to the contrary, you are beginning to have doubts.

columbus. Frankly and in confidence, as friend to friend, I confess that I'm beginning to feel a little unsure, especially because during this voyage, many of the signs which had given me great hope have proved empty – like the birds that flew overhead from the West, a few days after we left Gomera, and which I thought an indication of land nearby. Also, day after day, I have seen that the facts have not borne out the assumptions and predictions I had made before setting out to sea as to the various things that I believed would occur in the course of the voyage. So I'm beginning to think that, as these predictions have misled me – although they seemed almost infallible – it may also be that the main assumption, that we would find land on the other side of the ocean, will prove empty too. It is true that this assumption is so well founded that, if it is false, it would seem that we could not trust any human judgment except when it is based entirely on things we can actually see and touch. But, on the other hand, I realize that often, in fact most of the time, reality is at odds with theory. And I also ask myself, how can you know that each part of the world is so much like the others that, simply because the Eastern Hemisphere is occupied partly by land and partly by water, it must also follow that the Western Hemisphere is divided up between the two elements? How can you know that it is not totally occupied by one immense sea? Or that instead of land, or even land and water, it could not contain some other element? And if it is made of land and sea like the other, wouldn't it be possible that it is uninhabited? Or even uninhabitable? But suppose it is no less inhabited than ours; how can you be sure that there are rational creatures, as in ours? And even if there are, how can you be sure they are men and not some other kind of intelligent animals? And if they are men, that they are not quite different from those you know? Let's say, much bigger in body, much stronger, with much greater agility, naturally endowed with much greater intelligence and wit; also much better civilized and far more advanced in both art and science? This is what I keep asking myself. And after all, Nature is imbued with such power, and her effects are so varied and numerous that not only can we not judge with certainty what she has done and is doing in faraway places totally unknown to our world, but we may also wonder if it is not a grave mistake to argue the former on the basis of the latter. And it would not be against the probability of truth to imagine that the things of the unknown world – either all together or in part – are alien and wondrous to us. Here we see with our own eyes that in these waters the compass needle deflects from the North Star quite a bit toward the West – a novel phenomenon unheard of to seamen before now; and no matter how long I ponder, I cannot find a reason that satisfies me. For all this, however, I do not mean to imply that we should lend an ear to the fables of the ancients about the wonders of the unknown world and of this ocean, as, for instance, Hanno's fable about the countries filled with flames at night and about the rivers of fire flowing headlong into the sea. Indeed, we see how empty so far have been all the fears of dreadful prodigies and terrifying novelties felt by our men during this voyage – as when they saw that great mass of seaweed that seemed to turn the water into a meadow, somewhat obstructing our path, and they thought they had reached the ultimate limits of the navigable sea. But in answer to your question, I only mean to suggest that my assumption is based on the most probable arguments, not only in my judgment but in the judgment of many distinguished geographers, astronomers, and navigators, whom I have consulted, as you know, in Spain, Italy, and Portugal. Yet it might happen to be incorrect, for, as I repeat, many conclusions drawn from the best reasoning do not stand the test of experience, and this occurs more than ever when they concern things which are quite obscure to us.

gutierrez. Then, in effect, you have staked your life, and the lives of your companions, on an issue that has no more basis than a purely speculative assumption.

columbus. That's true. I can't deny it. But leaving aside the fact that every day men risk their lives for much smaller causes and for matters of very little value – and even without giving it any thought – consider this: if you and I and our companions were not on these ships in the middle of this sea, in this unknown solitude, in as uncertain and dangerous a condition as we can imagine, what other kind of life would we be living? What would we be doing? How would we be spending these days? More happily, perhaps? Or, rather, wouldn't we be in some anxiety or hardship – or filled with boredom? What is a condition free from uncertainty and danger? If content and happy, it is to be preferred to any other; if tedious and miserable, I don't see what other kind of condition would be less desirable. I won't remind you of the glory and the benefits we will reap, should the outcome equal our hopes. Even if we don't gain any other advantage from this voyage, it still seems most profitable to me insofar as for some time it keeps us free from boredom, makes life dear to us, makes many things valuable to us which we might have otherwise held in low esteem. The ancients write – as you have probably read or heard – that unhappy lovers, hurling themselves into the sea from the Rock of Santa Maura (which was then called the Leucadian Rock) and surviving, were freed from the amorous passion by the grace of Apollo. I don't know whether we should believe that they were thus cured, but I know well that after escaping such a danger, they must have briefly held dear the very life they previously hated, even without Apollo's favor; or, in any case, they must have held it dearer and more valuable than before. In my judgment, every sea voyage is almost like a leap from the Leucadian Rock, and it produces effects which, although the same, are more lasting. In this sense, a sea voyage is far superior. It is commonly believed that being constantly in danger of death, seamen and soldiers value their own life much less than other people. But for the same reason I believe that very few people love and value their life as much as seamen and soldiers. How many blessings we ignore only because we have them! How many things that cannot even be called blessings seem very dear and very precious to seamen only because they are deprived of them! Who ever counted among human blessings having a little land to stand on? No one except seamen and, above all, ourselves, who, because of the great uncertainty about the outcome of this voyage, have no greater desire than the sight of a bit of land. This is the first thought that comes to us when we awaken, with this thought we fall asleep, and if from afar we happen to discover the tip of a mountain or a forest or a similar thing, we will not be able to contain our joy; and having set foot on land, only the thought of finding ourselves again on solid ground and of being able to go here and there walking as we please will make us feel full of bliss for several days.

gutierrez. All this is quite correct, so much so that if your speculative assumption proves as true as your justification for having followed it, we shall no doubt enjoy this bliss – one day or another.

columbus. Personally, although I no longer dare promise it to myself with certainty, I hope, nevertheless, that we will soon enjoy it. For several days, as you know, the sounding line has been touching bottom; and the nature of what it brings to the surface seems a good sign to me. Toward evening, the clouds around the sun appear different in form and in color from those of the past days. The air, as you can feel, has become a little milder and warmer than in the past. The wind has no longer been blowing so full, and straight, and steady, but rather uncertain and variable as if it were interrupted by some obstacle. Add to this that reed floating in the sea which has apparently been recently cut and that little branch with its fresh red berries. And then the flocks of birds ... they have misled me before, but there are so many of them now and so large and they grow so much in number from day to day that I feel we can somewhat rely on them, especially because there are among them some birds which do not seem to be shaped like marine birds. In short, as much as I try to restrain myself, all these signs together give me great and good expectations.

gutierrez. This time God grant that it come true.

In Praise of Birds

One spring morning, Amelius, the solitary philosopher, was sitting with his books in the shade of his country house, reading. Struck by the singing of birds all around, he gradually began to listen and think, and he stopped reading. Finally, he took up his pen, and then and there he wrote what follows.

Birds are by nature the most joyous creatures in the world. I do not mean this in the sense that they always bring you joy whenever you see or hear them but that they themselves feel joy and gaiety more than any other animals. The other animals normally look serious and grave, and many of them even appear melancholy; they seldom give signs of joy, and when they do, these are slight and brief; during most of their enjoyment and pleasures they do not show exhilaration or any indication of gaiety. Even if they derive pleasure from the green fields, from the open and beautiful vistas, from the brilliant sunshine, from the crystalline and sweet air, they do not give any outward sign of it – except for the hares, about which it is said that at night when the moon shines, and especially when it is a full moon, they hop and play together, rejoicing in that brightness, as Xenophon writes. Mostly, birds show themselves extremely joyous in their movements and in their looks; and their virtue of bringing us gaiety by their presence comes only from the fact that their forms and their actions are always such that by nature they display a special ability and a special disposition for pleasure and joy – an appearance not to be deemed empty and deceptive. With every pleasure and satisfaction they experience, they sing; and the greater the pleasure or the satisfaction, the greater the vigor and the effort they put into their singing. And since they sing a great deal of the time, we must conclude that normally they are cheerful and enjoy life. And although it has been observed that when they are in love they sing better and more often and at greater lengths than at other times, it must not be believed that they are not moved to singing by other pleasures and other satisfactions than those of love. For we can clearly see that on a calm and serene day they sing more than on a dark and turbulent one; and during a storm they keep silent as they do any other time they are assailed by fear; and after a storm, they come out into the air singing and playing with one another. Similarly, we can see that they are used to singing in the morning when they wake, being moved partly by the gaiety they derive from the new day and partly by the pleasure, common to all animals, of feeling restored and refreshed by sleep. Likewise, they highly enjoy cheerful verdures, fertile vales, pure and transparent waters, beautiful landscapes. It is quite interesting that what appears agreeable and beautiful to us appears the same to them – as may be ascertained by the lures with which they are drawn into nets or birdlime in the hunting thickets and the like. It may also be ascertained from the nature of those places in the countryside that are most frequented by birds and where their singing is continuous and fervid. On the other hand, either none or very few of the other animals, except perhaps those that are domesticated and are used to living with men, share with us this notion of the amenity and the beauty of places. This should not be surprising, for they find pleasure only in what is natural. Now, in these things, a very large part of what we call natural is not so but is, in fact, rather artificial; thus cultivated fields, trees, and other plants trained and disposed in a certain order, rivers confined within precise boundaries and directed toward a definite course, and similar things have neither the condition nor the appearance they would have naturally. So that the aspect of every country in habited by generations of civilized men – even if we do not consider the cities and other places where men congregate to live together – is something artificial and very difierent from what it would be in nature. Some people say, and it would bear on this subject, that the voice of birds is softer and sweeter and their singing more modulated in our areas than where men are wild and primitive; and they conclude that birds, even being free, pick up a little of the civilization of those men whose quarters they frequent.

Whether these people speak the truth or not, it certainly was a remarkable provision of nature to assign to the same species of animals both song and flight; so that those whose job it was to amuse the other living beings with their voices should normally be in high places, from which the sound could spread about through a greater space and reach a larger number of listeners, so that the air, which is the element destined for sound, should be peopled with vocal and musical creatures. We truly draw great consolation and pleasure – and we men no more, in my opinion, than the other animals – from listening to the singing of birds. And I think that this comes mainly not from the sweetness of the sounds, no matter how great they are, nor from their variety, nor from their mutual resonance, but from that gaiety which is naturally contained in song in general and in the song of birds in particular. Which is, so to speak, a sort of laughter, uttered by the birds when they feel well and comfortable.

Thus, in some way, it might be said that birds share with man the privilege of laughter – a privilege the other animals do not have. In fact, some people thought that since man is defined as an intellectual and reasoning animal, he could no less adequately be defined as a laughing animal, for they believed that laughter is no less characteristic of man than reason. And this is indeed something to marvel at: that man, who is the most afflicted and the most miserable of all creatures, should possess the faculty of laughter, which is alien to every other animal. And also something to marvel at is the use we make of this faculty, for we see many in extremely severe accidents, others in the depths of sadness, and still others who scarcely retain any love for life at all, totally convinced as they are of the vanity of every human good, almost incapable of any joy, and deprived of all hope – and yet we see them laugh. As a matter of fact, the more they know the vanity of those goods and the unhappiness of life, and the less they can hope and the less they are suited for the enjoyment of pleasure, the more men are inclined to laughter. Yet the nature of laughter in general and its inner principles and modes, as regards that part of it which consists in the mind, can scarcely be defined and explained – except by saying that laughter is a form of temporary madness, raving, and delirium. For men, never being satisfied and never finding real pleasure in anything, cannot have a reasonable and just cause for laughter. It would also be interesting to investigate how and on what most probable occasion men first used and recognized this power of theirs. For there is no doubt that in a primitive condition, they generally appear serious, as do the other animals; and they even look melancholy. Thus, I am of the opinion that not only did laughter appear in the world after tears – as to which there cannot be any controversy – but that it took a good space of time before it was first experimented with and seen. And during that time neither did the mother smile at her child, nor did the child recognize her with a smile – as Virgil says. For if nowadays, and at least where people have become civilized, men begin to laugh shortly after they are born, they do so mainly as a result of example because they see others laugh. I would think that the first occasion and the first cause for men to laugh was drunkenness – which is also inherently characteristic of the human race. This originated long before men attained any kind of civilization; in fact, we know that there can scarcely be found any people so primitive who have not provided themselves with some beverage or some other means to inebriate themselves and who are not in the habit of doing so immoderately. This should not be surprising, for as men are unhappy beyond all other animals, so more than all others do they find pleasure in every painless alienation of the mind, in forgetting about themselves, in an interruption, so to speak, of life. And so, by suspending, or in some way decreasing, the sense and knowledge of their own ills, they receive no small benefit. And as to laughter, we can observe that, although they are of serious and sad appearance at other times, primitive people laugh profusely when drunk – talking abundantly and singing, contrary to their habits. But I will discuss these matters more extensively in a history of laughter, which I have in mind to write. After investigating its birth, I will proceed by narrating its exploits, its vicissitudes, and its fortunes, up to the present time – when it is given more dignity and power than ever before by holding a place in civilized nations, by performing a function through which in some way it assumes the roles previously played by virtue, justice, honor, and the like, and in many ways by restraining and frightening men from evil actions. Now, to conclude on the singing of birds, I will say that since we generally draw consolation and gaiety from the joy we see or know in others – if we do not envy them – Nature very laudably decided that the singing of birds, which is an expression of gaiety and a kind of laughter, should be public whereas the singing and the laughter of man, with respect to the rest of the world, are private; and she wisely saw to it that the earth and air should swarm with animals that continuously give out resonant and solemn sounds, as though to applaud universal life and incite other living creatures to gaiety, thereby bearing uninterrupted, though false, witness to the happiness of all things.

And that birds are and show themselves to be more joyous than the other animals is not without a profound reason. For as I implied at the beginning, Nature really made them better suited for pleasure and happiness. First of all, they do not seem to be subject to boredom. They change place every moment; they pass from one region to another, however remote, and from the lowest to the highest realms of the air, in a brief space of time and with prodigious ease; in the course of their lives they see and experience things that are infinite in number and most diverse in form; they continuously exercise their bodies; they greatly abound in open-air activities. All the other animals, when they have provided for their needs, like to sit quietly and leisurely; not one of them, with the possible exception of fish and also some flying insects, goes running about for sheer amusement. Similarly, primitive man – who hardly takes a step except to keep providing for his daily needs which demand but little and short work, or except when a storm, or some wild beast or another similar event drives him – likes mainly leisure and apathy; he consumes almost his entire day sitting indolently and silently inside his little shapeless hut, in the open air, or in the clefts and caverns of cliffs and rocks. Birds, on the contrary, remain in the same place for a very short while; they continuously come and go without any need whatsoever; they fly around for pleasure; and sometimes they enjoy flying hundreds of miles from the area where they usually stay, and then they return there the evening of the same day. Even during the short time they stay in one place, you will never see them sit still; they keep turning here and there, strolling about, bending, stretching their necks, shaking, fluttering with liveliness, agility, and an indescribable swiftness of movement. In short, from when a bird is unlocked from the egg until it dies, save for the intervals of sleep, it is never at rest for a moment. As a result of these observations, it seems apparent that by nature the normal state of the other animals, including men, is rest; of birds, movement.

To these qualities and external conditions correspond the internal ones, that is to say, those of the mind – which make them better suited for happiness than other animals. Their sense of hearing is extremely sharp, and their eyesight is so efficient and perfect that our minds can hardly imagine it; because of these powers they enjoy all day long immense and most diversified spectacles, and from high up they discover at once so great an expanse of land and distinctly perceive so many regions with their eyes as man can hardly comprehend at the same time; from which we must infer that they must possess very great strength and vivacity and very great power of imagination. Not of that kind of profound, fervid, and tempestuous imagination as Dante and Tasso possessed – which is a most fatal gift and the origin of most grievous and perpetual anxiety and anguish – but of the kind that is rich, varied, light, unstable, and childlike, which is the most abundant source of pleasant and joyful thoughts, sweet illusions, manifold pleasures and consolations; it is also the greatest and the most fruitful gift Nature can generously bestow on living souls. Thus, birds possess in great abundance what in this faculty is good and conducive to mental happiness without what is noxious and painful. And since they abound in external life, they are equally rich in the internal but in such a way that this abundance brings them advantages and pleasures, as with children – not disadvantages and misery, as generally with men. For as in their liveliness and outward mobility birds manifestly resemble children, so we may reasonably assume that they resemble them in their inner qualities as well. And were the blessings of childhood common to the other ages and the ills of these no greater than those of childhood itself, perhaps man would have cause to bear life patiently.

In my opinion, if considered in certain ways, the nature of birds surpasses in perfection the nature of the other animals. For example, if we consider that birds by far excel all the others in eyesight and in the faculty of hearing, which, according to the natural order concerning living creatures, are the principal senses, it then follows that the nature of birds is more perfect than the other natures of living creatures. Additionally, if, as we have seen, other animals are naturally inclined to rest and birds to movement – and movement is more alive than rest, life consisting actually in movement, while birds abound in external movement more than any other animal – and moreover, if eyesight and hearing, in which they excel all the others and which predominate among their powers, are the two senses most characteristic of the living, for they also are more vivid and mobile both in themselves as in the habits and other effects that they produce inwardly and outwardly in the animal; and, finally, if we consider the other things already mentioned, the conclusion follows that birds have more external and internal life than the other animals. Now, if life is more perfect than its opposite, at least in living creatures, and if, therefore, a greater abundance of life is greater perfection, also here it follows that the nature of birds is more perfect. At this point we cannot forget that birds are equally suited to withstand the extremes of cold and heat, even without any interval of time between one and the other. In fact, we often see that in little more than an instant, from the ground they soar through the air to very great altitudes, which is like saying to extremely cold areas, and in a short time many of them fly across a variety of climates.

Finally, as Anacreon wished he could be changed into a mirror to be continuously looked at by his beloved, or into a skirt to cover her, or into an ointment to anoint her, or into water to wash her, or into a breast band so that she would press him to her bosom, or into a pearl which she would wear around her neck, or into a shoe that at least she might press him with her foot – similarly, I would like to be changed for a while into a bird so that I could experience the contentment and the joy of their life.

Song of the Great Wild Rooster

Some Hebrew scholars and writers assert that between the sky and the earth, or rather half in one and half in the other, there lives a certain wild rooster, whose feet rest on the earth and whose crest and beak touch the sky. In addition to such peculiarities of his as can be read in those authors, this giant rooster has the use of reason; or, indeed, like a parrot, it has been taught by I know not whom to utter words in the manner of men. In fact, a song entitled Scir detarnegòl bara letzafra, that is to say, Morning Song of the Great Wild Rooster, written in Hebrew script and in a language mixed with Chaldean, Targumic, Rabbinic, Cabalistic, and Talmudic, was found in an ancient parchment. I have managed to understand it and to translate it into our vernacular as follows, not without great labor or without consulting various rabbis, cabalists, theologians, jurists, and Jewish philosophers. I have not been able to ascertain as yet whether this song is repeated by the rooster from time to time or every morning; whether it was sung only once; who hears it or who has heard it; whether its language is actually the language of the rooster or whether the song itself was translated from another tongue. As to the present rendering, I have sought in every way I could to make it as faithful as possible, and I have thought it best to use prose rather than verse, notwithstanding the fact that it was poetry. Its somewhat disconnected and perhaps occasionally turgid style should not be held against me, for it conforms to that of the original text, which in this respect corresponds to the norms of Oriental languages and especially of their poets.

Up, mortals, awake! The day is born again; truth returns to earth, and empty images depart. Arise; take up again the burden of life; return from the false to the real world!

This is the time when everyone collects and reviews in his mind all the thoughts of his present life, recalls to memory his plans, efforts, and affairs, represents to himself the pleasures and the afflictions that might come to him during the new day. And each one during this time wishes more than ever to find in his mind joyous expectations and pleasant thoughts. But very few are granted this wish. For to awake is unfortunate for everyone. No sooner are the wretched awakened than they fall back into the hands of their unhappiness. Sweetest of all things is that sleep which was brought about by a combination of joy and hope – which are both preserved whole and safe until the coming of day, but then they both fail or dwindle.

If the sleep of mortals were perpetual and one and the same with life; if under the day star all living creatures languished in the most profound quiet all over the earth and there appeared no activity whatever: no lowing of oxen in the meadows, no roar of wild beasts in the forests, no singing of birds in the air, no murmur of butter-flies nor buzzing of bees throughout the countryside, no voice, no movement arose in any place but that of waters, winds, and storms; then the universe would indeed be useless; but would there perhaps be in it a lesser quantity of happiness or a larger amount of misery than there is now? I ask you, O Sun, author of the day and guardian of our waking hours, in the course of the centuries that you have so far measured and consumed rising and setting, did you once see a single one of the living beings happy? Of the innumerable works of the mortals which you have seen until now, do you think that even one achieved its aim: the satisfaction, continuous or temporary, of the creature that had produced it? Rather, do you see now, or did you ever see, happiness within the confines of the world? In what field does it dwell, in what forest, on what mountain, in what valley, in what region inhabited or deserted, in what planet of the many your flames light up and warm? Maybe it hides from your sight or resides in the depths of the caverns or in the bosom of the earth or at the bottom of the sea? What living thing, what plant or anything else you give life to, what creature endowed with, or deprived of, vegetative or animal life partakes of it? And you yourself, who, like an indefatigable giant, night and day, without either sleep or respite, swiftly run the immeasurable path that is prescribed to you, are you happy or unhappy?

Mortals awake! You are not yet free from life. The time will come when no external force, no internal movement, will shake you from the quiet of sleep, in which you will then forever insatiably rest. Death is not granted to you as yet; only occasionally are you allowed a semblance of it for a short space of time. For life could not be sustained if it were not frequently interrupted. Too long a want of this brief and ephemeral sleep is in itself deadly and a cause of eternal sleep. Such a thing is life that in order to bear it, we must lay it down, now and again, to catch our breath and to refresh ourselves with a taste and almost a particle of death.

The very essence of things seems to have death as its real and only purpose. All that exists springs from nothingness, because what does not exist cannot die. It is certain that the ultimate purpose of existence is not happiness, for nothing is happy. It is true that living creatures aim at this end with every one of their works; but they do not attain it through any one of them; and during their entire lives they keep striving, straining themselves, and suffering without agonizing and without toiling toward anything but the achievement of this sole purpose of nature, which is death.

The first hours of the day are normally the most endurable for the living. Few people find their minds occupied by pleasant and joyous thoughts when they awake; but almost everyone produces and forms some rather quickly; for at that hour the human mind, although without any specific and particular reason, is above all inclined to cheerfulness and more disposed than at any other time to tolerate the ills of life. Therefore, if someone was filled with despair when caught by sleep, he again finds hope in his mind when he awakens, even if there is no reason for it. Many misfortunes and personal troubles, many causes for fear and for distress appear at that time much smaller than the night before. Also, often the anguish of the past day is scorned and almost laughed at as the result of illusions and of empty imagining. The evening is comparable to old age, while the beginning of the morning is like youth, which is generally at ease and confident; and the evening is sad, discouraged, and inclined to ominous expectations. But just as actual youth in life, so the one mortals experience every day is extremely brief and ephemeral; and very soon the day too grows older.

Although it is the best part of life, the flower of our years is yet a rather miserable thing. In fact, even this paltry blessing fails in such a short time that when man notices by many signs that it is declining, he has scarcely experienced the perfection of his being, or has hardly been able to feel and know his own powers when they already begin to diminish. Mortal creatures of all kinds spend the greatest part of life withering away. So much is nature intent upon pointing to death in all her works: for no other reason does old age prevail so manifestly and for so long a time in life and in the world. Every part of the universe hastens indefatigably toward death with marvellous determination and swiftness. Only the universe itself appears immune to decaying and to languishing; for if in the fall and in the winter it shows itself almost infirm and old, nevertheless, it always grows young again in the new season. But just as mortals in the first part of the day reacquire some portion of their youth and yet grow older every day and finally expire, so the universe may appear to grow young again at the beginning of every year, although it nevertheless continuously grows older. The time will come when this universe and nature herself will be no more. And just as of very great human kingdoms and empires and of their marvelous exploits, which were so very famous in other ages, there remains no sign of fame whatsoever; so too of the entire world, and of the infinite vicissitudes and calamities of all created things, no single trace will remain; but a naked silence and a most profound quiet will fill the immensity of space. Thus, this stupendous and frightening mystery of universal existence, before it can be declared or understood, will vanish and be lost.

The Copernicus

Scene One

the first hour and the sun

first hour. Good morning, Your Excellency.

sun. Yes, rather, good night.

first hour. The horses are ready.

sun. Good.

first hour. The morning star has been out for some time.

sun. Let her come and go as she likes.

first hour. What do you mean by that, Your Excellency?

sun. I mean that I want you to leave me alone.

first hour. But, Your Excellency, the night has already lasted so long that it can't last any longer. If we wait any more, Your Excellency, something really strange might happen.

sun. Whatever happens, I'm not going to move.

first hour. Oh, Your Excellency, what's that? Don't you feel well?

sun. No, no, I'm not feeling anything. I just don't want to move. And you, you mind your own business.

first hour. How can I, if you don't come? I'm the first hour of the day; and how can the day be, if Your Excellency isn't kind enough to come out as usual?

sun. If not to the day, you'll belong to the night – or the Hours of the night will work a double shift, and you and your day companions will do nothing. Because, do you know what? I'm tired of this continuous going around to give light to a few little animals that live on a handful of mud – so small that I, who have quite good eyesight, can't even see it. Tonight I have decided that I don't want to take any more trouble for this; and if men want to see some light, they should keep their fires burning or find some other way.

first hour. But, Your Excellency, what way do you want them to find, those poor little creatures? And to have to keep their lamps burning or to keep so many candles lit the whole space of the day will be excessively costly. If they had already found that kind of air to be used for burning, for lighting streets, rooms, shops, cellars, and everything else, at a very low cost, then I would say that it wouldn't be so bad. But the fact is that three hundred years, more or less, still have to pass before men find this kind of remedy. Mean-while, they'll run out of oil, and of wax, and of pitch, and of tallow; and they'll have nothing more to burn.

sun. They can go and catch fireflies and glowworms.

first hour. And what will they do against the cold? For without Your Excellency's assistance, the firewood of all the forests won't be enough to keep them warm. They'll also starve to death, for the earth will no longer bear fruit. And so in the course of a few years, even the breed of those poor animals will be lost. And when they'll have gone groping here and there about the earth for a while, looking for something to eat and to keep warm, finally, after there is nothing left to swallow and when the last spark of fire is no more, they'll all die in the dark, frozen like pieces of rock crystal.

sun. Why should I care? Am I, by any chance, the wet nurse of the human race, or the chef who must prepare and cook their food? And why should I care if a few invisible little creatures, millions of miles away, can't see and can't stand the cold without my light? And then, if I must also serve, so to speak, as a heater or a fireplace for this human family, it's only reasonable that if the family wants to warm themselves, they should come to the fireplace, and not that the fireplace should go running around the house. So, if the earth needs my presence, let her go moving around herself and do everything possible to get it; for, personally, I don't need anything from the earth that I should go and look out for her.

first hour. Your Excellency means to say, if I understand well, that now the earth should do what you have been doing in the past.

sun. Yes, now, and forever from now on.

first hour. Your Excellency is certainly right there, in addition to the fact that you can do whatever you like. Nevertheless, please consider how many beautiful things will necessarily go to rack and ruin if you establish this new order of things. The day will no longer have its beautiful gilded chariot, with its beautiful horses, that used to bathe in the sea; and without dwelling on other details, we poor Hours will no longer have a place in the sky, and from celestial maidens we'll become terrestrial, unless, as I expect, we dissolve into smoke. But be this as it may, the problem will be to convince the earth to go around, which must be quite difficult, for she is not used to it; and it must also seem strange to her to have to run forever and exert herself so much, after never having moved an inch from that place of hers. And if Your Excellency is seemingly beginning to lend an ear to laziness, I've heard that the earth is in no way more inclined to physical exertion now than she was in the past.

sun. In this case, need will goad her and make her jump and run as much as necessary. But here the fastest and surest way is to find a poet or a natural philosopher who would convince the earth to move or, in case he couldn't convince her, who would force her to. For in the long run, most of this business is in the hands of poets and of natural philosophers; as a matter of fact, they can do nearly anything. The poets are those who in the past (when I was younger and listened to them), with those beautiful songs of theirs, led me – big and fat as I am – to do of my own free will, as a sport or an honorable exercise, that extremely stupid job of running desperately around a small grain of sand. But now that I'm older and have turned to philosophy, in everything I look for what's useful and not for what's beautiful; and the sentiments of poets, when they don't make me sick, make me laugh. Before doing something, I want to have good and substantial reasons; and since I find no reason whatsoever for considering an active life preferable to a leisurely and pleasant one – for an active life could not give you any fruit worth the trouble or even the thought (in the world there is no fruit worth a penny) – I've resolved to leave the exertions and the discomforts to others and, as far as I'm concerned, live at home in peace and without doing anything. Besides being partly the effect of age, this change, as I told you, was caused by philosophers – people who these days have begun to gain power, and keep gaining it more and more. Therefore, if I want the earth to move and to run around in my place, in one respect a poet would be more suitable than a natural philosopher or a scientist, for poets, with one story or another, make people believe that the things of the world are really valuable and important and that they are very pleasant and beautiful, and they create a thousand cheerful hopes, and thus they persuade people to exert themselves and work hard, whereas philosophers dissuade them. However, since philosophers have begun to get the upper hand, I'm afraid that nowadays a poet would not be listened to by the earth any more than by me; or if he were listened to, he wouldn't have any effect. Therefore, I think it's better if we enlist the services of a natural philosopher or a scientist, for although philosophers are normally little suited, and still less inclined, to persuade others to work, it might nevertheless happen that in this extreme case they would manage to do something totally unusual – unless the earth decides that it is more advantageous to go to perdition rather than to trouble herself so much – in which case I wouldn't say that she is wrong. Enough, we'll see what happens. Now, do this: go down to the earth, or send one of your sisters, anyone you want; and if she finds one of those natural philosophers outside his house in the fresh air, studying the sky and the stars – for it is reasonable to expect that she will find some because of the extraordinary length of this night – without more ado, she should lift him up, throw him on her back, and bring him all the way up here to me; and I'll persuade him to do what's necessary. Do you understand?

first hour. Yes, Your Excellency. I'll do just that.

Scene Two

(Standing on his terrace, watching the eastern sky through a small paper tube – because the telescope had not been invented yet)

copernicus. Incredible. Either the clocks are all wrong, or the sun should have already risen more than an hour ago; and yet here we can't even see the faintest glimmer in the east, although the sky is as clear and limpid as a mirror. All the stars are shining as if it were midnight. Now go and check Almagest and Sacrobosco, and ask them to explain the reason for this. I have often heard about the night Jupiter spent with Amphitryon's wife; I also remember having recently read in a modern book by a Spaniard that the Peruvians say that once in ancient times there was in their country an extremely long night, as a matter of fact an interminable one, and that finally the sun came out of a lake they call Titicaca. But until now I thought that this was sheer nonsense; and just like all reasonable men I was sure that it was so. Now that I realize that reason and science aren't worth an iota, I have decided to believe that those, and similar things, may be perfectly true. In fact, I'm about to go to all the lakes and all the swamps I can find, to see if I can, by any chance, fish out the sun. But what's this roar that I hear – like the sound of the wings of a great bird?

Scene Three

the last hour and copernicus

last hour. Copernicus, I'm the Last Hour.

copernicus. The last hour? Well, I can't do anything about it. Only, if possible, give me enough time to write my last will and put my affairs in order – before I die.

last hour. What do you mean,‘die’? I'm not the last hour of life.

copernicus. Who are you then? The last canonical hour of the breviary?

last hour. I certainly believe that you like that one better than the others – when you are in the choir.

copernicus. But how do you know that I'm a canon priest? And how do you know me? You just called me by my name.

last hour. I got information about you from some people down below in the street. In short, I'm the last hour of the day.

copernicus. Ah, I understand. The First Hour is ill; that's why we don't see the day yet.

last hour. Allow me to go on. The day won't come any more – not today, not tomorrow, not ever, if you don't do something about it.

copernicus. That's a good one! As if it were my job to make the day!

last hour. I'll tell you how. But first you must come with me immediately to the house of the Sun, my master. You'll learn more along the way, and His Excellency will tell you part of it himself when we get there.

copernicus. All right. But if I'm not mistaken, the trip must be a rather long one. And how can I carry enough supplies so that I won't starve to death some years before I get there? Besides, I don't think His Excellency's lands produce enough for a single lunch.

last hour. Forget about these fears. You won't have to stay in the house of the Sun for long; and the trip will take but a moment – for in case you don't know, I'm a spirit.

copernicus. But I'm a body.

last hour. Well, there's no need for you to worry about these things; you're not a metaphysical philosopher. Come here, get on my shoulders, and leave the rest to me.

copernicus. Well, here we go ... Let's see how this thing is going to end.

Scene Four

copernicus and the sun

copernicus. Most illustrious sir.

sun. Forgive me, Copernicus, if I don't ask you to sit down; but we don't use chairs. We'll be done in a moment. You've already heard from my servant what this problem is all about. Personally – and from what the girl tells me about your ability – I think you are perfectly suited for the job we have in mind.

copernicus. Sir, I see many difficulties in this job.

sun. Difficulties should not frighten a man of your kind. As a matter of fact, people say that they increase the courage of the courageous. But then, what are these difficulties?

copernicus. First of all, no matter how great is the power of natural philosophy or science, I'm not sure it's so great as to convince the earth to begin to run rather than sit comfortably, and to work and exert herself rather than remain idle, especially in our times, which are not heroic at all.

sun. So, if you can't convince her, force her.

copernicus. Gladly, my illustrious sir, if I were a Hercules or even a Roland, and not a canon priest from Worms.

sun. What has that got to do with it? Aren't we told that one of your ancient mathematicians used to say that if he could stand somewhere outside the world, no doubt he could move heaven and earth? Now, you don't have to move heaven; and here you are in a place outside the earth. Therefore, if you're no less clever than that ancient one, you should be able to move her – whether she likes it or not.

copernicus. My dear sir, I could do that, but I would need a lever, which should be so long that not only I, but you yourself, illustrious sir, however rich you may be, wouldn't have enough to cover the cost of the necessary materials and of the labor. Another, and graver, difficulty is the following: as a matter of fact, it's like a knot of difficulties. Up to now the earth has held first place in the universe, that is to say, the center; and, as you know, she has been sitting motionless without anything else to do but look around at all the other globes of the universe, the largest as well as the smallest, the shiny as well as the dark, which have kept rolling above and below and by her sides with such a hurry, such a concern, such a vehemence that we are stunned if we just think about it. And, thus, everything proved to be at her services, and the universe looked like a court where the earth sat as if on a throne, and the other globes all around her, like courtiers, guards, and lackeys, tending to one job or another. As a result, the earth has always believed herself to be the empress of the universe; and, actually, while conditions remained as they were in the past, we can't say that hers was an unreasonable idea; as a matter of fact, I wouldn't deny that such an idea of hers rested on good foundations. And then what shall I tell you about men? We consider, and shall always consider, ourselves the first and the supremely important among all earthly creatures. Each one of us, even if dressed in rags and with no more than a piece of hard bread to gnaw on, thinks of himself as an emperor; and not just of Constantinople or of Germany or of half the earth – as the Roman emperors were – but as an emperor of the universe, an emperor of the sun, of the planets, of all the stars, visible and invisible, and the ultimate cause of the stars, of the planets, of your illustrious Excellency, and of all things. But now if we want the earth to abandon that central place, if we make her run, revolve, bustle about continuously, do exactly the same job as has so far been done by the other globes, and, finally, become one of the planets – this will mean that her earthly majesty, and their human majesties, will have to clear the throne and abandon the empire – being left with their rags and their miseries, which aren't few.

sun. What are you driving at with this talk, my dear Father Nicholas? Are you perhaps afraid that such an action would be high treason?

copernicus. No, most illustrious sir; for neither the codes, nor the Digest, nor the books of public law, nor those of imperial law, nor of civil law, nor of natural law, mention this kind of treason, as far as I can remember. But I mean to say that this business of ours is not going to be simply material, as it appears at first sight, and that its effects are not going to be restricted to physics, for it will upset all the steps on the ladder of the dignity of things and the order of beings; it will switch the purposes of creatures; and therefore it will cause an extremely great revolution in metaphysics as well as in fact, in every thing that touches the speculative side of knowledge. And as a result, if men can or want to reason well, they'll discover that they are something completely different from what they have been until now or from what they have imagined themselves to be.

sun. Son, those things don't frighten me at all; for I respect metaphysics as much as physics, and as much as chemistry – or necromancy, if you like. And men will have to be satisfied with being what they are, and if they don't like that, let them go on with their upside-down reasoning and with their arguing against the evidence of facts, as they will be able to do very easily. Thus, they'll continue to believe they are whatever they think – either barons, or dukes, or emperors, or anything else they like. This will comfort them, and those judgments of theirs won't annoy me in the slightest.

copernicus. All right, let's forget about men and about earth. But consider, my most illustrious sir, what we may expect to happen with the other planets. When they see that the earth has become one of them and does everything they do, they will no longer want to be so naked and unadorned, so deserted and sad as they have always been – with the earth alone having so many ornaments. They too will want their rivers, their seas, their mountains, their plants, and, among other things, their animals and their inhabitants; for they won't see any reason for being inferior to the earth in anything. And there will be another immense revolution in the universe: an endless number of new families will in a moment be seen springing up everywhere like mushrooms.

sun. And you can let them spring up. And let them be as many as they can; for my light and my heat will be enough for all of them – and at no extra cost; and the universe will have enough to feed, clothe, lodge, and treat them generously without getting into debt.

copernicus. But most illustrious sir, consider a little further, and you'll see yet another messy situation. The stars, too, when they see that you have sat down, not on a stool but on a throne, and that you are surrounded by such a beautiful court and such a population of planets – they, too, will want not only to sit down themselves and take a rest, but they'll want to reign as well; and in order to reign, one must have subjects; therefore, they'll want their own planets just as you have – each one his own. And these new planets will also have to be adorned and inhabited, like the earth. And at this point I won't tell you any more about the poor human race – which has already become almost nothing in relation to this present world. What will it become when so many thousands of other worlds burst forth so that the minutest star in the Milky Way won't be without one of her own? But even if we consider only your own interest, let me say that until now you have been, if not first, certainly second in the universe – let's say, next to the earth – and have had no equal, for the stars haven't had the audacity to compare themselves with you. But in this new state of the universe you'll have as many equals as there are stars with their worlds. So be careful that this change you want to make doesn't prejudice your own dignity.

sun. Don't you remember what your Caesar said when, crossing the Alps, he happened to pass near the hamlet of some poor barbarians? – that he would rather be first in that little hamlet than second in Rome. Similarly, I should prefer to be first in this world of ours rather than second in the universe. But it isn't ambition that moves me to change the present state of things; it's only the love of peace or, to be more exact, laziness. And so, I don't much care about having or not having equals or about being in first or in last place; for unlike Cicero I'm more interested in leisure than in dignity.

copernicus. Most illustrious sir, as far as I'm concerned, I'll do everything possible to get this leisure for you. But I'm afraid that even if I manage to succeed in my intent, it won't last very long. First, I'm almost sure that before many years have passed, you'll be forced to go whirling around like the pulley of a well or like a millstone – though without changing places. Then I suspect that finally, sooner or later, you'll find it necessary to begin to run again; I don't say around the earth; but what do you care about this? And perhaps that same revolving of yours will serve as a reason for your running. Enough, be it as it may; in spite of all difficulties and other considerations, if you insist in your resolution, I'll see if I can help you, so that if this doesn't work out, you'll believe that I could not – and not say that I'm a man without much courage.

sun. All right, my Copernicus, try.

copernicus. There is only one more difficulty.

sun. Tell me, what's that?

copernicus. I wouldn't like to be burned alive like the phoenix because of this. For if this happens, I'm sure that I wouldn't rise again from my ashes like that bird; and so, from then on I wouldn't see Your Excellency's face any more.

sun. Listen, Copernicus, you know that at the time when you philosophers and scientists had scarcely been born – I mean to say, when poetry held the field – I was a prophet. Now I want you to let me predict the future for the last time, and in memory of my ancient power I want you to believe me. So then, I tell you that perhaps after you, those who approve what you have done may get somewhat charred or something like that; but you yourself, as far as I can see, won't suffer at all because of this. And if you want to be even safer, follow this advice: dedicate the book you write on the subject to the pope. This way, I promise you that you won't even lose your canonry.

Dialogue Between an Almanac Peddler and a Passer-by

peddler. Almanacs, new almanacs; new calendars. Do you need any almanacs, Sir?

passer-by. Almanacs for the new year?

peddler. Yes, Sir.

passer-by. Do you think the new year is going to be a happy one?

peddler. Yes, Sir, absolutely.

passer-by. Like last year?

peddler. More, much more.

passer-by. Like the year before?

peddler. More, Sir, more.

passer-by. But like what other? Wouldn't you want the new year to be like one of these past years?

peddler. No, Sir, I wouldn't.

passer-by. How many new years ago did you start selling almanacs?

peddler. Sir, it must be twenty years.

passer-by. Which one of those twenty years would you want the next one to be like?

peddler. Me? I wouldn't know.

passer-by. Don't you remember any year in particular that you thought was happy?

peddler. Actually, I don't, Sir.

passer-by. But life is beautiful, isn't it?

peddler. Everybody knows that.

passer-by. Wouldn't you like to live those twenty years over again, and all your past years, beginning with the day you were born?

peddler. Eh, my dear Sir, I wish to God I could.

passer-by. But if you had to live exactly the same life all over again – with all its pleasures and all its pains?

peddler. I wouldn't like that.

passer-by. But what kind of life would you like to live over again? The life I've had, or a prince's, or who else's? Don't you think that I, the prince, or anyone else, would answer just like you, that having to live the same life over again, no one would want to go back to it?

peddler. I think so.

passer-by. You wouldn't go back either, unless you could in some other way?

peddler. No. Sir; I really wouldn't.

passer-by. But what kind of life would you like then?

peddler. Any kind, just as God would send it to me, with no other conditions.

passer-by. Any life at random, without knowing anything about it in advance, just as we don't know anything about the new year?

peddler. Precisely.

passer-by. That's what I would like too if I were to live all over again; and that's what everyone would like. But this means that, up until the end of this year, Fortune has treated everyone badly. And it's clear that every one thinks that he was allotted more, and greater, evil than good – if to live the same life all over again, with all its good and all its evil, no one would want to be born anew. The life that's beautiful is not the life we know, but the life we don't know; not the past life, but the future. With the new year, Fortune will start treating you and me and all the others well, and the happy life will begin. Isn't it true?

peddler. Let's hope so.

passer-by. Then show me your most beautiful almanac.

peddler. Here it is, Sir. This one is thirty cents.

passer-by. Here's thirty cents.

peddler. Thank you, Sir. Goodbye. Almanacs, new almanacs; new calendars.

译者导读

拉宾德拉纳特·泰戈尔（Rabindranath Tagore，1861-1941），印度著名诗人、作家、哲学家、艺术家以及社会活动家。他于1913年获得诺贝尔文学奖，是第一位获此殊荣的非欧洲人。中国读者对于泰戈尔的了解更多的是来自于他的诗歌作品，如《园丁集》《飞鸟集》《吉檀迦利》等。然而，泰戈尔的成就是多方面的。除了诗歌以外，他还创作并出版了大量的小说、戏剧、哲学以及政治学论著。

本次翻译出版的《民族主义》是泰戈尔于1916年在日本和美国所做的三篇演讲稿的合集，是其关于政治思想的重要论述。本书共分三个部分，分别是：日本的民族主义、西方的民族主义和印度的民族主义。而将这三个部分串联在一起的唯一主题则是泰戈尔对于源自西方的“民族主义”的深刻批判。

在“日本的民族主义”当中，泰戈尔对东西方文明进行了比较，对日本的崛起寄予了希望，同时还对她所面临的危险倾向提出了警告。泰戈尔为古老的东方文明进行辩护，认为它并非玄学，而是某种确实存在的、为人类心灵提供了庇护和滋养的智慧；它并非政治的文明，而是一种社会的和精神的文明，并且终将会有发扬光大的一天。泰戈尔还认为日本为亚洲各国树立了崛起的榜样，因为她不但获得了所有现代社会的禀赋，而且还深深地扎根于脚下这片古老的东方沃土。但是同时，泰戈尔还告诫日本不要盲目地模仿西方，不要以为实现了西方式的现代化就万事大吉了，特别是不要学习西方的民族主义而放弃自己固有的精神理想。

尽管三篇演讲稿的主题都是对于“民族主义”的批判，“西方的民族主义”仍然是对此讨论最为集中的一篇。泰戈尔认为，民族是指全体人民为了某个机械的目的，即获取政治的和经济的利益，而组织在一起所形成的团体。它是一个社会组织，是一台依靠贪婪的欲望来驱动的机器，它是人类道德理想的死敌。泰戈尔认为民族主义是理智的、科学的、机械的，而非人性的。尽管打着爱国主义的旗号，其实质则是民族的自私自利；对其他国家的人民，特别是对非民族主义的、贫弱国家的人民来说，则是残酷的剥削、束缚和压迫；而且，民族主义国家的人民往往会在浑然不知当中听由其政府的摆布，甚至于自豪而愉快地拜倒在本国的民族主义旗下。泰戈尔认为道德的律法才是人类永恒的真理，它不仅适用于个人，同样也适用于各个国家和组织。因此，与人类道德理想背道而驰的民族主义注定要喝下自己所酿成的毒酒，并且最终走上一条灭亡的不归之路。

在“印度的民族主义”中，泰戈尔认为印度同样不能盲目地学习西方，而要坚持走自己的道路。他认为印度所面临的最为严重的问题不是政治问题，而是社会问题，是种族问题，是过于森严的、种族隔离的壁垒。他抨击了印度的种姓制度，认为它尽管承认了社会差别的存在，但是却否认了生命易变性的法则。关于美国，泰戈尔认为她没有受到历史和传统的束缚，她乐观向上且感知力丰富，所以理应扛起未来文明的大旗，并且承担起向东方证明西方文明正当性的历史重任。

在演讲中，泰戈尔呼吁世界的和平和全人类的团结。他认为这个世界只有一部历史，那就是人类的历史。他的观点在过去、现在及将来都如夜空中的北斗一样指引着正义的人们前进的方向。总之，这是一本跨越时代的著作，无愧于“伟大的思想”这一名号。

翻译质量的高低从根本上取决于译者对于目标语的理解和对于母语的驾驭。以己昏昏，使人昭昭是万万行不通的。所以我们千万要警惕有人以某种不伦不类的、磕磕绊绊的、与原文貌合神离的译文来冒充所谓的“忠实于原文”。真正的“忠实于原文”是对于原文精神实质的深刻理解和以母语进行的流畅表达。它不能对原文进行阉割、遗漏、肢解和篡改，也不能打着“忠实”的幌子使得原本优美的原文变得味同嚼蜡，甚至于一团乱麻。这是本次翻译《民族主义》的一点个人体会，谨供读者参考。

日本的民族主义

I

对人们最残酷的奴役形式莫过于使其垂头丧气，因为这样就可以让他们在失去自信之中戴上绝望的枷锁。有人一遍又一遍地，有理有据地告诉我们，亚洲仍然活在过去——它就如同一座奢华的陵墓，以其庄严而华美的外表诉说着逝者的永垂不朽。他们说亚洲永远都不会走上进步的道路，因为它总是将视线投向过去。我们接受了这一指责，并且信以为真。据我所知，在印度有相当一部分受过教育的人们对这种指责所带来的羞辱感到厌倦，他们正试图调动一切可能调动的、自欺欺人的资源，努力将这一指责转变成某种可以自我吹嘘的事情。然而吹嘘只会掩盖羞耻，却并不能真正地说服自己。

就在这一切如此静止不动的时候，就在我们亚洲各国进入到一种恍恍惚惚的状态，认为任何的改变都不可能再发生的时候，日本从她的梦境中苏醒过来。她昂首阔步，将几百年来的无所作为甩在身后，并且以其卓越的成就站在了时代的潮头。这就打破了长久以来将我们陷于困境的魔咒——正是这一魔咒让我们相信，生活在某些地域内的某些种族的麻木不仁是理所当然的。然而我们却忘记了，伟大的王朝曾经在亚洲肇始，哲学、科学、艺术以及文学曾经在这里盛极一时，而世界上所有伟大的宗教都曾经在这里孕育。所以，我们不能说在亚洲的土壤和空气中有什么固有的东西会使我们的头脑变得迟钝，会使我们奋进的能力变得萎靡。几百年来，当西方在黑暗中昏昏欲睡的时候，我们东方人的确擎起了文明的火炬，而这一切都是我们并非思想懒惰或视野狭窄的明证。

然而漆黑的夜幕却降临在了东方的土地。时间的洪流戛然而止。亚洲似乎停止了进食新鲜的食物，转而靠咀嚼自己的过去维持生计——这是名副其实的自给自足。沉寂如死亡一般，那曾经传递过永恒真理的伟大声音也寂静了下来。正是这永恒的真理将人类从累世的污秽中拯救出来，就如同新鲜的、流动的空气不断涤荡着人世的罪恶，给人类送来甜美的祝福。

然而此时，生命似乎开始了休眠，进入到一种无所作为的状态——它静止不动，不思茶饭，完全靠过去的储备苟延残喘。它变得无能为力，肌肉松弛，并且因为不省人事而饱受讥讽。但是，在生命的律动中，此时的暂停一定预示着将来的重生。活动中的生命在不断地消耗着自身的能量。而这种挥霍无度并非长久之计，总有一天，生命将会奄奄一息，所有的付出都会停止，所有的冒险都将放弃，取而代之的将是休息和缓慢的恢复。

头脑的脾性总是倾向于走捷径：它热衷于形成习惯并且沿着已有的车辙前行，从而避免了每走一步都要重新思考的麻烦。思维定式一旦形成就会使头脑变得懒惰。它会惧怕在新的努力和尝试中失去已经占有的东西。它会在习惯的堡垒后面储藏自己的财产，以确保万无一失。然而，这其实是将它自身禁锢起来，从而不可能享有自己的全部财产。这是吝啬。有生命力的头脑一定不能将其自身与发展变化中的生活相隔绝。它们真正的自由并不会被圈在安全的藩篱后面，而是走在探索的大路上，尝试着各种新鲜的刺激和冒险。

早上醒来，整个世界都惊异地发现，日本已经在一夜之间冲破了重重旧习的包围，带着胜利的喜悦站立了起来。这一切都在令人难以置信的瞬间完成，就好像换了件衣服那样轻而易举，而不像是建造了一幢新的建筑。日本展现出了成熟的自信和一个新生命所特有的鲜活以及无限的潜能。人们担心，日本的崛起只不过是历史的偶然错误，是孩子式的游戏——就如同吹起的肥皂泡，带着完美的弧形曲线和绚丽的色彩，内心却是空空如也。但是日本已经毫无疑问地证明了，她力量的突然迸发并不是昙花一现，并不是岁月潮汐的偶然产物——从某个昏暗幽冥的深处翻卷而起，瞬间又被冲进了遗忘之海。

事实是，日本既古老又年轻。她拥有东方的、古老的文化传承——这一文化要求人们在自己的灵魂深处寻求真正的财富和力量；要求人们在面对挫折和危险时泰然自若，勇于牺牲自我而不计成本和回报；要求人们蔑视死亡，接受不可胜数的、我们作为人所应当履行的社会责任。一句话，现代的日本从历史悠久的东方脱颖而出，就如同一束莲花般优雅地绽放，而同时又牢牢地植根于脚下这片沃土。

日本，这个古老东方的孩子，已经无所畏惧地获取了所有现代社会所具有的禀赋。她毅然决然地冲破了积习的束缚，抛弃了懒惰头脑中的废物——这懒惰的头脑在其自身所设定的捷径和作茧自缚中才能找到安全感。由此，她已经顺应了时代的潮流，并且热切地、聪慧地承担起了现代文明的责任。

这就是日本给亚洲各国树立起的精神样板。我们已经看到了自身所具有的生命和力量；我们要做的就是要去除掉身上的死痂。我们已经看到了在逝者的庇护之下只会是死路一条，只有毫无保留地冒生命之险才会获得新生。

就我个人而言，我不相信日本通过模仿西方就可以变成今天的样子。我们不可能模仿生命，也不可能长时间地冒充强大。不仅如此，单纯的模仿只会产生虚弱，因为它束缚了我们的天性，阻断了我们的进步。它就像是在我们的骨架上套上了别人的皮肤，自此以后，只要我们稍有动作，皮肤和骨骼之间便会产生无休止的争斗。

事实上，科学并非人的本性，科学是通过学习知识和接受训练获得的。仅仅知道物质世界的法则并不能改变你的更深层次的人性。你可以从旁人那里学会知识，却不可能从他们那里学会性情。

但是，当我们还处在接受教育的模仿阶段的时候，我们并不能区分哪些是基本的要素，哪些是非基本的；哪些是能学会的，哪些是学不会的。这就有点像原始人所相信的，某些外部表象的偶发事件所具有的魔力——尽管这些偶发事件往往与某些真理相伴而生。于是我们便担心如果不将果壳连同果仁一同吞掉的话，那么就有可能遗漏掉一些有价值和可受用的东西。然而，即便是我们的贪欲对于大量的占有感到洋洋自得，我们的生命本性也会去消化吸收——对于一个生命体来说，只有这种占有才是真正的占有。只要有生命，它就会根据其自身所固有的需要来决定取舍。生命体不会随着其食物的样子而改变模样；相反，它会将食物消化吸收为其身体的一部分。唯有如此，它才能茁壮成长，而不是简单的占有，抑或是放弃自己的个性。

日本已经从西方引进了食物，而非生死攸关的本性。她一定不能在从西方那里获得的科学装备中迷失自我，从而变成一部单纯的、借来的机器。日本有自己的灵魂，而这一灵魂一定要支配她的所有诉求。日本所表现出来的健康活力充分地证明了，她有能力这样做，她的消化吸收过程正在进行中。我真诚地希望日本永远都不要在炫耀学习西方的成果时失去对自己灵魂的信仰。因为这种炫耀本身就如同羞辱，最终会导致贫穷和虚弱。只有招摇过市的纨绔子弟才会把钱都花在自己的新头饰上面，而不是去丰富自己的头脑。

整个世界都在等着瞧，这个伟大的东方民族会怎样地利用她从现代社会的手中所接受的机遇和责任。如果只是单纯地效仿西方，那么她将会令大家的殷切期望化为泡影。因为迄今为止，西方文明在世人面前所暴露出的严重问题仍未得到圆满的解答。比如，个人和国家间的矛盾，劳资矛盾，男人和女人间的矛盾；人们对于物质的贪欲和对于精神生活的追求之间的矛盾，各个民族不约而同的自私自利与对于人性崇高理想的追求之间的矛盾；庞大的商业和国家组织所带来的、林林总总的丑恶现象与人类所具有的朴素、美和休闲的天然本性之间的矛盾，等等——所有这一切的矛盾都有待于以某种迄今仍未想见的方式加以调和。

我们看到，人类文明的洪流正因为它不可胜数的支流所携带冲刷下来的垃圾废物而变得病入膏肓。我们看到，尽管它吹嘘自己是如何地热爱人类，然而事实上它已然变成了人类的最大威胁，相比人类早期历史上所遭受的、游牧野蛮民族的突然入侵所带来的伤害还要大得多。我们看到，尽管它吹嘘自己热爱自由，然而事实上它比过去任何社会的、任何奴隶制的形式都要糟糕——它的奴役的锁链牢不可破，因为它要么无影无形，要么假借自由的名义显身。我们看到，在它恶毒的、肮脏污秽的魔咒之下，人类失去了对于所有那些曾经使他们变得伟大的、英雄史诗般的人生理想的信仰。

因此，你们不能草率地接受现代文明的所有脾性、方法和结构，并且认为它们都理所当然。你们一定要将自己的思想、自己的精神力量、自己对于朴素的热爱、自己所认可的社会责任等等，融入其中，从而为这台巨大的、笨拙的进步之车开辟出一条崭新的道路，去除掉它在前进的过程中发出的刺耳尖叫。这台车每前进一步都会对人类的生命和自由造成巨大的牺牲，而你们一定要把这牺牲降到最低。多少世代以来，你们都以自己独特的方式进行着感知、思考和工作；你们享受着生活、崇拜着神明；而这些都不要弃之如敝屣。它存在于你们的血液中、你们的骨髓里、你们的肌理中、你们的脑袋里；它一定会在你们浑然不知当中改变你们所接触到的一切，甚至非你所愿。一旦你们真正圆满地解决了人类的问题，你们就会获得自己的生命哲学，并且逐步形成你们自己的生活艺术。你们必须将这一切运用到现实的条件当中，由此，新的创造就会产生出来，而不仅仅是重蹈覆辙——这一创造将属于你们人民的灵魂所有，并且你们可以自豪地将其作为对于人类福祉的贡品敬献给全世界。在所有的亚洲国家当中，只有你们日本有条件可以自由地依据你们的天赋和需求来使用从西方那里获得的物质财富。因此，你们的责任就更为重大，因为正是通过你们的声音，亚洲才得以对欧洲摆到人类会议桌上的诸多问题作出解答。在你们的土地上，实验将会进行下去。东方将会通过这一实验改变现代文明的面貌，以人类的心灵替代冷漠的功利——它对于权力和成功斤斤计较，却对和谐的成长、真理以及美丽视而不见、听而不闻。

我非常乐意同你们一起回味过去的时光。那时，整个东亚，从缅甸到日本，都以最亲密的友谊作为纽带与印度紧密地联系在一起。那友谊是存在于民族间的、唯一的自然纽带。它是心有灵犀的，是一套使得人性中反映最深层次需要的信息在我们之间可以自由传递的神经系统。那时，我们彼此并不惧怕对方；我们不需要武装自己以求相互制约；我们之间的关系不是建立在自私自利、剥削和掠夺彼此财富的基础之上；我们交流思想和理念，互换最崇高的爱的礼物；语言和风俗的迥异并没有阻碍我们彼此心心相印；没有什么身体或是精神层面的、种族的优越感或是傲慢无礼伤害我们之间的关系；我们的文学和艺术在这紧密团结在一起的、心灵的阳光普照下生叶开花，同时，生活在不同地域、操着不同语言、有着不同历史的各个种族都认同人类、最崇高的团结和最亲密的爱的纽带。我们难道不记得了吗？在那些充满和平和善意的、人们团结一致为生命的最高目标而奋斗的过去的时光里，你们的天性，依靠自身所具有的不朽的膏油，帮助你们的人民在新的时代获得了重生，帮助你们的人民摆脱了旧体制的束缚并且换上一副新的、年轻的皮囊，帮助你们的人民从这个世界前所未见的、最伟大的、革命的震荡中走出来而毫发无伤。

从欧洲的土地上萌芽，并且像多产的杂草一样在全世界蔓延开来的政治文明是建立在排他性的基础之上的。它总是虎视眈眈地拒“外人”于千里之外，或是干脆消灭他们。它嗜血成性，同类相残；它吞噬掉其他民族的资源并且试图毁灭他们的未来；它唯恐其他的种族获得成功——用它的话来说叫作危险；它试图在自己的边界之外扼杀一切伟大的事物；它压制其他羸弱的种族，希望它们永远羸弱。在这种政治文明大行其道之前，在它张开血盆大口吞噬掉地球上的各个大洲之前，我们有过战争、掠夺、王权的更迭以及由此引起的悲惨境遇。但是，我们从未见过如此可怕和绝望的贪婪，如此大规模的国家间的奴役，如此将大部分的世界绞成肉馅的庞大机器，如此恐怖的嫉妒——它张开丑恶的爪牙，随时准备将对方开膛破肚、剖腹挖心。这一政治文明是科学的而非人性的。它强大有力，因为它为达目的而孤注一掷，就像一位百万富翁为了攫取钱财宁可出卖灵魂。它背信弃义，并且厚颜无耻地编织谎言的罗网；它在自己的庙宇中供奉着巨大的贪婪偶像，并且以其奢华的膜拜仪式为傲——它称之为爱国主义。我敢保证，这一所谓的政治文明不可能长久地维系下去，因为在这个世界上还有道德的律法。它适用于个人，也同样适用于人类有组织的群体。没有人可以一方面以个人的名义享受这些道德律法所带来的好处，而另一方面却以国家的名义违背这些律法。这种公然的对于道德理想的腐蚀会慢慢地影响到每个社会成员，逐渐地在人们看不到的地方滋生虚弱，从而引起人们对于人性当中所有神圣东西的怀疑，这种怀疑正是人类衰老的病症。你们一定要记住，这一政治文明，这一爱国主义的信条还没有接受长期的考验。古希腊的明灯在其最初点燃之地已经熄灭；古罗马的权杖已经死去，并被掩埋在了它那广阔帝国的废墟之下。但是文明，其植根于社会和人类的精神理想，在中国和印度仍然拥有着生命。尽管以现代的、机械功率的标准来衡量，它可能略显虚弱和渺小，然而，它就如同细小的种子一样，仍然蕴藏着生命。一旦时机成熟，上天播撒下仁慈的雨露，它就会发芽、成长；它就会抽出仁爱的枝条，并且开花结果。但是，权力的摩天大厦一旦坍塌，贪婪的机器一旦破碎，即便是上帝的甘露也不会使其获得新生；因为它们本身不是生命，而是作为一个整体与生命对抗——它们是在对抗永恒真理之后所留下的支离破碎的残骸。

然而，我们却受到这样的指责：你们东方所珍爱的理想是静止的；它们没有前进的动力，也没有开拓新知识和才能的前景；作为东方诸多老朽文明支柱的哲学体系轻视所有外在的证据，对其主观的臆断麻木不仁且自鸣得意。这一指责证明了，当我们对知识的掌握含混不清的时候，我们就会倾向于指责作为客体的知识本身是含混不清的。对于西方的观察家来说，我们的文明看上去都是玄学，这就如同对一个聋子来说，弹钢琴不过是手指的运动而不是什么音乐。他不会相信我们的制度建立在某种已经发现的、深刻的现实基础之上。

不幸的是，所有现实的证据都还在实现的过程当中。而你只会根据亲眼所见的事实来判断场面的真实性，所以对我们来说，想要向某个怀疑我们文明的人作出解释绝非易事。但我还是要说，我们的文明并非一个由抽象的推论构成的混沌体系，它已经得出了某种不容置疑的真理——这种真理能够为人类的心灵提供庇护和滋养。我们的文明已经催生了一种内在的直觉——一种直觉的洞察力，一种在一切有限的事物中看到无限实情的洞察力。

但是那个人会说：“你们没有取得什么进步；你们根本就没动弹。”这时候我会问他：“你怎么知道我们没有进步呢？判断事物进步与否要看它的目标是什么。一列火车开到了终点算是进步了——它确实移动了位置。但是对于一棵已经长成的大树来说，它是不会像那列火车一样有确切的移动的；它的成长进步是生命内在的成长。它活着，带着对阳光的渴望——这渴望刺痛着它的叶片，在它寂静的树液中缓缓地流淌。”

我们也已经存活了几个世纪了；我们仍然活着，并且渴望着获得一个不断得以实现的现实——这一现实超越了死亡，并且赋予它意义；这一现实脱离了所有生活中的罪恶，并且给它带来和平与纯洁，以及欢愉的、对于自我的摒弃。这种现实是内心生活的产物，它是有生命的。当一个年轻人拖着满是灰尘的、疲倦的身躯回到家中的时候，当一个士兵战斗负伤的时候，当你的财富付之流水而自尊心遭受打击的时候，当一个人的心灵在浩繁的事实面前渴求真理，在彼此矛盾的诉求中期盼和谐的时候，你就需要它了。它的价值并不体现于物质财富的增长，而是体现在精神上的满足。

有些事物是不能等待的。如果你要战斗，或是想要在市场中占据有利的位置，你就必须冲过去，跑过去，或是急行军走过去。你绷紧了神经，时刻准备着捕捉到那些稍纵即逝的机遇。但是有些理想并不会跟我们的生活玩捉迷藏的游戏；他们从种子到花朵，从花朵到果实，缓慢地生长；他们要求得到无限的空间和天堂的光辉从而变得成熟，而且他们所结出的果实能够禁得住经年的摧残和漠视。东方，带着她的理想，怀抱着数个世纪的阳光和寂寞的星辰，能够耐心地等待——直到有一天，为了权宜之计而手忙脚乱的西方气喘吁吁，停下脚步。欧洲，在匆匆忙忙赶赴约会的疾驰中，会轻蔑地向车窗外田野中的收割者瞟上几眼。此时她陶醉于自己的一路狂飙，难免会认为那个收割者的动作是多么的迟缓，并且总是在不断地倒退。然而狂飙走到了尽头，约会也失去了意义，而且饥饿的心灵吵闹着索要食物。直到最后，她终于来到行动迟缓的、在骄阳下忙碌着的收割者的身旁。因为，如果说公务不能等待，或是说做买卖不能等待，抑或是说对于新鲜刺激急不可待，那么爱是可以等待的，美是可以等待的，遭受苦难所获得的智慧、耐心奉献所收获的果实、纯粹的信仰所带来的谦卑和温和是可以等待的。因此，东方一定会等到属于她的时代的来临。

我会毫不犹豫地承认欧洲的伟大之处，因为她的伟大是毋庸置疑的。我们会情不自禁地、全心全意地热爱她，并且满怀羡慕之情地向她致以最崇高的敬意——因为亘古以来，在文学和艺术方面，欧洲就以其美和真理的永不枯竭的瀑布流水灌溉滋养着所有的国家；因为欧洲正在以其强大无比且不知疲倦的心智席卷着全宇宙的峰峦和深渊，人们对她无所不包且渊博无比的知识推崇备至，而且正在将其伟大的学识和心智应用于救死扶伤，减轻人们的痛苦——而到目前为止，我们都还在心甘情愿地、无计可施地承受着这些苦难；因为欧洲正使得我们脚下的这片土地孕育出多得超乎人们想象的果实，她正将自然的伟大力量玩弄于股掌之间使其为人类服务。如此伟大的成就必然有其精神的推动力。因为只有人类的精神才能对抗所有的桎梏，才能对自身的最终成功抱有信仰；它将搜索的目光抛向远方、洞穿迷雾，它满心欢喜地以身赴死，为的是达到它在今生所不能达到的目标，它接受失败却从不放弃。在欧洲的心灵深处流淌着最为纯净的爱的血液，那是对于正义的爱，充满为了更高理想而自我牺牲的精神。数百年来的基督教文化已经在她的生命深处沉积下来。在欧洲，我们见到过那些置肤色和信仰于不顾，为了维护人权挺身而出的义士；他们勇敢地面对来自自己一方的各种流言蜚语甚至谩骂攻击，为了仁爱的理想而战斗，为了反对疯狂的穷兵黩武，为了反对有时控制了整个民族的、要求进行野蛮的报复和掠夺的狂暴情绪而振臂一呼；他们随时准备为自己的民族在过去所犯下的错误进行补救，并且徒劳地想要截住怯懦的、非正义的洪水，而这洪水正因为来自受害者一方软弱无力、不痛不痒的抵抗而四处奔流。在现代的欧洲，确有这样一些游侠，他们还没有丢掉自己的信仰；他们信仰无私的、对于自由的热爱，信仰超越地理边界或是国家私利的理想。这些人证明了，在欧洲，永世长流的水的源头还没有枯干，而正是在那里她将一遍又一遍地获得新生。而在另外一些地方，欧洲正在有意识地忙于积累自己的力量，违背并且嘲笑着自己内心的天性；她正在将自己的邪恶堆积得高耸入云，吵闹着要得到上天的惩罚，并且将自己灵魂和肉体的丑恶嘴脸传染给整个地球——用她无情的商业肆意地凌辱着人们对于美和善的良知。当欧洲的脸庞转向其人性的一面时她是多么的仁慈啊，而当她的脸庞转向自己利益一方的时候她又是多么的恶毒啊——她会竭尽所能达到目的，而这些目的却与人类的无限和永恒的目标背道而驰。

东亚一直在沿着自己的道路前行。她形成了自己的文明——这是一种社会的而非政治的文明；它不是一种掠夺性的、拥有机械效能的文明，而是一种精神的文明；它建立在人性所具有的、全部的、各种各样的、深层次关系的基础之上。各族人民生活当中的问题的解决方案都来自于远离尘嚣的苦思冥想，并且在丝毫没有受到王朝更迭和外敌入侵干扰的情况下，超然地付诸实施。但是现在，外面的世界突然降临，要想远离尘嚣再也不可能了。然而，我们一定不要为此而感到遗憾，这就像一株植物，永远都不要因为其播种期的隐伏状态被打破而感到遗憾一样。现在是我们应当把世界的问题当作自己的问题的时候了；我们必须把文明的精神与世界上所有民族的历史相调和；我们一定不要以一种愚蠢的、高傲的姿态，将自己封闭在曾经保护并且孕育我们理想的谷壳和地壳里；因为这些谷壳和地壳一定会被打破，唯其如此，生机勃勃的美丽生命才会喷涌而出，将礼物奉献给这个阳光灿烂的世界。

在此项冲破藩篱面对世界的任务中，日本已经代表东方第一个站了起来。她已经将希望注满了全亚洲的心灵。这种希望提供了隐藏的火种，而这火种正是一切创造性工作所必需的。现在亚洲感到，她必须以有生命力的成就证明自己的生命；她不应当再被动地休眠，或是以恐惧和献媚的蠢态虚弱地模仿西方。由此，我们要感谢这个太阳升起的国度，并且郑重地要求她记住自己所要完成的东方使命。她应当将更为完整的人性的活力注入到现代文明的心脏中去。她一定不要允许有害的灌木将它窒息；而要引领它向上，直达阳光和自由，直达纯净的空气和广阔的天际。在那里，每当黎明和黑暗来临的时候，它都能接收到上天的启迪。让日本的伟大理想昭示于世人吧，就如同她高高耸立的富士山山顶上的白雪一样，让所有地方的人们都看到——它卓尔不群，有美艳处女一般曼妙的身姿，而同时又坚定强壮，恬静庄严。

II

我曾经游历过很多国家，见到过各色人等；然而在我的游历当中，却从来没有见到过像在这片土地上存在着的、如此特殊的人性。在其他伟大的国家，人们的权力会凸显出来，而我也见到过庞大的组织机构，他们在各个方面都富有效率。在那些国家，服装、家具、奢华的招待等等方面的铺张炫耀程度让人咂舌。他们似乎要让你自惭形秽，就像是一个闯入盛宴的、不名一文的不速之客一样；他们善于让你感到羡慕或是大吃一惊。在那里，你不会感到作为一个人的至高无上；相反你会感到被抛到了一堆光怪陆离的物品堆中。但是在日本，给人最深印象的东西不是权力或是财富的炫耀。你所到之处能看到的，大都是爱和赞赏，而不是野心和贪婪。你所看到的是这样一个民族：她的心灵已经释放了出来，并且大量地体现在了其最常见的日常用品中、社会制度里、温文尔雅的举止上，以及它优雅而练达的处事方式等方面。

日本留给我最深的印象是你们已经认识到了自然的秘密，不是通过科学分析的方法，而是通过你们的同情心。你们已经获知了她的种种姿态所代表的语言，她的缤纷色彩所奏响的音乐，她的不规则中的对称，她的自由运动中的韵律；你们已经看到了她是如何统领庞大的物质群体而避免摩擦的，她的造物间的矛盾是如何转化为舞蹈和音乐的形式爆发的，她的生机勃勃是如何地充满了自我抛弃，而不仅仅是肆意的展示。你们已经发现，自然以美的形式储存了自己的力量；这种美，就如同母亲一样，用胸怀哺育着所有巨大的力量，并让它们充满生机，而自己却恬静安详。你们已经知道，自然的能量通过其完美的节奏使其自身免于枯竭，而同时，以其温柔的曲线带走了世间的疲劳。我感到你们已经能够将这些秘密融入到你们的生命当中去，而且那世间万物当中所蕴含的真理已经走入了你们的灵魂。对于事物表面知识的获取用不着花很长的时间，然而对于它们精神实质的掌握则需要数个世纪的训练和自我约束。同自然和谐地融为一体要比从表面上控制她困难得多，然而唯其如此才能叫作真正的智慧。你们的种族已经表现出了如此的智慧，不是通过获取，而是通过创造；不是通过物品的展示，而是通过它的内在本质向外透露。所有的民族都有这种创造性的力量；而这种力量，在抓住人类的本性并且根据它的理想赋予它某种形式方面也总是跃跃欲试。但在这里，在日本，这一力量似乎已经取得了成功，并且深深地进入到了所有人的头脑中，渗透到了他们的肌肉和神经里。你们的本能已经变得真实，感官变得敏锐，而且你们的手已经获得了自然的技巧。欧洲的智慧给予了她的人民以组织的力量，这一点主要表现在政治、商业以及科学知识的统筹等方面。日本的智慧不仅让你们看到了自然的美，而且给了你们可以使得它在生活中得以实现的力量。

所有特定的文明都是对某些特定人类经验的解读。欧洲似乎已经强烈地感受到宇宙中各种事物间的矛盾冲突，而这些矛盾冲突只有通过征服的手段才能将其置于控制之下。因此，欧洲总是准备战斗，而且她大部分的精力都集中到了对于力量的组织上面。但是日本感到，在她的世界里，有某种神灵的存在，而它则唤起了她灵魂深处某种虔诚的崇拜。日本并不吹嘘对于自然的掌控，而是带着无与伦比的关心和快乐，带给自然以爱的奉献。日本与外部世界的关系是深层次的心灵的交汇。她已经与本国的群山、海洋、溪流，以及繁花似锦、枝繁叶茂的森林结成了爱的精神纽带；她已经对林地的沙沙低语和叹息、波浪的呜咽和抽泣敞开了心扉；她已经研究了太阳和月亮全部阴晴圆缺的变化，并且会高兴地关门歇业，以便迎接其果园、花园和麦田里的收获季节。这种对于外部世界的灵魂敞开心扉的状态并不仅仅局限在你们上层社会的小圈子里；它并不是外来文化强加给你们的东西，相反，它属于你们的全体人民——男人和女人。你们灵魂的这种与外部世界的某个神灵相交汇的经历体现在了你们的文明之中。这是一种人际关系的文明。你们对于国家所担负的责任自然而然地呈现出了如同子女孝敬父母那样的特点；由此，你们的国家就像一个家庭，而天皇则是你们的家长。你们国家的团结并非来自出于防御或是进攻目的而诉诸武力时所结成的同盟，也不是来自为了使得每个人都分得赃物而不得不将他们置身险境进行冒险的劫掠时所形成的团伙。它不是为了某个秘而不宣的目的而被迫组织起来的结果，而是一种家庭关系的延续和一种在广阔的时空范围内所形成的心灵的契约。你们文化的核心是“慈爱”（maitri：loving kindness）——以一颗慈爱的心对待他人，以一颗慈爱的心对待自然。这种爱是通过一种美的语言的形式加以传达的，而这种美的语言在这个国家随处可见。这就是为什么，像我这样的陌生人不会在这些美的化身和爱的造化面前感到嫉妒和屈辱，相反会愿意分享这种展示人类心灵时所带来的快乐和光荣。

这使得我更为担心给日本文明带来威胁的变化，因为这一变化就如同套在某个人身上的枷锁一样。由于现代社会所具有的巨大的同一性——它唯一的、共同的纽带就是利益，世界上没有哪个国家像日本这样，可怜巴巴地将尊严和有节制的美所隐藏的力量暴露在了这种同一性之下。

但是危险就在这里——有组织的丑恶侵袭着人们的头脑，靠着它庞大的体量和咄咄逼人的气势占据了上风。然而，它嘲讽的对象却是人们心灵深处的情感。它强硬且独断专行；不管你愿不愿意，它都出现在你的面前。它让我们的理智俯首称臣——我们就像野蛮人供奉那些因为看上去丑恶才显得强大的偶像一样，为它的祭坛献上祭品。因此，它与那些谦虚的、深刻的、生命当中微妙而精致的东西之间的竞争是多么令人恐惧啊。

我敢肯定，在日本一定有人对你们所传承下来的理想并不赞同，他们的目标是获取利益而不是自身的成长。他们大肆地吹嘘自己已经使得日本现代化了。如果说一个民族的精神要与时代的精神相和谐的话，那么在这一点上我是同意他们的意见的；不过我还是要告诫他们，现代化不过是现代主义的表象而已，这就像作诗不过是诗歌艺术的表象而已一样。这不过是模仿，不同的是，表象看上去比原本的东西更夸张，同时也更死板。我们必须记住，那些有真正现代精神的人并不需要现代化，这就如同真正勇敢的人靠的并不是嘴上吹牛。现代主义并不是欧洲人的服装；也不是欧洲的孩子们上课并接受训练时所在的某些丑陋的建筑物；也不是一些方形的房子——墙面平直，平行的窗户排列整齐，而欧洲人则住在里面终其一生；当然现代主义也不是欧洲女士们的帽子，上面缀满了毫不搭调的饰物。这些并不“现代”，仅仅是“欧洲”而已。真正的现代主义是自由的思想，而不是被奴役的品位。它是思想和行动的独立，而不是欧洲学校校长们的监护；它是科学，而不是科学在生活当中的错误应用。例如，我们对某位教授科学的老师简单地加以模仿，而他却将科学降格为迷信，荒谬地祈求它帮助实现所有不可能完成的目标。

单纯依靠科学来生活对于一些人是有吸引力的，因为这种生活具备所有游乐活动的特点；它假装严肃，然而并不深刻。如果你出去狩猎，那么你的同情心则越少越好；因为你唯一目的就是追逐并杀死猎物，并因此感到自己是更为伟大的动物，感到自己的猎杀方法是严密和科学的。科学的生活是一种肤浅的生活。它以技巧和完善的方法追求成功，然而对于更高层次的、人的天性则不予理会。有些头脑简单的人把生活规划得就好像是狩猎一样，他们的理想就是成为成功的猎手；然而这些睡在骷髅所制成的奖杯堆中的人是迟早会被噩梦惊醒的。

我从来都主张日本应当获得进行自我保护的现代武器。但是这种行动不要超过她进行自我防御的需求。她一定要明白，真正的力量并不在于武器本身，而是在于使用武器的人；如果有谁急切地渴望权力，并且以他的灵魂为代价扩充军力，那么他的处境就会比他的敌人更加危险。

所有有生命的东西都容易受到伤害；因此，他们要求得到保护。在自然界，生命体通过它自身的材料所制成的外壳保护自己。所以这些外壳与生命的成长是相互协调的，否则的话，时间一到，他们就会轻易地垮掉并被遗忘。人类的真正保护来自于他的精神理想——它与人类的生命休戚相关并且一同成长。然而不幸的是，所有人类的铠甲都是没有生命的——有的是钢铁制成的，行动不便且机械呆板。因此，在利用这些铠甲的同时，人类还需小心保护他自身不被铠甲所控制。如果他灵魂虚弱，不得不削足适履而穿上这件铠甲的话，那么他灵魂的萎缩则无异于慢性自杀。日本自己，一定要坚定地信仰道德的生存法则，相信西方各国正走在通往自杀的道路上；因为在那里，他们正在以各种组织的巨大重量压抑并且窒息着自己的人性，为的是让自己大权在握，同时让他人俯首称臣。

日本的危险并不在于模仿西方的外部特征，而是在于她接受西方民族主义的动机并且为己所用。日本的社会理想在其政治的操控下已经显现出了失败的迹象。我可以看到她从科学那里借鉴来的座右铭：“适者生存”，就赫然地挂在她当代历史的大门上。这个座右铭的意思就是，“照顾好你自己，永远不要管会给别人带来什么损失”——这是瞎子的座右铭，因为他们看不到东西，所以只相信自己的触觉。但是明眼人一看便知，人与人之间紧密相连，你攻击了别人也必会遭到别人的反戈一击。道德的律法是人类最伟大的发现，它发现了这样一条奇妙的真理——以人为鉴可以明得失。这一真理不但具有主观的价值，而且在我们生活的方方面面都有体现。那些不懈地将对道德的无视奉为爱国主义的圭臬的国家一定会暴毙而终。在历史上，我们曾见过多次的外敌入侵，但是他们从来都没有深深地触动过人民的灵魂。这些侵略不过是个人野心膨胀的结果而已。人民并不会为那些冒险行动卑鄙可耻的一面负责任；相反，他们自身会从这些冒险行动所具有的英雄和人性的方面受益匪浅。由此，他们培养了坚定不移的忠诚，对于所肩负的责任的全身心投入，完全的自我牺牲的勇气，以及面对死亡和危险时所表现出的大无畏精神。因此，位于人民心中的理想并不会由于某个国王或是将军所采取的政策而发生剧烈的变化。但是现在，西方民族主义的精神却大行其道：全体人民从小就接受想尽一切办法鼓动仇恨和野心的教育。人们编造历史上的、片面的真理和谎言；人们不断地丑化其他的种族和文化；人们经常错误地建造大事件的纪念碑，从而不断地鼓吹邻国和其他国家对于自己所造成的罪恶的威胁，然而事实上，出于人性的原因，这些所谓的大事本应当被快速地遗忘。这样做无异于毒害我们人性的本源，是在败坏我们与生俱来的、最伟大和最美好的理想。它是在将无与伦比的自私自利作为一种普世的宗教，提供给世界各国来朝拜。我们可以从科学的手中获取各种各样的东西，而唯独不能索取这颗将置道义于死地的仙丹妙药。永远都不要认为，我们给其他种族造成的痛苦不会落到自己的头上，或是我们在自家房前屋后种下的仇恨会像一堵围墙一样保护我们的永世平安。以某种变态的、唯我独尊的虚荣心为整个民众洗脑；教育他们以自己道德上的冷漠和攫取的不义之财为荣；通过展出在战争中所缴获的战利品以达到对战败国家永远的羞辱，并且在学校里面展出这些东西以培养孩子们对于其他国家的蔑视等等，上面所说的这些所作所为，都是在模仿带着溃烂脓疮的西方——是疾病对于生命力的吞噬造成了它的肿胀。

我们赖以生存的粮食作物是历经数百年的选择和培育才形成的。然而我们并不食用的植物则并不需要数代人的耐心照料。除去杂草并不是件容易的事情；但是，如果疏忽大意，那么毁掉我们的粮食作物，让它们回复到最初的野生状态，则是件轻而易举的事。文化也与此类似，它竭力地适应了你们这里的土壤——它与生活息息相关且通达人情。所以它在过去的时代需要我们进行耕耘和除草，现在同样需要我们的悉心照料。单纯的现代事物，例如科学和组织的方法，是可以移植的；但是攸关生死的人性的东西一旦被从其生长的土壤中移除则会死掉，因为它的纤维极为脆弱，根须不可胜数且交错纵横。因此，我为西方的政治理想所强加到你们原有的政治理想上所造成的压力而感到担忧。在政治文明中，国家是一个抽象的概念，而人与人之间的关系则是功利的。因为这样的政治文明并不是植根于情感，所以它易于操控却险象环生。半个世纪的时间对于你们来说已经足够来驾驭这台机器了；你们当中有些人对于它的喜爱超过了对于与你们的国家同时降生并且历经数百年培育而成的生命理想的热爱。这就像一个孩子，在他玩得兴起的时候，竟然会觉得自己对于玩物的喜爱超过了对于母亲的爱。

人们通常并不能意识到自己的伟大之处。你们的文明，它的主要推动力来自于人际关系的纽带，是在没有受到鬼鬼祟祟的自我分析的影响下，在健康生活的沃土中孕育成长起来的。但是单纯的政治关系是完全自觉的；它是一种富于侵略性的突然喷发的火焰。它靠突然的喷发引起你们的注意。现在是时候了，你们大家应当认识到自己赖以生存的真理是什么，而不再任人摆布却浑然不知。过去，是上帝赐予你们的礼物；而现在，你们必须作出自己的选择。

所以你们要向自己提出以下这些疑问：“我们是否错误地认识了世界，并且把与世界的关系建立在了对于人类本性一无所知的基础之上了呢？西方将她的国家福祉置于对于人性普遍不信任的藩篱的保护之下，这种做法可取吗？”

你们一定已经察觉了，无论何时，西方在讨论某个东方民族可能的崛起时，她的口吻中便充满了强烈的恐惧。之所以会这样，是因为西方所赖以发迹的力量是一种邪恶的力量；只有将这种力量据为己有她才会感到安全，而令其他的国家颤抖。现在欧洲文明的主要野心就是排他性地占有这一魔鬼。她所有的军事力量和外交手段都服务于这一目的。但是这种花费不菲的、为罪恶的神灵招魂而举行的奢华仪式正将她由繁荣引向了灾难的边缘。西方所释放到这个世界上的恐怖的仇恨，反过头来威胁到了她自身，并且驱使她实行越来越多的残暴政策；这使得她惶惶不可终日，并且除了自己给别国带来的，而最终又回报到自身的灾难以外，忘记了一切。欧洲牺牲其他的国家作为祭品，以敬献给这尊政治的魔鬼。只要其他国家的尸身还算新鲜，她便以其为食并且吃得腰滚肚圆——但是尸体最终一定会烂掉的，而死者的复仇方式就是将污染传到四面八方，从而毒害进食者的生命。日本拥有所有人性的财富，她的英雄主义和美的和谐统一，她的深深的自我克制和丰富的自我表现；然而，若不是她证明了，撒旦的猎犬不仅可以在欧洲的狗窝里繁育，同样也可以在日本得以生养并且以人类的苦难为食的话，那么西方各国是不会对她表示尊重的。只有当日本也获取了，只要她愿意就可以随时打开的，将地狱的烈火烧遍美好人间的灾难之门的钥匙的时候，只有当世界走向毁灭，而日本也能够随着他们的节拍与之一起大跳抢劫、谋杀、奸淫无辜妇女的魔鬼的舞蹈的时候，他们才会承认日本与自己拥有同等的地位。我们知道，在人类早期道德观念还不成熟的时候，他只会因为害怕上帝的恶毒手段而对其感到敬畏。但是，我们可以自豪地仰望这一人类的理想吗？在我们的文明发展了数百年之后，各个国家就像夜间潜行的野兽一样彼此惧怕对方；他们关闭了彼此间好客的大门；只有出于侵略或是防御的目的他们才会联合起来；他们将自己的商业秘密、国家秘密、军事秘密藏在洞穴里；为了获得和平，他们将本不属于自己的肉块投食给了彼此的鹰犬；他们压制想要挣扎着站起来的衰弱的民族；他们用右手给衰弱的民族派发宗教，而同时用左手对他们巧取豪夺——所有这些，有一丝值得我们羡慕的地方吗？我们要向这种民族主义的神灵顶礼膜拜吗？它正在向全世界播撒着恐惧、贪婪和猜疑的种子。它正在散布着无耻的外交谎言。它正在进行着造作的表演，鼓吹自己以促进和平、善意以及全体人类的手足之情为己任。当我们涌进西方的市场，以我们自己的传统来换取这种外国产品的时候，我们的心中就没有产生过怀疑吗？我知道，要了解自己并非易事；一个醉汉会狂怒地否认自己喝醉了；然而，西方正在焦虑地思考着她自身的问题，并且试图加以改变。但是她就如同一只贪婪的饕餮，并不真心想放弃暴饮暴食的习惯，而是天真地希望能够通过吃药来治愈自己消化不良的噩梦。欧洲还不打算放弃她在政治上的不人道，尽管这种不人道体现出了所有人类的低级情欲；她只相信对于制度的修改，而不相信对于心灵的改变。

我们乐意以头脑而不是心灵购买他们用机器制造出来的制度。我们会试用这些制度并且加以完善，但是我们不能将它们供奉在我们的家中或是庙宇里。有的种族会崇拜他们所猎杀的动物；在饥饿的时候，我们可以从他们那里买下肉食，但我们却不能学习他们猎杀动物后的崇拜行为。我们不能以诸如“生意归生意”“战争归战争”“政治归政治”等迷信的说法毒害我们孩子们的思想。我们一定要明白，人类的生意不仅仅是生意，战争不仅仅是战争，而政治也不仅仅是政治。你们日本拥有自己的工业；要想知道你们的工业是多么的诚实和真切，看一看你们的产品就明白了——它们造型优雅而又结实耐用，它们在几乎观察不到的细节的方面也处理得一丝不苟。然而，来自于世界那端的谎言的潮汐已经席卷了你们的大地，在他们那里，生意归生意，而诚实也不过是最好的对策而已。当你们看到商业广告的时候就从来没有感到过羞耻吗？那些商业广告不仅给整个城镇都涂抹上了谎言和夸张，而且还侵入到农民们诚实劳动着的绿色的田野中，侵入到了早晨第一缕清澈的阳光所照射到的山岗上。当谎言和欺骗骄傲地打着贸易、政治和爱国主义的旗号在海外大行其道时，那种不间断的腐蚀会轻易地让我们的荣誉感和敏锐的思想变得迟钝起来，进而使得任何对于他们永久性地侵入我们生活的指责，都会被认为是多愁善感和缺乏男子汉气概的表现。

现在的情况是，子孙后代们积极地编织着谎言，也不会因为从谎言中获得利益而感到羞耻；相反，他们的父辈却是宁死也要信守诺言，他们鄙视靠欺骗以赢取庸俗的利益，在战斗中他们宁可失败也不愿意丧失荣誉。这一切的改变都是因为受到了“现代”这个词的魔力的影响。但是，如果“现代”就是指纯粹的功利的话，那么美可是属于所有时代的；如果“现代”就是指卑鄙的自私自利的话，那么人类的理想可不是什么新鲜的发明。所以我们必须明白，无论“现代”因着方法和机器的缘故，如何擅长削弱人类的劳动能力，它都将不得善终。

然而，当我们试图将自己的思想从欧洲傲慢的声言中解放出来的时候，当我们试图帮助自己从沉迷的泥潭中脱身的时候，我们可能会走向另外一个极端——对于所有西方的东西不作区别地加以怀疑。幻想破灭时的反应与最初幻想产生时的冲动一样的虚幻。我们需要努力达到一种正常的思想状态。在这种状态下，我们可以清楚地看到自身所存在的危险，并且在公正地对待产生危险的源头的前提下，对其加以规避。我们总会自然而然地希望能够以欧洲之道还治欧洲之身，并且以眼还眼、以牙还牙。但是，这种做法本身就是在模仿欧洲的最恶劣的行径之一：她在对待自己所描述的黄、红、棕、黑等等各个种族的人民时的所作所为就是如此。我们曾经以完全轻蔑的态度和残忍来威胁那些属于某一特定宗教、肤色或是社会阶级的人们。在对人性进行攻击这一点上，我们东方人不得不承认自己所犯下的罪行并且承认我们的罪过，即便不是更大，起码也与欧洲人不相上下。我们的弱点是遇到强权就俯首称臣。正是由于我们害怕自己的这个弱点，所以我们才会试图以另外一个弱点来代替它——对西方所取得的成就视而不见。只有当我们真正地了解了欧洲的伟大和善良，才能让我们有效地远离欧洲的卑鄙和贪婪。当面对人类苦难的时候，我们很容易作出不公正的判断——悲观失望是由于一方面崇信理想，而另一方面心智却饱受摧残而造成的。只有当对给信念带来力量的真理失去信心时，当信念遭受了巨大的挫败并且祈盼着自己能够涅槃重生的时候，我们才会对人性感到绝望。我们必须承认西方有这样一个活的灵魂——它悄无声息地与强大的组织机构进行着斗争——正是这些组织机构将男人、女人和儿童压得粉碎；正是这些组织机构的机械的零部件置精神的和人道的律法于不顾。这一灵魂，在与它缺乏自然同情心的种族进行交往的时候，拒绝让自己的触角因为疏忽大意的危险习惯而完全地失去敏锐。如果西方的力量仅仅是如动物或机器一般的力量的话，那么她永远都不可能达到如今的成就。她心中的神性正在由于她双手所带给这个世界的伤害而受到煎熬——也正是从她的这种高尚天性的疼痛中流淌出了神秘的、能够将这些伤害治愈的膏油。她曾经一次又一次地否定自己，并且亲手解开她套在无助的人们身上的锁链；尽管她为了攫取钱财，以武力相逼迫，将毒药强行灌入某个伟大民族的喉咙，可她还是在清醒之后，退出行动，并且再次把双手洗得干干净净。这不时地证明了她还保有隐藏的人性源泉，尽管它看上去似乎已经死掉或是枯竭。这还说明，能够帮助她摆脱如此胆怯而又凶残的行径的本来天性并不是贪婪，而是对于无私理想的尊崇。无论对于我们还是对于欧洲来说，认为欧洲仅仅是通过炫耀自己的力量才使得现代东方诸民族神魂颠倒的说法，都是完全不公正的。欧洲道德本性的光辉穿透加农炮的硝烟和市场上扬起的尘土而大放异彩。她给我们带来了道德自由的理想，这一理想的根基要比社会习俗扎得更深，而且它的活动范围则是世界性的。

东方已经本能地感到，即便是带着厌恶的情绪，自己仍有很多东西要向西方学习。这些要学习的东西不仅仅包括能够产生力量的材料，而且还包括欧洲的内涵，比如人类的心智以及他的道德天性。欧洲一直在教育我们，公序良俗的约束力要高于家庭和宗族的约束力；使得社会免受个人不确定性影响的神圣的法治精神，确保了社会的进步以及对于社会全体成员的公平正义。最重要的是，历经数百年的牺牲和不懈的努力，欧洲在我们面前高举起了自由的旗帜——良知的自由、思想和行动的自由、艺术和文学理念的自由，等等。由于欧洲已经获得了我们深深的敬意，所以，她的极为虚弱和错误的方面对于我们来说就会变得极为危险——这种危险就像是与我们最喜爱的食物混在一起同时端上来的毒药一样。有一种可以信赖的、保障我们安全的方法，这就是，在对抗她的诱惑和剧烈的侵蚀时，我们可以与欧洲结为盟友；因为一直以来，欧洲都有着她自己的善恶标准。通过这一标准，我们可以探知她的堕落，衡量她的失败；通过这一标准，我们可以在她自己的法庭上传唤她，并且揭露她的丑行——唯其如此，才能彰显真正的高贵。

然而，我们所担心的是她的毒药要比食物更厉害，她今天所拥有的力量并非是健康的标志，而是恰恰相反；因为，她的力量可能是由于其生命体暂时地失去平衡所致。我们担心的是，当罪恶获取了巨大的身形，它就会拥有致命的魔力——尽管最终它一定会因为自己反常的比例失衡而失去重心，但在它轰然倒下之前所造成的伤害可能是难以弥补的。

因此，我请求你们要坚定信心，同时保持清醒的头脑。一定要知道，靠钢铁的、高效的螺栓结合在一起的，在野心勃勃的车轮上奔跑着的，现代进步的庞然大物一定不会长久地维系。撞车是迟早的事，因为它不得不在指定好的线路上行走；它太过笨重，所以不能自由地选择自己的路径，而当它一旦脱离了轨道，长长的车厢就会翻倒。总有一天它会变成一堆废铁，严重地阻塞世界的交通。难道现在我们还没有看到这一迹象吗？我们还没有听到战争的喧嚣、仇恨的尖叫、和绝望的哀嚎吗？我们还没有看到长久以来在民族主义的深处所沉积并被翻搅起来的、难以名状的污秽吗？所有这些都在向我们的灵魂哭诉，告诉我们，民族的自私的高塔，尽管它以爱国主义的名义打起了反叛天庭的旗号，也一定会摇摇欲坠并且最终倒塌，一定会被它自己的大块头所压倒，它的旗帜一定会淹没于尘土，它的光亮终将会熄灭。兄弟们，当火灾的烈焰对着星辰发出噼啪作响的欢笑时，你们一定要对星辰，而不是对破坏性的烈火充满信心。因为，当大火燃尽熄灭的时候，留下的只是一堆灰烬，而永恒的光芒则会再一次在东方闪耀——在那孕育了人类历史的，太阳初升的东方闪耀。谁又敢说这一天还没有来临，而太阳还没有升起在亚洲最东方的天际呢？就像我的先哲所做过的那样，我要向东方的日出敬礼，它定会再一次地照亮整个世界。

我知道，我的声音太过微弱，不可能盖过这个熙熙攘攘的时代的喧嚣。任何一个街边的顽童都会轻而易举地给我取个“空想家”的绰号。这个“空想家”的标签会一直粘在我的上衣后摆上面，永远都洗刷不掉，从而让所有可敬的人们都对我嗤之以鼻。我知道，现如今，如果有谁在一群体格强健而又躁动不安的人当中并被冠以“理想主义者”的名号，那么他要冒多么大的风险！因为现在，王权已经失去了往日的威严，而预言家们则变成了一个时代错误；现如今，来自市场的喧闹淹没了所有声响。然而有一天，当我站在横滨市的郊区，对它所呈现出的现代景象震惊不已的时候，我看到了你们城市南方大海上的日落，我发现了长满松树的山岗中所蕴含的静谧和庄严——雄伟的富士山在金色的地平线的映衬下正变得模糊不清，就像一位天神被他自己的光辉所笼罩——永恒的音乐之声在寂静的黑夜中奏响，而我感到，天空与大地，以及黄昏与黎明所作的抒情歌谣只能是属于诗人和理想主义者，而并非属于那些对于所有情感都粗鲁地加以鄙视的商人们——我感到，在对于自己的神性不理不睬之后，人类将会再次记起上苍其实是一直与这个世界相联系的，它永远都不会将这个世界抛弃给现代追逐名利、嗜血成性并且对天哀嚎的群狼。

西方的民族主义

人类的历史是由我们所遭遇到的困难塑造而成的。这些困难给我们提出了疑问，同时也期望得到我们的解答，而对没能完成这一任务的惩罚则是死亡或是衰退。

世界上不同的民族所遭遇到的困难是不尽相同的，而我们克服这些困难的方式也各有不同。

生活在亚洲历史早期的塞西亚人不得不设法解决他们自然资源匮乏的问题。他们最初想到的解决方法就是将整个部族，不分男女老幼，都组织起来，以团伙的方式去抢劫。而那些主要从事社会协作性质的、建设性工作的人们简直拿他们没有办法。

但所幸的是，人类最初选择的道路并非他的真正道路。如果他的天性不是那么复杂的话，如果他像一群恶狼一样头脑简单的话，那么到此时此刻，那些从事抢劫的游牧部落就会控制整个世界。但是人类，当他遇到困难的时候，一定会承认他是人，他必须对自己天性中更高级别的才能加以利用。如果他忽视了这些，那么即便可能会取得眼下的成功，这成功也必将会成为他的死亡陷阱。因为对于一些低等的生物来说是困难的东西，对于像人类这种更高级的生命来说则是机遇。

印度从其历史的最开端就面临着这样的问题——种族问题。在印度，人种学意义上的不同种族已经有了亲密的接触。这一事实曾经是、将来也一定是这个国家历史上最重要的问题。我们的使命就是正视它，以实事求是的态度对待它，从而证明我们的仁爱。除非我们完成了自己的使命，其他的任何利益都不会与我们有缘。

世界上其他民族要么需要克服其自然环境所带来的困难，要么需要战胜他们的强邻所带来的威胁。他们组织起了自己的力量，以便充分地保障自身不受自然界和邻国的奴役，甚至利用其手中过剩的力量威胁他人。但是在印度，我们的困难来自于内部。我们的历史就是一部不间断的、社会调整的历史，而不是一部讲述将力量组织起来进行防御或是侵略的历史。

无论是苍白含混的世界主义还是对本民族狂热的自我崇拜都不是人类历史的目标。一直以来，印度都在试图完成自己的任务。她一方面对差异进行社会规范，另一方面，则倡导对于团结精神的认同。印度犯下了严重的错误，因为她在种族之间建立了过于森严的壁垒，以使得对于种族三六九等的划分可以无限期地延续；她常常毒害孩子们的思想并且限制他们的生活，以达到将他们划归到特定社会等级的目的。但是几个世纪以来，人们已经进行了新的实验，作出了新的调整。

印度的使命就像是一位家庭主妇的使命：她要为无数的客人提供合适的食宿，而这些客人的习惯和要求却各不相同。这样就产生了极为复杂的情况——要应对这些情况，不仅仅要依靠老练和机智，还要依靠同情心以及人与人之间的真正团结。为了实现这种团结，从早期《奥义书》[1]的时代一直到现在，许多精神导师一直在努力地工作着，他们的任务之一就是通过全心全意的、对于上帝的觉悟来蔑视所有人与人之间的差异。事实上，我们的历史从来就不是王朝兴衰的历史，不是争夺政治权位的历史。在印度，有关这些方面情况的记载已经为人们所唾弃、忘记，因为它们并不能代表我们人民的真正历史。我们的历史是有关社会生活的历史，是有关实现精神理想的历史。

但是我们感到自己的任务还未完成。世界的洪流已经席卷了我们的国家，新的元素被介绍进来，而更为广泛的调整正在蓄势待发。

因为西方所提供的教导和榜样与我们认为印度所应当完成的任务背道而驰，所以我们更为迫切地认识到了上述这一点。在西方，商业和政治的国家机器制造出了包装整齐的人性的压缩包，它们自有用处并且市场价值高昂；但是，它们是用铁条捆绑好的，以精密和仔细的科学手段进行了分门别类。显然，上帝造的人应当具有人性，但是西方这件现代产品却拥有令人赞叹的、棱角分明的大工业制成品的味道。所以，造物主一定很难相信这件产品拥有什么灵魂，并且是按照他自己的神圣模样生产出来的。

但是我满怀期望。我要说的是，无论你怎样看待她，印度就是印度。一个拥有至少五千年历史的印度。一个试图和平地生活、深刻地思考的印度。她完全不关心政治，不关心政府，她唯一的雄心壮志就是将这个世界当作精神的存在加以认知，在这世界里以温顺而倾慕的精神度过她生命的每一刻，并且高兴地意识到自己与这个世界之间存在着的永恒的、密切的联系。这正是人性中边远的一部分，它的行为如孩子，而智慧却如长者。然而就在此刻，西方民族却突然闯了进来，打破了这里的宁静。

尽管历经了早期历史上的战争、阴谋和欺诈，印度却依然保持着超然的态度。因为她拥有属于自己的家庭、土地、学校和庙宇。在学校里，老师们和学生们在朴素、关爱和求知的气氛中生活在一起，而她的自治村庄则拥有简明的法律以及和平的管理。然而，印度所关心的并非她的王权。王权的更迭于印度就像是过眼云烟——一会儿染上了绚烂的紫色，一会儿又乌云压城，电闪雷鸣。王朝更迭过后留下的是一片狼藉，但是就像是自然灾害一样，人们对它所留下的痕迹不久便忘却了。

但这次却不同了。这次不仅仅是掠过印度生活表层的过眼云烟，例如骑兵和步兵，盛装的大象，白色的帐篷和华盖，驮着王室物品的、四平八稳地走过来的骆驼队，由铜鼓和长笛所组成的乐队，大理石砌成的圆顶的清真寺，宫殿和陵墓等等，就像奢华的起泡酒所漾起的泡沫一样到处都是；也不仅仅是关于叛逆和效忠的故事，财富流转的故事，命运起伏的故事等等；这次来的是西方民族，它将自己机械的触手深深地扎入了这片土地。

因此我对你们说，正是“我们”作为证人被召集起来，来证明所谓的民族对于人类来说意味着什么。大家都知道曾经入侵印度的莫卧尔人和帕坦人的游牧部落，但是对我们来说他们都是人类种族，他们有自己的宗教和习俗，自己的好恶和爱憎——我们从未把他们当作一个民族来看待。我们根据不同的情况，时而爱他们时而恨他们；我们为他们打过仗，也曾经与之为敌；我们与他们用同一种语言交谈；而我们在决定王国命运的时候也发挥了积极的作用。但是，这次我们要面对的不是国王，不是人类种族，而是一个民族——而我们自己却还不是一个民族。

现在让我们从自己的经验出发来回答这样一个问题：到底什么是民族呢？

民族是指，全体人民为了某个机械的目的，即获取政治和经济的利益，而组织在一起所形成的团体。这样的社会团体，其目的非常明确。它自身就是目的。它是人作为一种社会存在的，自然的自我表露。它是对人际关系的自然规范，以便人们能够在与他人的合作过程中产生自己的人生理想。民族还有其有关政治的一面，但是它仅仅服务于特定的目的，即进行自我保护。它仅仅是权力的一面，而非人类的理想。早期的时候，它在社会中有自己单独的活动区域，局限在专业人士的范围之内。但是在科学和日益完善的组织的帮助之下，它的权力开始增长并且开始获得大量的财富。接着，它便以极快的速度跨越出了自己的活动范围。然后，它以对于物质繁荣的贪欲，彼此的相互嫉妒，以及对于对方变得强大而产生的恐惧等等，来刺激它所有毗邻的社会团体。现在它已经是欲罢不能了，因为竞争越来越激烈，组织越来越庞大，而自私自利则变得至高无上。它利用人类的恐惧和贪婪，在社会中占据了越来越大的空间，而且最终成为了统治力量。

你完全有可能，由于习惯所致，没有意识到生机勃勃的社会纽带正在分崩离析，正在让位于单纯的机械的组织。但是它所表露出的迹象其实是随处可见的。正因为如此，我们看到，男人和女人之间已经爆发了战争，因为将他们和谐地连接在一起的自然纽带正在崩断；因为男人们被驱赶上了专业主义的道路，忙于为自己也为他人生产财富，他们不断地为了自己或是为了迎合普遍的官僚作风而转动权力的车轮，然而女人们却被冷落一旁，孤独终老或是孤军奋战。因此，自然的合作状态被竞争所打破。男人和女人对待彼此关系的心理也在发生着变化，变为了一种包含原始的斗争元素的心理，而不再是那种以相互的自我牺牲为基础的，追求完善的人性。那些已经失去了与现实之间联系的元素，同时也就失去了存在的意义。这就像是气体的微粒被打进了过于狭小的容器，它们彼此之间会不断地发生冲突，直到有一天它们会冲破将其困锁在一起的这个容器。

下面，我们看一下那些自称为无政府主义者的人们。他们憎恨以任何一种形式将权力强加给个人。他们之所以如此，唯一的原因就是权力已经变得过于抽象——它是一种在民族的政治的实验室里，通过对人性进行分解而造就的科学产品。

那么，经济领域内的罢工又说明了什么呢？它们就像是从荒芜的土地上突然冒出来的带着刺儿的灌木丛一样，每次被砍倒而每次又都恢复了生机。生产财富的机制正在日益地膨胀变大，并且与其他所有的社会需求之间失去了比例平衡，而真正意义的人则在它的重压下扭曲变形，这又说明了什么呢？这种现状不可避免地导致了从人类理想的整体性和健全性中所释放出来的各种元素间无休止的争斗，而长期的经济冲突则在劳资之间持续地爆发。因为财富和权力的贪婪从来都没有满足的时候，而个人利益所作出的妥协也从来都不可能达到最终的和解。它们一定会继续产生嫉妒和猜疑，直到最后，突然的灾难或是一次精神的重生才会结束这一切。

当这个叫作民族的、政治和经济的组织，在以牺牲高尚的社会生活的和谐为代价的情况之下变得强大有力的时候，人类的灾难也就来临了。当一位父亲变成赌徒的时候，他头脑中对于家庭的责任就会退居次席，于是他便不再是一个人了，而是变成了一个依靠贪婪驱动的机器人。此时，他能够做出来原本在他头脑正常状态下所不耻的事情。社会的情形也与此相同。当社会变成了一个完美的权力组织的时候，就不会有什么罪恶勾当是它所不能为之的，因为此时，获得成功是一台机器的目标和评判其价值的依据，而所谓善良不过是人类所追求的目标而已。当这个组织的引擎开始变得体积庞大，而它机器的零部件则由人来充当的时候，于是乎作为个人的人便被消灭了，取而代之的是机器人。而结果是，所有一切都演变成为一场政策革命——一场由没有同情心和道德责任感的、机器当中由人所组成的零部件来付诸实施的政策革命。也许人类的道德本性会利用这台机器来为自己正名，但是此时，整套的绳索和滑轮会咯吱作响，人类心灵的力量会在人类机器力量的包围下变得纠结混乱，从而，人类道德的目的只会以某种扭曲的形象艰难地展现出来。

这个叫作民族的、抽象的东西，正在统治着印度。我们在印度见过某个品牌的罐装食品在广告中宣称，整个食品的制造和包装过程中都没有接触过人手。这一描述同样适合于对于印度的统治，因为它也极少被人手碰到过。总督们并不需要学会我们的语言，除了作为官员，他们也不需要同我们有什么私人的瓜葛；他们只需要站得远远的就可以帮助或是阻碍我们实现自己的愿望，他们能够带领我们实行某种政策，而后又通过其官僚机构的操控收回成命。在英国的报纸上，我们可以看到相关的栏目以某种庄重哀婉的语气报道伦敦街道上所发生的某些事故，然而对于发生在印度的，某些面积比不列颠群岛还大的地方的灾难却只是蜻蜓点水，一带而过。

但是我们这些被统治的人并不是一个抽象的概念。我们是具有各种感官的个体。强加给我们的、单纯冷酷的政策可能会直接刺入我们生命的要害，阉割掉我们的雄风，带给我们永远的无助，从而威胁到我们人民的全部未来。而与此同时，它却可能永远都不会触及人性的另一面，或是仅仅以最软弱无力的方式对它有所触碰。作为个体的人，永远都不会在浑然不知中作出如此大规模和全面的、履行可怕责任的行动。只有当人类变换成一只代表抽象概念的八爪鱼时，这些行动才有可能被付诸实施——它向四面八方伸出其蠕动的腕足，并且将其不可胜数的吸盘附着在遥远的未来身上。在民族的这种统治之下，被统治的一方成为了怀疑的对象；而且这种怀疑来自于一个体型庞大的、组织有序的血肉之躯。它对我们施以惩罚，在一大片滴血的心灵之上留下痛苦的印记，但是这些惩罚仅仅是来自于一种抽象的力量，而远方某个国家的全体人民则在这一力量之中丧失了自己的人性。

然而我来到这里并不是要讨论影响到我自己国家的问题，而是要探讨影响到全体人类未来的问题。这个问题不是关于英国政府的问题，而是关于民族治下的政府的问题——这个民族代表了其全体人民的私利，它最没有人性，也最没有精神。我们唯一的，有关民族的切身经历是来自于不列颠民族的。只要民族的统治一天不停止，我们就有理由相信不列颠民族的统治是最好的统治之一。于是，我们需要再一次地考虑东西方的关系——对于东方来说，西方确实必不可少。我们东西方是互为补充的，因为我们对待生活有着不同的看法，而这些不同的看法又给我们展现出了真理的不同侧面。因此，如果说西方的精神的确是披着暴风雨的伪装来到了我们的田野的话，那么毋庸讳言，它也在我们这里撒下了不朽的、生命的种子。而在印度，当我们能够将西方文明当中永恒的东西吸收到我们自己的生命之中时，我们就一定可以达成这两个伟大世界的和谐共生。而随后，一方对另外一方的、让人恼怒的统治就会终结。除此之外，我们还要明白，印度的历史并非专属于某个特定的种族，它是一个创造的过程——在这期间，来自世界上的很多不同的种族都作出了自己的贡献。它们包括：德拉威人和雅利安人，古希腊人和波斯人，西方和中亚的伊斯兰教徒，等等。现在终于轮到英国人忠实于印度的历史并且为它作出贡献来了。我们既没有权力也没有力量将英国人从构建印度命运的进程当中排除在外。因此，这里我所谈到的民族，更多的是同人类的历史相关，而非特指印度的历史。

如今的历史已经来到了这样一个阶段：有道德的、完善的人正在浑然不知当中让位于政治的和商业的人——那些仅仅服务于特定目的的人。在科学的巨大进步的帮助下，这种人所占的比例和所拥有的权力正在迅速膨胀，从而引起了人类道德天平的失衡，在没有灵魂的组织的阴影笼罩之下蒙蔽了他人性的一面。我们感觉到，这一现状已经如铁腕一般控制了我们的生命根基。因此，为了人类，我们必须站起来并且对所有人发出警告，告诉人们，民族主义是一种罪恶的、残忍的瘟疫，它正在席卷当今人类世界，并且吞噬掉它的道德活力。

我深爱着作为人类的不列颠种族，并且对它满怀敬意。它曾孕育了豪爽的人们、伟大的思想家和伟大事业的践行者，它曾创造了伟大的文学。我知道，不列颠人民热爱正义和自由，而且痛恨谎言。他们思想纯洁、行为坦率、友谊真挚，在为人处世方面诚实可靠。我与他们文学界的人们相接触的个人经历，使得我不仅仅对他们的思想和表达的能力钦佩有加，而且对他们的侠义人格更是羡慕不已。就像感觉到了太阳的伟大一样，我们也感觉到了不列颠人民的伟大。但是，至于不列颠民族，它就如同将太阳遮盖起来的，在寂静的大自然当中升腾而起的一团厚厚的迷雾。

这个民族统治下的政府既不是英国式的也不是其他什么东西；它是一种应用科学，因此，无论在哪里使用它，它的原理都大同小异。它就像是一台液压机，它的压力是不带有感情的，所以是非常有效的。它力量的大小会随着引擎的不同而不同。有些液压机甚至于是由手工推动的，所以它们在挤压的时候会松松垮垮，较为舒适，然而这些液压机在其精神实质和操作方法上却都大体相同。我们的政府即便是荷兰式的，法国式的，抑或是葡萄牙式的政府，它的基本特点也会跟现在的政府保持一致。只有在某些情况下，当它的组织还不十分完善的时候，一些人性的碎片将会附着在它的残骸之上，允许我们做一些与我们自己的心灵相关联的事情。

在民族统治我们之前我们也有过其他的外国政府，这些外国政府就像其他所有政府一样，自身也有某些机械的元素。但是这些政府与民族统治下的政府之间的区别就像是手工织机与机械织机之间的区别。在手工织机的产品当中我们能够看到人类手指所留下的、活生生的魔法般的印记，而且它的嗡嗡声与生命的韵律和谐共鸣。但是机械织机的产品却是冷酷无情的、没有生命的、精确的和单调乏味的。

我们必须承认，在历史上个人统治的时期曾经有过暴政、不公和敲诈勒索的情形。它们所产生的痛苦和不安是我们唯恐避之不及的。对我们来说，法律的保护不仅仅是恩惠，它还对我们教益颇丰。法律教给我们要遵守规则，而这些规则对于保持文明的稳定和进步的持续是必不可少的。通过法律，我们认识到在这世界上有着普世的正义标准——所有的人，无论他们的社会等级与肤色，都拥有在这一普世的正义标准之下接受平等保护的权利。

印度的现政府所推行的法治已经在这个幅员辽阔的、由不同种族和风俗习惯的人民所聚居的国家建立起了秩序。它已经使得这里的人民能够彼此更加密切地接触，并且培养他们所共同拥有的理想。

但是这种在印度的各个不同种族之间建立起共同的、同志般友谊的纽带的愿望并非来自于西方的民族，而是来自于西方的精神。无论何时，亚洲人民所接受到的，来自于西方的教益，都与西方的民族没有什么关系。只有当日本能够成功地抵御此种西方民族的统治时，她才会在最大程度上得到西方文明的好处。尽管中国已经在其道德和物质生活的最源头被这种民族下了毒，然而如果她能克服它的阻碍，那么她为了学习西方最好的东西所付出的努力就仍然有可能取得成功。就在几天以前，波斯刚刚从其长时间的沉睡中被西方唤醒，然而紧接着就在民族的铁蹄蹂躏之下再次销声匿迹。同样的现象也发生在这个国家——在这里，人民热情好客，但是民族却完全不同——它让一位作为他自己国家中一员的东方的客人在自己的国家感受到了屈辱。

在印度，我们忍受着西方精神同西方民族之间的矛盾所带来的痛苦。民族以一种吝啬的方式向我们少量地施舍西方文明的好处。它试图控制我们所得到的营养物质，使其所包含的活力成分尽可能地接近于零。它分配给我们的教育残缺不全且严重不足，这足以使得西方人的道德准则蒙羞受辱。我们在西方国家看到，他们鼓励、训练，并且提供所有的便利条件给他们自己的人民，为的是使他们能够适应扩散至全球的、伟大的商业和工业运动。然而在印度，我们得到的唯一帮助却是因为贫穷落后而受到的民族的嘲弄。民族剥夺了我们的机会，将我们的教育减少到在一个外国人当权的政府当中供职所需要的最低程度。而与此同时，它通过与我们称兄道弟并且大肆地鼓吹傲慢的市侩思想——东方是东方，西方是西方，东西方永远不会有交集等等方法，来使得它的良心得到安慰。我们的老师说，在他对印度将近两个世纪的调教之后，她不仅仍然不适合建立自治政府，而且在其文化素养方面也仍然没有创新的能力。假如我们必须接受这一嘲弄的话，那么，我们是应当把这一结果归咎于我们所固有的、缺乏学习西方文化本性中的某些东西的能力呢，还是应当将其归咎于已经承担起了教化东方的责任的民族所表现出来的谨小慎微的吝啬呢？我们可能会承认，自己缺乏某些日本人民所具有的品质，但是我们不能接受自己的智力与他们比较起来就是天然地缺乏创造性的说法，即便这些话是出自于那些我们很难加以驳斥的人之口。

事实是，西方民族主义的核心和根源就是对抗和征服的精神；它的根基并不是社会合作。它已经逐渐形成了一套完善的权力组织，而非精神上的理想主义。它就像是一群掠食者，必须占有自己的猎物。它真心真意地不能容忍看到自己的猎场转化成为种植的园地。事实上，这些民族之间也在彼此争斗，为的是扩大它们猎物的品种和保留林地的范围。因此，西方的民族就像是堤坝一样阻碍着西方文明自由地流入到非民族主义的国家。因为这一文明是权力的文明，所以它具有排他性；它自然而然地不愿意向那些已经被它选作是自己剥削对象的国家敞开它力量的源泉。

但是即便如此，人类毕竟要遵守道德的律法；那些排他性的文明——它们依靠剥削其他文明而发家致了富，却不允许它们共享其利益，必然会在其道德局限性当中携带着它们自己的死亡判决书。它们所带来的奴隶制度会在不知不觉中将它们对于自由的热爱消耗殆尽。对于成为自己猎物的国家的压迫而给它们造成的无助感，会每时每刻地反作用于它的制造者。被民族剥夺了自我持续更生能力的，世界上的大多数国家总有一天会成为它最为可怕的负担，并且将其拉下马，投入到毁灭的深渊。什么时候权力为了能够为所欲为而将其道路上的关卡全部移走，什么时候它就成功地驶向了其最终的灭亡。权力的道德闸线每天都会在其不知不觉中变得懒惰松弛，而它所走的光滑的捷径此时就会成为一条通向死亡的不归之路。

在我们得到的西方文明的所有事物当中，西方民族以最为慷慨的态度给予我们的就是法律和秩序。当我们教育的奶瓶将近枯竭，公共卫生事业在绝望中吮吸着自己大拇指的时候，军事组织、地方官员的衙署、警察部门、犯罪调查科、秘密特工系统，等等，却成长得异常膀大腰圆，占满了我们国家的每一寸土地。这是为了维持秩序。但是，这种秩序难道不正是一种消极的好处吗？它难道是为了给人民的生活带来更多的、自由发展的机会吗？这种秩序的完善就如同一枚鸡蛋壳的完善一样，它的真正价值在于为小鸡提供了安全庇护和营养，而不在于它给吃早餐的人提供了方便。单纯的管理是非生产性的；它不具有创造性，没有活力。它就是一台蒸汽压路机，其重量和力量让人畏惧，其用处显而易见；但是，它并不能使土地变得富饶。当它一番苦干之后就会施与我们和平的恩惠，而我们则只得低声地埋怨道：“和平固然是好，不过怎么也好不过上帝所赐予我们的生命。”

另一方面来说，我们先前的政府严重地缺乏一个现代政府所具备的很多优点。但是，由于这些政府并不是民族统治下的政府，所以它们的质地松散，留有很大的间隙，而正是通过这些间隙，我们的生命在其中得以穿针引线并且留下自己的印记。我敢肯定，在旧政府统治时期，一定有些东西是我们极为厌恶的。但是我们知道，当我们赤脚走在满是砾石的地面上时，我们的双脚会逐渐地适应这反复无常的、不友好的土地；然而，哪怕是最微小的砾石碎块儿在我们的鞋子里找到了立足之地的话，我们都不会忘记，也不会原谅它的入侵。这些鞋子就是民族统治下的政府——它紧箍着我们的双脚，它以一种包裹紧密的系统控制着我们的步伐——在这个系统里面，我们双脚只能获得最低限度的自由以作出调整。因此，当你作出统计数据，拿我们的双脚在先前的政府统治时期所遭遇的砾石数量和在现政府统治下所遇到的少许的砾石碎块儿的数量进行比较的时候，这些数据其实并不能说明问题。因为问题的关键并不在于外在障碍物数量的多少，而在于面对这些障碍物时人们所感到的、无能为力的程度的深浅。这种对于自由的限制是一种更为根本性的罪恶。这并非由于它的数量而是由于它的本质。于是我们不得不承认这样一个看上去似是而非的说法：当西方的精神在自由的旗帜下阔步前进的时候，西方的民族却锻造出了人类历史上史无前例的、组织的钢铁链条——它最冷酷无情，也最牢不可破。

当印度人民还未陷于这种组织的统治之下时，变化的弹性是足够大的，它足以让有力量、有精神的人们感觉到他们能够将自己的命运掌握在自己手中。那时，人们从不缺少对于突发事件的期待，统治者和被统治者双方都拥有更为自由的想象力，而这想象力则对历史进程产生了影响。那时，我们所面对的未来并不是一道死气沉沉的、白色的花岗岩所砌成的围墙——它永远地阻断了我们显示并且增长自己的力量，它之所以给我们带来绝望，是因为，我们的力量正在由于科学的麻醉作用而从其根基上变得萎缩退化。每一个非民族的个人都在一个整体民族的控制之下，而这个民族如同机器一般，时时刻刻都保持着警觉，它不会像人一样疏忽大意或是区别对待。只要轻轻地按下它的按钮，这个怪物组织就会立刻启动，而它那双丑陋的、充满好奇心的大眼睛可以让广大的、被统治的人民群众中的任何一个个人都无处藏身。只要稍微转动一下它的螺丝钉，哪怕只有一丝一毫，它对所有人，包括男人、女人和儿童的控制就会收紧，达到令其窒息的程度；而这些人们想要从自己的国家，甚至于从任何其他的国家中逃离出来都是不可想象的。

在持续、巨大、非人性的力量对人性的至死重压下，现代世界正在痛苦地呻吟着。不仅仅是被压迫的种族，你们这些生活在幻觉中的、自以为是自由的人们，每天都在牺牲掉你们的自由和人性以向民族主义的偶像献祭。你们生活在弥漫着浓浓的、乌烟瘴气的世界里，这里面充斥了怀疑、贪婪和恐惧。

我曾经在日本看到，全体人民都自愿地将思想和自由交给他们的政府，听由其摆布。他们的政府通过各种各样的教育机构规范他们的思想，制造他们的感官，当有迹象表明他们正在倾向于某种精神生活的时候，它就会充满怀疑地警觉起来，将他们领上一条狭窄的道路——不是一条通向真理的道路，而是一条使得他们能够按照它所制定的方案紧密地团结在一起的道路。日本人民愉快地、自豪地接受了这种四处弥漫的精神枷锁，因为，他们焦躁地渴望着自己变身为一台叫作民族的权力的机器，并且在追名逐利的集体活动中与其他机器同流合污。

当我们询问他们这样做的原因是什么的时候，刚刚拜倒在民族主义旗下的狂热的追随者这样回答道：“只要民族在这个世界上蔓延滋生，我们就不可能自由地将我们自己的人性提得更高。我们必须利用自己所拥有的所有本领，通过在最大程度上变得邪恶的方式来对抗邪恶。因为在当今世界上，唯一可能的手足情谊就是与流氓无赖一起沆瀣一气，狼狈为奸。”日本和俄国所结成的兄弟般的友爱关系最近刚刚在日本得到了大张旗鼓地欢呼庆祝。这种友谊并非来自于基督教或是佛教精神的复兴；相反，它是建立在一种现代的、信仰的基础之上的关系——它相信只有彼此之间进行流血的恐吓才能使双方各自变得更安全。没错，我们必须承认这些事实是当今世界上民族的事实；而民族所笃信的唯一道德就是世界上所有的民族都应当竭尽他们的物质、道德和精神资源，以便在权力斗争的竞赛中击败对方。古代的时候，斯巴达千方百计地使自己变得强大；她通过丧失自己的人性达到了这一目的，然而最终，却还是在人性的丧失中死去。

但是，现在的时代正在由于道义的衰微而变得痛苦不堪，而这种道义的衰微不仅仅局限于那些被奴役的种族；对于另外一些种族而言，由于他们被蒙在鼓里，相信自己是自由的，所以这种在隐秘和自愿中所遭受到的伤害则更加严重。因此，了解到这一情况，我们并未感到丝毫的安慰。你们可以自由地选择以更高的人生理想作为筹码来换取利益和权力，而我要将你们留在自己的精神废墟旁边，好好思考一下你们所得到的繁荣昌盛到底为何物。但是，当你们将全体人民自我扩张的本能都组织起来，并使其登峰造极，而自鸣得意的时候，难道你们就永远都不会为此行径受到惩罚吗？我要问问你们：在人类的历史上，在它最黑暗的时期，有过什么样的灾难可以像这种可怕的民族一样，将其毒牙深深地嵌入到世界裸露的肌体之中，并且每时每刻都紧咬牙关，毫不松懈呢？

你们，西方的人们，你们制造出了这种怪胎，你们能想象得出来，在这个人类受苦受难的，鬼魅横行的，由可怕的抽象的人类组织所主宰的世界上凄凉的绝望吗？你们能设身处地地为那些非民族主义国家的人民想一想吗？他们似乎是命中注定要接受对于他们自己人性的永恒诅咒。他们不仅仅要受到持续的、人性的摧残，而且还要高声地为一台机器设备大唱赞歌，歌颂它在无休止的、假冒天意的拙劣表演中所显示出的仁慈。

你们不曾见过吗？自从民族之肇始，它所带来的如同妖魔鬼怪一般的恐怖便让整个世界为之颤抖。哪里有黑暗的角落，哪里可能就会有其隐秘的恶毒；而人们则生活在永远的不信任之中，只恨自己后背没有再多长出一双眼睛。每一个脚步声，每一个邻里做出动作时所发出的沙沙声，都会将恐惧的战栗传遍四方。这种恐惧孕育了所有人性之中最卑鄙可耻的东西。它使得人们几乎是公开地对残忍的暴行不以为耻。聪明的谎言变成了自我麻醉的工具。神圣的誓言则变成了一出闹剧——因为其神圣而引人发笑。民族，尽管它强大有力、繁荣昌盛，尽管它旌旗招展、赞歌飘扬，尽管它在教堂里念诵着亵渎神明的祷告，尽管它装腔作势的文学为其爱国主义大肆吹捧，也不可能掩盖这样一个事实——民族本身就是其最大的罪恶，它所采取的所有预防措施都是与其自身相对立的；而且，这个世界上每诞生一个新的民族都会在其他民族的心目中产生新的恐惧。它的唯一愿望就是利用世界上其他国家的衰微，就像某些依靠被麻痹的猎物的肉为食的昆虫一样，让那些弱国苟延残喘，继续存活下去，以便为自己提供营养丰富的美味佳肴。因此，它乐意将自己有毒的汁液注射到其他活着的、无害的、非民族的要害器官当中去。为了这一目的，民族已经并且还在占据着亚洲最最富饶的牧场。伟大的中国，她富有古代的智慧和社会伦理，她勤劳而且自制，现在就像是一头鲸鱼一样，在民族的心中唤起了强取豪夺的渴望。她颤抖的身体已经被自诩为一贯正确的，科学而自私的民族所投下的几柄鱼叉扎中。而就当她可怜巴巴地试图甩掉自己的人性传统和社会理想，并且竭尽最后一点点资源想要把自己训练成现代的、高效的国家的时候，民族却处处作梗，横加阻挠。它用经济的绳索将中国绑紧，然后试图将她拖上岸并且切成碎片，接下来便公然地举办向上帝感恩的祈祷仪式，感谢他对于现存罪恶的帮扶以及对于可能产生的罪恶的消灭。为了这一切，民族一直在讨要着历史的垂青，祈盼着它的剥削活动能够天长地久；它命令自己的唱诗班到世界各地去演奏，宣扬自己是社会精华，是人类之花，是上帝竭尽全力撒向非民族国家裸露着的脑壳的祝福。

我知道你们的建议是什么。你们会说：你们也发展成为一个民族吧，这样就可以抵抗它的侵犯了。不过，这算得上是真正的、一个人对另外一个人提出的建议吗？这样做难道是必须的吗？我宁可相信你们提出这样的建议：在处理同他人的关系时要更友好、更公正、更真诚；要控制你的贪欲，要生活得淳朴而健康，还要让你对人性中神圣之物的认识更加完美，等等。但是你们会说，对我们自己来说，最有价值的东西不是灵魂而是那台机器；人类的得救所依赖的是他能否将自己训练得完全适合机器轮子和计数轮旋转时的固定节奏；在政治的、永不停息的斗牛场上，机器必须与机器竞争，民族必须与民族对立——难道你们一定要这样认为吗？

你们会说：基于对恐惧的共识，这些机器会达成彼此互不侵犯的协议。但是，这样一个蒸汽锅炉之间所结成的同盟会向你展示一个灵魂，一个拥有自己良知和上帝的灵魂吗？而在世界上其他更多的，没有恐惧可以约束到你们的地方，又会发生什么事呢？无论那些非民族主义的国家现在多么安全，没有受到熔炉、铁锤和螺丝刀的整治，这也不过是列强间彼此猜忌的结果而已。但是，当列强不再是无数单独的机器，而是结合在一起，成为一个贪婪的、商业的或是政治的集体组织的时候，其他的那些国家，他们享受过生活也遭受过痛苦，曾经爱过也曾经祈祷过，曾经深刻地思考过也曾经任劳任怨地工作过，而他们唯一的过错就是没有像那些机器一样组织起来，他们还会拥有哪怕是最为渺茫的希望吗？

但是你们会说：“这没关系，不适者必失败——他们会死掉，这就是科学。”

不，错了。为了你们自己的得救，我要说，他们要活下去，这才是真理。我这样说是需要极大的勇气的，但是我敢断言，人类的世界是道德的世界，这并不是因为我们盲目地这样相信，而是因为真理就是如此，忽视这一点就会给我们带来危险。而且，人类的这种道德本性不应以方便为由被分割保存。你们不应以保护性的关税壁垒将道德仅仅局限在国内消费，而对外则在自由贸易的许可证下让它随意变通。

这一真理你们还没有认识到吗？残酷的战争已经将其魔爪伸入到欧洲的内脏；而在欧洲的战场上，她囤积的财富正在化为灰烬，她的人性正在片片散落。你们会惊奇地问道：她到底做了什么会落得如此下场？问题的答案是，西方一直以来都在系统地石化其道德本性，目的是为她庞大而高效的组织奠定坚实的基础。她一直以来都在为了这个组织的强大而让每个个人都忍饥挨饿。

在你们欧洲中世纪的时候，人们朴素而自然，他们带着强烈的激情和愿望，试图找到将灵魂与肉体的冲突相调和的办法。在贯穿欧洲的充满青春活力的动荡岁月中，无论是世俗的还是精神的力量都对她的本性施加了巨大的影响，并且为其塑造了具有完整性的道德人格。欧洲伟大的人性正是要归功于那一时期的磨练——对于其人性完整性的磨练。

接下来便是理智的时代、科学的时代。我们都知道理智是非人性的。我们的生命和心灵是合二为一的，但是我们的头脑却可以从人格中分离出去，只有它可以在思想的世界里自由地游移。我们的理智是一位苦行的修道者，它不穿衣服，不吃食物，不睡觉，没有愿望，感觉不到爱或是恨或是对于人性弱点的怜悯，它只是无动于衷地通过生活的变迁兴衰进行推理。它对所有事物都刨根问底，因为它与这些事物本身毫无个人感情的瓜葛。语法专家会径直走过整篇诗歌，毫无障碍地直奔单词的词根，因为他想要探寻的不是诗歌的真相，而是词汇法则。一旦他发现了这一法则，他就可以教会人们如何掌握单词。这是一种力量——它可以满足某种特殊的用途，满足人类的某些特定的需要。

现实的存在就是某个事物的各个组成部分在整体的平衡中所表现出来的和谐。你打破了这种和谐，手里攥着彼此斗争的游离的原子，这一事物也就失去了意义。那些垂涎权力的人们试图掌握这些原始的、斗争的元素，并且通过某些狭窄的渠道将它们强行塞进某个装置，以便让它们为人类的某些特定需要提供暴力的服务。

人类需要的满足事关重大。这可以让他获得在物质世界行动的自由。它可以让他在更为广阔的时间和空间范围内获得利益，让他在更短的时间内完成任务，并且以压倒性的优势占据更大的空间。因此，他便可以轻而易举地超越那些生活在节奏缓慢，且空间没有得到充分利用的世界里的人们。

这种权力前进的步伐越走越快。而且，因为它是从人类整体中分离出来的一部分，所以它不久就超越了人类的整体。有道德的人类落在了后面，因为它不得不应付整个现实的存在，而不仅仅是没有人性的、抽象的事物法则。

于是人类理智和物质的力量远远超过了道德的力量，就像是一头形态夸张的长颈鹿一样，脑袋陡然间竖起，距离身体的其他部分有数英里远，结果使得正常的联系也无法进行。这个贪婪的脑袋拥有巨大的牙齿，一直在用力地咀嚼世界上长得最高的树叶，然而它所获得的营养物质要花太久的时间才能到达它的消化器官，而它的心脏正在由于缺血而痛苦不堪。对于当今人类本性中的不和谐，西方似乎一直在美滋滋地毫无察觉。它所有注意力都被其巨大无比的物质成功引向了对自己肥硕身材的洋洋得意之中。伴随着铁路线无休止的延伸给自己带来的好运气，西方逻辑中的乐观主义精神也继续向前直达永远。如果有谁认为所有的明天不过是今天的翻版，不过是二十四个小时不断的累加，那么就未免太过浅薄了。因为他没有注意到，在人类不断膨胀的仓库和他空虚饥饿的人性之间的裂痕正在日益扩大。逻辑并不清楚，在无尽的财富和优越的物质条件的最底层，用来恢复道德世界之平衡的地震正在酝酿当中；总有一天，精神空虚的海湾会将永远眷恋着尘世浮华的仓库拽进自己无底的深渊。

一个完整的人并不体现在他的力量上，而是体现在他的完善上。因此，要想让一个人仅仅获得力量，你就必须尽量地缩小他的灵魂。当我们具有完整的人性的时候，我们是不会彼此掐对方的喉咙的；我们社会生活的本能，我们道德理想的传统不允许我们这样做。如果你想让我去杀人，那么首先你必须通过能使我的意志丧失、思想麻木、行动机械的训练来破坏我的完整人性，然后那种与人类真理没有丝毫关系，因此很容易变得野蛮和机械的，抽象的毁灭力量就会从我已经解体的、复杂的人性当中释放出来了。将人类从他的自然环境中带走，将他带离充实的集体生活，以及在这生活中他与美、爱和社会责任等等建立起的活生生的联系，这样，你就会将他转变成为许多机器的碎片，从而生产出大量的财富。将树木变为柴火，它就会为你而燃烧，但是自此就永远都不会再开出生命的花朵，结出生命的果实了。

这种非人化的过程在商业和政治领域内一直进行着。这种完全发展成熟的，拥有巨大力量和惊人胃口的机械，在机械能量的长期阵痛中分娩降生了，而西方已经将其命名为民族。就像我之前曾经暗示过的，因为它具有的抽象的品质，它轻而易举地就跑在了完善的、有道德的人类前头。而且，由于它拥有一颗恶灵的心脏以及一个机器人才有的冷酷的完美，所以，它正在制造的灾难让年轻的月球上的火山喷发也自愧弗如。结果是，人与人之间的怀疑就像是荨麻身上的刺毛一样刺痛着这个文明的四肢。每个国家都在向其他国家满是污泥的水底投下间谍的罗网，希望获取他们的秘密——那些在外交的烂泥的深处酝酿着的背信弃义的秘密。而民族的所谓秘密，不外乎是在其腐烂的深处所从事的拐骗、谋杀、背叛以及所有丑陋罪行的地下交易。因为每一个民族都有它自己的盗窃、撒谎和背信弃义的历史，所以国际间的怀疑和嫉妒就会大行其道，而且国际间的鲜廉寡耻就会达到滑稽可笑的程度。民族伸张正义的风笛会根据时间的不同和外交联盟的重新组合而改变调门，所以我们只能将其作为政治音乐厅的另外一种表演形式来欣赏。

我刚刚到访过日本。在那里，我劝告这个新生的民族要站在更高的人类理想的立场上，永远不要效仿西方将民族主义有组织的自私自利奉为圭臬，永远不要因为自己邻国的衰弱而幸灾乐祸，永远不要不择手段地对付弱国，即便是如此举动极为卑鄙却可以免受惩罚，而同时却将自己带着人性光辉的右脸转向那些有能力给它一拳的国家，为的是得到它们赞赏的亲吻。有些报纸以它们富有诗意为由表扬了我的言论，而同时不忘揶揄我，说我的言论是失败民族的诗歌。我觉得它们说得对。日本已经在一所现代的学校里学会了如何变得强大。学习结束了，而她必须要享受课程所带来的收获。西方用她隆隆的炮声在日本的大门口这样说道：民族，出现吧——于是一个民族就出现了。而既然它已经存在了，那么为什么你们不能发自内心地感到纯净的喜悦并且为它祝福呢？为什么我在英国的报纸上看到，当日本吹嘘她自己的文明有多么优越的时候你们却恶语相加呢？要知道，几个世纪以来，英国以及其他的民族一直在像日本这样恬不知耻地吹嘘自己的文明啊。这就是因为自私自利的理想主义必须依靠持续剂量的自我褒扬来维持自己的陶醉状态。但是当它们看到其他民族与自己一样的，似乎是再自然和无害不过的不道德行为时，就会感到震惊和愤怒。所以，当你们看到按照你们自身形象塑造出来，并且开始为自己的民族大声聒噪的、民族主义的日本的时候，你们就摇摇头说，这样做可不好。这难道不就是你们在这里提高了嗓门，呼吁作好准备，来应付又一个能够带来更大伤害的罪恶力量的原因之一吗？日本提出抗议说，她拥有武士道精神，她永远都不会背叛自己心怀感激的美国。但是你们很难相信她的说辞，因为民族的智慧并不在于对人性的信仰，而是在于对人性的完全不信任。你们自言自语道，我们所要对付的不是拥有武士道的日本，不是拥有道德理想的日本，而是作为民族的日本；而只有当两个民族拥有共同的利益，或是至少他们利益不相冲突的时候，他们才能彼此信任对方。事实上，你们的本能告诉自己，当另外一个民族出现在民族的竞技场上时，就说明与人类崇高理想格格不入的罪恶又一次得到了壮大，并且它的成功证明了厚颜无耻是通向繁荣昌盛的道路，而善良只适合于弱者，是上帝留给失败者的唯一慰藉。

没错，这就是民族的逻辑。它永远都不会倾听真理和善良的声音。它会继续跳这种道德败坏的圆圈舞，将钢铁与钢铁连接，机器与机器连接，将所有朴素的信仰和人类生活理想的甜蜜花朵都踩在自己脚下加以蹂躏。

但是我们自欺欺人地认为，现代的人类比以往任何时候都要站得靠前。这种自我欺骗的原因在于，人类现在可以得到比以往更为丰富的生活必需品，而他所患的疾病也能得到更为有效的治疗。但是造成所有这些的主要原因并不是道德的贡献，而要归功于智慧的力量。它数量巨大，但是它源自表面且只在表面铺开。知识和效率在其外在的影响方面显得强大而有力，但是它们只是人类的奴仆，而非人类自身。它们的服务就像是宾馆里所提供的服务，尽管周到详尽，却缺乏地主之谊；它更多的是提供方便而不是热情好客。

因此我们不要忘了，散布在各个领域内的科学组织正在增强的是我们的力量，而不是我们的人性。随着我们力量的增长，民族的自我崇拜占据了支配的地位，每个个人都自愿地允许民族像骑驴那样骑在我们自己的身上；于是便出现了这种具有灾难性后果的怪现象：个人奉献出所有的祭品来崇拜一个神，而这个神却通常在道德方面比他还要低级。如果这个神像每个个人那样真实存在的话，这种情况是不大可能出现的。

下面我再解释一下这一点。在印度的有些地方，寡妇们每隔两周都会有一天不吃不喝，这被看作是一种极为虔诚的举动。尽管人们的本性并非这样残忍，此种行为还是会经常导致残忍、无意义和不人道的结果。然而，这种非真实的、抽象的虔诚极大地削弱了人们的道德感，这就像是一个不会无端地伤害一只动物的人，当他给自己的感觉器官灌下抽象的、“运动”的汤药的时候，就会使得大量无辜的动物遭受可怕的痛苦。因为这些抽象的观念来自于我们的理智，它们属于逻辑的范畴，所以，它们能够轻易地让个人在其薄雾中踪迹难寻。

民族的观念是人类发明的最为强有力的麻醉剂之一。在它乌烟瘴气的影响下，整个民族，在对民族的道德扭曲全然无知的情况下，会将其最恶毒的、利己主义的、系统的行动纲领付诸实施——而事实上，如果有谁指出了这一点，他反而会招致来自持有这种民族主义观念之人们的危险的愤恨。

但是，这种情况会无限期地持续，不断地在我们人类的天性上制造出大面积的道德感知力的荒原吗？它会永远都逃脱报应吗？难道这种机械组织的巨大力量会没有任何限制，而它在同这个世界的斗争中，不会因为自己的可怕力量和速度而将自身更为彻底地摧毁吗？你相信罪恶可以通过与同其他罪恶的竞争来实现永远的相互制约吗？你相信费尽心机的讨论就可以将魔鬼锁在彼此妥协的临时牢笼里吗？

这场爆发在民族间的欧洲战争就是一种报应。人类一定不要在自己的生活中堆满了物质的东西而不是心灵，堆满了制度和政策而不是活的人际关系。现在是时候了，为了整个愤怒的世界，欧洲应当充分地认识到，在她自己的身上有一种叫作民族的、可怕而荒谬的东西。

民族依靠残缺的人性而发迹。人类，作为上帝最美好的造物，以好战而贪财的木偶形象被大量地从民族主义的工厂中生产了出来，而他们却对自己如机械一般可怜的完美愚蠢地感到洋洋得意。人类社会变得越来越像一出牵线木偶秀，在高效的牵线装置的操控下，政客们、士兵们、厂商们和官僚们都一一献演。

但是，将自私自利当作神一样来崇拜永远都不可能使其无尽的仇恨和嫉妒、恐惧和虚伪、怀疑和专制自己画上句号。这些妖魔鬼怪会长得身形巨大，却永远都不可能协调发展。这种民族可能会长到你想象不到的肥胖的程度，然而它仍然不是一个活着的躯体，而是一堆钢铁，一团蒸汽，或是一座座办公大楼。它会一直长到自己畸形的外壳再也装不下它那丑陋而肥硕的躯体，于是它便会开始噼啪开裂，急促地喷火冒烟，并且在加农炮的吼叫声中发出濒死的哀鸣。在这场战争中，民族开始了其死亡前的阵痛。突然间，它所有的机械装置都发了疯。它开始跳起了复仇女神的舞蹈，将它自己的四肢打碎并且将它们散落在尘埃中。这是这场虚幻悲剧的最后一幕。

那些对人类怀有信心的人们一定会热切地希望，民族的暴政一定不要恢复其先前的爪牙，恢复其无所不及的铁臂和巨大无比的内腔——里面只有胃而没有心；他们希望人类会摆脱包裹着自己的抽象的含混，并且获得个性的新生。

面纱已经撩起。在这场可怕的战争中，西方已经直面了自己的造物——她曾经将自己的灵魂出卖给它的那个造物。她应该清楚它的真面目了。

在过去，西方从来没有察觉出自己的道德本性正在秘密地、缓慢地腐烂分解。这一过程常常以怀疑主义的教条的形式显现；而更多的时候，它是以更为危险且微妙的形式表现出来——她对这个世界的大部分进行了破坏和侮辱，然而自己却浑然不知。现在她必须清楚，真相已经站在自家门口了。

然后，就会有一些西方的孩子们从这种幻觉，这种建立在自私自利的基础之上的，扭曲的手足之情的奴役之中解放出来；他们将会成为上帝的孩子而不是作为机器的奴仆，因这些机器将灵魂变成了商品，将生命变成了零件，并且以其铁爪刨出了世界的心脏，而与此同时，却对自己的所作所为全然无知。

我们这些一直以来低着头的非民族的国家将会明白，我们所低头相向的这片土地要比用来建造傲慢权力的砖头更为神圣。因为这片肥沃的土地充满了生机、美丽和对神的崇拜。我们要感谢上帝，是他创造了我们，是他让我们挨过寂静的、绝望的黑夜，忍受着傲慢者所施以的凌辱，背负着强大者才有的负担；然而，尽管经历了所有这一切，尽管我们的心灵曾经因为怀疑和恐惧而战栗，我们却从来没有盲目地相信过机器能够给人类带来拯救，相反，我们紧握着对上帝的信仰，紧握着人类灵魂的真谛。我们仍然怀抱着希望，希望当权力羞于占据它的宝座并且乐意为爱让路的时候，希望当黎明为了清洗民族所遗留下的斑斑血迹而沿着人性的大道走来的时候，我们能够受到上帝召唤，召唤我们带上自己的一坛圣水——一坛信仰的圣水——来滋润、净化人类的历史，并且以其喷洒的水滴向几个世纪以来饱受践踏的土地献上祝福，保佑它硕果累累。

印度的民族主义

我们印度的真正问题不在于政治，而是在于社会。其实这种情况普遍地存在于所有的国家，而非印度所独有。我不相信有什么孤立存在的政治利益。西方的政治支配了西方的理想，而我们印度则正在试图模仿你们。我们必须记住，欧洲文明自然而然地具有政治和经济的侵略性的特点，因为，欧洲的各个民族自其肇始就具有种族的统一性，而欧洲的自然资源对其居民来说又是匮乏的。所以，一方面他们没有内部的混乱，而另一方面则要对付他们强大而贪婪的邻国。于是在他们彼此之间便进行了完美的联合，同时对其他国家采取了警惕、敌意的态度，这便成了他们解决自己问题的办法。过去，他们组织起来去抢劫；现在，他们秉承同样的精神，组织起来共同剥削整个世界。

但是，印度自有史以来就一直面对着这样的问题——种族问题。每一个民族都一定要弄清楚自己的使命是什么，而我们印度人一定要认识到，当我们要在政治上有所作为的时候，我们就会露出丑态，原因就在于我们还没有能够最终完成上帝下达给我们的旨意。

你们美国也同我们一样，多年以来面对着一直想要设法解决的种族团结问题。在这里很多人问我有关印度的种姓歧视的情况。但是他们向我问起这个事情的时候，总是带有一种优越感。所以，我也想把这个问题稍加修正之后问一问你们美国的批评家们：“你们是怎样对待红种印第安人和黑人的呢？”你们并没有改变对于他们的种族歧视的态度。你们使用了暴力的方法来使自己远离其他种族。所以，在这一问题没有得到解决之前，在这里，在美国，你们就没有权利指责印度。

尽管困难重重，印度还是有所作为的。她试着对种族关系进行了调整，承认了种族间确实存在的、真正的不同之处，并且试图找出各个种族间团结的基础。这个基础来自于我们的圣人，例如那纳克，卡比尔，柴塔尼亚[2]，等等，他们倡导印度的各个种族信仰同一个上帝。

在解决我们自己问题的时候，我们同样应当致力于解决世界的问题。印度所经历的一切就是世界现在的样子。整个世界正在科学的帮助下变为一个国家。现在已经是时候了，你们必须要为这个世界找到一个团结的、非政治的基础。如果印度能够给这个世界提交她的解决方案的话，那么这将是对于全体人类的贡献。这世界上只有一部历史，那就是人类的历史。所有国家的历史不过是这部历史当中的各个章节而已。我们在印度愿意为这一伟大的事业受苦受难。

每个人都会爱他自己。因此，他残忍的本能会使得他为了追逐单纯的个人私利而与其他人争斗。但是同时人类还拥有更高级的同情和互助的本能。那些缺乏这一更高级别的道德力量的人们将不能同其他人结为伙伴的关系，所以他们注定会灭亡或生活在低级的状态。只有那些拥有这种强烈合作精神的民族才会生存下来并且创造出文明。所以我们发现，自有史以来，人类就不得不在彼此斗争和联合之间作出选择，在满足他们自己私欲和满足所有人共同利益之间作出选择。

在人类历史的早期，每个国家都受到地理疆域和交流手段的局限，所以这个问题相对来说并不突出，因为人类在他们各自独立的区域里发展他们对于团结的理解就已经足够了。那时候，他们自己之间联合起来与其他人斗争。但是，他们真正的伟大之处正是在于这种联合起来的道德精神，而正是这种精神塑造了他们的艺术、科学和宗教。那时候，人类所关注的最重要的一个事情就是某个特定种族的成员彼此之间的密切接触。那些通过他们更崇高的本性而真正做到了这种密切接触的种族会在人类的历史上留下他们的印记。

当今时代最重要的事情就是人类的不同种族已经聚集在了一起。我们又一次地面临着两个选择：不同的族群是继续彼此间的争斗，还是找出某些和解和互助的真正基础；不同的族群之间是继续无休止的竞争，还是展开彼此间的合作。

我会毫不犹豫地说，那些拥有爱的道德力量和团结精神的人们，那些对外来人抱有最少的敌意并且具有设身处地为他人着想的同情心的人们，会在我们当今这个时代占据永久的位置，成为最适应这个时代的人；而那些不断地发展自己与外来人为敌的，具有偏狭的本能的人将会被淘汰出局。因为这就是我们所面临的问题，而我们不得不借助更为崇高的本性来解决它，从而证明我们的人性。那些伤害他人并且避免被他人所伤害的庞大组织，那些靠损人利己而发财的庞大组织，它们是不会帮助我们的。恰恰相反，由于它们的千钧重力、巨额成本，以及对人类活力的抑制，它们会严重地阻碍我们在一个更为崇高的文明所提供的更为广大的生活空间中获得自由。

在民族的演变过程中，兄弟友谊的道德文化受到了地理边界的限制，因为那时候这些边界是真实存在的。现在这些边界已经成为想象中的传统界限，而不具备真正的阻隔性质。所以现在人类的道德本性一定要严肃地对待这种情况，否则它将会有灭顶之灾。这种环境改变所造成的第一个冲动是人类卑鄙的贪婪和残忍的仇恨的膨胀。如果这种情况无限期地持续下去，军事力量继续壮大到难以想象的荒谬程度，机器和仓库以它们的尘灰、烟雾和丑陋覆盖了这个美丽的地球的话，那么这世界终将会在自杀式的熊熊烈焰中走向灭亡。因此，人类将不得不竭尽其爱的全力，擦亮他的眼睛，再一次作出巨大的道德修正；这种道德修正将在整个人类世界中进行，而不仅仅局限于少数的几个民族。生活在当今时代的每个人都接到了这样的召唤：要为迎接新时代的曙光作好自身和周边环境的准备，因为在新的时代里人们将会在全体人类的精神团结中发现自己的灵魂。

如果西方想要从这些低矮斜坡的混乱中挣扎出来，爬上人类精神的制高点的话，那么我想，美国就要肩负起其特殊的使命，完成这一上帝和人类的愿望。你们的国家充满了期待，希望能够推陈出新。欧洲有其敏锐的思维习惯和约定俗成的社会习俗，但是美国还没有定型。我知道美国很少受到过去传统的束缚，而且我意识到实验主义是美国年轻的标志。美国的荣耀在于未来而不是过去；而且，如果谁具有洞悉未来的本领的话，那么他一定会爱上未来的美国。

美国注定要向东方证明西方文明的正当性。欧洲已经对人性失去了信心，已经变得狐疑而病弱。而另一方面，美国则并不悲观失望或是麻木不仁。作为一个民族你们知道，没有最好只有更好，而你们进步的动力就来自于对这一点的认知。有一些习惯不光是被动的，同时还是高傲的和富于侵略性的。它们不仅仅像是一堵围墙，而更像是带刺儿的荨麻围成的树篱。欧洲多年以来一直都在培育着这种习惯的树篱，直到它们浓密地、茁壮地、高高地将欧洲围拢起来。欧洲对于自己传统的自豪感已经扎根在了她的心灵深处。我并不认为这种自豪感是毫无道理的。但是，任何一种形式的傲慢都会最终导致愚昧无知。像所有人造的兴奋剂一样，傲慢的最初影响只是一种反应水平的提升；而接下来，随着掺加剂量的增大，就会产生一种误导性的狂喜。欧洲的傲慢，在其外表和内在的习惯上面，都在逐渐地变得顽固。她不仅不能忘了自己是西方，而且还会利用每一次机会抛出这一事实，从而羞辱他人。这就是为什么，欧洲变得没有能力将自己最好的东西与东方分享；而与此同时，不能够以正确的态度接受东方已经储藏了多达数百年的智慧。

美国的民族习惯和传统还没有来得及将它们的根须紧紧地束缚住你们自己的心灵。当你们将自己不停漂泊的生活同欧洲固定的传统相比较的时候，你们经常会感到并且抱怨自己所处的劣势，因为欧洲可以将自己的伟大之处放到其历史背景之中最大限度地展现出来。但是在当今这个过渡的时代，当文明的新纪元跨越无限的未来时空向世界上的各个种族吹响其召唤的号角的时候，正是这种毫无挂碍的自由将会让你们响应它的号召，并且实现它的目标——为了这一目标，欧洲曾经开始其旅程，但是却在半路迷失了自我。之所以会如此，是因为欧洲被她自己的傲慢的权力和贪婪的占有所蛊惑，从而误入了歧途。

不仅仅是你们美国人的思维不受习惯的束缚，你们的历史也没有受到任何肮脏的、陈年旧账的羁绊，所以你们美国适合于扛起未来文明大旗的重任。所有欧洲伟大的民族都在世界的其他地方造下罪孽。这使得它们的同情心在道德和理智方面都受到了破坏，而这种同情心是理解其他与己不同的种族所必需的。英国人永远都不会真正地理解印度，因为他们在考虑有关印度的问题时并非没有私利。如果将英国同德国或法国进行比较的话，你就会发现，在英国，带着一定程度的同情心的洞察力或是一丝不苟的精神对印度的文学和哲学进行研究的学者是最少的。在两国的关系并不正常，而且是建立在民族的自私和傲慢的基础之上的时候，这种冷漠和蔑视的态度就再自然不过了。但是你们美国的历史是没有私利的历史，这就是为什么你们能够帮助日本学习西方文明，这就是为什么中国在其最黑暗、最危险的时期对你们却抱有最大的信赖。事实上，你们肩负着一个伟大未来的全部责任，因为你们没有受到贪婪吝啬的过去历史的羁绊。因此，在世界上所有的国家当中，美国必须清醒地认识到这一未来；她一定要擦亮眼睛，在青春活力的鼓舞下对人类充满信心。

美国和印度之间存在着共同之处——两个国家都要将各个不同的种族团结在一起。

在印度，我们一直以来都在试图找到所有种族的某些共同之处，而这些共同之处将是各个种族真正团结的明证。仅仅将政治或是经济作为种族团结的基础是不够的。有思想、有能力的人们会找到种族团结的精神基础，并且实现这一精神上的团结，宣扬这一精神上的团结。

印度从来都没有过真正意义上的民族主义观念。尽管从孩提时代开始，我就被灌输以“对于民族的崇拜要好于对于上帝和人性的敬畏”的思想，可是我还是相信自己已经摆脱了这种说教的桎梏；而且我深信不疑的是，通过与“国家要比人类的理想更为伟大的说教”的斗争，我的同胞们会真正地收获他们的印度。

目前，受过教育的印度人正试图从历史当中吸取某些与我们祖先的经验教训截然相反的经验教训。事实上，东方正在努力学习它的历史——一个并非是它自己生活写照的历史。例如，日本认为她正在靠采用西方的方法而变得强大；但是，当她用光了自己祖上的遗产之后，所剩下的便仅仅是从西方文明那里借来的武器。她并没有从自身内部得到发展。

欧洲有自己的过去。因此欧洲的力量来自于她的历史。我们印度一定要下定决心，不能从其他民族那里借来他们的历史，而且，如果我们割断了自己的历史那就等同于自杀。当你们借来本不属于自己生活的东西的时候，这些东西就会毁了你们的生活。

因此，我相信，与西方文明在它自己的运动场上展开竞争对于印度来说毫无益处。但是，如果我们不顾外界的污言秽语，坚持走自己的路的话，我们就会收获颇丰。

有一些课程会给我们传递信息或是为了提高理智而训练我们的头脑。这些课程简单易学，便于利用。但是还有其他的课程会影响到我们的深层本性并且改变我们的人生轨迹。在我们学习这些课程并且以我们自己的遗产作为代价为此买单之前，我们一定要暂停并且好好考虑一下。在人类历史上的某些年代，人们发明了烟花爆竹，并且以其力量和动感让我们头晕目眩。这些烟花爆竹不仅仅嘲笑我们家里朴素的灯盏，而且嘲笑永恒的星辰。但是我们不要由于这种刺激就草率地决定舍弃我们的灯盏。我们要耐心地忍受暂时的侮辱，并且意识到它们尽管灿烂却不持久，因为这种极端的爆炸在产生力量的同时又让它筋疲力尽。与它们的收获和产出相较而言，这些烟花爆竹所耗费的能量和物质是致命的。

总之，我们的理想是在我们自己的历史当中演化而来的。即便是我们只希望将自己的理想制成拙劣的烟花爆竹也改变不了这一点，因为构成我们理想的材料与你们的材料是不同的，而它们的道德目的也是不同的。如果我们下定决心要不惜一切代价买进政治上的民族主义的话，那么其荒唐可笑的程度就如同瑞士为了自己的生存而野心勃勃地建造一支强大的、足以比肩英国的海军一样。我们所犯的错误就在于，我们认为人类想要变得伟大，其途径只有一条——就是这条以其极端傲慢的姿态摆在我们面前的痛苦之路。

我们必须确定自己拥有未来，而且这一未来属于那些拥有丰富的道德理想而不仅仅是拥有物质财富的人。人类拥有这样的特权：他为了收获果实而工作，而这些果实并非触手可及；他调整自己的生活不是为了与某些眼下成功的范例，甚至于不是与他自己谨小慎微的、胸无大志的过去保持被动的一致，而是要与无限的、心中怀抱着的、最最期待的理想未来相向而行。

我们必须承认西方来到印度是命中注定的。然而一定要有人向西方展示东方，并且说服西方相信东方为人类的文明史作出了贡献。印度不是西方的乞丐。即便是西方这样认为，我也不赞成印度应当摆脱所有西方的文明并且在我们的独立中与世隔绝。我们应当紧密相连。如果上帝让英国成为我们沟通的、紧密相连的渠道的话，那么我愿意以自己最大的谦恭接受这一事实。我对于人类的本性怀有极大的信心，而且我认为西方将会发现什么才是她真正的使命。当我意识到西方文明正在背叛人们对它的信任，阻挠实现自己的初衷的时候，我对它进行了严厉的批评。西方一定不要为了她的私利而在这个世界上引起祸端；而是要通过对无知者施以教化，对弱者给予帮助，让他们获得足够的力量，从而抵抗她的侵略方式，将自身从最大的、强大者容易遭遇的险境中拯救出来。而且，西方一定不要将物质主义作为最终追求的目标，而是要意识到，她所提供的服务是要将精神从物质的暴政下解放出来。

我并非反对某个特定的民族，而是反对所有民族的共同理念。那么什么是民族呢？

民族是指一国的全体人民以一个有组织的力量呈现出来的样子。这个组织不停地致力于使其全体成员变得更强大、更高效。但是，在作出这种为了变得强大和高效的努力之后，人类自我牺牲和富于创造性的更高本性的力量就会消耗殆尽。之所以如此，是因为人类牺牲的力量被从它终极的、道德的目标上转移到了对于这个机械的、组织的维护上来。然而在这个过程中，因为他拥有了所有道德提升的满足感，所以对于人性来说变得极度危险。当人类能够将自己的责任转化到这台由他的理智，而非由他完全的道德人格所创造出来的机器之上的时候，他便会感到自己从良知的规范之下解脱了出来。通过这台机器，热爱自由的民族让奴隶制在这个世界上的广大地区永久地持续，而他们却因为履行了自己的职责而骄傲地感到心安理得；那些生来正直的人们在其行动和思想上变得残忍而不公，而同时他们却感到自己是在帮助这个世界得到其应有的惩罚；那些诚实的人们会为了自我的膨胀而继续盲目地剥夺其他人的人权，而与此同时却辱骂那些受害者，说他们罪有应得。我们在自己的生活中见到过，即便是小的商业和行业组织也会在本性并不坏的人们身上产生感情的冷漠；而且我们完全可以想象得出来，它在这个所有民族都在疯狂地组织起来捞取财富和权力的世界上引起了多么大的道德浩劫。

民族主义是一个巨大的威胁。它是一种独特的东西，并且已经在印度的麻烦堆中潜藏了多年。因为我们已经被一个在其态度上具有严格政治性的民族统治、控制了多年，所以，尽管我们继承了过去的遗产，我们还是试图在自己的身上发展出一种对于自己最终政治命运的信仰。

印度有不同的政党，它们有不同的理想。其中一些政党正在为政治独立而斗争。而另外一些政党则认为争取政治独立还为时尚早。它们认为印度应当取得与英国其他殖民地一样的权利，并且希望印度尽量争取自治。

在印度的政治纷争的早期历史当中，并不存在像今天这样的政党间的冲突。那时候有一个政党叫作印度国大党[3]；它并没有真正的纲领。他们会对当局发一些牢骚或是提出抗议，期望他们予以改正。他们希望在地方议会中获得更大的代表权，在市政府中得到更多的自由。他们要的东西都很琐碎，然而却缺乏建设性的理想。因此我对他们的方法不感兴趣。我深信，印度最需要的是来自自身的建设性的工作。尽管在这种工作中，我们每前进一步所取得的道义上的胜利，都是在严酷的迫害下，以失败和痛苦为代价换来的，然而，我们仍然要甘冒所有的风险，继续履行我们本应履行的职责。我们必须向高高在上的统治者表明，我们拥有道德的力量，拥有为真理而受难的力量。如果我们无所证明我们就只有乞讨。如果我们希望得到的东西即刻就能得到满足的话，那么反而是有害的。我曾经反复地告诉过我的同胞们，要团结起来，一起为了弘扬我们自我牺牲的精神去创造机会，而不要一同去乞讨。

然而，国大党失去了权力，因为人们不久就意识到他们所采取的残缺的政策是徒劳无益的。于是国大党分裂了[4]，出现了极端主义分子。他们主张行动上的独立，并且抛弃乞讨的方法——他们认为这种乞讨的方法是让一个人摆脱对自己国家的责任的最简便易行的方法。他们的理想是以西方的历史为基础的。他们并不关心印度存在的特殊问题。他们不承认这样一个显而易见的事实：我们的社会组织当中的某些因素使得印度人民难以与外国人相抗衡。如果出于某种原因，英国被赶走了，那么我们将会怎么办呢？我们不过是会沦为其他民族的牺牲品而已。同样的社会问题仍将持续。我们印度人民不得不考虑的是这样一个问题：将那些产生缺少自尊并且完全依赖统治者的社会习俗和理念摈弃掉——这种问题完全是由于印度的种姓制度的控制，以及盲目、懒惰地依赖传统的权威性的习惯所造成的，而这些传统是与当今时代难以协调的时代错误。

我再一次地提醒你们注意印度无法回避的困难和她为了克服这些困难而进行的斗争。印度的问题就是世界问题的缩影。印度的疆域太过广大，种族太过多样。她相当于很多的国家聚集在了一个地理区域内。她与欧洲的情况恰恰相反；在那里，就相当于一个国家分裂成了多个国家。因此，欧洲在其文化和成长壮大方面不仅得益于其一国的优势，而且得益于其多国的力量。反观印度，由于她生来具有多样性，而后天又成为一个国家，所以她自始至终都蒙受其松散的多样性和衰弱的一致性所带来的痛苦。真正的一致性就如同一只圆球；它滚动起来，很容易地携带其自身的负荷。但是多样性就像是一个有很多棱角的物体，要想推拉它就要费尽全力。应当说明的是，印度的这种多样性并非她自身的创造，而是从她历史的开端就不得不接受的一个事实。在美国和澳大利亚，欧洲人几乎是通过消灭原住民的方式让问题得到了简化。即便是在当今时代，我们同样能看到种族灭绝的幽灵在徘徊——它冷淡地将外国人拒之门外，而这样做的人们自己在其所霸占的这片土地上，其实就是外国人。而印度自其肇始就容忍了种族的多样性，而且这种包容的精神贯穿了她的整个历史。

印度的种姓制度就是这种包容精神的产物。因为，她一直以来就做着各种实验，希望创造出一种能将不同的民族结合在一起的社会团结，而与此同时，各个民族又能充分地享受、保有自己独特性的自由。所以这种纽带一直保持尽可能的松散，而同时又在环境的允许下保持尽可能的紧密。这就产生了一种类似于社会同盟的合众国的东西，她的常见名称就是印度教。

印度曾经感到，无论种族的多样性有多少缺点，它都是必不可少的；而且你永远都不可能逼迫天性进入到你出于方便而设置的狭窄范围之内，而无需终究有一天为此付出高昂的代价。在这一点上印度是正确的；但是她却没有认识到人类彼此间的差异并非像阻隔的群山那样，永远地固定在那里——它们是随着生命的流动而流动的，它们正改变着自己的轨迹、形状和大小。

因此，在种姓制度的规章里面，印度承认了差别，然而她却没有承认易变性的生命法则。为了避免冲突，印度建立起了不可移动的边界壁垒，从而给她众多的种族带来了和平和秩序的、消极的好处，然而并没有给他们带来发展和变化的、积极的机会。她接受了产生多样性的自然，但是却忽略了自然正是利用这种多样性从事其有着无穷的变化和组合方式的世界游戏。她真实地面对生命的丰富多彩，但是却无视其永远变动的事实。因此，生命就从她的社会体系当中脱离了出来，取而代之的是她竭尽一切仪式所膜拜的，由无数她亲手打造的隔间所构成的，宏大无比的牢笼。

在印度试图避免行业利益的冲突的时候，发生了同样的事情。她将不同的行业和职业与不同的种姓相联系。这种做法可以一劳永逸地减轻竞争所带来的无休止的嫉妒和仇恨——这种竞争滋生了残忍，制造了浓重的、充满了谎言和欺骗的氛围。然而印度的这种做法同样强调了遗传的法则，忽略了变化的规律，因此逐渐地将艺术退化成为工艺，将天才堕落成为技工。

然而，西方的观察家们却没能洞悉这样一个事实：印度在其种姓制度当中很严肃地承担起了，以避免所有的矛盾和摩擦为目的的，解决种族问题的责任。她给每个种族在其活动范围内以自由。毋庸讳言，印度在这方面还没有获得完全的成功。但是，你们必须承认，尽管西方在种族同一性方面拥有更大的优势，然而她却从来没有关注过这个问题；而且，每当遇到这样的问题时，她都会试图通过采取置之不理的方式将它轻描淡写。这也是西方反亚风潮的原因所在——她剥夺了外国人在西方国家诚实谋生的权利。在大多数的殖民地国家，你们只在他们从事伐木和取水的工作时才会接纳他们。你们要么对外国人大门紧闭，要么就奴役他们，而这就是你们对于种族矛盾问题的解决之道。无论这样做可能存在什么样的好处，你们都必须承认，这种做法并非源自文明的、更为高尚的动机，而是来自于更为低级的、贪婪和仇恨的骚动。你们说这就是人类的本性——不过别忘了，印度在通过固定的、社会等级的藩篱来强行地划分种族差别的时候，也认为自己了解人类的本性。但是只有当吃过了苦头之后，我们才发现人类的本性并非它看上去的那个样子；而是存在于现实当中，存在于它无限的可能性当中。当我们盲目地攻击人性，说它衣衫褴褛的时候，它便会脱下伪装，露出庐山真面目——我们所攻击的竟然是我们的上帝。我们出于傲慢或是自私的目的对别人进行丑化的同时，同样也会丑化我们自己的人性——这是一种最为严厉的惩罚，因为当我们发现它的时候为时已晚了。

不单单是你们与外国人的关系，你们自己社会中不同阶层间的关系也都没有达到和谐一致。矛盾和竞争的精神在你们这里可以自由地横冲直撞。由于它的起源是对于财富和权力的贪婪，所以它的最终结局除了暴毙之外别无选择。在印度，商品的生产是根据社会调解的规律进行的。它的基础是合作，其目的是充分地满足社会的需求。但是在西方，商品生产是在竞争的催动下进行的，它的目标是为个人捞取财富。但是个人就像是几何线条一样；它有长度却没有宽度，并且还没有达到足以长久地容纳什么东西的深度。因此，它的贪婪或攫取是永无止境的。在这种几何线条不断的成长过程中，它会与其他的线条交织、纠缠在一起，但是在其与世隔绝的、纤细的状态下，永远都不会获得完善的理想。

我们知道自己的胃口是有一定限度的，而且我们知道超越了这一限度就会有损我们的健康。但是，对于占有财富和权力的贪欲来说，难道就没有超越它就会陷入死亡的界限吗？在这些民族的、物质主义的狂欢节上，西方的各个民族不正是在单纯地生产财富而忽略创造理想的过程中挥霍着他们的生命活力吗？难道说一个文明可以忽略道德健康的法则，并且通过大肆地吞咽物质财富而无休止地膨胀下去吗？人类按照其社会理想，会自然而然地限制自己的贪欲，使其从属于人类本性当中的、更为高尚的目的。但是在经济领域里，我们的贪欲除了受到供给和需求的限制以外不受其他任何的限制；而供给和需求则是可以人为地创造的，这就给个人提供了机会，让他沉溺于一场无尽的、让人肚满肠肥的盛宴之中。在印度，我们的社会本能对我们的贪欲加以限制——可能这种限制造成了极端的压抑——但是在西方，没有道德目的的经济组织的幽灵，却驱赶着人们永久地追逐着财富；难道对于这种行为就没有有益于身心的界限吗？

在各种社会制度中努力成形的理想有两个目标。一个是为了人类和谐的发展而管控我们的激情和贪欲，另外一个就是帮助人类养成对其同类的无私的爱。因此，社会就是人类道德和精神渴望的表现形式，而这些渴望则属于人类更为崇高的本性。

我们的食物是具有创造性的，它能强健我们的身体；但是酒则不然，它只能给我们以刺激。我们的社会理想创造了人类世界，但是当我们的思想偏离了这些社会理想，转而贪婪地追求权力的时候，在这种醉酒的状态之下，我们就会生活在一个不正常的世界里面。在这里，我们的力量并非健康的标志，我们的解放也并非是获得了自由。因此，当我们的思想不自由的时候，政治的自由并不能给予我们自由。一辆汽车并不能自由地行动，因为它不过是台机器而已。只有当我自己是自由的时候，我才能利用这台车达到我自由的目的。

我们永远都不要忘记，在当今，那些已经获得了政治自由的人们不见得就是自由的；他们不过是强大而已。他们放纵的激情正在创造出披着自由伪装的，巨大的奴役性质的组织。那些把赚钱当作他们最高目标的人们正在无意识中出卖他们的生命和灵魂给富人或是给某些代表金钱的联合体。那些迷恋政治权力，并且为自己扩大了对于其他种族的控制而感到洋洋自得的人们，逐渐地放弃了他们的自由和人性，将其交给了那些为了奴役其他民族而必须建立起来的组织。在那些所谓的自由国家中，大多数的人们并不自由；他们正在少数人的驱使之下去完成他们自己也不清楚的任务。这种情况之所以产生是因为，人们并没有将道德的和精神的自由看作是自己的目标。他们以自己的激情制造出巨大的旋涡；他们因为自己快速的旋转而感到头晕眼花、如醉如痴，并且就此以为那就是自由。但是，伺机袭击他们的厄运就像是死亡一样不可避免——因为人类的真理是道德的真理，人类的解放是精神生活的解放。

印度当今大多数民族主义者的通行观点就是，我们在社会和精神理想方面已经达到了尽善尽美的程度，社会建设性工作在我们出生前的几千年前就已经开始了，而且现在，我们可以自由地在政治方面大展拳脚。我们从来没有想过将我们如今的软弱无能归咎于我们的社会缺陷，因为我们已经将下面这一点当作了我们民族主义的信条：我们祖先所创立的这一制度将会永远适用，因为他们拥有洞悉古今的超人的眼光，并且拥有为未来提供无限滋养的神奇力量。因此，我们认为自己的痛苦和缺陷都是由历史上来自于外部的突然袭击所造成。这就是为什么我们认为自己的唯一任务就是要在社会奴役的流沙之上建造一个自由的政治奇迹。事实上，我们是要阻断自己的历史河流的本来路径，并且单纯地从其他民族的历史源泉那里借来力量。

我们印度有些人妄想着单纯的政治自由就可以让我们获得自由。他们把西方的说教当作了绝对的真理，却丢掉了自己对于人性的信仰。我们一定不要忘记，我们在自己的社会中所抱有的任何缺陷都会在政治方面成为危险的策源地。那种导致我们盲目地崇拜社会制度中的陈规陋习的惯性，同样会在我们的政治中建造出由不可移动的壁垒围成的监狱牢房。狭隘的同情心使得我们有可能将令人恼怒的奴役强加给相当大的一部分人类，而与此同时，它会在政治中坚持不懈地制造出不公正的专制。

当我们的民族主义者们谈论理想的时候，他们忘了我们民族主义的基础是不牢固的。那些赞成这些理想的人们，自己在其社会实践方面却往往最为保守。例如，民族主义者说：看一看瑞士吧，尽管那里有种族差异，但其人民还是团结成了一个民族。可是，诸位不要忘了，瑞士的各个种族是可以彼此交往的，是可以通婚的，因为他们有着相同的血统。然而在印度却没有与生俱来的共同权利。当我们谈论西方民族的时候，我们忘了，那里的各个民族之间并不存在彼此间的——像我们各个种姓之间所存在着的——生理上的排斥。一个血脉不相连通的民族中的各个种族，会在没有强迫或是没有金钱利诱的情况下为了彼此而流血牺牲吗？全世界范围之内有这样的例子吗？我们可以希冀这些阻碍我们种族融合的、道德的藩篱不会阻碍我们在政治上的团结吗？

于是，我们必须再次完全地承认这个事实：我们的社会限制仍然是如此残暴，以至于它可以将人们变成懦夫。如果有人告诉我他持有异端的观点，但是他不能坚持自己的看法，因为那样的话他就会为社会所不容，那么我会原谅他为了生存而在谎言中生活。强迫我们过同伴的生活——他们即便是在食物的选择方面也与我们不同，成为他们负担的社会思维习惯一定会在我们的政治组织当中持续下去，并且最终导致高压政治的机器被创造出来，用以摧毁每一个显示着生命迹象的合理的差异。暴政只会在我们的政治生活中增加不可避免的谎言和伪善。自由的名号就那么值钱吗？我们宁愿牺牲掉自己的道德自由来同它作交换吗？

当我们拥有年轻活力的时候，我们对于自己习惯的放纵并不会马上产生影响。但是这种放纵会逐渐地吞噬我们的活力，而且当我们的生命开始走下坡路的时候，我们就不得不为此买单，并且还清债务，从而导致我们的破产。在西方，尽管你们的人性正在由于它在每一次运用权力的过程中所发作的间发性酒狂而受到折磨，可是你们仍然能够趾高气扬。印度也处在她年富力强的时期，所以能够在自己的内脏器官中携带僵化而完善的、社会组织的致死的重量；但是这一重量对她来说事关重大，并且已经逐渐地让她的生命天性麻痹瘫痪。这就是印度的知识阶层对社会需求变得麻木不仁的原因。他们以为静止的社会结构正是说明了它们的完美无瑕——而且，因为我们的社会有机体已经失去了健康的、疼痛的感觉，所以他们就误以为它并不需要帮助。因此他们认为，他们所有的能量只需在政治领域内发挥就可以了。这就像一个人，他的双腿已经萎缩并且失去了功能，可是他却试图欺骗自己，说自己的双腿不能动了是因为它们已经获得了最终的解脱，而自己唯一的过错就是缺少拐杖而已。

关于印度的社会和政治重建就说这么多吧。现在我们谈一下印度的工业。经常有人问我，自从英国政府到来以后，印度是否有过工业的重建。我们必须记住，在英国统治印度之初，我们的工业就受到了抑制；而且从那时候起，我们没有得到过任何真正的帮助或是鼓励，以使我们能够同世界上的商业组织的怪兽进行对抗。各个民族都号令我们要保持一个纯粹农业国的地位，甚至于永远都忘了如何使用武力。于是印度就被变成了很多份的、易消化的食物，随时准备提供给任何一个，哪怕是牙齿还没有发育完全的民族进行吞咽。

因此，印度在其工业创新方面鲜有作为。我个人并不相信当今臃肿的商业组织。它们的丑陋的事实表明，它们与所谓创新是格格不入的。自然的巨大力量不是在丑陋，而是在美丽当中展露其真理。美丽是当造物主对自己的造物感到满意的时候，在其上面签下的自己的姓名。所有傲慢地忽略了完美法则，厚颜无耻地展示其丑陋的产品，都是对上帝永远的冒犯。只要你们的商业缺乏优雅的高贵，它就不是真正的商业。“美丽”和她的双胞胎哥哥“真理”在成长的过程中要求得到的是闲情雅致和自我控制。但是庞大的、占有的贪欲却总要超越时空的限制。它的唯一目标就是生产和消费。它对于美丽的自然和活着的人类均没有怜悯。它会冷酷地、毫不犹豫地将他们的美丽和生命榨取出来，然后将其铸成钱币。在人类早期的时候，我们鄙视这种商业的丑陋和粗俗，因为那时候我们拥有闲暇的时光，能够拨开云雾，透视人性当中的完美。那时候，人类正直地以自己单纯谋财的本能为耻。但是，在这个科学的年代，金钱由于其变态膨胀的体积而为自身赢得了王位。而且，当金钱聚集了大量的财富而羞辱人类更为崇高的本性，并且在其周边驱除掉美丽和高尚的情感的时候，我们便屈服了。因为我们已经卑鄙地接受了它双手奉上的贿赂，而且，我们的想象力已经在它硕大无比的肉身面前卑躬屈膝。

但是，正是它的笨拙和无尽的复杂表明了它的失败。一位专业的游泳者不会通过激烈的动作展示其肌肉的力量，而是以看不到的、完美的优雅和安静显露其力量。人类与动物的真正区别就在于，人类的力量和价值是内在的和隐形的。但是，如今人类的商业文明却不仅仅是占据了大量的时间和空间，而且正在浪费时间和空间。它的动作激烈、噪音大而不和谐。它携带着对于自己的诅咒，因为它正在将自己所依赖的人性践踏得扭曲变形。它正在竭尽全力，以幸福为代价捞取金钱。人类正在将自身最小化，为的是能够给这些商业组织提供宽敞的空间。人类正在嘲弄他的情感使其蒙羞，因为这些情感会挡住他的机器们前进的道路。

在我们的神话中有这样一个故事，如果有谁想要通过苦修以求达到永生的话，那么他就一定会受到来自不朽之神因陀罗的诱惑。如果他禁不住这些诱惑，他就会迷失。几百年来，西方一直在致力于追求不朽。因陀罗已经给她送去了诱惑来考验她。这个华丽的诱惑就是财富。西方接受了它，因此她的人性的文明便在机器的荒原上迷失了方向。

这种以丑恶装点门面的、残忍的商业主义对于全体人类来说都是威胁，因为它正在把权力的理想凌驾于完善的理想之上。它正在使得利己主义的歪理邪说在无耻的赤裸中欢呼雀跃。我们的神经要比我们的肌肉更加脆弱。宝贵的东西因其宝贵而需要我们悉心的呵护；如果失去了我们的呵护，它们就会像失去了呵护的婴儿一样变得无助。因此，当无情的、野蛮的权力在人性的大道上横冲直撞的时候，它便以其粗野吓跑了我们几个世纪以来以牺牲为代价所珍爱的理想。

诱惑对于强者来说是致命的，对于弱者来说更是如此。即便是不朽之神所送上的诱惑，我也不欢迎它来到印度。让我们的生命外表简朴而内在丰富吧。让我们的文明牢牢地建立在社会合作，而非经济盘剥和对抗的基础之上吧。如何在经济恶魔嗜血的利齿间做到这一切，则是摆在所有对于人类灵魂拥有信仰的，东方各民族的思想家面前的任务。接受那些与我们有不同理想的人们所开出的条件只会证明我们的懒惰和无能。我们应当积极地促使世界诸强国引领历史的发展，使其达到完善的彼岸。

从上面我说的话你们就知道我并不是一个经济学家。我愿意承认供需规律的存在，承认人类的痴迷——他们想要占有更多的东西，而不是于己有益的东西。然而我坚信，在人性之中存在着一种完美的和谐。在那里，贫穷不能带走他的财富；在那里，失败可能导致成功，死亡可能让他不朽；在那里，作为永恒正义之神所作出的补偿，那些落后的民族会将他们所受到的凌辱转化为金灿灿的胜利。

Nationalism in Japan

Ⅰ

The worst form of bondage is the bondage of dejection, which keeps men hopelessly chained in loss of faith in themselves. We have been repeatedly told, with some justification, that Asia lives in the past — it is like a rich mausoleum which displays all its magnificence in trying to immortalize the dead. It was said of Asia that it could never move in the path of progress, its face was so inevitably turned backwards. We accepted this accusation, and came to believe it. In India, I know, a large section of our educated community, grown tired of feeling the humiliation of this charge against us, is trying with all its resources of self-deception to turn it into a matter of boasting. But boasting is only a masked shame, it does not truly believe in itself.

When things stood still like this, and we in Asia hypnotized ourselves into the belief that it could never by any possibility be otherwise, Japan rose from her dreams, and in giant strides left centuries of inaction behind, overtaking the present time in its foremost achievement. This has broken the spell under which we lay in torpor for ages, taking it to be the normal condition of certain races living in certain geographical limits. We forgot that in Asia great kingdoms were founded, philosophy, science, arts and literatures flourished, and all the great religions of the world had their cradles. Therefore it cannot be said that there is anything inherent in the soil and climate of Asia to produce mental inactivity and to atrophy the faculties which impel men to go forward. For centuries we did hold torches of civilization in the East when the West slumbered in darkness, and that could never be the sign of sluggish minds or narrowness of vision.

Then fell the darkness of night upon all the lands of the East. The current of time seemed to stop at once, and Asia ceased to take any new food, feeding upon its own past, which is really feeding upon itself. The stillness seemed like death, and the great voice was silenced which sent forth messages of eternal truth that have saved man's life from pollution for generations, like the ocean of air that keeps the earth sweet, ever cleansing its impurities.

But life has its sleep, its periods of inactivity, when it loses its movements, takes no new food, living upon its past storage. Then it grows helpless, its muscles relaxed, and it easily lends itself to be jeered at for its stupor. In the rhythm of life, pauses there must be for the renewal of life. Life in its activity is ever spending itself, burning all its fuel. This extravagance cannot go on indefinitely, but is always followed by a passive stage, when all expenditure is stopped and all adventures abandoned in favour of rest and slow recuperation.

The tendency of the mind is economical: it loves to form habits and move in grooves which save it the trouble of thinking anew at each of its steps. Ideals once formed make the mind lazy. It becomes afraid to risk its acquisitions in fresh endeavours. It tries to enjoy complete security by shutting up its belongings behind fortifications of habits. But this is really shutting oneself up from the fullest enjoyment of one's own possessions. It is miserliness. The living ideals must not lose their touch with the growing and changing life. Their real freedom is not within the boundaries of security, but on the high-road of adventures, full of the risk of new experiences.

One morning the whole world looked up in surprise when Japan broke through her walls of old habits in a night and came out triumphant. It was done in such an incredibly short time that it seemed like a change of dress and not like the building up of a new structure. She showed the confident strength of maturity, and the freshness and infinite potentiality of new life at the same moment. The fear was entertained that it was a mere freak of history, a child's game of Time, the blowing up of a soap-bubble, perfect in its rondure and colouring, hollow in its heart and without substance. But Japan has proved conclusively that this sudden revealment of her power is not a short-lived wonder, a chance product of time and tide, thrown up from the depth of obscurity to be swept away the next moment into a sea of oblivion.

The truth is that Japan is old and new at the same time. She has her legacy of ancient culture from the East — the culture that enjoins man to look for his true wealth and power in his inner soul, the culture that gives self-possession in the face of loss and danger, self-sacrifice without counting the cost or hoping for gain, defiance of death, acceptance of countless social obligations that we owe to men as social beings. In a word, modern Japan has come out of the immemorial East like a lotus blossoming in easy grace, all the while keeping its firm hold upon the profound depth from which it has sprung.

And Japan, the child of the Ancient East, has also fearlessly claimed all the gifts of the modern age for herself. She has shown her bold spirit in breaking through the confinements of habits, useless accumulations of the lazy mind, which seeks safety in its thrift and its locks and keys. Thus she has come in contact with the living time and has accepted with eagerness and aptitude the responsibilities of modern civilization.

This it is which has given heart to the rest of Asia. We have seen that the life and the strength are there in us; only the dead crust has to be removed. We have seen that taking shelter in the dead is death itself, and only taking all the risk of life to the fullest extent is living.

I, for myself, cannot believe that Japan has become what she is by imitating the West. We cannot imitate life, we cannot simulate strength for long, nay, what is more, a mere imitation is a source of weakness. For it hampers our true nature; it is always in our way. It is like dressing our skeleton with another man's skin, giving rise to eternal feuds between the skin and the bones at every movement.

The real truth is that science is not man's nature, it is mere knowledge and training. By knowing the laws of the material universe you do not change your deeper humanity. You can borrow knowledge from others, but you cannot borrow temperament.

But at the imitative stage of our schooling we cannot distinguish between the essential and the non-essential, between what is transferable and what is not. It is something like the faith of the primitive mind in the magical properties of the accidents of outward forms which accompany some real truth. We are afraid of leaving out something valuable and efficacious by not swallowing the husk with the kernel. But while our greed delights in wholesale appropriation, it is the function of our vital nature to assimilate, which is the only true appropriation for a living organism. Where there is life it is sure to assert itself by its choice of acceptance and refusal according to its constitutional necessity. The living organism does not allow itself to grow into its food; it changes its food into its own body. And only thus can it grow strong and not by mere accumulation, or by giving up its personal identity.

Japan has imported her food from the West, but not her vital nature. Japan cannot altogether lose and merge herself in the scientific paraphernalia she has acquired from the West and be turned into a mere borrowed machine. She has her own soul, which must assert itself over all her requirements. That she is capable of doing so, and that the process of assimilation is going on, have been amply proved by the signs of vigorous health that she exhibits. And I earnestly hope that Japan may never lose her faith in her own soul, in the mere pride of her foreign acquisition. For that pride itself is a humiliation, ultimately leading to poverty and weakness. It is the pride of the fop who sets more store on his new head-dress than on his head itself.

The whole world waits to see what this great eastern nation is going to do with the opportunities and responsibilities she has accepted from the hands of the modern time. If it be a mere reproduction of the West, then the great expectation she has raised will remain unfulfilled. For there are grave questions that western civilization has presented before the world but not completely answered. The conflict between the individual and the state, labour and capital, the man and the woman; the conflict between the greed of material gain and the spiritual life of man, the organized selfishness of nations and the higher ideals of humanity; the conflict between all the ugly complexities inseparable from giant organizations of commerce and state and the natural instincts of man crying for simplicity and beauty and fulness of leisure — all these have to be brought to a harmony in a manner not yet dreamt of.

We have seen this great stream of civilization choking itself from debris carried by its innumerable channels. We have seen that with all its vaunted love of humanity it has proved itself the greatest menace to Man, far worse than the sudden outbursts of nomadic barbarism from which men suffered in the early ages of history. We have seen that, in spite of its boasted love of freedom, it has produced worse forms of slavery than ever were current in earlier societies — slavery whose chains are unbreakable, either because they are unseen, or because they assume the names and appearance of freedom. We have seen, under the spell of its gigantic sordidness, man losing faith in all the heroic ideals of life which have made him great.

Therefore you cannot with a light heart accept the modern civilization with all its tendencies, methods and structures, and dream that they are inevitable. You must apply your eastern mind, your spiritual strength, your love of simplicity, your recognition of social obligation, in order to cut out a new path for this great unwieldy car of progress, shrieking out its loud discords as it runs. You must minimize the immense sacrifice of man's life and freedom that it claims in its every movement. For generations you have felt and thought and worked, have enjoyed and worshipped in your own special manner; and this cannot be cast off like old clothes. It is in your blood, in the marrow of your bones, in the texture of your flesh, in the tissue of your brains; and it must modify everything you lay your hands upon, without your knowing, even against your wishes. Once you did solve the problems of man to your own satisfaction, you had your philosophy of life and evolved your own art of living. All this you must apply to the present situation, and out of it will arise a new creation and not a mere repetition, a creation which the soul of your people will own for itself and proudly offer to the world as its tribute to the welfare of man. Of all countries in Asia, here in Japan you have the freedom to use the materials you have gathered from the West according to your genius and your need. Therefore your responsibility is all the greater, for in your voice Asia shall answer the questions that Europe has submitted to the conference of Man. In your land the experiments will be carried on by which the East will change the aspects of modern civilization, infusing life in it where it is a machine, substituting the human heart for cold expediency, not caring so much for power and success as for harmonious and living growth, for truth and beauty.

I cannot but bring to your mind those days when the whole of eastern Asia from Burma to Japan was united with India in the closest tie of friendship, the only natural tie which can exist between nations. There was a living communication of hearts, a nervous system evolved through which messages ran between us about the deepest needs of humanity. We did not stand in fear of each other; we had not to arm ourselves to keep each other in check; our relation was not that of self-interest, of exploration and spoliation of each other's pocket; ideas and ideals were exchanged, gifts of the highest love were offered and taken; no difference of languages and customs hindered us in approaching each other heart to heart; no pride of race or insolent consciousness of superiority, physical or mental, marred our relation; our arts and literatures put forth new leaves and flowers under the influence of this sunlight of united hearts, and races belonging to different lands and languages and histories acknowledged the highest unity of man and the deepest bond of love. May we not also remember that in those days of peace and goodwill, of men uniting for those supreme ends of life, your nature laid by for itself the balm of immortality which has helped your people to be born again in a new age, to be able to survive its old outworn structures and take on a new young body, to come out unscathed from the shock of the most wonderful revolution that the world has ever seen?

The political civilization which has sprung up from the soil of Europe and is overrunning the whole world, like some prolific weed, is based upon exclusiveness. It is always watchful to keep the aliens at bay or to exterminate them. It is carnivorous and cannibalistic in its tendencies, it feeds upon the resources of other peoples and tries to swallow their whole future. It is always afraid of other races achieving eminence, naming it as a peril, and tries to thwart all symptoms of greatness outside its own boundaries, forcing down races of men who are weaker, to be eternally fixed in their weakness. Before this political civilization came to its power and opened its hungry jaws wide enough to gulp down great continents of the earth, we had wars, pillages, changes of monarchy and consequent miseries, but never such a sight of fearful and hopeless voracity, such wholesale feeding of nation upon nation, such huge machines for turning great portions of the earth into mince-meat, never such terrible jealousies with all their ugly teeth and claws ready for tearing open each other's vitals. This political civilization is scientific, not human. It is powerful because it concentrates all its forces upon one purpose, like a millionaire acquiring money at the cost of his soul. It betrays its trust, it weaves its meshes of lies without shame, it enshrines gigantic idols of greed in its temples, taking great pride in the costly ceremonials of its worship, calling this patriotism. And it can be safely prophesied that this cannot go on, for there is a moral law in this world which has its application both to individuals and to organized bodies of men. You cannot go on violating these laws in the name of your nation, yet enjoy their advantage as individuals. This public sapping of ethical ideals slowly reacts upon each member of society, gradually breeding weakness where it is not seen, and causing that cynical distrust of all things sacred in human nature, which is the true symptom of senility. You must keep in mind that this political civilization, this creed of national patriotism, has not been given a long trial. The lamp of ancient Greece is extinct in the land where it was first lighted; the power of Rome lies dead and buried under the ruins of its vast empire. But the civilization, whose basis is society and the spiritual ideal of man, is still a living thing in China and in India. Though it may look feeble and small, judged by the standard of the mechanical power of modern days, yet like small seeds it still contains life and will sprout and grow, and spread its beneficent branches, producing flowers and fruits when its time comes and showers of grace descend upon it from heaven. But ruins of skyscrapers of power, and broken machinery of greed, even God's rain is powerless to raise up again; for they were not of life, but went against life as a whole — they are relics of the rebellion that shattered itself to pieces against the eternal.

But the charge is brought against us that the ideals we cherish in the East are static, that they have not the impetus in them to move, to open out new vistas of knowledge and power, that the systems of philosophy which are the mainstays of the time-worn civilizations of the Fast despise all outward proofs, remaining stolidly satisfied in their subjective certainty. This proves that when our knowledge is vague we are apt to accuse of vagueness our object of knowledge itself. To a western observer our civilization appears as all metaphysics, as to a deaf man piano-playing appears to be mere movements of fingers and no music. He cannot think that we have found some deep basis of reality upon which we have built our institutions.

Unfortunately all proofs of reality are in realization. The reality of the scene before you depends only upon the fact that you can see, and it is difficult for us to prove to an unbeliever that our civilization is not a nebulous system of abstract speculations, that it has achieved something which is a positive truth — a truth that can give man's heart its shelter and sustenance. It has evolved an inner sense — a sense of vision, the vision of the infinite reality in all finite things.

But he says, 'You do not make any progress; there is no movement in you.' I ask him, 'How do you know it? You have to judge progress according to its aim. A railway train makes its progress towards the terminus station — it is movement. But a full-grown tree has no definite movement of that kind; its progress is the inward progress of life. It lives, with its aspiration towards light tingling in its leaves and creeping in its silent sap.'

We also have lived for centuries; we still live, and we have our aspiration for a reality that has no end to its realization — a reality that goes beyond death, giving it a meaning, that rises above all evils of life, bringing its peace and purity, its cheerful renunciation of self. The product of this inner life is a living product. It will be needed when the youth returns home weary and dust-laden, when the soldier is wounded, when the wealth is squandered away and pride is humbled, when man's heart cries for truth in the immensity of facts, and harmony in the contradiction of tendencies. Its value is not in its multiplication of materials, but in its spiritual fulfilment.

There are things that cannot wait. You have to rush and run and march if you must fight or take the best place in the market. You strain your nerves and are on the alert when you chase opportunities that are always on the wing. But there are ideals which do not play hide-and-seek with our life; they slowly grow from seed to flower, from flower to fruit; they require infinite space and heaven's light to mature, and the fruits that they produce can survive years of insult and neglect. The East with her ideals, in whose bosom are stored the ages of sunlight and silence of stars, can patiently wait till the West, hurrying after the expedient, loses breath and stops. Europe, while busily speeding to her engagements, disdainfully casts her glance from her carriage window at the reaper reaping his harvest in the field, and in her intoxication of speed cannot but think of him as slow and ever receding backwards. But the speed comes to its end; the engagement loses its meaning and the hungry heart clamours for food, till at last she comes to the lowly reaper reaping his harvest in the sun. For if the office cannot wait, or the buying and selling, or the craving for excitement, love waits, and beauty, and the wisdom of suffering and the fruits of patient devotion and reverent meekness of simple faith. And thus shall wait the East till her time comes.

I must not hesitate to acknowledge where Europe is great, for great she is without doubt. We cannot help loving her with all our heart and paying her the best homage of our admiration — the Europe who, in her literature and art, pours out an inexhaustible cascade of beauty and truth fertilizing all countries and all time; the Europe who, with a mind which is titanic in its untiring power, is sweeping the height and the depth of the universe, winning her homage of knowledge from the infinitely great and the infinitely small, applying all the resources of her great intellect and heart in healing the sick and alleviating those miseries of man which up till now we were contented to accept in a spirit of hopeless resignation; the Europe who is making the earth yield more fruit than seemed possible, coaxing and compelling the great forces of nature into man's service. Such true greatness must have its motive power in spiritual strength. For only the spirit of man can defy all limitations, have faith in its ultimate success, throw its searchlight beyond the immediate and the apparent, gladly suffer martyrdom for ends which cannot be achieved in its lifetime and accept failure without acknowledging defeat. In the heart of Europe runs the purest stream of human love, of love of justice, of spirit of self-sacrifice for higher ideals. The Christian culture of centuries has sunk deep in her life's core. In Europe we have seen noble minds who have ever stood up for the rights of man irrespective of colour and creed; who have braved calumny and insult from their own people in fighting for humanity's cause and raising their voices against the mad orgies of militarism, against the rage for brutal retaliation or rapacity that sometimes takes possession of a whole people; who are always ready to make reparation for wrongs done in the past by their own nations and vainly attempt to stem the tide of cowardly injustice that flows unchecked because the resistance is weak and innocuous on the part of the injured. There are these knight-errants of modern Europe who have not lost their faith in the disinterested love of freedom, in the ideals which own no geographical boundaries or national self-seeking. These are there to prove that the fountainhead of the water of everlasting life has not run dry in Europe, and from thence she will have her rebirth time after time. Only there, where Europe is too consciously busy in building up her power, defying her deeper nature and mocking it, she is heaping up her iniquities to the sky, crying for God's vengeance and spreading the infection of ugliness, physical and moral, over the face of the earth with her heartless commerce heedlessly outraging man's sense of the beautiful and the good. Europe is supremely good in her beneficence where her face is turned to all humanity; and Europe is supremely evil in her maleficent aspect where her face is turned only upon her own interest, using all her power of greatness for ends which are against the infinite and eternal in Man.

Eastern Asia has been pursuing its own path, evolving its own civilization, which was not political but social, not predatory and mechanically efficient but spiritual and based upon all the varied and deeper relations of humanity. The solutions of the life problems of peoples were thought out in seclusion and carried out behind the security of aloofness, where all the dynastic changes and foreign invasions hardly touched them. But now we are overtaken by the outside world, our seclusion is lost for ever. Yet this we must not regret, as a plant should never regret when the obscurity of its seed-time is broken. Now the time has come when we must make the world problem our own problem; we must bring the spirit of civilization into harmony with the history of all nations of the earth; we must not, in foolish pride, still keep ourselves fast within the shell of the seed and the crust of the earth which protected and nourished our ideals; for these, the shell and the crust, were meant to be broken, so that life may spring up in all its vigour and beauty, bringing its offerings to the world in open light.

In this task of breaking the barrier and facing the world Japan has come out the first in the East. She has infused hope in the heart of all Asia. This hope provides the hidden fire which is needed for all works of creation. Asia now feels that she must prove her life by producing living work; she must not lie passively dormant, or feebly imitate the West, in the infatuation of fear and flattery. For this we offer our thanks to this Land of the Rising Sun and solemnly ask her to remember that she has the mission of the East to fulfil. She must infuse the sap of a fuller humanity into the heart of modern civilization. She must never allow it to get choked with noxious undergrowth, but lead it up towards light and freedom, towards the pure air and broad space where it can receive, in the dawn of its day and the darkness of its night, heaven's inspiration. Let the greatness of her ideals become visible to all men like her snow-crowned Fuji rising from the heart of the country into the region of the infinite, supremely distinct from its surroundings, beautiful like a maiden in its magnificent sweep of curve, yet firm and strong and serenely majestic.

Ⅱ

I have travelled in many countries and have met with men of all classes, but never in my travels did I feel the presence of the human so distinctly as in this land. In other great countries signs of man's power loomed large, and I saw vast organizations which showed efficiency in all their features. There, display and extravagance, in dress, in furniture, in costly entertainments, are startling. They seem to push you back into a corner, like a poor intruder at a feast; they are apt to make you envious, or take your breath away with amazement. There, you do not feel man as supreme; you are hurled against a stupendousness of things that alienate. But in Japan it is not the display of power or wealth that is the predominating element. You see everywhere emblems of love and admiration, and not mostly of ambition and greed. You see a people whose heart has come out and scattered itself in profusion in its commonest utensils of everyday life, in its social institutions, in its manners, which are carefully perfect, and in its dealings with things which are not only deft but graceful in every movement.

What has impressed me most in this country is the conviction that you have realized nature's secrets, not by methods of analytical knowledge, but by sympathy. You have known her language of lines, and music of colours, the symmetry in her irregularities, and the cadence in her freedom of movements; you have seen how she leads her immense crowds of things yet avoids all frictions, how the very conflicts in her creations break out in dance and music, how her exuberance has the aspect of the fulness of self-abandonment, and not a mere dissipation of display. You have discovered that nature reserves her power in forms of beauty; and it is this beauty which, like a mother, nourishes all the giant forces at her breast, keeping them in active vigour, yet in repose. You have known that energies of nature save themselves from wearing out by the rhythm of a perfect grace, and that she, with the tenderness of her curved lines, takes away fatigue from the world's muscles. I have felt that you have been able to assimilate these secrets into your life, and the truth which lies in the beauty of all things has passed into your souls. A mere knowledge of things can be had in a short enough time, but their spirit can only be acquired by centuries of training and self-control. Dominating nature from outside is a much simpler thing than making her your own in love's delight, which is a work of true genius. Your race has shown that genius, not by acquirement but by creation, not by display of things but by manifestation of its own inner being. This creative power there is in all nations, and it is ever active in getting hold of men's natures and giving them a form according to its ideals. But here, in Japan, it seems to have achieved its success, and deeply sunk into the minds of all men, and permeated their muscles and nerves. Your instincts have become true, your senses keen, and your hands have acquired natural skill. The genius of Europe has given her people the power of organization, which has specially made itself manifest in politics and commerce and in coordinating scientific knowledge. The genius of Japan has given you the vision of beauty in nature and the power of realizing it in your life.

All particular civilization is the interpretation of particular human experience. Europe seems to have felt emphatically the conflict of things in the universe, which can only be brought under control by conquest. Therefore she is ever ready for fight, and the best portion of her attention is occupied in organizing forces. But Japan has felt, in her world, the touch of some presence, which has evoked in her soul a feeling of reverent adoration. She does not boast of her mastery of nature, but to her she brings, with infinite care and joy, her offerings of love. Her relationship with the world is the deeper relationship of heart. This spiritual bond of love she has established with the hills of her country, with the sea and the streams, with the forests in all their flowery moods and varied physiognomy of branches; she has taken into her heart all the rustling whispers and sighing of the woodlands and sobbing of the waves; the sun and the moon she has studied in all the modulations of their lights and shades, and she is glad to close her shops to greet the seasons in her orchards and gardens and cornfields. This opening of the heart to the soul of the world is not confined to a section of your privileged classes; it is not the forced product of exotic culture, but it belongs to all your men and women of all conditions. This experience of your soul, in meeting a personality in the heart of the world, has been embodied in your civilization. It is a civilization of human relationship. Your duty towards your state has naturally assumed the character of filial duty, your nation becoming one family with your Emperor as its head. Your national unity has not been evolved from the comradeship of arms for defensive and offensive purpose, or from partnership in raiding adventures, dividing among each member the danger and spoils of robbery. It is not an outcome of the necessity of organization for some ulterior purpose, but it is an extension of the family and obligations of the heart in a wide field of space and time. The ideal of maitri is at the bottom of your culture — maitri with men and maitri with Nature. And the true expression of this love is in the language of beauty, which is so abundantly universal in this land. This is the reason why a stranger like myself, instead of feeling envy or humiliation before these manifestations of beauty, these creations of love, feels a readiness to participate in the joy and glory of such revealment of the human heart.

And this had made me all the more apprehensive of the change which threatens Japanese civilization, as something like a menace to one's own person. For the huge heterogeneity of the modern age, whose only common bond is usefulness, is nowhere so pitifully exposed against the dignity and hidden power of reticent beauty as in Japan.

But the danger lies in this, that organized ugliness storms the mind and carries the day by its mass, by its aggressive persistence, but its power of mockery is directed against the deeper sentiments of the heart. Its harsh obtrusiveness makes it forcibly visible to us, overcoming our senses — and we bring sacrifices to its altar, as does a savage to the fetish which appears powerful because of its hideousness. Therefore its rivalry with things that are modest and profound and have the subtle delicacy of life is to be dreaded.

I am quite sure that there are men in your country who are not in sympathy with your inherited ideals, whose object is to gain and not to grow. They are loud in their boast that they have modernized Japan. While I agree with them so far as to say that the spirit of the race should harmonize with the spirit of the time, I must warn them that modernizing is a mere affectation of modernism, just as an affectation of poesy is poetizing. It is nothing but mimicry, only affectation is louder than the original, and it is too literal. One must bear in mind that those who have the true modern spirit need not modernize, just as those who are truly brave are not braggarts. Modernism is not in the dress of the Europeans, or in the hideous structures where their children are interned when they take their lessons, or in the square houses with flat, straight wall-surfaces, pierced with parallel lines of windows, where these people are caged in their lifetime; certainly modernism is not in their ladies' bonnets, carrying on them loads of incongruities. These are not modern, but merely European. True modernism is freedom of mind, not slavery of taste. It is independence of thought and action, not tutelage under European schoolmasters. It is science, but not its wrong application in life — a mere imitation of our science teachers who reduce it into a superstition, absurdly invoking its aid for all impossible purposes.

Life based upon mere science is attractive to some men, because it has all the characteristics of sport; it feigns seriousness, but is not profound. When you go a-hunting, the less pity you have the better; for your one object is to chase the game and kill it, to feel that you are the greater animal, that your method of destruction is thorough and scientific. And the life of science is that superficial life. It pursues success with skill and thoroughness, and takes no account of the higher nature of man. But those whose minds are crude enough to plan their lives upon the supposition that man is merely a hunter and his paradise the paradise of sportsmen will be rudely awakened in the midst of their trophies of skeletons and skulls.

I do not for a moment suggest that Japan should be unmindful of acquiring modern weapons of self-protection. But this should never be allowed to go beyond her instinct of self-preservation. She must know that the real power is not in the weapons themselves, but in the man who wields those weapons; and when he, in his eagerness for power, multiplies his weapons at the cost of his own soul, then it is he who is in even greater danger than his enemies.

Things that are living are so easily hurt; therefore they require protection. In nature, life protects itself within its coverings, which are built with life's own material. Therefore they are in harmony with life's growth, or else when the time comes they easily give way and are forgotten. The living man has his true protection in his spiritual ideals which have their vital connection with his life, and grow with his growth. But, unfortunately, all his armour is not living — some of it is made of steel, inert and mechanical. Therefore, while making use of it, man has to be careful to protect himself from its tyranny. If he is weak enough to grow smaller to fit himself to his covering, then it becomes a process of gradual suicide by shrinkage of the soul. And Japan must have a firm faith in the moral law of existence to be able to assert to herself that the western nations are following that path of suicide, where they are smothering their humanity under the immense weight of organizations in order to keep themselves in power and hold others in subjection.

What is dangerous for Japan is not the imitation of the outer features of the West, but the acceptance of the motive force of western nationalism as her own. Her social ideals are already showing signs of defeat at the hands of politics. I can see her motto, taken from science, 'Survival of the fittest', writ large at the entrance of her present-day history — the motto whose meaning is, 'Help yourself, and never heed what it costs to others', the motto of the blind man who only believes in what he can touch, because he cannot see. But those who can see know that men are so closely knit that when you strike others the blow comes back to yourself. The moral law, which is the greatest discovery of man, is the discovery of this wonderful truth, that man becomes all the truer the more he realizes himself in others. This truth has not only a subjective value, but is manifested in every department of our life. And nations who sedulously cultivate moral blindness as the cult of patriotism will end their existence in a sudden and violent death. In past ages we had foreign invasions, but they never touched the soul of the people deeply. They were merely the outcome of individual ambitions. The people themselves, being free from the responsibilities of the baser and more heinous side of those adventures, had all the advantage of the heroic and the human disciplines derived from them. This developed their unflinching loyalty, their singleminded devotion to the obligations of honour, their power of complete self-surrender and fearless acceptance of death and danger. Therefore the ideals, whose seats were in the hearts of the people, would not undergo any serious change owing to the policies adopted by the kings or generals. But now, where the spirit of western nationalism prevails, the whole people is being taught from boyhood to foster hatreds and ambitions by all kinds of means — by the manufacture of half-truths and untruths in history, by persistent misrepresentation of other races and the culture of unfavourable sentiments towards them, by setting up memorials of events, very often false, which for the sake of humanity should be speedily forgotten, thus continually brewing evil menace towards neighbours and nations other than its own. This is poisoning the very fountainhead of humanity. It is discrediting the ideals which were born of the lives of men who were our greatest and best. It is holding up gigantic selfishness as the one universal religion for all nations of the world. We can take anything else from the hands of science, but not this elixir of moral death. Never think for a moment that the hurts you inflict upon other races will not infect you, or that the enmities you sow around your homes will be a wall of protection to you for all time to come. To imbue the minds of the whole people with an abnormal vanity of its own superiority, to teach it to take pride in its moral callousness and ill-begotten wealth, to perpetuate the humiliation of defeated nations by exhibiting trophies won from war, and using these in schools in order to breed in children's minds contempt for others, is imitating the West where she has a festering sore, whose swelling is a swelling of disease eating into its vitality.

Our food crops, which are necessary for our sustenance, are products of centuries of selection and care. But the vegetation, which we have not to transform into our lives, does not require the patient thoughts of generations. It is not easy to get rid of weeds; but it is easy, by process of neglect, to ruin your food crops and let them revert to their primitive state of wildness. Likewise the culture, which has so kindly adapted itself to your soil — so intimate with life, so human — not only needed tilling and weeding in past ages, but still needs anxious work and watching. What is merely modern — as science and methods of organization — can be transplanted; but what is vitally human has fibres so delicate, and roots so numerous and far-reaching, that it dies when moved from the soil. Therefore I am afraid of the rude pressure of the political ideals of the West upon your own. In political civilization, the state is an abstraction and the relationship of men utilitarian. Because it has no root in sentiments, it is so dangerously easy to handle. Half a century has been enough for you to master this machine; and there are men among you whose fondness for it exceeds their love for the living ideals, which were born with the birth of your nation and nursed in your centuries. It is like a child who, in the excitement of his play, imagines he likes his play-things better than his mother.

Where man is at his greatest, he is unconscious. Your civilization, whose mainspring is the bond of human relationship, has been nourished in the depth of a healthy life beyond reach of prying self-analysis. But a mere political relationship is all-conscious; it is an eruptive inflammation of aggressiveness. It has forcibly burst upon your notice. And the time has come when you have to be roused into full consciousness of the truth by which you live, so that you may not be taken unawares. The past has been God's gift to you; about the present, you must make your own choice.

So the questions you have to put to yourselves are these: 'Have we read the world wrong, and based our relation to it upon an ignorance of human nature? Is the instinct of the West right, where she builds her national welfare behind the barricade of a universal distrust of humanity?'

You must have detected a strong accent of fear whenever the West has discussed the possibility of the rise of an eastern race. The reason of it is this, that the power by whose help she thrives is an evil power; so long as it is held on her own side she can be safe, while the rest of the world trembles. The vital ambition of the present civilization of Europe is to have the exclusive possession of the devil. All her armaments and diplomacy are directed upon this one object. But these costly rituals for invocation of the evil spirit lead through a path of prosperity to the brink of cataclysm. The furies of terror, which the West has let loose upon God's world, come back to threaten herself and goad her into preparations of more and more frightfulness; this gives her no rest, and makes her forget all else but the perils that she causes to others and incurs herself. To the worship of this devil of politics she sacrifices other countries as victims. She feeds upon their dead flesh and grows fat upon it, so long as the carcasses remain fresh — but they are sure to rot at last, and the dead will take their revenge by spreading pollution far and wide and poisoning the vitality of the feeder. Japan had all her wealth of humanity, her harmony of heroism and beauty, her depth of self-control and richness of self-expression; yet the western nations felt no respect for her till she proved that the bloodhounds of Satan are not only bred in the kennels of Europe but can also be domesticated in Japan and fed with man's miseries. They admit Japan's equality with themselves only when they know that Japan also possesses the key to open the floodgate of hell-fire upon the fair earth whenever she chooses, and can dance in their own measure the devil dance of pillage, murder and ravishment of innocent women, while the world goes to ruin. We know that, in the early state of man's moral immaturity, he only feels reverence for the god whose malevolence he dreads. But is this the ideal of man which we can look up to with pride: after centuries of civilization nations fearing each other like the prowling wild beasts of the night-time; shutting their doors of hospitality; combining only for purpose of aggression or defence; hiding in their holes their trade secrets, state secrets, secrets of their armaments; making peace-offerings to each other's barking dogs with the meat which does not belong to them; holding down fallen races which struggle to stand upon their feet; with their right hands dispensing religion to weaker peoples, while robbing them with their left — is there anything in this to make us envious? Are we to bend our knees to the spirit of this nationalism, which is sowing broadcast over all the world seeds of fear, greed, suspicion, unashamed lies of its diplomacy, and unctuous lies of its profession of peace and goodwill and universal brotherhood of Man? Can our minds be free from doubt when we rush to the western market to buy this foreign product in exchange for our own inheritance? I am aware how difficult it is to know one's self; and the man who is intoxicated furiously denies his drunkenness; yet the West herself is anxiously thinking of her problems and trying experiments. But she is like a glutton, who has not the heart to give up his intemperance in eating, and fondly clings to the hope he can cure his nightmares of indigestion by medicine. Europe is not ready to give up her political inhumanity, with all the baser passions of man attendant upon it; she believes only in modification of systems, and not in change of heart.

We are willing to buy their machine-made systems, not with our hearts, but with our brains. We shall try them and build sheds for them, but not enshrine them in our homes or temples. There are races who worship the animals they kill; we can buy meat from them when we are hungry, but not the worship which goes with the killing. We must not vitiate our children's minds with the superstition that business is business, war is war, politics is politics. We must know that man's business has to be more than mere business, and so should be his war and politics. You had your own industry in Japan; how scrupulously honest and true it was, you can see by its products — by their grace and strength, their conscientiousness in details, where they can hardly be observed. But the tidal wave of falsehood has swept over your land from that part of the world where business is business, and honesty is followed merely as a best policy. Have you never felt shame when you see the trade advertisements, not only plastering the whole town with lies and exaggerations, but invading the green fields, where the peasants do their honest labour, and the hilltops, which greet the first pure light of the morning? It is so easy to dull our sense of honour and delicacy of mind with constant abrasion, while falsehoods stalk abroad with proud steps in the name of trade, politics and patriotism, that any protest against their perpetual intrusion into our lives is considered to be sentimentalism, unworthy of true manliness.

And it has come to pass that the children of those who would keep their word at the point of death, who would disdain to cheat men for vulgar profit, who even in their fight would much rather court defeat than be dishonourable, have become energetic in dealing with falsehoods and do not feel humiliated by gaining advantage from them. And this has been effected by the charm of the word 'modern'. But if undiluted utility be modern, beauty is of all ages; if mean selfishness be modern, the human ideals are no new inventions. And we must know for certain that however modern may be the proficiency which cripples man for the sake of methods and machines, it will never live to be old.

But while trying to free our minds from the arrogant claims of Europe and to help ourselves out of the quicksands of our infatuation, we may go to the other extreme and bind ourselves with a wholesale suspicion of the West. The reaction of disillusionment is just as unreal as the first shock of illusion. We must try to come to that normal state of mind by which we can clearly discern our own danger and avoid it without being unjust towards the source of that danger. There is always the natural temptation in us of wishing to pay back Europe in her own coin, and return contempt for contempt and evil for evil. But that again would be to imitate Europe in one of her worst features, which comes out in her behaviour to people whom she describes as yellow or red, brown or black. And this is a point on which we in the East have to acknowledge our guilt and own that our sin has been as great, if not greater, when we insulted humanity by treating with utter disdain and cruelty men who belonged to a particular creed, colour or caste. It is really because we are afraid of our own weakness, which allows itself to be overcome by the sight of power, that we try to substitute for it another weakness which makes itself blind to the glories of the West. When we truly know that Europe which is great and good, we can effectively save ourselves from the Europe which is mean and grasping. It is easy to be unfair in one's judgement when one is faced with human miseries — and pessimism is the result of building theories while the mind is suffering. To despair of humanity is only possible if we lose faith in truth which brings to it strength, when its defeat is greatest, and calls out new life from the depth of its destruction. We must admit that there is a living soul in the West which is struggling unobserved against the hugeness of the organizations under which men, women and children are being crushed, and whose mechanical necessities are ignoring laws that are spiritual and human — the soul whose sensibilities refuse to be dulled completely by dangerous habits of heedlessness in dealings with races for whom it lacks natural sympathy. The West could never have risen to the eminence she has reached if her strength were merely the strength of the brute or of the machine. The divine in her heart is suffering from the injuries inflicted by her hands upon the world — and from this pain of her higher nature flows the secret balm which will bring healing to these injuries. Time after time she has fought against herself and has undone the chains which with her own hands she fastened round helpless limbs; and though she forced poison down the throat of a great nation at the point of the sword for gain of money, she herself woke up to withdraw from it, to wash her hands clean again. This shows hidden springs of humanity in spots which look dead and barren. It proves that the deeper truth in her nature, which can survive such a career of cruel cowardliness, is not greed, but reverence for unselfish ideals. It would be altogether unjust, both to us and to Europe, to say that she has fascinated the modern eastern mind by the mere exhibition of her power. Through the smoke of cannons and dust of markets the light of her moral nature has shone bright, and she has brought to us the ideal of ethical freedom, whose foundation lies deeper than social conventions and whose province of activity is worldwide.

The East has instinctively felt, even through her aversion, that she has a great deal to learn from Europe, not merely about the materials of power, but about its inner source, which is of the mind and of the moral nature of man. Europe has been teaching us the higher obligations of public good above those of the family and the clan, and the sacredness of law, which makes society independent of individual caprice, secures for it continuity of progress, and guarantees justice to all men of all positions in life. Above all things Europe has held high before our minds the banner of liberty, through centuries of martyrdom and achievement — liberty of conscience, liberty of thought and action, liberty in the ideals of art and literature. And because Europe has won our deep respect, she has become so dangerous for us where she is turbulently weak and false — dangerous like poison when it is served along with our best food. There is one safety for us upon which we hope we may count, and that is that we can claim Europe herself as our ally in our resistance to her temptations and to her violent encroachments; for she has ever carried her own standard of perfection, by which we can measure her falls and gauge her degrees of failure, by which we can call her before her own tribunal and put her to shame — the shame which is the sign of the true pride of nobleness.

But our fear is that the poison may be more powerful than the food, and what is strength in her today may not be a sign of health, but the contrary; for it may be temporarily caused by the upsetting of the balance of life. Our fear is that evil has a fateful fascination when it assumes dimensions which are colossal — and though at last it is sure to lose its centre of gravity by its abnormal disproportion, the mischief which it creates before its fall may be beyond reparation.

Therefore I ask you to have the strength of faith and clarity of mind to know for certain that the lumbering structure of modern progress, riveted by the iron bolts of efficiency, which runs upon the wheels of ambition, cannot hold together for long. Collisions are certain to occur, for it has to travel upon organized lines; it is too heavy to choose its own course freely, and once it is off the rails its endless train of vehicles is dislocated. A day will come when it will fall in a heap of ruin and cause serious obstruction to the traffic of the world. Do we not see signs of this even now? Does not the voice come to us through the din of war, the shrieks of hatred, the wailings of despair, through the churning of the unspeakable filth which has been accumulating for ages in the bottom of this nationalism — the voice which cries to our soul that the tower of national selfishness, which goes by the name of patriotism, which has raised its banner of treason against heaven, must totter and fall with a crash, weighed down by its own bulk, its flag kissing the dust, its light extinguished? My brothers, when the red light of conflagration sends up its crackle of laughter to the stars, keep your faith upon those stars and not upon the fire of destruction. For when the conflagration consumes itself and dies down, leaving its memorial in ashes, the eternal light will again shine in the East — the East which has been the birthplace of the morning sun of man's history. And who knows if that day has not already dawned, and the sun not risen, in the easternmost horizon of Asia? And I offer, as did my ancestor rishis, my salutation to that sunrise of the East, which is destined once again to illumine the whole world.

I know my voice is too feeble to raise itself above the uproar of this bustling time, and it is easy for any street urchin to fling against me the epithet of 'unpractical'. It will stick to my coat-tail, never to be washed away, effectively excluding me from the consideration of all respectable persons. I know what a risk one runs from the vigorously athletic crowds in being styled an idealist in these days, when thrones have lost their dignity and prophets have become an anachronism, when the sound that drowns all voices is the noise of the market-place. Yet when, one day, standing on the outskirts of Yokohama town bristling with its display of modern miscellanies, I watched the sunset in your southern sea, and saw its peace and majesty among your pine-clad hills — with the great Fujiyama growing faint against the golden horizon, like a god overcome with his own radiance — the music of eternity welled up through the evening silence, and I felt that the sky and the earth and the lyrics of the dawn and the dayfall are with the poets and idealists, and not with the marketmen robustly contemptuous of all sentiment — that, after all the forgetfulness of his divinity, man will remember again that heaven is always in touch with his world, which can never be abandoned for good to the hounding wolves of the modern era, scenting human blood and howling to the skies.

Nationalism in the West

Man's history is being shaped according to the difficulties it encounters. These have offered us problems and claimed their solutions from us, the penalty of non-fulfilment being death or degradation.

These difficulties have been different in different peoples of the earth, and in the manner of our overcoming them lies our distinction.

The Scythians of the earlier period of Asiatic history had to struggle with the scarcity of their natural resources. The easiest solution that they could think of was to organize their whole population, men, women, and children, into bands of robbers. And they were irresistible to those who were chiefly engaged in the constructive work of social co-operation.

But fortunately for man the easiest path is not his truest path. If his nature were not as complex as it is, if it were as simple as that of a pack of hungry wolves, then, by this time, those hordes of marauders would have overrun the whole earth. But man, when confronted with difficulties, has to acknowledge that he is man, that he has his responsibilities to the higher faculties of his nature, by ignoring which he may achieve success that is immediate, perhaps, but that will become a death-trap to him. For what are obstacles to the lower creatures are opportunities to the higher life of man.

To India has been given her problem from the beginning of history — it is the race problem. Races ethnologically different have in this country come into close contact. This fact has been and still continues to be the most important one in our history. It is our mission to face it and prove our humanity by dealing with it in the fullest truth. Until we fulfil our mission all other benefits will be denied us.

There are other peoples in the world who have to overcome obstacles in their physical surroundings, or the menace of their powerful neighbours. They have organized their power till they are not only reasonably free from the tyranny of Nature and human neighbours, but have a surplus of it left in their hands to employ against others. But in India, our difficulties being internal, our history has been the history of continual social adjustment and not that of organized power for defence and aggression.

Neither the colourless vagueness of cosmopolitanism, nor the fierce self-idolatry of nation-worship, is the goal of human history. And India has been trying to accomplish her task through social regulation of differences on the one hand, and the spiritual recognition of unity on the other. She has made grave errors in setting up the boundary walls too rigidly between races, in perpetuating in her classifications the results of inferiority; often she has crippled her children's minds and narrowed their lives in order to fit them into her social forms, but for centuries new experiments have been made and adjustments carried out.

Her mission has been like that of a hostess who has to provide proper accommodation for numerous guests, whose habits and requirements are different from one another. This gives rise to infinite complexities whose solution depends not merely upon tactfulness but upon sympathy and true realization of the unity of man. Towards this realization have worked, from the early time of the Upanishads[〔1〕] up to the present moment, a series of great spiritual teachers, whose one object has been to set at naught all differences of man by the overflow of our consciousness of God. In fact, our history has not been of the rise and fall of kingdoms, of fights for political supremacy. In our country records of these days have been despised and forgotten, for they in no way represent the true history of our people. Our history is that of our social life and attainment of spiritual ideals.

But we feel that our task is not yet done. The world-flood has swept over our country, new elements have been introduced, and wider adjustments are waiting to be made.

We feel this all the more because the teaching and example of the West have entirely run counter to what we think was given to India to accomplish. In the West the national machinery of commerce and politics turns out neatly compressed bales of humanity which have their use and high market value; but they are bound in iron hoops, labelled and separated off with scientific care and precision. Obviously God made man to be human, but this modern product has such marvellous square-cut finish, savouring of gigantic manufacture, that the Creator will find it difficult to recognize it as a thing of spirit and a creature made in His own divine image.

But I am anticipating. What I was about to say is this. Take it in whatever spirit you like, here is India, of about fifty centuries at least, who tried to live peacefully and think deeply, the India devoid of all politics, the India of no nations, whose one ambition has been to know this world as of soul, to live here every moment of her life in the meek spirit of adoration, in the glad consciousness of an eternal and personal relationship with it. It was upon this remote portion of humanity, childlike in its manner, with the wisdom of the old, that the Nation of the West burst in.

Through all the fights and intrigues and deceptions of her earlier history India had remained aloof. Because her homes, her fields, her temples of worship, her schools, where her teachers and students lived together in the atmosphere of simplicity and devotion and learning, her village self-government with its simple laws and peaceful administration — all these truly belonged to her. But her thrones were not her concern. They passed over her head like clouds, now tinged with purple gorgeousness, now black with the threat of thunder. Often they brought devastations in their wake, but they were like catastrophes of nature whose traces are soon forgotten.

But this time it was different. It was not a mere drift over her surface of life — drift of cavalry and foot soldiers, richly caparisoned elephants, white tents and canopies, strings of patient camels bearing the loads of royalty, bands of kettledrums and flutes, marble domes of mosques, palaces and tombs, like the bubbles of the foaming wine of extravagance; stories of treachery and loyal devotion, of changes of fortune, of dramatic surprises of fate. This time it was the Nation of the West driving its tentacles of machinery deep down into the soil.

Therefore I say to you, it is we who are called as witnesses to give evidence as to what our Nation has been to humanity. We had known the hordes of Mughals and Pathans who invaded India, but we had known them as human races, with their own religions and customs, likes and dislikes — we had never known them as a nation. We loved and hated them as the occasions arose; we fought for them and against them, talked with them in a language which was theirs as well as our own, and guided the destiny of the Empire in which we had our active share. But this time we had to deal, not with kings, not with human races, but with a nation — we, who are no nation ourselves.

Now let us, from our own experience, answer the question: what is this Nation?

A nation, in the sense of the political and economic union of a people, is that aspect which a whole population assumes when organized for a mechanical purpose. Society as such has no ulterior purpose. It is an end in itself. It is a spontaneous self-expression of man as a social being. It is a natural regulation of human relationships, so that men can develop ideals of life in co-operation with one another. It has also a political side, but this is only for a special purpose. It is for self-preservation. It is merely the side of power, not of human ideals. And in the early days it had its separate place in society, restricted to the professionals. But when with the help of science and the perfecting of organization this power begins to grow and brings in harvests of wealth, then it crosses its boundaries with amazing rapidity. For then it goads all its neighbouring societies with greed of material prosperity, and consequent mutual jealousy, and by the fear of each other's growth into powerfulness. The time comes when it can stop no longer, for the competition grows keener, organization grows vaster, and selfishness attains supremacy. Trading upon the greed and fear of man, it occupies more and more space in society, and at last becomes its ruling force.

It is just possible that you have lost through habit the consciousness that the living bonds of society are breaking up, and giving place to merely mechanical organization. But one sees signs of it everywhere. It is owing to this that war has been declared between man and woman, because the natural thread is snapping which holds them together in harmony; because man is driven to professionalism, producing wealth for himself and others, continually turning the wheel of power for his own sake or for the sake of the universal officialdom, leaving woman alone to wither and to die or to fight her own battle unaided. And thus there, where co-operation is natural, has intruded competition. The very psychology of men and women about their mutual relation is changing and becoming the psychology of the primitive fighting elements, rather than of humanity seeking its completeness through the union based upon mutual self-surrender. For the elements which have lost their living bond of reality have lost the meaning of their existence. Like gaseous particles forced into a too narrow space, they come in continual conflict with each other till they burst the very arrangement which holds them in bondage.

Then look at those who call themselves anarchists, who resent the imposition of power, in any form whatever, upon the individual. The only reason for this is that power has become too abstract — it is a scientific product made in the political laboratory of the Nation, through the dissolution of personal humanity.

And what is the meaning of these strikes in the economic world, which like the prickly shrubs in a barren soil shoot up with renewed vigour each time they are cut down? What but that the wealth-producing mechanism is incessantly growing into vast stature, out of proportion to all other needs of society, and the full reality of man is more and more crushed under its weight? This state of things inevitably gives rise to eternal feuds among the elements freed from the wholeness and wholesomeness of human ideals, and interminable economic war is waged between capital and labour. For greed of wealth and power can never have a limit, and compromise of self-interest can never attain the final spirit of reconciliation. They must go on breeding jealousy and suspicion to the end — the end which only comes through some sudden catastrophe or a spiritual rebirth.

When this organization of politics and commerce, whose other name is the Nation, becomes all-powerful at the cost of the harmony of the higher social life, then it is an evil day for humanity. When a father becomes a gambler and his obligations to his family take the secondary place in his mind, then he is no longer a man, but an automaton led by the power of greed. Then he can do things which, in his normal state of mind, he would be ashamed to do. It is the same thing with society. When it allows itself to be turned into a perfect organization of power, then there are few crimes it is unable to perpetrate, because success is the object and justification of a machine, while goodness only is the end and purpose of man. When this engine of organization begins to attain a vast size, and those who are mechanics are made into parts of the machine, then the personal man is eliminated to a phantom, everything becomes a revolution of policy carried out by the human parts of the machines, with no twinge of pity or moral responsibility. It may happen that even through this apparatus the moral nature of man tries to assert itself, but the whole series of ropes and pulleys creak and cry, the forces of the human heart become entangled among the forces of the human automaton, and only with difficulty can the moral purpose transmit itself into some tortured shape of result.

This abstract being, the Nation, is ruling India. We have seen in our country some brand of tinned food advertised as entirely made and packed without being touched by hand. This description applies to the governing of India, which is as little touched by the human hand as possible. The governors need not know our language, need not come into personal touch with us except as officials; they can aid or hinder our aspirations from a disdainful distance, they can lead us on a certain path of policy and then pull us back again with the manipulation of office red tape. The newspapers of England, in whose columns London street accidents are recorded with some decency of pathos, need take but the scantiest notice of calamities which happen in India over areas of land sometimes larger than the British Isles.

But we, who are governed, are not a mere abstraction. We, on our side, are individuals with living sensibilities. What comes to us in the shape of a mere bloodless policy may pierce into the very core of our life, may threaten the whole future of our people with a perpetual helplessness of emasculation, and yet may never touch the chord of humanity on the other side, or touch it in the most inadequately feeble manner. Such wholesale and universal acts of fearful responsibility man can never perform, with such a degree of systematic unawareness, where he is an individual human being. These only become possible where the man is represented by an octopus of abstractions, sending out its wriggling arms in all directions of space, and fixing its innumerable suckers even into the far-away future. In this reign of the nation, the governed are pursued by suspicions; and these are the suspicions of a tremendous mass of organized brain and muscle. Punishments are meted out which leave a trail of miseries across a large bleeding tract of the human heart, but these punishments are dealt by a mere abstract force in which a whole population of a distant country has lost its human personality.

I have not come here, however, to discuss the question as it affects my own country, but as it affects the future of all humanity. It is not a question of the British government, but of government by the Nation — the Nation which is the organized self-interest of a whole people, where it is least human and least spiritual. Our only intimate experience of the Nation is with the British Nation, and as far as the government by the Nation goes there are reasons to believe that it is one of the best. Then, again, we have to consider that the West is necessary to the East. We are complementary to each other because of our different outlooks upon life which have given us different aspects of truth. Therefore if it be true that the spirit of the West has come upon our fields in the guise of a storm it is nevertheless scattering living seeds that are immortal. And when in India we become able to assimilate in our life what is permanent in western civilization we shall be in a position to bring about a reconciliation of these two great worlds. Then will come to an end the one-sided dominance which is galling. What is more, we have to recognize that the history of India does not belong to one particular race but to a process of creation to which various races of the world contributed — the Dravidians and the Aryans, the ancient Greeks and the Persians, the Mohammedans of the West and those of central Asia. Now at last has come the turn of the English to become true to this history and bring to it the tribute of their life, and we neither have the right nor the power to exclude this people from the building of the destiny of India. Therefore what I say about the Nation has more to do with the history of Man than specially with that of India.

This history has come to a stage when the moral man, the complete man, is more and more giving way, almost without knowing it, to make room for the political and the commercial man, the man of the limited purpose. This process, aided by the wonderful progress in science, is assuming gigantic proportion and power, causing the upset of man's moral balance, obscuring his human side under the shadow of soulless organization. We have felt its iron grip at the root of our life, and for the sake of humanity we must stand up and give warning to all, that this nationalism is a cruel epidemic of evil that is sweeping over the human world of the present age and eating into its moral vitality.

I have a deep love and a great respect for the British race as human beings. It has produced great-hearted men, thinkers of great thoughts, doers of great deeds. It has given rise to a great literature. I know that these people love justice and freedom, and hate lies. They are clean in their minds, frank in their manners, true in their friendships; in their behaviour they are honest and reliable. The personal experience which I have had of their literary men has roused my admiration not merely for their power of thought or expression but for their chivalrous humanity. We have felt the greatness of this people as we feel the sun; but as for the Nation, it is for us a thick mist of a stilling nature covering the sun itself.

This government by the Nation is neither British nor anything else; it is an applied science and therefore more or less similar in its principles wherever it is used. It is like a hydraulic press, whose pressure is impersonal, and on that account completely effective. The amount of its power may vary in different engines. Some may even be driven by hand, thus leaving a margin of comfortable looseness in their tension, but in spirit and in method their differences are small. Our government might have been Dutch, or French, or Portuguese, and its essential features would have remained much the same as they are now. Only perhaps, in some cases, the organization might not have been so densely perfect, and therefore some shreds of the human might still have been clinging to the wreck, allowing us to deal with something which resembles our own throbbing heart.

Before the Nation came to rule over us we had other governments which were foreign, and these, like all governments, had some element of the machine in them. But the difference between them and the government by the Nation is like the difference between the hand-loom and the power-loom. In the products of the hand-loom the magic of man's living fingers finds its expression, and its hum harmonizes with the music of life. But the power-loom is relentlessly lifeless and accurate and monotonous in its production.

We must admit that during the personal government of former days there have been instances of tyranny, injustice and extortion. They caused sufferings and unrest from which we are glad to be rescued. The protection of law is not only a boon, but it is a valuable lesson to us. It is teaching us the discipline which is necessary for the stability of civilization and for continuity of progress. We are realizing through it that there is a universal standard of justice to which all men, irrespective of their caste and colour, have their equal claim.

This reign of law in our present government in India has established order in this vast land inhabited by peoples different in their races and customs. It has made it possible for these peoples to come in closer touch with one another and cultivate a communion of aspiration.

But this desire for a common bond of comradeship among the different races of India has been the work of the spirit of the West, not that of the Nation of the West. Wherever in Asia the people have received the true lesson of the West it is in spite of the western Nation. Only because Japan had been able to resist the dominance of this western Nation could she acquire the benefit of western civilization in fullest measure. Though China has been poisoned at the very spring of her moral and physical life by this Nation, her struggle to receive the best lessons of the West may yet be successful if not hindered by the Nation. It was only the other day that Persia woke up from her age-long sleep at the call of the West to be instantly trampled into stillness by the Nation. The same phenomenon prevails in this country also, where the people are hospitable, but the Nation has proved itself to be otherwise, making an eastern guest feel humiliated to stand before you as a member of the humanity of his own motherland.

In India we are suffering from this conflict between the spirit of the West and the Nation of the West. The benefit of western civilization is doled out to us in a miserly measure by the Nation, which tries to regulate the degree of nutrition as near the zero-point of vitality as possible. The portion of education allotted to us is so raggedly insufficient that it ought to outrage the sense of decency of western humanity. We have seen in these countries how the people are encouraged and trained and given every facility to fit themselves for the great movements of commerce and industry spreading over the world, while in India the only assistance we get is merely to be jeered at by the Nation for lagging behind. While depriving us of our opportunities and reducing our education to the minimum required for conducting a foreign government, this Nation pacifies its conscience by calling us names, by sedulously giving currency to the arrogant cynicism that the East is east and the West is west and never the twain shall meet. If we must believe our schoolmaster in his taunt that, after nearly two centuries of his tutelage, India not only remains unfit for self-government but unable to display originality in her intellectual attainments, must we ascribe it to something in the nature of western culture and our inherent incapacity to receive it or to the judicious niggardliness of the Nation that has taken upon itself the white man's burden of civilizing the East? That Japanese people have some qualities which we lack we may admit, but that our intellect is naturally unproductive compared to theirs we cannot accept even from them whom it is dangerous for us to contradict.

The truth is that the spirit of conflict and conquest is at the origin and in the centre of western nationalism; its basis is not social co-operation. It has evolved a perfect organization of power, but not spiritual idealism. It is like the pack of predatory creatures that must have its victims. With all its heart it cannot bear to see its hunting-grounds converted into cultivated fields. In fact, these nations are fighting among themselves for the extension of their victims and their reserve forests. Therefore the western Nation acts like a dam to check the free flow of western civilization into the country of the No-Nation. Because this civilization is the civilization of power, therefore it is exclusive; it is naturally unwilling to open its sources of power to those whom it has selected for its purposes of exploitation.

But all the same, moral law is the law of humanity, and the exclusive civilization which thrives upon others who are barred from its benefit carries its own death-sentence in its moral limitations. The slavery that it gives rise to unconsciously drains its own love of freedom dry. The helplessness with which it weighs down its world of victims exerts its force of gravitation every moment upon the power that creates it. And the greater part of the world which is being denuded of its self-sustaining life by the Nation will one day become the most terrible of all its burdens, ready to drag it down into the bottom of destruction. Whenever the Power removes all checks from its path to make its career easy, it triumphantly rides into its ultimate crash of death. Its moral brake becomes slacker every day without its knowing it, and its slippery path of ease becomes its path of doom.

Of all things in western civilization, those which this western Nation has given us in a most generous measure are law and order. While the small feeding-bottle of our education is nearly dry, and sanitation sucks its own thumb in despair, the military organization, the magisterial offices, the police, the Criminal Investigation Department, the secret spy system, attain to an abnormal girth in their waists, occupying every inch of our country. This is to maintain order. But is not this order merely a negative good? Is it not for giving people's life greater opportunities for the freedom of development? Its perfection is the perfection of an egg-shell, whose true value lies in the security it affords to the chick and its nourishment and not in the convenience it offers to the person at the breakfast table. Mere administration is unproductive; it is not creative, not being a living thing. It is a steam-roller, formidable in its weight and power, having its uses, but it does not help the soil to become fertile. When after its enormous toil it comes to offer us its boon of peace we can but murmur under our breath that 'peace is good, but not more so than life, which is God's own great boon'.

On the other hand, our former governments were woefully lacking in many of the advantages of the modern government. But because those were not the governments by the Nation, their texture was loosely woven, leaving big gaps through which our own life sent its threads and imposed its designs. I am quite sure in those days we had things that were extremely distasteful to us. But we know that when we walk barefooted upon ground strewn with gravel, our feet come gradually to adjust themselves to the caprices of the inhospitable earth; while if the tiniest particle of gravel finds its lodgement inside our shoes we can never forget and forgive its intrusion. And these shoes are the government by the Nation — it is tight, it regulates our steps with a closed-up system, within which our feet have only the slightest liberty to make their own adjustments. Therefore, when you produce your statistics to compare the number of gravels which our feet had to encounter in former days with the paucity in the present regime, they hardly touch the real point. It is not a question of the number of outside obstacles but the comparative powerlessness of the individual to cope with them. This narrowness of freedom is an evil which is more radical, not because of its quantity but because of its nature. And we cannot but acknowledge this paradox: that while the spirit of the West marches under its banner of freedom, the Nation of the West forges its iron chains of organization which are the most relentless and unbreakable that have ever been manufactured in the whole history of man.

When the humanity of India was not under the government of the Organization, the elasticity of change was great enough to encourage men of power and spirit to feel that they had their destinies in their own hands. The hope of the unexpected was never absent, and a freer play of imagination, on the part of both the governor and the governed, had its effect in the making of history. We were not confronted with a future, which was a dead white wall of granite blocks eternally guarding against the expression and extension of our own powers, the hopelessness of which lies in the reason that these powers are becoming atrophied at their very roots by the scientific process of paralysis. For every single individual in the country of the No-Nation is completely in the grip of a whole nation, whose tireless vigilance, being the vigilance of a machine, has not the human power to overlook or to discriminate. At the least pressing of its button the monster organization becomes all eyes, whose ugly stare of inquisitiveness cannot be avoided by a single person amongst the immense multitude of the ruled. At the least turn of its screw, by the fraction of an inch, the grip is tightened to the point of suffocation around every man, woman and child of a vast population, for whom no escape is imaginable in their own country or even in any country outside their own.

It is the continual and stupendous dead pressure of the inhuman upon the living human under which the modern world is groaning. Not merely the subject races, but you who live under the delusion that you are free, are every day sacrificing your freedom and humanity to this fetish of nationalism, living in the dense poisonous atmosphere of world-wide suspicion and greed and panic.

I have seen in Japan the voluntary submission of the whole people to the trimming of their minds and clipping of their freedom by their government, which through various educational agencies regulates their thoughts, manufactures their feelings, becomes suspiciously watchful when they show signs of inclining towards the spiritual, leading them through a narrow path not towards what is true but what is necessary for the complete welding of them into one uniform mass according to its own recipe. The people accept this all-pervading mental slavery with cheerfulness and pride because of their nervous desire to turn themselves into a machine of power, called the Nation, and emulate other machines in their collective worldliness.

When questioned as to the wisdom of its course, the newly converted fanatic of nationalism answers that 'so long as nations are rampant in this world we have not the option freely to develop our higher humanity. We must utilize every faculty that we possess to resist the evil by assuming it ourselves in the fullest degree. For the only brotherhood possible in the modern world is the brotherhood of hooliganism.' The recognition of the fraternal bond of love between Japan and Russia, which has lately been celebrated with an immense display of rejoicing in Japan, was not owing to any sudden recrudescence of the spirit of Christianity or of Buddhism, but it was a bond established according to the modern faith in a surer relationship of the mutual menace of bloodshedding. Yes, one cannot but acknowledge that these facts are the facts of the world of the Nation, and the only moral of it is that all the peoples of the earth should strain their physical, moral and intellectual resources to the utmost to defeat one another in the wrestling match of powerfulness. In ancient days Sparta paid all her attention to becoming powerful; she did become so by crippling her humanity, and died of the amputation.

But it is no consolation to us to know that the weakening of humanity from which the present age is suffering is not limited to the subject races, and that its ravages are even more radical because insidious and voluntary in peoples who are hypnotized into believing that they are free. This bartering of your higher aspirations of life for profit and power has been your own free choice, and I leave you there, at the wreckage of your soul, contemplating your protuberant prosperity. But will you never be called to answer for organizing the instincts of self-aggrandizement of whole peoples into perfection and calling it good? I ask you: what disaster has there ever been in the history of man, in its darkest period, like this terrible disaster of the Nation fixing its fangs deep into the naked flesh of the world, taking permanent precautions against its natural relaxation?

You, the people of the West, who have manufactured this abnormality, can you imagine the desolating despair of this haunted world of suffering man possessed by the ghastly abstraction of the organizing man? Can you put yourself into the position of the peoples, who seem to have been doomed to an eternal damnation of their own humanity, who not only must suffer continual curtailment of their manhood, but even raise their voices in paeans of praise for the benignity of a mechanical apparatus in its interminable parody of providence?

Have you not seen, since the commencement of the existence of the Nation, that the dread of it has been the one goblin-dread with which the whole world has been trembling? Wherever there is a dark corner, there is the suspicion of its secret malevolence; and people live in a perpetual distrust of their back where they have no eyes. Every sound of a footstep, every rustle of movement in the neighbourhood, sends a thrill of terror all around. And this terror is the parent of all that is base in man's nature. It makes one almost openly unashamed of inhumanity. Clever lies become matters of self-congratulation. Solemn pledges become a farce — laughable for their very solemnity. The Nation, with all its paraphernalia of power and prosperity, its flags and pious hymns, its blasphemous prayers in the churches, and the literary mock thunders of its patriotic bragging, cannot hide the fact that the Nation is the greatest evil for the Nation, that all its precautions are against it, and any new birth of its fellow in the world is always followed in its mind by the dread of a new peril. Its one wish is to trade on the feebleness of the rest of the world, like some insects that are bred in the paralysed flesh of victims kept just enough alive to make them toothsome and nutritious. Therefore it is ready to send its poisonous fluid into the vitals of the other living peoples who, not being nations, are harmless. For this the Nation has had and still has its richest pasture in Asia. Great China, rich with her ancient wisdom and social ethics, her discipline of industry and self-control, is like a whale awakening the lust of spoil in the heart of the Nation. She is already carrying in her quivering flesh harpoons sent by the unerring aim of the Nation, the creature of science and selfishness. Her pitiful attempt to shake off her traditions of humanity, her social ideals, and spend her last exhausted resources in drilling herself into modern efficiency, is thwarted at every step by the Nation. It is tightening its financial ropes around her, trying to drag her up on the shore and cut her into pieces, and then go and offer public thanksgiving to God for supporting the one existing evil and shattering the possibility of a new one. And for all this the Nation has been claiming the gratitude of history and all eternity for its exploitation, ordering its band of praise to be struck up from end to end of the world, declaring itself to be the salt of the earth, the flower of humanity, the blessing of God hurled with all His force upon the naked skulls of the world of No-Nations.

I know what your advice will be. You will say: form yourselves into a nation, and resist this encroachment of the Nation. But is this the true advice, that of a man to a man? Why should this be a necessity? I could well believe you if you had said: be more good, more just, more true in your relation to man; control your greed, make your life wholesome in its simplicity and let your consciousness of the divine in humanity be more perfect in its expression. But must you say that it is not the soul, but the machine, which is of the utmost value to ourselves, and that man's salvation depends upon his disciplining himself into a perfection of the dead rhythm of wheels and counterwheels, that machine must be pitted against machine, and nation against nation, in an endless bullfight of politics?

You say: these machines will come into an agreement for their mutual protection, based upon a conspiracy of fear. But will this federation of steam-boilers supply you with a soul, a soul which has her conscience and her God? What is to happen to that larger part of the world where fear will have no hand in restraining you? Whatever safety they now enjoy, those countries of No-Nation, from the unbridled licence of forge and hammer and turnscrew, results from the mutual jealousy of the powers. But when, instead of being numerous separate machines they become riveted into one organized gregariousness of gluttony, commercial and political, what remotest chance of hope will remain for those others, who have lived and suffered, have loved and worshipped, have thought deeply and worked with meekness, but whose only crime has been that they have not organized?

But, you say, 'That does not matter, the unfit must go to the wall — they shall die, and this is science.'

No, for the sake of your own salvation, I say, they shall live, and this is truth. It is extremely bold of me to say so, but I assert that man's world is a moral world, not because we blindly agree to believe it, but because it is so in truth which would be dangerous for us to ignore. And this moral nature of man cannot be divided into convenient compartments for its preservation. You cannot secure it for your home consumption with protective tariff walls, while in foreign parts making it enormously accommodating in its free trade of licence.

Has not this truth already come home to you now, when this cruel war has driven its claws into the vitals of Europe, when her hoard of wealth is bursting into smoke and her humanity is shattered into bits on her battlefields? You ask in amazement: what has she done to deserve this? The answer is that the West has been systematically petrifying her moral nature in order to lay a solid foundation for her gigantic abstractions of efficiency. She has all along been starving the life of the personal man into that of the professional.

In your medieval age in Europe, the simple and the natural man, with all his violent passions and desires, was engaged in trying to find out a reconciliation in the conflict between the flesh and the spirit. All through the turbulent career of her vigorous youth the temporal and the spiritual forces both acted strongly upon her nature, and were moulding it into completeness of moral personality. Europe owes all her greatness in humanity to that period of discipline — the discipline of the man in his human integrity.

Then came the age of intellect, of science. We all know that intellect is impersonal. Our life and our heart are one with us, but our mind can be detached from the personal man and then only can it freely move in its world of thoughts. Our intellect is an ascetic who wears no clothes, takes no food, knows no sleep, has no wishes, feels no love or hatred or pity for human limitations, who only reasons unmoved through the vicissitudes of life. It burrows to the roots of things, because it has no personal concern with the thing itself. The grammarian walks straight through all poetry and goes to the root of words without obstruction, because he is seeking not reality, but law When he finds the law, he is able to teach people how to master words. This is a power — the power which fulfils some special usefulness, some particular need of man.

Reality is the harmony which gives to the component parts of a thing the equilibrium of the whole. You break it, and have in your hands the nomadic atoms fighting against one another, therefore unmeaning. Those who covet power try to get mastery of these aboriginal fighting elements, and through some narrow channels force them into some violent service for some particular needs of man.

This satisfaction of man's needs is a great thing. It gives him freedom in the material world. It confers on him the benefit of a greater range of time and space. He can do things in a shorter time and occupies a larger space with more thoroughness of advantage. Therefore he can easily outstrip those who live in a world of a slower time and of space less fully occupied.

This progress of power attains more and more rapidity of pace. And, for the reason that it is a detached part of man, it soon outruns the complete humanity. The moral man remains behind, because it has to deal with the whole reality, not merely with the law of things, which is impersonal and therefore abstract.

Thus man, with his mental and material power far outgrowing his moral strength, is like an exaggerated giraffe whose head has suddenly shot up miles away from the rest of him, making normal communication difficult to establish. This greedy head, with its huge dental organization, has been munching all the topmost foliage of the world, but the nourishment is too late in reaching his digestive organs, and his heart is suffering from want of blood. Of this present disharmony in man's nature the West seems to have been blissfully unconscious. The enormity of its material success has diverted all its attention towards self-congratulation on its bulk. The optimism of its logic goes on basing the calculations of its good fortune upon the indefinite prolongation of its railway lines towards eternity. It is superficial enough to think that all tomorrows are merely todays, with the repeated additions of twenty-four hours. It has no fear of the chasm, which is opening wider every day, between man's ever growing storehouses and the emptiness of his hungry humanity. Logic does not know that, under the lowest bed of endless strata of wealth and comforts, earthquakes are being hatched to restore the balance of the moral world; and one day the gaping gulf of spiritual vacuity will draw into its bottom the store of things that have their eternal love for the dust.

Man in his fulness is not powerful, but perfect. Therefore, to turn him into mere power, you have to curtail his soul as much as possible. When we are fully human, we cannot fly at one another's throats; our instincts of social life, our traditions of moral ideals stand in the way. If you want me to take to butchering human beings, you must break up that wholeness of my humanity through some discipline which makes my will dead, my thoughts numb, my movements automatic, and then from the dissolution of the complex personal man will come out that abstraction, that destructive force, which has no relation to human truth, and therefore can be easily brutal or mechanical. Take away man from his natural surroundings, from the fulness of his communal life, with all its living associations of beauty and love and social obligations, and you will be able to turn him into so many fragments of a machine for the production of wealth on a gigantic scale. Turn a tree into a log and it will burn for you, but it will never bear living flowers and fruit.

This process of dehumanizing has been going on in commerce and politics. And out of the long birth-throes of mechanical energy has been born this fully developed apparatus of magnificent power and surprising appetite which has been christened in the West as the Nation. As I have hinted before, because of its quality of abstraction it has, with the greatest ease, gone far ahead of the complete moral man. And having the conscience of a ghost and the callous perfection of an automaton, it is causing disasters with which the volcanic dissipations of the youthful moon would be ashamed to be brought into comparison. As a result, the suspicion of man for man stings all the limbs of this civilization like the hairs of the nettle. Each country is casting its net of espionage into the slimy bottom of the others, fishing for their secrets, the treacherous secrets which brew in the oozy depths of diplomacy. And what is their secret service but the Nation's underground trade in kidnapping, murder and treachery and all the ugly crimes bred in the depth of rottenness? Because each Nation has its own history of thieving and lies and broken faith, therefore there can only flourish international suspicion and jealousy, and international moral shame becomes anaemic to a degree of ludicrousness. The Nation's bagpipe of righteous indignation has so changed its tune according to the variation of time and to the altered groupings of the alliances of diplomacy, that it can be enjoyed with amusement as the variety performance of the political music hall.

I am just coming from my visit to Japan, where I exhorted this young Nation to take its stand upon the higher ideals of humanity and never to follow the West in its acceptance of the organized selfishness of Nationalism as its religion, never to gloat upon the feebleness of its neighbours, never to be unscrupulous in its behaviour to the weak, where it can be gloriously mean with impunity, while turning its right cheek of brighter humanity for the kiss of admiration to those who have the power to deal it a blow. Some of the newspapers praised my utterances for their poetical qualities, while adding with a leer that it was the poetry of a defeated people. I felt they were right. Japan had been taught in a modern school the lesson how to become powerful. The schooling is done and she must enjoy the fruits of her lessons. The West in the voice of her thundering cannon had said at the door of Japan: let there be a Nation — and there was a Nation. And now that it has come into existence, why do you not feel in your heart of hearts a pure feeling of gladness and say that it is good? Why is it that I saw in an English paper an expression of bitterness at Japan's boasting of her superiority of civilization — the thing that the British, along with other nations, have been carrying on for ages without blushing? Because the idealism of selfishness must keep itself drunk with a continual dose of self-laudation. But the same vices which seem so natural and innocuous in its own life make it surprised and angry at their unpleasantness when seen in other nations. Therefore, when you see the Japanese nation, created in your own image, launched in its career of national boastfulness, you shake your head and say, it is not good. Has it not been one of the causes that raise the cry on these shores for preparedness to meet one more power of evil with a greater power of injury? Japan protests that she has her bushido, that she can never be treacherous to America to whom she owes her gratitude. But you find it difficult to believe her — for the wisdom of the Nation is not in its faith in humanity but in its complete distrust. You say to yourself that it is not with Japan of the bushido, the Japan of the moral ideals, that you have to deal — it is with the abstraction of the popular selfishness, it is with the Nation; and Nation can only trust Nation where their interests coalesce, or at least do not conflict. In fact your instinct tells you that the advent of another people into the arena of nationality makes another addition to the evil which contradicts all that is highest in Man and proves by its success that unscrupulousness is the way to prosperity — and goodness is good for the weak and God is the only remaining consolation of the defeated.

Yes, this is the logic of the Nation. And it will never heed the voice of truth and goodness. It will go on its ring-dance of moral corruption, linking steel unto steel, and machine unto machine, trampling under its tread all the sweet flowers of simple faith and the living ideals of man.

But we delude ourselves into thinking that humanity in these modern days is more to the front than ever before. The reason for this self-delusion is because man is served with the necessaries of life in greater profusion and his physical ills are being alleviated with more efficacy. But the chief part of this is done, not by moral sacrifice, but by intellectual power. In quantity it is great, but it springs from the surface and spreads over the surface. Knowledge and efficiency are powerful in their outward effect, but they are the servants of man, not the man himself. Their service is like the service in a hotel, where it is elaborate but the host is absent; it is more convenient than hospitable.

Therefore we must not forget that the scientific organizations vastly spreading in all directions are strengthening our power, but not our humanity. With the growth of power the cult of the self-worship of the Nation grows in ascendancy, and the individual willingly allows the Nation to take donkey-rides upon his back; and there happens the anomaly which must have such disastrous effects, that the individual worships with all sacrifices a god which is morally much inferior to himself. This could never have been possible if the god had been as real as the individual.

Let me give an illustration of this point. In some parts of India it has been enjoined as an act of great piety for a widow to go without food and water on a particular day every fortnight. This often leads to cruelty, unmeaning and inhuman. And yet men are not by nature cruel to such a degree. But this piety being a mere unreal abstraction completely deadens the moral sense of the individual, just as the man who would not hurt an animal unnecessarily would cause horrible suffering to a large number of innocent creatures when he drugs his feelings with the abstract idea of 'sport'! Because these ideas are creations of our intellect, because they are logical classifications, therefore they can so easily hide in their mist the personal man.

And the idea of the Nation is one of the most powerful anaesthetics that man has invented. Under the influence of its fumes the whole people can carry out its systematic programme of the most virulent self-seeking without being in the least aware of its moral perversion — in fact it can feel dangerously resentful if it is pointed out.

But can this go on indefinitely, continually producing barrenness of moral insensibility upon a large tract of our living nature? Can it escape its nemesis for ever? Has this giant power of mechanical organization no limit in this world against which it may shatter itself all the more completely because of its terrible strength and velocity? Do you believe that evil can be permanently kept in check by competition with evil, and that conference of prudence can keep the devil chained in its makeshift cage of mutual agreement?

This European war of Nations is the war of retribution. Man, the person, must protest for his very life against the heaping up of things where there should be the heart, and systems and policies where there should flow living human relationship. The time has come when, for the sake of the whole outraged world, Europe should fully know in her own person the terrible absurdity of the thing called the Nation.

The Nation has thriven long upon mutilated humanity. Men, the fairest creations of God, came out of the National manufactory in huge numbers as war-making and money-making puppets, ludicrously vain of their pitiful perfection of mechanism. Human society grew more and more into a marionette show of politicians, soldiers, manufacturers and bureaucrats, pulled by wire arrangements of wonderful efficiency.

But the apotheosis of selfishness can never make its interminable breed of hatred and greed, fear and hypocrisy, suspicion and tyranny, an end in themselves. These monsters grow into huge shapes but never into harmony. And this Nation may grow on to an unimaginable corpulence, not of a living body, but of steel and steam and office buildings, till its deformity can contain no longer its ugly voluminousness — till it begins to crack and gape, breathe gas and fire in gasps, and its death-rattles sound in cannon roars. In this war the death-throes of the Nation have commenced. Suddenly, all its mechanism going mad, it has begun the dance of the Furies, shattering its own limbs, scattering them into the dust. It is the fifth act of the tragedy of the unreal.

Those who have any faith in Man cannot but fervently hope that the tyranny of the Nation will not be restored to all its former teeth and claws, to its far-reaching iron arms and its immense inner cavity, all stomach and no heart; that man will have his new birth, in the freedom of his individuality, from the enveloping vagueness of abstraction.

The veil has been raised, and in this frightful war the West has stood face to face with her own creation, to which she had offered her soul. She must know what it truly is.

She had never let herself suspect what slow decay and decomposition were secretly going on in her moral nature, which often broke out in doctrines of scepticism, but still oftener and in still more dangerously subtle manner showed itself in her unconsciousness of the mutilation and insult that she had been inflicting upon a vast part of the world. Now she must know the truth nearer home.

And then there will come from her own children those who will break themselves free from the slavery of this illusion, this perversion of brotherhood founded upon self-seeking, those who will own themselves as God's children and as no bond-slaves of machinery, which turns souls into commodities and life into compartments, which, with its iron claws, scratches out the heart of the world and knows not what it has done.

And we of the No-Nations of the world, whose heads have been bowed to the dust, will know that this dust is more sacred than the bricks which build the pride of power. For this dust is fertile of life, and of beauty and worship. We shall thank God that we were made to wait in silence through the night of despair, had to bear the insult of the proud and the strong man's burden, yet all through it, though our hearts quaked with doubt and fear, never could we blindly believe in the salvation which machinery offered to man, but we held fast to our trust in God and the truth of the human soul. And we can still cherish the hope that, when power becomes ashamed to occupy its throne and is ready to make way for love, when the morning comes for cleansing the blood-stained steps of the Nation along the highroad of humanity, we shall be called upon to bring our own vessel of sacred water — the water of worship — to sweeten the history of man into purity, and with its sprinkling make the trampled dust of the centuries blessed with fruitfulness.

注释

〔1〕About 200 prose and verse treatises on metaphysical philosophy, dating from around 400 BC.

Nationalism in India

Our real problem in India is not political. It is social. This is a condition not only prevailing in India, but among all nations. I do not believe in an exclusive political interest. Politics in the West have dominated western ideals, and we in India are trying to imitate you. We have to remember that in Europe, where peoples had their racial unity from the beginning, and where natural resources were insufficient for the inhabitants, the civilization has naturally taken on the character of political and commercial aggressiveness. For on the one hand they had no internal complications, and on the other they had to deal with neighbours who were strong and rapacious. To have a perfect combination among themselves and a watchful attitude of animosity against others was taken as the solution of their problems. In former days they organized and plundered; in the present age the same spirit continues — and they organize and exploit the whole world.

But from the earliest beginnings of history India has had her own problem constantly before her — it is the race problem. Each nation must be conscious of its mission, and we in India must realize that we cut a poor figure when we try to be political, simply because we have not yet been finally able to accomplish what was set before us by our providence.

This problem of race unity which we have been trying to solve for so many years has likewise to be faced by you here in America. Many people in this country ask me what is happening to the caste distinctions in India. But when this question is asked me, it is usually done with a superior air. And I feel tempted to put the same question to our American critics with a slight modification: 'What have you done with the Red Indian and the Negro?' For you have not got over your attitude of caste towards them. You have used violent methods to keep aloof from other races, but until you have solved the question, here in America, you have no right to question India.

In spite of our great difficulty, however, India has done something. She has tried to make an adjustment of races, to acknowledge the real differences between them where these exist, and yet seek for some basis of unity. This basis has come through our saints, like Nanak, Kabir, Chaitanya[〔1〕] and others, preaching one God to all races of India.

In finding the solution of our problem we shall have helped to solve the world problem as well. What India has been, the whole world is now. The whole world is becoming one country through scientific facility. And the moment is arriving when you must also find a basis of unity which is not political. If India can offer to the world her solution, it will be a contribution to humanity. There is only one history — the history of man. All national histories are merely chapters in the larger one. And we are content in India to suffer for such a great cause.

Each individual has his self-love. Therefore his brute instinct leads him to fight with others in the sole pursuit of his self-interest. But man has also his higher instincts of sympathy and mutual help. The people who are lacking in this higher moral power and who therefore cannot combine in fellowship with one another must perish or live in a state of degradation. Only, those peoples have survived and achieved civilization who have this spirit of co-operation strong in them. So we find that from the beginning of history men had to choose between fighting with one another and combining, between serving their own interest or the common interest of all.

In our early history, when the geographical limits of each country and also the facilities of communication were small, this problem was comparatively small in dimension. It was sufficient for men to develop their sense of unity within their area of segregation. In those days they combined among themselves and fought against others. But it was this moral spirit of combination which was the true basis of their greatness, and this fostered their art, science and religion. At that early time the most important fact that man had to take count of was the fact of the members of one particular race of men coming in close contact with one another. Those who truly grasped this fact through their higher nature made their mark in history.

The most important fact of the present age is that all the different races of men have come close together. And again we are confronted with two alternatives. The problem is whether the different groups of peoples shall go on fighting with one another or find out some true basis of reconciliation and mutual help; whether it will be interminable competition or co-operation.

I have no hesitation in saying that those who are gifted with the moral power of love and vision of spiritual unity, who have the least feeling of enmity against aliens, and the sympathetic insight to place themselves in the position of others, will be the fittest to take their permanent place in the age that is lying before us, and those who are constantly developing their instincts for fight and intolerance of aliens will be eliminated. For this is the problem before us, and we have to prove our humanity by solving it through the help of our higher nature. The gigantic organizations for hurting others and warding off their blows, for making money by dragging others back, will not help us. On the contrary, by their crushing weight, their enormous cost and their deadening effect upon living humanity, they will seriously impede our freedom in the larger life of a higher civilization.

During the evolution of the Nation the moral culture of brotherhood was limited by geographical boundaries, because at that time those boundaries were true. Now they have become imaginary lines of tradition divested of the qualities of real obstacles. So the time has come when man's moral nature must deal with this great fact with all seriousness or perish. The first impulse of this change of circumstance has been the churning up of man's baser passions of greed and cruel hatred. If this persists indefinitely, and armaments go on exaggerating themselves to unimaginable absurdities, and machines and storehouses envelop this fair earth with their dirt and smoke and ugliness, then it will end in a conflagration of suicide. Therefore man will have to exert all his power of love and clarity of vision to make another great moral adjustment which will comprehend the whole world of men and not merely the fractional groups of nationality. The call has come to every individual in the present age to prepare himself and his surroundings for this dawn of a new era, when man shall discover his soul in the spiritual unity of all human beings.

If it is given at all to the West to struggle out of these tangles of the lower slopes to the spiritual summit of humanity then I cannot but think that it is the special mission of America to fulfil this hope of God and man. You are the country of expectation, desiring something else than what is. Europe has her subtle habits of mind and her conventions. But America, as yet, has come to no conclusions. I realize how much America is untrammelled by the traditions of the past, and I can appreciate that experimentalism is a sign of America's youth. The foundation of her glory is in the future, rather than in the past, and if one is gifted with the power of clairvoyance, one will be able to love the America that is to be.

America is destined to justify western civilization to the East. Europe has lost faith in humanity, and has become distrustful and sickly. America, on the other hand, is not pessimistic or blasé. You know, as a people, that there is such a thing as a better and a best, and that knowledge drives you on. There are habits that are not merely passive but aggressively arrogant. They are not like mere walls, but are like hedges of stinging nettles. Europe has been cultivating these hedges of habits for long years, till they have grown round her dense and strong and high. The pride of her traditions has sent its roots deep into her heart. I do not wish to contend that it is unreasonable. But pride in every form breeds blindness at the end. Like all artificial stimulants its first effect is a heightening of consciousness, and then with the increasing dosage it muddles it and brings an exultation that is misleading. Europe has gradually grown hardened in her pride in all her outer and inner habits. She not only cannot forget that she is western, but she takes every opportunity to hurl this fact against others to humiliate them. This is why she is growing incapable of imparting to the East what is best in herself, and of accepting in a right spirit the wisdom that the East has stored for centuries.

In America national habits and traditions have not had time to spread their clutching roots around your hearts. You have constantly felt and complained of your disadvantages when you compared your nomadic restlessness with the settled traditions of Europe — the Europe which can show her picture of greatness to the best advantage because she can fix it against the background of the past. But in this present age of transition, when a new era of civilization is sending its trumpet-call to all peoples of the world across an unlimited future, this very freedom of detachment will enable you to accept its invitation and to achieve the goal for which Europe began her journey but lost herself mid-way. For she was tempted out of her path by her pride of power and greed of possession.

Not merely your freedom from habits of mind in individuals, but also the freedom of your history from all unclean entanglements, fits you in your career of holding the banner of civilization of the future. All the great nations of Europe have their victims in other parts of the world. This not only deadens their moral sympathy but also their intellectual sympathy, which is so necessary for the understanding of races which are different from one's own. Englishmen can never truly understand India, because their minds are not disinterested with regard to that country. If you compare England with Germany or France you will find she has produced the smallest number of scholars who have studied Indian literature and philosophy with any amount of sympathetic insight or thoroughness. This attitude of apathy and contempt is natural where the relationship is abnormal and founded upon national selfishness and pride. But your history has been disinterested, and that is why you have been able to help Japan in her lessons in western civilization, and that is why China can look upon you with the best confidence in this, her darkest period of danger. In fact you are carrying all the responsibility of a great future because you are untrammelled by the grasping miserliness of a past. Therefore, of all countries of the earth, America has to be fully conscious of this future; her vision must not be obscured and her faith in humanity must be strong with the strength of youth.

A parallelism exists between America and India — the parallelism of welding together into one body various races.

In my country we have been seeking to find out something common to all races, which will prove their real unity. No nation looking for a mere political or commercial basis of unity will find such a solution sufficient. Men of thought and power will discover the spiritual unity, will realize it, and preach it.

India has never had a real sense of nationalism. Even though from childhood I had been taught that idolatry of the Nation is almost better than reverence for God and humanity, I believe I have outgrown that teaching, and it is my conviction that my countrymen will truly gain their India by fighting against the education which teaches them that a country is greater than the ideals of humanity.

The educated Indian at present is trying to absorb some lessons from history contrary to the lessons of our ancestors. The East, in fact, is attempting to take unto itself a history, which is not the outcome of its own living. Japan, for example, thinks she is getting powerful through adopting western methods but, after she has exhausted her inheritance, only the borrowed weapons of civilization will remain to her. She will not have developed herself from within.

Europe has her past. Europe's strength therefore lies in her history. We in India must make up our minds that we cannot borrow other people's history, and that if we stifle our own we are committing suicide. When you borrow things that do not belong to your life, they only serve to crush your life.

And therefore I believe that it does India no good to compete with western civilization in its own field. But we shall be more than compensated if, in spite of the insults heaped upon us, we follow our own destiny.

There are lessons which impart information or train our minds for intellectual pursuits. These are simple and can be acquired and used with advantage. But there are others which affect our deeper nature and change our direction of life. Before we accept them and pay their value by selling our own inheritance, we must pause and think deeply. In man's history there come ages of fireworks which dazzle us by their force and movement. They laugh not only at our modest household lamps but also at the eternal stars. But let us not for that provocation be precipitate in our desire to dismiss our lamps. Let us patiently bear our present insult and realize that these fireworks have splendour but not permanence, because of the extreme explosiveness which is the cause of their power, and also of their exhaustion. They are spending a fatal quantity of energy and substance compared to their gain and production.

Anyhow, our ideals have been evolved through our own history, and even if we wished we could only make poor fireworks of them because their materials are different from yours, as is also their moral purpose. If we cherish the desire of paying our all to buy a political nationality it will be as absurd as if Switzerland had staked her existence on her ambition to build up a navy powerful enough to compete with that of England. The mistake that we make is in thinking that man's channel of greatness is only one — the one which has made itself painfully evident for the time being by its depth of insolence.

We must know for certain that there is a future before us and that future is waiting for those who are rich in moral ideals and not in mere things. And it is the privilege of man to work for fruits that are beyond his immediate reach, and to adjust his life not in slavish conformity to the examples of some present success or even to his own prudent past, limited in its aspiration, but to an infinite future bearing in its heart the ideals of our highest expectations.

We must recognize that it is providential that the West has come to India. And yet someone must show the East to the West, and convince the West that the East has her contribution to make to the history of civilization. India is no beggar of the West. And yet even though the West may think she is, I am not for thrusting off western civilization and becoming segregated in our independence. Let us have a deep association. If Providence wants England to be the channel of that communication, of that deeper association, I am willing to accept it with all humility. I have great faith in human nature, and I think the West will find its true mission. I speak bitterly of western civilization when I am conscious that it is betraying its trust and thwarting its own purpose. The West must not make herself a curse to the world by using her power for her own selfish needs but, by teaching the ignorant and helping the weak, she should save herself from the worst danger that the strong are liable to incur by making the feeble acquire power enough to resist her intrusion. And also she must not make her materialism to be the final thing, but must realize that she is doing a service in freeing the spiritual being from the tyranny of matter.

I am not against one nation in particular, but against the general idea of all nations. What is the Nation?

It is the aspect of a whole people as an organized power. This organization incessantly keeps up the insistence of the population on becoming strong and efficient. But this strenuous effort after strength and efficiency drains man's energy from his higher nature where he is self-sacrificing and creative. For thereby man's power of sacrifice is diverted from his ultimate object, which is moral, to the maintenance of this organization, which is mechanical. Yet in this he feels all the satisfaction of moral exaltation and therefore becomes supremely dangerous to humanity. He feels relieved of the urging of his conscience when he can transfer his responsibility to this machine which is the creation of his intellect and not of his complete moral personality. By this device the people which loves freedom perpetuates slavery in a large portion of the world with the comfortable feeling of pride in having done its duty; men who are naturally just can be cruelly unjust both in their act and their thought, accompanied by a feeling that they are helping the world to receive its deserts; men who are honest can blindly go on robbing others of their human rights for self-aggrandizement, all the while abusing the deprived for not deserving better treatment. We have seen in our everyday life even small organizations of business and profession produce callousness of feeling in men who are not naturally bad, and we can well imagine what a moral havoc it is causing in a world where whole peoples are furiously organizing themselves for gaining wealth and power.

Nationalism is a great menace. It is the particular thing which for years has been at the bottom of India's troubles. And inasmuch as we have been ruled and dominated by a nation that is strictly political in its attitude, we have tried to develop within ourselves, despite our inheritance from the past, a belief in our eventual political destiny.

There are different parties in India, with different ideals. Some are struggling for political independence. Others think that the time has not arrived for that, and yet believe that India should have the rights that the English colonies have. They wish to gain autonomy as far as possible.

In the beginning of the history of political agitation in India there was not the conflict between parties which there is today. At that time there was a party known as the Indian Congress;[〔2〕] they had no real programme. They had a few grievances for redress by the authorities. They wanted larger representation in the Council House, and more freedom in Municipal Government. They wanted scraps of things, but they had no constructive ideal. Therefore I was lacking in enthusiasm for their methods. It was my conviction that what India most needed was constructive work coming from within herself. In this work we must take all risks and go on doing the duties which by right are ours, though in the teeth of persecution, winning moral victory at every step, by our failure and suffering. We must show those who are over us that we have in ourselves the strength of moral power, the power to suffer for truth. Where we have nothing to show, we have only to beg. It would be mischievous if the gifts we wish for were granted to us at once, and I have told my countrymen, time and again, to combine for the work of creating opportunities to give vent to our spirit of self-sacrifice, and not for the purpose of begging.

The party, however, lost power because the people soon came to realize how futile was the half policy adopted by them. The party split,[〔3〕] and there arrived the Extremists, who advocated independence of action, and discarded the begging method — the easiest method of relieving one's mind from his responsibility towards his country. Their ideals were based on western history. They had no sympathy with the special problems of India. They did not recognize the patent fact that there were causes in our social organization which made the Indian incapable of coping with the alien. What should we do if, for any reason, England was driven away? We should simply be victims for other nations. The same social weaknesses would prevail. The thing we in India have to think of is this: to remove those social customs and ideals which have generated a want of self-respect and a complete dependence on those above us — a state of affairs which has been brought about entirely by the domination in India of the caste system, and the blind and lazy habit of relying upon the authority of traditions that are incongruous anachronisms in the present age.

Once again I draw your attention to the difficulties India has had to encounter and her struggle to overcome them. Her problem was the problem of the world in miniature. India is too vast in its area and too diverse in its races. It is many countries packed in one geographical receptacle. It is just the opposite of what Europe truly is; namely, one country made into many. Thus Europe in its culture and growth has had the advantage of the strength of the many as well as the strength of the one. India, on the contrary, being naturally many, yet adventitiously one, has all along suffered from the looseness of its diversity and the feebleness of its unity. A true unity is like a round globe; it rolls on, carrying its burden easily. But diversity is a many-cornered thing which has to be dragged and pushed with all force. Be it said to the credit of India that this diversity was not her own creation; she has had to accept it as a fact from the beginning of her history. In America and Australia, Europe has simplified her problem by almost exterminating the original population. Even in the present age this spirit of extermination is making itself manifest, in the inhospitable shutting out of aliens, by those who themselves were aliens in the lands they now occupy. But India tolerated difference of races from the first, and that spirit of toleration has acted all through her history.

Her caste system is the outcome of this spirit of toleration. For India has all along been trying experiments in evolving a social unity within which all the different peoples could be held together, while fully enjoying the freedom of maintaining their own differences. The tie has been as loose as possible, yet as close as the circumstances permitted. This has produced something like a United States of a social federation, whose common name is Hinduism.

India had felt that diversity of races there must be and should be, whatever may be its drawbacks, and you can never coerce nature into your narrow limits of convenience without paying one day very dearly for it. In this India was right; but what she failed to realize was that in human beings differences are not like the physical barriers of mountains, fixed for ever — they are fluid with life's flow, they are changing their courses and their shapes and volumes.

Therefore in her caste regulations India recognized differences, but not the mutability which is the law of life. In trying to avoid collisions she set up boundaries of immovable walls, thus giving to her numerous races the negative benefit of peace and order but not the positive opportunity of expansion and movement. She accepted nature where it produces diversity, but ignored it where it uses that diversity for its world-game of infinite permutations and combinations. She treated life in all truth where it is manifold, but insulted it where it is ever moving. Therefore Life departed from her social system and in its place she is worshipping with all ceremony the magnificent cage of countless compartments that she has manufactured.

The same thing happened where she tried to ward off the collisions of trade interests. She associated different trades and professions with different castes. This had the effect of allaying for good the interminable jealousy and hatred of competition — the competition which breeds cruelty and makes the atmosphere thick with lies and deception. In this also India laid all her emphasis upon the law of heredity, ignoring the law of mutation, and thus gradually reduced arts into crafts and genius into skill.

However, what western observers fail to discern is that in her caste system India in all seriousness accepted her responsibility to solve the race problem in such a manner as to avoid all friction, and yet to afford each race freedom within its boundaries. Let us admit India has not in this achieved a full measure of success. But this you must also concede: that the West, being more favourably situated as to homogeneity of races, has never given her attention to this problem, and whenever confronted with it she has tried to make it easy by ignoring it altogether. And this is the source of her anti-Asiatic agitations for depriving aliens of their right to earn their honest living on these shores. In most of your colonies you only admit them on condition of their accepting the menial positions of hewers of wood and drawers of water. Either you shut your doors against the aliens or reduce them into slavery. And this is your solution to the problem of race-conflict. Whatever may be its merits you will have to admit that it does not spring from the higher impulses of civilization, but from the lower passions of greed and hatred. You say this is human nature — and India also thought she knew human nature when she strongly barricaded her race distinctions by the fixed barriers of social gradations. But we have found out to our cost that human nature is not what it seems, but what it is in truth, which is in its infinite possibilities. And when we in our blindness insult humanity for its ragged appearance it sheds its disguise to disclose to us that we have insulted our God. The degradation which we cast upon others in our pride or self-interest degrades our own humanity — and this is the punishment which is most terrible, because we do not detect it till it is too late.

Not only in your relation with aliens but with the different sections of your own society you have not achieved harmony of reconciliation. The spirit of conflict and competition is allowed the full freedom of its reckless career. And because its genesis is the greed of wealth and power it can never come to any other end but to a violent death. In India the production of commodities was brought under the law of social adjustments. Its basis was co-operation, having for its object the perfect satisfaction of social needs. But in the West it is guided by the impulse of competition, whose end is the gain of wealth for individuals. But the individual is like the geometrical line; it is length without breadth. It has not got the depth to be able to hold anything permanently. Therefore its greed or gain can never come to finality. In its lengthening process of growth it can cross other lines and cause entanglements, but will ever go on missing the ideal of completeness in its thinness of isolation.

In all our physical appetites we recognize a limit. We know that to exceed that limit is to exceed the limit of health. But has this lust for wealth and power no bounds beyond which is death's dominion? In these national carnivals of materialism are not the western peoples spending most of their vital energy in merely producing things and neglecting the creation of ideals? And can a civilization ignore the law of moral health and go on in its endless process of inflation by gorging upon material things? Man in his social ideals naturally tries to regulate his appetites, subordinating them to the higher purpose of his nature. But in the economic world our appetites follow no other restrictions but those of supply and demand which can be artificially fostered, affording individuals opportunities for indulgence in an endless feast of grossness. In India our social instincts imposed restrictions upon our appetites — maybe it went to the extreme of repression — but in the West the spirit of economic organization with no moral purpose goads the people into the perpetual pursuit of wealth; but has this no wholesome limit?

The ideals that strive to take form in social institutions have two objects. One is to regulate our passions and appetites for the harmonious development of man, and the other is to help him to cultivate disinterested love for his fellow-creatures. Therefore society is the expression of those moral and spiritual aspirations of man which belong to his higher nature.

Our food is creative, it builds our body; but not so wine, which stimulates. Our social ideals create the human world, but when our mind is diverted from them to greed of power then in that state of intoxication we live in a world of abnormality where our strength is not health and our liberty is not freedom. Therefore political freedom does not give us freedom when our mind is not free. An automobile does not create freedom of movement, because it is a mere machine. When I myself am free I can use the automobile for the purpose of my freedom.

We must never forget in the present day that those people who have got their political freedom are not necessarily free; they are merely powerful. The passions which are unbridled in them are creating huge organizations of slavery in the disguise of freedom. Those who have made the gain of money their highest end are unconsciously selling their life and soul to rich persons or to the combinations that represent money. Those who are enamoured of their political power and gloat over their extension of dominion over foreign races gradually surrender their own freedom and humanity to the organizations necessary for holding other peoples in slavery. In the so-called free countries the majority of the people are not free; they are driven by the minority to a goal which is not even known to them. This becomes possible only because people do not acknowledge moral and spiritual freedom as their object. They create huge eddies with their passions, and they feel dizzily inebriated with the mere velocity of their whirling movement, taking that to be freedom. But the doom which is waiting to overtake them is as certain as death — for man's truth is moral truth and his emancipation is in the spiritual life.

The general opinion of the majority of the present-day nationalists in India is that we have come to a final completeness in our social and spiritual ideals, the task of the constructive work of society having been done several thousand years before we were born, and that now we are free to employ all our activities in the political direction. We never dream of blaming our social inadequacy as the origin of our present helplessness, for we have accepted as the creed of our nationalism that this social system has been perfected for all time to come by our ancestors, who had the superhuman vision of all eternity and supernatural power for making infinite provision for future ages. Therefore, for all our miseries and shortcomings, we hold responsible the historical surprises that burst upon us from outside. This is the reason why we think that our one task is to build a political miracle of freedom upon the quicksand of social slavery. In fact we want to dam up the true course of our own historical stream, and only borrow power from the sources of other peoples' history.

Those of us in India who have come under the delusion that mere political freedom will make us free have accepted their lessons from the West as the gospel truth and lost their faith in humanity. We must remember that whatever weakness we cherish in our society will become the source of danger in politics. The same inertia which leads us to our idolatry of dead forms in social institutions will create in our politics prison-houses with immovable walls. The narrowness of sympathy which makes it possible for us to impose upon a considerable portion of humanity the galling yoke of inferiority will assert itself in our politics in creating the tyranny of injustice.

When our nationalists talk about ideals they forget that the basis of nationalism is wanting. The very people who are upholding these ideals are themselves the most conservative in their social practice. Nationalists say, for example: look at Switzerland where, in spite of race differences, the people have solidified into a nation. Yet, remember that in Switzerland the races can mingle, they can intermarry, because they are of the same blood. In India there is no common birthright. And when we talk of western nationality we forget that the nations there do not have that physical repulsion, one for the other, that we have between different castes. Have we an instance in the whole world where a people who are not allowed to mingle their blood shed their blood for one another except by coercion or for mercenary purposes? And can we ever hope that these moral barriers against our race amalgamation will not stand in the way of our political unity?

Then again we must give full recognition to this fact that our social restrictions are still tyrannical, so much so as to make men cowards. If a man tells me that he has heterodox ideas, but that he cannot follow them because he would be socially ostracized, I excuse him for having to live a life of untruth, in order to live at all. The social habit of mind which impels us to make the life of our fellow-beings a burden to them where they differ from us even in such a thing as their choice of food, is sure to persist in our political organization and result in creating engines of coercion to crush every rational difference which is the sign of life. And tyranny will only add to the inevitable lies and hypocrisy in our political life. Is the mere name of freedom so valuable that we should be willing to sacrifice for its sake our moral freedom?

The intemperance of our habits does not immediately show its effects when we are in the vigour of our youth. But it gradually consumes that vigour, and when the period of decline sets in then we have to settle accounts and pay off our debts, which leads us to insolvency. In the West you are still able to carry your head high, though your humanity is suffering every moment from its dipsomania of organizing power. India also in the heyday of her youth could carry in her vital organs the dead weight of her social organizations stiffened to rigid perfection, but it has been fatal to her, and has produced a gradual paralysis of her living nature. And this is the reason why the educated community of India has become insensible of her social needs. They are taking the very immobility of our social structures as the sign of their perfection — and because the healthy feeling of pain is dead in the limbs of our social organism they delude themselves into thinking that it needs no ministration. Therefore they think that all their energies need their only scope in the political field. It is like a man whose legs have become shrivelled and useless, trying to delude himself that these limbs have grown still because they have attained their ultimate salvation, and all that is wrong about him is the shortness of his sticks.

So much for the social and the political regeneration of India. Now we come to her industries, and I am very often asked whether there is in India any industrial regeneration since the advent of the British government. It must be remembered that at the beginning of the British rule in India our industries were suppressed, and since then we have not met with any real help or encouragement to enable us to make a stand against the monster commercial organizations of the world. The nations have decreed that we must remain purely an agricultural people, even forgetting the use of arms for all time to come. Thus India is being turned into so many predigested morsels of food ready to be swallowed at any moment by any nation which has even the most rudimentary set of teeth in its head.

India therefore has very little outlet for her industrial originality. I personally do not believe in the unwieldy organizations of the present day. The very fact that they are ugly shows that they are in discordance with the whole creation. The vast powers of nature do not reveal their truth in hideousness, but in beauty. Beauty is the signature which the Creator stamps upon His works when He is satisfied with them. All our products that insolently ignore the laws of perfection and are unashamed in their display of ungainliness bear the perpetual weight of God's displeasure. So far as your commerce lacks the dignity of grace it is untrue. Beauty and her twin brother Truth require leisure and self-control for their growth. But the greed of gain has no time or limit to its capaciousness. Its one object is to produce and consume. It has pity neither for beautiful nature nor for living human beings. It is ruthlessly ready without a moment's hesitation to crush beauty and life out of them, moulding them into money. It is this ugly vulgarity of commerce which brought upon it the censure of contempt in our earlier days, when men had leisure to have an unclouded vision of perfection in humanity. Men in those times were rightly ashamed of the instinct of mere money-making. But in this scientific age money, by its very abnormal bulk, has won its throne. And when from its eminence of piled-up things it insults the higher instincts of man, banishing beauty and noble sentiments from its surroundings, we submit. For we in our meanness have accepted bribes from its hands and our imagination has grovelled in the dust before its immensity of flesh.

But its very unwieldiness and its endless complexities are its true signs of failure. The swimmer who is an expert does not exhibit his muscular force by violent movements, but exhibits some power which is invisible and which shows itself in perfect grace and reposefulness. The true distinction of man from animals is in his power and worth which are inner and invisible. But the present-day commercial civilization of man is not only taking too much time and space but killing time and space. Its movements are violent; its noise is discordantly loud. It is carrying its own damnation because it is trampling into distortion the humanity upon which it stands. It is strenuously turning out money at the cost of happiness. Man is reducing himself to his minimum in order to be able to make amplest room for his organizations. He is deriding his human sentiments into shame because they are apt to stand in the way of his machines.

In our mythology we have the legend that the man who performs penances for attaining immortality has to meet with temptations sent by Indra, the Lord of the Immortals. If he is lured by them he is lost. The West has been striving for centuries after its goal of immortality. Indra has sent her the temptation to try her. It is the gorgeous temptation of wealth. She has accepted it, and her civilization of humanity has lost its path in the wilderness of machinery.

This commercialism with its barbarity of ugly decorations is a terrible menace to all humanity, because it is setting up the ideal of power over that of perfection. It is making the cult of self-seeking exult in its naked shamelessness. Our nerves are more delicate than our muscles. Things that are the most precious in us are helpless as babes when we take away from them the careful protection which they claim from us for their very preciousness. Therefore, when the callous rudeness of power runs amuck in the broadway of humanity it scares away by its grossness the ideals which we have cherished with the martyrdom of centuries.

The temptation which is fatal for the strong is still more so for the weak. And I do not welcome it in our Indian life, even though it be sent by the Lord of the Immortals. Let our life be simple in its outer aspect and rich in its inner gain. Let our civilization take its firm stand upon its basis of social co-operation and not upon that of economic exploitation and conflict. How to do it in the teeth of the drainage of our lifeblood by the economic dragons is the task set before the thinkers of all oriental nations who have faith in the human soul. It is a sign of laziness and impotency to accept conditions imposed upon us by others who have other ideals than ours. We should actively try to adapt the world powers to guide our history to its own perfect end.

From the above you will know that I am not an economist. I am willing to acknowledge that there is a law of demand and supply and an infatuation of man for more things than are good for him. And yet I will persist in believing that there is such a thing as the harmony of completeness in humanity, where poverty does not take away his riches, where defeat may lead him to victory, death to immortality, and where in the compensation of Eternal Justice those who are the last may yet have their insult transmuted into a golden triumph.

注释

〔1〕Nanak (1469-1533), Kabir (1440-1518), Chaitanya (1485-1533).

〔2〕The Indian National Congress was founded in 1885.

〔3〕In 1907, at the annual session of the Indian National Congress, held at Surat.

导读

亚瑟·叔本华（1788—1860）是一位以无神论和悲观主义闻名于世的德国哲学家，是整个西方哲学传统中最杰出的悲观主义者。叔本华赞成一种否定欲望的生活方式，他认为，情感、身体和性欲都会带来痛苦。他的这种悲观哲思影响了许多思想家，其中包括尼采、维特根斯坦、爱因斯坦和弗洛伊德。

在《论世间苦难》中，叔本华称，如果我们生活的直接目的并非受苦，那我们的存在就是世界上与其目的最不相符的东西。换句话说，痛苦和不幸是生活惯例，而非特例。

就像时间只有在我们感到无聊时，才会停滞，仿佛河央戏水的孩童，欢乐的时光总是如风般匆匆而逝，可一旦被关进小书房里，哪怕是片刻橙黄的午后——听梧桐叶间的蝉声，看书桌上的黄纸黑字——也是难以打发和消磨的。

我们大部分时间都在工作、担心和痛苦，成了机械生物，麻木、茫然。可承受痛苦并不可怕，可怕的是人感受不到痛苦的侵扰，就好像瘫痪的双肢，哪怕被碾成齑粉，也不知道痛苦的存在，也看不到一丝反抗的生机。但即使所有愿望都得到满足，也会感到无聊或者想要自杀。这就是精神之苦难。

如果我们与年轻时的好友重逢，过去时光犹在眼前，那相见时，两人心中涌起的最强烈的感觉就是对人生的彻底失望。因为，在青春岁月玫瑰色的黎明下，人生曾多么美好，它曾许诺很多，如今却鲜少兑现。

面对这些苦难，叔本华认为，要有效地指引我们生活的方向，最有效的是调整自己，把世界当作赎罪之所，流放之地。这种生活观有一个好处：我们不会再惊讶地或愤慨地看待同胞的缺点与弊病。因为我们始终记住自我的位置，始终把生存着的每个人看作是罪孽的产物，被生下来是一种罪孽，而每个人的生活都是对这种罪孽的补偿与救赎。

生命迁流不定，万物变动不居，如此世间，幸福不值一想。我们的存在仅停留在短暂的现在，此外别无所依。世界本不该存在，因而人也不该存在。这些看似悲观的理论背后却隐藏着深刻的人生要义。叔本华的这种论调教会人们看清世界和他人，铭记一生的要事：宽容、耐心、尊重与悲悯，这些是我们每个人都需要也应当给予的。

书中有关现时的论述十分精彩。叔本华将现时同人生过程与目的捆绑，称大多数人回首一生时都会发现，自己一直活在过渡状态，即活在现时，而现时是暂时的，只是通往目的的途径。我们一生都在追求，但实则终其一生一无所获，因为所求之物一旦获得即觉空虚。目标一旦实现，愉悦随即消失。面对这样的问题，我们首先要认识到生命图景的本质，在叔本华看来它“犹如胡乱拼凑的图画，近看粗陋，要想显得美，只能远观”。叔本华用其惯用的悲观论调告诫人们“应尽力把生活看成一个泡影，一个幻灭的过程”。

所谓苦难，不过我们意志导向之必然，因为“随顺己愿的，我们从不注意或觉察”，也就是说，当我们注意和觉察时，我们的意志必先遭遇了某种挫折，经历了某种震惊。叔本华用他的方式还原了世间苦难的本质。

梁美令

随笔集

论世间苦难

1

如果我们生活的直接目的并非受苦，那我们的存在就是世界上与其目的最不相符的东西。世间充斥痛苦，欲求产生痛苦，这样如影随形、无穷无尽的悲苦困窘竟然毫无意义、纯属偶然，这样的设想未免荒谬。的确，个别的不幸是偶发事件，但不幸就总体而言却是定则。

2

正如一条平缓流动、无所遮拦的河，随顺己愿的，我们从不注意或觉察，这是人和动物的天性；若我们需注意到什么，那么我们的意志必先遭遇挫折，必先经历某种震惊。反之，举凡与意志相违、相妨、相抗，即一切不快不幸之事，总是立刻引起我们的重视，清楚直接。周身无恙，我们了无所知；但当方寸之躯被鞋夹痛，我们不去想整体的成功，反倒只想细枝末节，或那些不断激扰我们的事物。有鉴于此，我常要人注意：安乐幸福是否定性的概念，痛苦则是肯定性的概念。

因此，几乎所有形而上学都把恶解释成某种否定性的东西，这是我了解到的最荒谬之事。因为恶恰恰是肯定性的，是不言自明的；而善，即幸福安乐，则是否定性的，无非是欲的停止或痛苦的消除。

另一个证据是：通常我们感觉，快乐并不像我们所向往的那样强烈，而痛苦要比预料的强烈得多。

有人宣称，世间快乐多于痛苦，或两者至少相抵。欲验其真伪，可作一简单比较：一只动物正大嚼猎物，则食肉者与被食者的感受孰强孰弱？

3

每有悲苦不幸，最有效的安慰即是观察他人之不幸尤甚于我，此法人人可行。但就人类整体的不幸而言，这又有什么意义？

历史向我们展现了列国的存亡，但除战争与骚乱以外别无可述，和平年代只是偶尔出现的短暂间隙和插曲。同样，个体的生命也是无休止的斗争，不仅是与譬喻意义上的欲求和无聊的斗争，更是与他人实实在在的斗争。环顾皆是敌人，争斗永无止息，他至死仍剑不离手。

4

在纠缠我们的种种苦恼中，时间的逼迫是重要的一个。时间从不容我们喘息片刻，而是执鞭追赶，有如监工。除非我们被交付给无聊，否则时间不会停止迫害。

5

若无大气压力，我们的身体就会炸为碎片。同样，我们的生活若无欲求、劳役、灾祸和挫败的压迫，人的自大心理也会膨胀，即便不会爆炸，也会发展为最放肆的愚蠢，乃至疯狂。甚至可以说，我们时刻需要一些烦恼、悲伤或欲求，正如船只需要压舱的货物使之直线前进。

苦扰悲辛确是贯穿几乎所有人生活的运命。然而，如果一有欲望即能满足，问题便会随之而来：人该如何填补生活，该如何打发时间？设想一下：人类迁移到某个世外桃源，那里万物自由生长，烤熟的火鸡飞来飞去，相爱的人一眼就找到对方，并安安稳稳长相厮守，那么，一些人会无聊至死或者上吊自杀，一些人会挑起争斗，互相杀戮，这样他们就会人为地制造苦难，比大自然施加给我们的苦难更多。因此对于这样一个物种来说，现有的生存状态和生存形式再合适不过了。

6

如上文重申，满足和安乐是否定性的，而苦难是肯定性的，因此，衡量一种生活幸福与否，不应根据其中的快乐和满足有多多，而应根据肯定性因素即苦难有多少。虽然如此，动物的命运要比人的命运更可忍受。让我们对两者略加详查。

不管人类的苦乐形式如何多样，如何引诱人们舍此逐彼，苦乐的物质基础都是肉体的快感和痛苦。这一基础范围很窄，包括拥有或没有健康、食物、不受寒冷和潮湿侵袭的环境，以及性欲的满足。所以，人并不比动物享有更多的肉体快感，只不过是他更加发达的神经系统强化了每一种快感，如同强化每一种痛感一样。他心中涌起的情感要比动物强烈多少倍，他的激情要比动物深刻浓烈多少倍，根本无法相提并论！而最终他得到的无非是同样的东西：健康、食物、栖身之所，诸如此类。

之所以如此，最重要的原因是，因为顾及未有的和未来的，他的一切都得到了极大的强化，这实际上是烦恼、恐惧和希望的根源。这些情绪一旦激起，对人的影响就会远远大于当下的实际苦乐——动物的感官即仅限于此。由于缺少反思能力，在动物身上不会像人那样，快乐和悲伤通过记忆和预期累积起来。在动物那里，当下的痛苦不管重复多少次，都和最初时一样——痛苦不会累加。因此，动物所特有的沉着和冷漠令人羡慕。而在人那里，从那些与动物相同的苦乐因素中，产生了感官对幸福和苦楚的强化。这种强化能让幸福瞬间达到极致，有时足以致人死命，也能把苦楚引向生不如死的绝望。更进一步考虑，事实情况是，最初人的需求并不比动物的需求更难满足，但人刻意地去强化自己的需求以强化其快乐，这样才有了奢侈品、甜点、烟草、鸦片、酒、服饰及相关的一切。在此之上，同样由于反思，又加入了一种先是引起快乐、后又招致痛苦、为他所独有的东西，他对此痴迷不已，远远超过此外的一切。这种东西就是野心及荣辱感，简言之，他会思考别人眼中自己的形象。这个形象表现不一，往往千奇百怪，超越肉体的苦乐，成为他一切努力的目标。的确，他比动物更能享受智力的乐趣。这些乐趣程度不一，从简单的玩笑和交谈到思维的最高成就。但与此相抵消的是，无聊与痛苦相伴而行。动物不知无聊为何物，至少自然状态的动物是如此，极为聪明的驯养动物对无聊也只略知一二；但对人类来说，无聊却堪称苦刑。欲求和无聊确是人生的两极。最后还要提到的是，人的性欲满足局限在很偏执的对象上，有时强化成热烈的爱情。因此对人来说，性带来的欢乐很短暂，痛苦却很漫长。

令人惊异的是，仅仅有了动物没有的思想，人本该在动物同样具有的简单的苦与乐基础上，建构起深广得多的幸福和不幸，本该任由强烈的情绪、激情和战栗印在他脸上，留下长存的皱纹，但事实却是，他能得到的动物也能得到，而动物付出的情感代价要小得无法与之相比。不过，因为有了思想，人的痛苦程度远大于快乐。人真正懂得死亡是怎么回事，这更极大地加剧了痛苦，而动物并不真正懂得死亡的意义，所以死亡从不在其视野之内，而不像人类那样总是想着死，因此只是本能地逃避死亡。

动物对活着本身要比人类知足得多，植物则完全如此，而人的知足程度取决于他的无聊程度和麻木程度。故此，动物的生命较之人类，包含更少的痛苦，也包含更少的欢乐。直接原因是：一方面，动物不受烦恼和忧虑的影响，也没有随之产生的种种折磨；另一方面，动物没有希望，也就没有对美好未来的憧憬，以及相伴而生的想象力的蛊惑——这些都是极苦和至乐之源。动物不去希望也从不忧虑，因为它们的意识局限在清楚直接的东西之上，因此也就局限在现在——动物是现时的化身。不过正因为如此，动物在无忧无虑安享现时这一方面与我们相比堪称真正的睿智。它们身上这种突出的沉静让常常骚动不满的我们羞愧不已。

7

如果上述讨论证明，人的一生比动物更为痛苦，是因为他们的认知能力更强，那我们现在可以进而推求更普遍的规律，从而形成更为全面的见解。

知识本身是永远没有痛苦的。痛苦只对意志产生作用，存在于意志的受阻、受妨或受挫。不过，意志的受挫若被感知为痛苦，必有认识相伴而行。这就是为什么连生理痛苦也总是受制于神经及其与大脑的连接，因此如果连接肢体与大脑的神经被切断，或大脑本身受到氯仿的毒害而失去活力，那么肢体受伤也不会被感觉到。精神痛苦受认识影响自不待言，痛苦随认识程度而加深也显而易见。这样我们就可以打一个比方形容整个关系：意志是琴弦，意志受挫或受妨是琴弦的振动，认识是共鸣板，痛苦则是发出的声音。

这意味着不止无机物不能感知痛苦，植物也是如此，不管遭受多少挫折。另外，所有动物，包括纤毛虫，都会体验到痛苦。这是因为动物的本质特点是认识，无论认识多么不完善。动物的生命每高一等，痛苦就相应增加一级。但即便是最高级的动物也不可能感知人所感知的痛苦，因为即使是最高级的动物也没有思想和观念。不错，痛苦的强度达到顶点时，也可能用理性否定意志——若非如此，那将毫无意义，残忍至极。

8

弱冠之时，我们坐在未来的人生前，如同孩子坐在戏院的幕布前，对将要发生的一切满怀欣喜，充满期待。幸而我们并不知道上演的究竟会是什么。因为对知道的人来说，孩子有时就像蒙冤的罪犯，被判处的不是死刑，而是终身监禁，而他们对刑罚的内容还毫无察觉。虽然如此，每个人都渴望活到老年，到那时候他就可以说：“今天很糟，还会一天天糟下去，直到最后糟得不可救药。”

9

若有可能，想象一下阳光普照之处的一切困窘、痛苦和磨难，你就会承认，假如太阳为地球带来的生命迹象像月球那样少，地球和月球一样还处在结晶状态，那情况将要好得多。

你也可将我们的生命视为一段不和谐的插曲，打乱了天赐的虚无宁静。无论何时何地，即便是认为生活尚可忍受的人，活得越久，越会清楚地了解，生活就整体而言是一个挫败，不，是一场骗局。如果年轻时的好友多年后重逢，过去时光犹在眼前，那相见时两人心中涌起的最强烈的感觉就是对人生彻底的失望。在青春岁月玫瑰色的黎明里，人生曾显得那么美好，它许诺的那么多，兑现的又那么少。这种感觉会牢牢地抓住他们，以致他们甚至觉得不值一提，只是默默地将它作为谈话的基调。

若生殖行为不是欲望的产物，也不伴随快感，而是一件纯由理性决定的事情，人类是否还会继续存在？我们每个人是否会对未来一代充满悲悯，乃至宁愿让他们不至背负生活的重担，或希望至少不是自己将重担无情地压在下一代身上？

因为世界是地狱，人一方面是受苦的灵魂，另一方面又是地狱里的魔鬼。

据说梵天因忽然堕落或因错误而创造世界，为赎清此罪恶或错误，不得不存于世界当中，直到他将自身从世界中解救出去。说得非常好！依佛教之言，涅槃状态胜妙谌然，长久宁静之后，不知何故受到染污，世界由此生成。因此，世界起源出于定数，这一点应主要从道德意义上理解——虽然物质世界的起源与此完全相同，太古时期不知何故产生雾带，太阳由此产生。尽管如此，因为世界由罪而成，所以物质世界不断变坏，直至今日这可悲的境地。说得妙极了！对希腊人来说，世界及诸神受造于不可解的必然性，这聊备一说。阿胡拉·玛兹达与安格拉·曼纽[1]征战不断，这也值得思考一下。但像耶和华这样的神主动自愿地创造这样一个充满欲望和苦痛的世界，甚而以此为荣，称此为善，这就未免让人难以接受了。

即便莱布尼茨的论证是对的，在所有可能产生的世界中，现在的世界是最好的，这仍旧不能证明神爱世人。因为造物主不仅创造世界，也创造了可能性本身，因此他本可以创造出更好的世界。

不过总的说来，世界是一个至慧、至善且有至高权能的存在的成功之作，这个观点会遭到两个事实的大声反对：世界充满苦难，并且世界上最高级的物种——人——明显是不完美的，人实则是怪诞的漫画人物。这是一种无法解决的矛盾。恰恰相反，正是这些事例支持我们刚才说的，证明我们对世界的看法是正确的：世界是我们自身罪恶的产物，因此最好压根就不存在。根据上述的推理，这些实例成了对造物主的有力控诉，为愤世嫉俗提供了素材。而根据我们的推理，这些实例成了对我们自己本性和意志的控诉，并集合起来教会我们谦卑。因为这些事例引导我们达到这样一个观点：我们就像浪荡儿所生的孩子，来到世界上已负罪累累，正因为我们必须不断赎清此罪，我们的存在才会这样卑微，存在的终点才会是死亡。总的说来，正是世间之罪导致了多种多样、深重难耐的世间之苦，这一点再明确不过，此处所说不是物质—经验的联系，而是形而上的联系。亚当夏娃堕落的故事因此是唯一能让我接受《旧约》的东西，我甚至认为这是《旧约》中唯一的形而上的真实，尽管它披着寓言的外衣——因为我们的存在最像是恶行的苦果，对禁忌之欲的惩罚。

要有效地指引我们的生活方向，最有用的是调整自己，把世界当作赎罪之所，流放之地。这样做，你就会根据事物的本质规范自己的期望，充分了解到我们每个人都在此间为自己的存在而受罚，每个人都有自己的受罚方式，而不再把生活中的苦痛祸乱当作不正常的东西而希望它们并不存在，而是觉得它们都是适当、合理的。这样的观点能让我们不惊奇，当然也不再愤慨地看待大多数人所谓的弊端，如道德和智力的缺点，以及由此表现出来的现象——因为我们应该时刻记住我们的位置，并由此首先把生存着的每个人看作罪孽的产物，被生下来是一种罪孽，每个人的生活都是对这种罪孽的补偿。

相信世界本不该存在，因而人也不该存在，这事实上会教会我们彼此宽容：置身我们这样的处境，又能对他人作何希求？因此真该考虑一下，人们见面时的问候不应该是“先生”，而应是“同病相怜的兄弟”。这听起来虽很古怪，但切合现实，让我们看清他人，提醒我们最必要之事：宽容、耐心、忍耐和慈悲，这些是我们每个人都需要也都应当给予的。

论存在之虚无

1

存在的虚无体现在存在的整体形式上：时空无际，时空中的个体却有穷；现时稍纵即逝，却是现实性的唯一体现；偶然性和相对性存在于万事万物；永远都在趋近，却永远无法到达；永远都在欲求，却永远无法满足；人生的奋斗总是遭遇挫败。生存意志本如自在之物长存不坏，但时间使得其间的万物短暂易朽，生存意志发现的只是奋斗的徒劳。赖时间之故，万物在我们手中化为乌有，丧失一切真正价值，这就是时间。

2

不再存在的和未曾存在的一样，几乎算不上存在，但将在下一刻存在的必定曾经存在，因此，最重要的现时要比最重要的过去更具现实性，前者与后者的关系乃是有与无的关系。

令我们吃惊的是，在不曾存在无数世代以后，我们突然存在了，片刻之后，我们又将不复存在无数世代。事情不应该是这样，心灵这样说。即便蒙昧之人想到这里也会希望，时间不过是一种观念。不过，时间和空间一样，是所有真正的形而上学的关键，因为它容许一种与自然秩序截然不同的事物秩序。这正是康德的伟大之处。

我们生命中的每一刻只短暂地属于当下，然后就永远地归于过去。一到傍晚，我们就又少了一天。若不是我们在生命的最深处隐隐感到：我们分得了不竭的永恒之泉，从中我们总能获取新的生命、新的时间，那么，眼见短促的生命一潮一潮退去，我们几乎会发狂。

你的确可以认同这样的说法：最高的智慧是享受现时，并以此为生活的目标，因为现时是唯一真实的，其他一切都是假象。但你也可以将这种生活方式称为最大的愚蠢，因为现时转瞬即逝，像梦一样消失无踪，不值得为此大费周章。

3

我们的存在仅停留在短暂的现在，此外别无所依。因此，存在的本质形式是无休止的动荡，我们不断寻求的安宁无从获得——就像一个人跑步下山，停下脚步就会跌倒，要保持不倒只能跑个不停；或像在指尖保持平衡的杆木；或像一颗行星，若不再拼命向前疾奔，就会跌入太阳。生命的特点就是这样迁流不定。

如此世间，稳定恒常了不可得，万物变动不居，混乱不堪，只能大步向前，才不会从高空吊索上坠落。如此世间，幸福不值一想。在这个只有柏拉图所谓“永远趋近，永远无法到达”的地方，幸福没有安身之所。首先，每个人都不幸福，用一生时间苦苦追寻心目中的幸福却很少得到，即便得到也会失望。然而，他照例终归会驶入港口，船倾桅折。其次，生命仅是一连串的短促现时，现在又已到尽头，幸与不幸没有区别。

4

我们生命的图景犹如胡乱拼凑的图画，近看粗陋，要想显得美，只能远观。这就是为什么所求之物一旦获得即觉空虚，这就是为什么尽管我们一生都在希求更好的事物，同时也经常对过去恋恋不舍。相反，现时被认为是暂时的，只是通往目的的途径。因此，大多数人回首一生时都会发现，自己一直活在过渡状态，他们吃惊地看到，他们放手的正是自己的生命，正是他们生活中期望的东西。

5

生命首先表现为一个任务，保有自身的任务，即糊口。若此任务完成，所得的便成了负担，于是有了第二个任务：做些什么，以赶走猎禽般盘旋在安定生活之上的无聊。于是，第一个任务是得到什么，第二个任务是忘记所得的，否则所得的便成了负担。

人的生命必是一个错误，这只需略加考察即可证明。人是各种难以满足的需求的集合体，需求的满足别无他物，只是无痛苦的状态，人被无聊所占据；无聊直接证明：存在本身没有价值，因为无聊无非是对存在之虚无的感受。如果生命，以欲求为我们本性和存在的生命，本具正面价值和真正内涵，便不会有无聊一事，存在本身即能令我们完整和满足。实际情况却是，我们从存在本身中并不能获得乐趣，除非我们在追求什么，这样由于遥不可及、困难重重，我们的目标就显得似乎能够令我们满足（而一旦获得，这种假象即告破灭）；或者除非我们正从事纯智力的活动，这样实际上我们置身生活之外远观，犹如戏院里的看客。即便感官愉悦本身也存在于不断的追求之中，目标一旦实现，愉悦随即消失。我们若非从事上述这样或那样的活动，而是回到存在本身，我们便被存在的虚无和徒劳所左右，这种感觉就叫作无聊。

6

人体组织极为精巧复杂，生存意志的体现莫过于此。人体终将化为齑粉，全部本质、所有努力付之一炬——这是大自然明确无误的宣告：意志努力求生，却终归徒劳。若努力本身是有价值的，是理应无条件存在的，则努力的结果绝不应该是消亡。

但我们的开场和收场又有怎样的不同！开场时我们纵情声色，收场时我们肢体分解，死填沟壑。就安适和享受而言，由此至彼之路也一落千丈：快乐梦幻的童年，意气风发的青年，劳碌奔波的成年，虚弱间或悲惨的老年，致命疾病的折磨，最后是死亡的剧痛——难道存在看起来不像一个错误，其恶果渐次昭彰？

我们应尽力把生活看成一个泡影，一个幻灭的过程，因为显然，我们所经历的一切累积起来都在制造幻灭。

论自在之物及其表象的对立

1

自在之物指独立存在于我们感官之外的东西，即实际存在的东西。德谟克里特称其为物质，洛克[2]也大抵如此，对康德来说它等于X，对我来说它是意志。

2

我们对地球的了解仅限于表层，而不是内部广大坚硬的部分。同样，我们依照经验对事物及世界的了解仅是其表象，即其表层。对表象的精确认识构成了最广义的物理学。但表象存在的前提是有一个同时具有面积和体积的内层，并可推论出该内层具有某种性质，这两点是形而上学的主题。力图根据表象的规律获知自在之物的本质，这就像从面积及其定律获知体积一样。每一种教条的先验哲学都想从表象的规律认识自在之物，这就像想让两个截然不同的物体重合一样，必定会失败，因为不管怎么摆弄，总有这个角或那个角露出来。

3

事物既是表象又是自在之物，所以也就有两种解释：物理学和形而上学的。物理学用因果律加以解释，形而上学则用意志加以解释。同一个东西，在无知无觉的自然中称为自然力，在更高一级被称为生命力，在动物和人那里就称为意志。因此严格说来，人的智力及品质的高下与好恶也许可以追溯到纯物理的原因——智力可追溯到大脑和神经系统的构造，以及影响大脑和神经的血液循环；道德品质可追溯到心脏、脉管、血液、肺、肝、脾、肾、肠、生殖器等的构造及综合作用。这样做肯定需要更确切地了解物理学和伦理学的规律，远远超过比沙和卡巴尼斯[3]掌握的知识。某人的智力和道德品质可进而追溯到更远的原因，即其父母的构造，前提是父母提供的种子造就的生命与他们类似，而非更高级或者更好。相反，形而上学必须把同一个人看作其意志幽灵般的化身，该意志完全自由，无比重要，造就了为自身服务、与自身适应的智力。因此，人之所为必从己出，无论他是否一时糊涂，迷失本性，或肉体软弱使然。

4

考量自然生物的生存及习性时，比方说，一个动物站在我们面前，尽管我们有动物学和畜牧学的知识，它仍是一个不解之谜。那么，自然非要如此执拗，对我们的质询充耳不闻？难道自然不像所有伟大之物一样，坦荡、直率，甚至一派天真？自然不予作答，是因为我们问错了问题，因为问题出自错误的假设，因为问题包含矛盾，岂有别故哉！若自然本不可解，永不可解，自然中怎会存在因果关联？不，绝非如此。自然不可解，是因为我们在无因果处强求因果。我们力图抵达自然的本质，借助充足理由律，每一个现象似乎都在透露自然的本质，然而，这无非是我们的智力对表象（即事物表层）的理解方式。在表象的范畴内，因果适用有效，但我们却想将其应用于表象的范畴以外。例如，在表象的范畴内，一只动物的存在可以解释为生殖行为，这其实只是一个最简单的因果推论，没什么神秘可言，这一解释完全打破了不可知的状态。就生殖而言，我们尚缺几个因果联系的环节，但这并没有实质差别，因为即便我们不缺，我们最终仍要站在不可知面前，因为表象就是表象，它变不成自在之物。

5

我们抱怨说，生活一团暗昧，我们并不了解整体存在的本质，尤其是我们自身与其他存在的关系。人生短暂，我们的认识也完全受限于短暂的人生，因为我们既不能追溯生前，亦不能看穿死后，因此吾人之意识如同闪电，只是短暂地照亮夜空。好像有邪灵恶意关闭了我们获取更多认识的大门，以我们的挫折为乐。

但此类抱怨并不合理，因为它来自一种幻想，幻想又出自错误的前提，即认为事物之整体出自智力，因此在成为现实之前，作为理式而存在。由此前提出发，事物之整体因出自认识范畴，便全然可知，全然可解，可为知识所穷尽，但事实恐非如此。我们抱怨所不知的，任何人均无所知，甚或根本无从得知，即不能被觉知。理式乃认识所由，认识所系，但仅是存在的外层，是次要辅助之物，换言之，理式之必要，并非对于事物整体之保有，仅是对于动物个体的延续。因此，事物的整体存在进入认识范畴纯属偶然，程度亦颇为有限——如果动物意识是一幅画，它仅是画的背景，而意志之所求才是关键，位居画面前景。因为偶然，产生了时空世界，即理式世界，此世界在认识范畴之外根本不会存在。既然认识的存在仅是为了动物个体的延续，那么认识的全部构造和所有形式，如时间和空间，亦仅是为个体之目的所造。要达成目的，仅需了解个别现象之间的关系，不必了解事物的本质及普遍整体。

康德曾言，或多或少困扰我们每个人的形而上学问题没有直接的答案，也没有满意的解决方法。究其原因，这些问题源于我们的智力形式：时间、空间及因果关系，而智力原为个体意志规定动机，即说明意欲的对象及占有的方法。一旦智力被滥用，引向事物的存在本身，引向世界的整体和内在构成，则上述智力形式——事物间的相邻、相续、相关——即产生种种形而上问题，如起因与目的、世界及个人的始与终、个体死后的消亡或存续、意志的自由，等等。不妨假设，这些形式一旦消除，对事物的意识却仍存在，那么此类问题便不是悬而未决，而是根本不存在的——这些问题将彻底消失，表述问题的语句将毫无意义，因为此类语句完全来自这些形式，而这些形式的目的不是理解世界及存在，仅是理解我们自身的愿望。

这种看待问题的方式，解释并客观证明了康德的理论，而康德对他的理论仅从主观角度加以证明。康德认为，因果形式只能应用于世俗领域，不能应用于超验领域。不妨换一个角度：智力是形而下的，不是形而上的，因为智力从属于意志的客观化，来源于意志，仅为服务意志而存在。然而，智力的作用仅限于自然中的事物，而不是自然之外之上的事物。显然，动物的智力只为发现和获取食物，智力的发达程度取决于这种目的。人也没什么两样，只不过人保有和延续自身更难，欲望不断膨胀，因此需要更发达的智力。仅当智力超越常规，摆脱意志的奴役时，智力才有富余，当富余达到一定程度时，就叫作天才。这样的头脑首先是客观的，但也可以更进一步，某种程度上成为形而上的，或至少努力成为形而上的，因为智力保持客观的结果是，自然本身即事物整体成为智力的考察对象。在这样的智力里，自然第一次认识到：自身存在，但也可不存在，或以其他形式存在。而在平平无奇的智力中，自然不能清晰地觉知自身，正如磨坊主听不到研磨机的声音，或香料生产商闻不到香料的气味。寻常智力囿于自然，认为自然是理所当然之事，只有灵光一闪时，它才能感知到自然，对其所见大感惊奇，但惊奇感随即消失。这样平庸的头脑就算成千上万，在哲学上能取得怎样的成绩也就不难想见了。但如果智力源自形而上学，以形而上学为使命，就能推动哲学的发展，正如推动其他科学的发展。这样的智力越多，推动作用就越强。

论对生存意志的肯定与否定

1

造就世间现象的，也能不如此作为，乃至不作为，这可以说是一个显而易见的公理，总的说来不言自明。倘若前一种状态构成了生命中有所求的现象，那么后一种状态则构成了无所求的现象，这实际上等同于吠檀多哲学的深睡境和佛教的涅槃。

否定生存意志绝不意味着物质的消亡，仅仅意味着无欲无求——先前不断欲求的不再欲求。意志如同自在之物，我们只能通过欲求行为来了解。因此，无求之后，意志为何物，会做些什么，我们既不能言说也无法觉察。因此否定生存意志对我们而言，是从有到无的转变，我们是欲求的现象。

2

希腊伦理学和印度教伦理学之间存在着明显的对立，前者的目标（虽然柏拉图除外）是实现幸福的生活，有福的生活，而后者的目标则相反，《数论颂》开篇便直言：要彻底从生活中解救出去。

还有一个类似的对立，因其直观而更加突出：你在佛罗伦萨的美术馆里看到美丽的古代石棺，上面用轻快的笔触描绘整个婚礼的仪式，从最初的求婚到婚姻之神用火炬照亮通向婚房的道路；接着比较一下基督教的棺材，上有十字架象征悲痛，盖着黑色帘幕，其间的反差极为明显。两者都渴望在面对死亡时提供安慰，两者方法相反，但都是正确的。一个表达的是对生存意志的肯定，不管生活的面貌如何瞬息变幻，生活永远受到肯定；另一个则通过苦难和死亡的符号来表达对生存意志的否定，以及从死亡和撒旦统治之下的世界中抽身而出的救赎。古希腊—罗马异教与基督教之间真正的精神对立是肯定生存意志和否定生存意志，这是基督教的唯一可取之处。

3

我的伦理学与其他欧洲哲学家的伦理学，两者关系正是教会意义上《新约》和《旧约》的关系。《旧约》把人置于律法之下，但律法并不能带来救赎。相反，《新约》宣布律法是不够的，实则把人从对律法的遵从中解放出来。[4]《新约》宣扬神的恩典以取代律法，人可通过信仰、善心和彻底否定自我进入神恩的国度。《新约》称，这是脱罪与出世之路，因为撇开新教徒和唯理论者不论，《新约》的真正灵魂无疑是苦行的精神。这种苦行的精神正是对生存意志的否定，从《旧约》到《新约》的转变，从律法至上到信仰至上的转变，从因德释罪到因信得救，从受罪与死的统治到在基督中永生，严格说来表明了从单纯提倡美德到否定生存意志的转变。在我之前，所有的哲学伦理学无论呈现什么面貌，都紧抓住《旧约》精神不放——《旧约》设定了既无根基也无趣向的绝对道德律令，所含道德戒条和禁忌之后，悄然引入了一个独断专行的耶和华。相反，我的伦理学有根基、有目标、有趣向，最重要的是，它从理论上阐明了正义与善良的形而上学基础，并进一步说明若实施得当将最终导致什么样的结果。同时，它坦言世界的可憎本质，并指出解脱之道即在于否定意志。因此，我的伦理学实则是《新约》的精神，此外的一切伦理学都属《旧约》精神，甚至在理论上等同于犹太教，即赤裸裸的暴戾的一神论。就此而言，我的学说可以称为真正的基督教哲学，不管在舍深刻而取浅薄的人眼中，这种说法如何自相矛盾。

4

稍加深思即可发现，欲成为罪，并非因为欲望之间偶然碰撞而招致伤害和罪恶。如果欲望产生的就是这样的后果，那它必然从一开始就根本是有罪的，整个生存意志都应该摒弃。世间充斥的残忍和磨难，实际上只是生存意志以各种形式客观化的必然结果，因此只是肯定生存意志的注脚。人必有死，这证明我们的存在本身有罪。

5

如若从自在之物出发，从生存意志出发来理解世界，你会发现世界的核心和重中之重即生殖行为。相反，若你从表象世界、经验世界和理式世界出发，又会有怎样的不同！这里生殖行为被看作全然孤立的、单独的、次要的，被看作二等事物而应掩盖和隐藏，被看作自相矛盾的反常行为，只是源源不断地提供笑料。然而，对我们来说，这只不过是撒旦在伪装他的把戏——难道人们没有注意到，性欲是这个高尚世界最高明的骗术，只为某个女人钟情痴迷之时尤为如此，因为它承诺的太多，给予的又少得可怜。

女人在生殖行为中的角色从某种程度上说要比男人更加无辜，因为男人给予孩子意志，这是最初之罪，因此也是一切恶的源头；而女人给予孩子认识，这开辟了救赎之路。生殖行为是宇宙的交点，它宣布：“生存意志又一次得到了肯定。”妊娠和受孕则宣布：“在意志之上，又一次加入了认识之光。”这样，认识再一次找到了出离世界的道路，救赎的希望再一次成为可能。

这正说明一个明显的事实：若被人撞见其性行为，每个女人都会羞愧得宁可死去，但怀胎时她们却无一丝羞愧，甚至带着骄傲。原因在于，性交之罪在某种程度上被怀孕消解了，性交承载了两性关系的所有羞耻和丑陋，而怀孕虽与性交密切相关，却始终保持纯洁无辜，甚至有些神圣。

性交主要是男人之事，怀孕完全是女人之事。孩子从父亲那里继承意志和性格，从母亲那里继承智力。后者是解脱之门，前者是禁锢之锁。性交标志着不管认识取得多少进步，生存意志仍旧存在于时间之中；生存意志成为新的肉身，标志着在意志之上，又一次加入了明亮的认识之光，又一次有了救赎的可能，其标志即是怀孕。因此，怀孕光荣坦荡，任行无碍；性交则像一个罪犯，自动遁形。

6

不义之行，邪恶之举，就施行者而言，表明对生存意志的肯定有多强，因此也就标志着他离真正的解脱——即对生存意志的否定——以及出脱世间还有多远，求知之路还有多长，忍受苦难还有多久。就忍受者而言，尽管恶行在形而下意义上是恶的，在形而上学意义上却是善的，就实质而言则是有益的，因为这些行为助他走上真正的解脱之路。

7

世界精神：因此，这就是你劳作和受苦的目的，是你存在的目的，也是此外种种存在的目的。

人：但我从生存中能够获得什么？生存若是充盈的，我得到的只是悲苦；若是空虚的，我得到的只有无聊。我付出那么多辛苦，受到那么多折磨，你能给我的却少得可怜。

世界精神：唯其贫乏，这种报酬对你的辛劳和苦恼来说才是的。

人：怎么会这样！我理解不了。

世界精神：我知道。（旁白）我是否要告诉他生活的价值正在于此，即教他停止对生活的欲求？因为应由生活亲自教会他这一最重要的入门仪式。

论我们的本质存在不能被死亡摧毁

1

你应该读读让·保罗的《塞利娜》，看一看最聪明的头脑如何试图处理它误以为荒谬的问题——他固守一个错误观念不肯抛弃，尽管无法忍受其荒谬，一直深受困扰。[5]这一观念即是我们每个人的意识在死后保持原样，继续存在。让·保罗的这种挣扎和纠结表明：此类真假参半的观念并不像想象中的那样，是有价值的错误，而是绝对有害的——因为将灵与肉错误地对立起来，以及将整个人提高到永存不变的自在之物的位置，使我们不能真正认识到由于表象和自在之物不是一回事，所以我们的本质存在不受时间、因果和变迁的影响，是不可摧毁的。此外，这个错误观念甚至不能被当作真理的替代品，因为理性会不断地质疑其中的荒谬，连其中蕴含的真理也一并抛弃，因为真理只有保持纯粹才能继续存在，真理一受谬误的诱惑，就沾染了谬误的脆弱。

2

日常生活中，如果有人什么都想知道，又什么都不想学，他向你问起死后的存在，那么最恰当也许也是最正确的回答是：“你死后和你生前一样。”因为这个回答暗示，要求某种存在物有开端却没有结束，这样做毫无道理。不过，这个回答也隐含着一层意思——有两种不同的有，因此也有两种不同的无。不过你也许会回答：“不管你死后会是什么样子，即便一切化为乌有，都是自然而然的，适合于你的，正像你现在的机体存在一样，因此你最应该担心的是转变的那一刻。”是的，以成熟的心态考虑这个问题，就会把我们引向这样的结论：我们这样的生命压根不存在反而更好，所以我们不再存在或一段时间不再存在，就像我们原本不曾存在过一样，从理性的角度看来，并不值得我们忧虑。

3

设想有这样一种生物，它们无所不察，无所不知，那么我们死后存在与否这个问题，对这样的生物而言也许毫无意义，因为脱离我们现有的暂时性的个体存在，存在或消亡不再有任何内容，只是无差别的概念。因此，无论毁灭的观念还是存续的观念，都不适用于我们内在的本质存在，即我们皆为其表象的自在之物。因为，这些概念都从时间领域借用而来，而时间不过是现象的形式。另外，我们只能根据物质世界的样子想象：现象性表象之核心不可摧毁，则必定像多变的物质世界一样，稳居时间之内，继续存在。如果表象的核心不再存在，我们则会根据形式的样子想象：承载形式的质料消失，形式也消失，因此我们暂时的终止即是彻底的消亡。这两种观点都是用现象世界的形式套用自在之物。但如果说某物不可败坏，但又不继续存在，对此我们甚至不能形成抽象的观念，因为我们本能上做不到。

然而事实上，新的事物不断出现，现存的事物不断消亡，这应被看成由双镜头装置（大脑功能）制造出来的幻象，我们看待万事万物只能透过这两个镜头，这两个镜头叫作时间和空间，因果关系就存在于时空的相互渗入之中。在这样的条件下，我们所知的皆是现象，我们不知道事物本身是什么样子，即不知道独立于我们感知之外的事物是什么样子。这就是康德哲学的真正核心。

4

人死去，自在之物也化为乌有，这是不可想象的。人类凭直觉可以直接认识到：人的死亡是应时而终的现象——一切现象的形式，而自在之物却不受其影响。我们都感到：我们并非某人凭空创造的存在，因此我们相信，虽然死亡能终结我们的生命，却不能终结我们的存在。

5

越是清楚地觉察到万物脆弱、虚无和梦幻般的特点，你越会清晰地觉察到自己内部存在的不朽，因为上述特点有此映衬方显鲜明，正如要觉察轮船行驶的速度，只能去看静止的河岸，而不是看轮船本身。

6

现时有两半：客观的和主观的。只有客观的一半表现为对时间的直觉，因此不可阻挡地随波逝去；主观的一半站定脚跟，始终不变。唯其如此，我们仍能鲜活地回忆起久远的过去，我们虽深知存在的短暂，但仍意识到自身的不朽。

只要活着，我们就意识到，我们一直站在时间的中段，而绝非其终点。由此可以推知，我们每个人身上都体现着无尽时间不变的中段。恰恰是这一点给了我们活着的信心，而不用始终生活在死亡的恐惧之中。

借助回忆和想象，一个人可以真切回想起早年生活的经历。那么，他就比别人更加清楚贯穿整个时间的一个个现时瞬间的特质。了解到所有现时瞬间的特质，就会明白，最为短促的瞬间乃是唯一永久的东西。通过这样的直觉体认，他就会知道，此刻按最严格意义来讲是现实的唯一表现形式，它的根在我们之内，来自我们内部而非外部。这样，他就不会怀疑自身存在的不可毁坏。相反他会明白，虽然他死的时候会失去客观世界，失去客观世界借以显露自身的媒介——智力，但他的存在却不会受其影响。因为他内部蕴含的现实和外部一样多。

若不承认这些，就得坚持相反的观点：“时间是完全客观和真实的，它独立于我而存在。我只是偶然地被抛入时间之中，我只占有一小部分时间，因此只得到了昙花一现的现实，就像成千上万人一样。现在他们已经化为乌有，我很快也一样。反之，时间是真实的，它会脱离我继续存在。”我认为，这种观点的乖张甚至荒谬之处必明确加以阐明。

也就是说，实则可将生命视为一场幻梦，死亡才是梦醒。但必须记住，个性和个体属于梦中意识而非清醒时的意识，这就是为什么死亡对于个体来说好像是消亡。这样看来，死亡无论如何不应看成转到一个全新的陌生的状态，而是回到原本属于我们的状态，人生不过是从这个状态的暂时脱离。

实际上，意识在死亡中毁灭，但产生意识的却并没有毁灭。因为意识首先依赖于智力，而智力依赖于生理进程——很明显，智力是大脑的功能，也因此受到神经系统和血液循环系统的共同调节，更确切地说，智力受到大脑调节，而心脏滋养、驱动并不断刺激大脑。大脑精巧神秘的结构解剖学可以描述但生理学却不能作出解释，正是从大脑中产生了客观世界的现象及我们的思维活动。不应认为，个体意识，即任何一种意识，能够脱离肉体而存在，因为任何意识的前提都是认知，而认知必然是大脑的功能。确切地说，因为大脑是智力的客观形式。那么，既然智力在生理上是次要的，因此在经验现实即现象领域中是次要的，是生命过程的产物。从心理角度来说，智力也是次要的，与此相反，只有意志才是首要的，无论在哪里都是第一要素。因此，既然意识不直接隶属于意志，而受制于智力，而智力又受制于生理机能，那么意识无疑会因死亡而消失，就像在睡梦或任何一种眩晕或晕厥中消失一样。但是别灰心！消失的是怎样的意识呢？一个隶属于大脑的、肉体性的、和动物一样但相对更加紧张的意识。人的意识和动物的意识没有实质区别，尽管我们的意识最发达。这种意识就其根源和目的而言，无非是帮助动物获取所需的权宜之计。相反，死亡带我们回到的是我们的本原状态，即存在的内在状态，生命诞生、延续、现在走向消亡，这是这一状态的变动性所在。它是与表象世界相对的自在之物的状态。

认知受制于大脑，是非常间接的代用品，正因为如此，它是对现象的认知，因此在本原状态完全是多余的，所以我们才会失去它。对我们来说，认知随着现象世界终止而消亡，认知也只不过是现象世界的中介，并只对它来说有些用处。在本原状态，即便有人让我们保留这种动物性的认知，我们也会弃之不顾，正像瘸子病愈后会丢掉拐杖一样。大脑意识仅适用于现象，仅仅产生现象，如果有人哀叹它消失之际日益迫近，那他堪比皈依基督教的格陵兰岛人——听说天堂里没有海豹，他们拒绝上天堂。

此外，这里讨论的一切都基于一个假设：我们只能设想，一种状态如果不是无意识的，便是有意识的，并且带有一切认知基本形式的印记——主体和客体的分立，能知和所知的分立。但我们必须认识到：知者和被知者均只受我们的动物性所支配，动物性是非常次要的，衍生的，因此绝不是本质生命和本质存在的本原状态。生命和存在可以用其他方式形成，但却不是无意识的。归根结底，我们的内在真实无非是意志，它本身并不具有认知。那么，如果死亡剥夺了我们的智力，我们只是转到无认知的本原状态，它不是无意识的状态，而是一个更高的状态。在那里，主客的对立消失了，因为应知的和能知的实际上将不可分离，一切认知的基本条件（恰恰是这种对立）因此消失了。

7

现在，让我们再一次向外观察而不是向内寻求，我们客观地看待呈现在我们面前的世界，那么死亡对我们来说必是从有到无，出生则将是从无到有，但两者都不是绝对真实的，因为它们只具有现象世界的真实。这样，我们或能逃脱死亡，这也并不比我们司空见惯的生殖行为更加神奇。死去的回到所有生命的起点，也是自身生命的起点。这样看来，我们的生命应被看成从死亡那里得到的一笔贷款，睡眠则是这笔贷款的日利息。死亡明确宣布，它是个体的终结，但个体内含有新生命的种子，因此死去的不会永远死去，而出生的都不是真的新生。死去的已遭摧毁，但种子脱离出来，发育成新的生命，进入存在领域，不知从何而来，不知为何而生。这就是生生不息的奥秘，它向我们揭示：现有生命的内部含有一切未来生命真实的种子，故而现有生命必定已经存在过。因此，每一个当其盛年的动物都在向我们呼告：“为什么要为生命的短促而悲叹？如果不先于我的同类死去，我又如何存在？”不管世界舞台的剧本和面具如何变化，出场的总是同样的演员。我们相对而坐，谈兴渐浓，目光炯炯，嗓门提高，千年之前别人也是这样聚坐谈论——事未变，人亦未变，千年之后仍将如此。阻止我们体会到这一点的是时间的拨弄。

灵魂不死和生生不息的区别显而易见，前者是所谓的灵魂整个进入新的肉体，后者是个体的分解与重构，只有意志继续存在，采取新的生命形式，得到新的智力。

无论何时，都是雄性储存人类的意志，雌性储存智力。因此，我们每个人都是由父母的一部分构成，这些部分通过生殖过程结合，又通过死亡分裂，因此死亡才是个体的终结。我们对此个体的死亡伤痛不已，感觉到我们真的失去了它，但个体之死无非像一个化合物被不可逆地分解。但这里我们不应忘记，我们从母亲那里继承的智力并不像从父亲那里继承的意志那样牢固和绝对，原因在于智力是第二性的，性质仅是形而下的，全然依赖于生物机体。

因此人们可以从两个相对的角度考察每个人。从一个角度看，他是朝生暮死的个体，肩负错谬和缺憾，在时间中有始有终；从另一个角度看，他是不可摧毁的本原存在，客体化为存在的万物。

8

色拉叙马霍斯[6]：简单说吧，我死后会是什么样子？请说得明确！

菲勒里息斯[7]：什么都是，什么都不是。

色：我就知道！用矛盾陈述来回答问题，这把戏太老套了。

菲：用世俗认识所用的语言来回答超验问题，必然导致矛盾。

色：你说，什么叫超验，什么又叫世俗认识所用的语言？我也熟悉这些字眼。我是从我老师那里学到的，但这些只是仁慈上帝的表述，我老师的哲学即建立于此，合理且适当。若上帝存于世间某处，他就是世俗的；若他存于世界之外，他就是超验的。这很清楚，你也能理解。但没人能理解你那过时的康德式的术语，它们到底是什么意思？

菲：超验知识超越一切可能经验，力图如实把握自在之物；世俗的知识则局限于可能经验的樊篱，因此只能谈论现象。你，作为一个人，死亡时走到终点。但你的个体性并非你本质和终极的存在，只是它的表现——你的个体性不是自在之物，只是自在之物的现象形式，以时间的面貌出现，因此有开端也有结束。相反，你的存在本身对时间、开端、结束、特定个体的局限都一无所知，因此个体性不能取消它——它无处不在，无人不有。因此，就前一层意义说，你死时归于空无；就后一层意思说，你死后遍于一切。这就是为什么我说你死后什么都是，什么都不是。你提的问题几乎不可能有更好的简短回答，虽然这个回答确实含有矛盾。之所以如此，正是因为你的生命存在于时间中，但你的永生却在永恒之中，因此你的永生也可以说不可毁坏，但不再存在——这又是一个矛盾陈述了。

色：如果我的永生不包括我个体的继续存在，那你的永生我可一个子儿也不愿意掏。

菲：也许你愿意还还价。假设我保证你的个体将继续存在，但此前得有三个月全无知觉的深睡状态呢？

色：我愿意。

菲：但既然你全无知觉，你就没有时光流逝的观念，因此你熟睡时，清醒的世界时间过去三个月或是一万年对你来说都是一样。因为不管哪种情况，你醒来时都只能猜想你睡了多久。因此你三个月还是一万年之后重获个体都是一样。

色：这倒不容易否定。

菲：但假设，现在一万年过去了，却忘了叫醒你，我想这算不上多大的不幸，因为你不存在的时间比你短暂的存在要长那么多，你对此已经很习惯了。不过可以确定的是，你一点儿也不知道你没被叫醒。如果你知道，推动你现在现象形式的神秘作用在这一万年片刻也没有停止，制造和推动着同类的现象，那你也会心满意足。

色：不，你不能这样骗我放弃我的个体。我已经约定，我的个体应继续存在，我不能让步，接受因机能和现象造成的存在的丧失。我，我，我要存在！我要的是这个，而不是靠别人说服才相信的我的存在。

菲：但看看四周，叫着“我，我，我要存在”的不止你一个，凡有一点儿意识的事物都是如此。因此，你的这种渴望恰恰不是你个人的，而是万物无一例外共有的——他并非来自你的个体性，而是来自存在本身。它存于存在着的万物内部，是万物存在的原因，因此存在本身就能满足这一渴望。这一渴望仅仅适用于此，而不是专门适用于某个特定的个体存在。有此热望的仅间接属于个体，直接而内在的是万物同具、始终如一的生存意志本身。这样，既然存在是意志的自由创造，乃至无非意志的反映，因此就不能脱离意志而存在。不过，意志只能暂时满足于存在，因为永不厌足的根本不可能被满足。个体对意志来说没有差别，无足轻重。表面上个体显得很重要，因为每个人不能直接认识意志，只能直接认识自己。结果，个体以更大的代价保有自身存在，而不是保有同类物种。这样说来，个体性并不完美，反倒是局限，没有个体性不是损失，而是收获。所以不要为自身存在忧虑。是的，如果你了解存在的真谛，看到你的存在是普遍存在的生存意志，这些忧虑对你来说就会是幼稚的、荒唐透顶的。

色：你才幼稚，你才荒唐透顶，你们哲学家都是这样。像我这样的成年人要是在你这样的傻子身上花几分钟，那全是为了打发时间。现在我有更重要的事情去做，再见！

论自杀

1

据我所知，只有一神教即犹太教的信徒把自我毁灭视为犯罪。尤其令人吃惊的是，无论在《旧约》还是《新约》中，都找不到对自杀的禁止，甚至找不到明确的反对。因此，宗教导师只好根据自己创造的哲学来反对自杀，然而他们创造的哲学根基太浅，缺少力量，为了弥补，他们不得不借助一些字眼的力量来表达他们对自杀的嫌恶，也就是说，他们求助于谩骂。于是我们听到，自杀是最怯懦的行为，只有心智失常的人才会犯下这种罪行，诸如此类的陈词滥调；或者毫无理由地宣称，自杀是“错误的”，虽然世间万物中，人最有权处置的是自己的生命。让我们暂且认定这一问题取决于道德情感，然后比较一下以下两个消息带给我们的感受：某个熟人犯下罪行，如杀人、施暴、背叛或偷窃，以及他自愿结束自己的生命。前者会引起强烈的愤慨，要求对他采取惩罚或报复；后者则激起惋惜和悲伤，我们很可能佩服其勇气，而不是给予道德谴责。谁没有亲友主动离开人世？人们想到他们时会心怀厌恶，好像他们是罪犯吗？依我看，反倒应该要求那些教士说说，他们凭什么在讲坛上或书桌上，把很多为我们所尊敬和热爱的人所做的一种行为定义为罪行，并拒绝体面地安葬那些自愿离开人世的人。他们从权威的《圣经》里找不到一点依据，也不能提出一条有力的哲学论证。很显然，人们需要的是理由，而不是空话和指责。即便刑法把自杀定为犯罪，这也不能成为教会这样做的理由，并且这绝对是一个荒唐的立法——什么样的惩罚能阻止一心求死之人呢？如果惩罚的是自杀的企图，也只有自杀未遂者才能受到惩罚。

唯一令人信服的反对自杀的道德论证是，自杀与实现最高道德目标背道而驰，因为自杀表面上是种解脱，却取代了从苦难世界的真正解脱。不过，这种错误和罪行相去甚远，但基督教的教士偏要说自杀是犯罪。

基督教的核心包含如下真理：苦难（十字架）是人生的真正目的，这就是它否定自杀的原因，因为自杀与此目的相悖，而古人立意较低，赞同自杀甚至将其视为荣耀。不过，这种对自杀的反对是出于禁欲的立场，因此必须站在比欧洲道德哲学家高得多的立场上看，这种论证才是有效的。如果我们降低这个立场，谴责自杀就失去了站得住脚的道德理由。因此，一神教的教士狂热地反对自杀——这种狂热既无《圣经》依据也无可信的理由——就一定有秘而不宣的理由：主动放弃生命，对那些宣扬一切皆善的人岂不是一种嘲弄？如果真是这样，那这就成了一神教强制人们乐观的又一例证。一神教谴责自我毁灭，以便不被自我毁灭的行为所谴责。

2

一般来说，惧生甚于畏死，人才会了结其生命。但对死亡的畏惧像看守出口的哨兵，阻止人自杀。如果生命的终点完全是否定性的，是存在的骤然停止，也许每个活人都已了结自己的生命。但死亡也有肯定性的东西：肉体的消灭。这对自杀是一种阻吓，因为肉体是生存意志的现象形式。

战胜畏死之心通常不像局外人看来那样艰难，原因在于精神痛苦和肉体痛苦的对立。肉体痛苦强烈或者漫长，我们就对其他烦恼无动于衷，我们关心的只是好起来。同样，剧烈的精神痛苦让我们对肉体痛苦感到麻木——我们轻视肉体痛苦。事实上，如果肉体痛苦能压倒精神痛苦，就能让我们忘记精神痛苦，获得片刻喘息，因此是有益的。正是这个理由让自杀变得容易：在精神饱受摧残的人看来，自杀引起的肉体痛苦变得毫无意义。

论女人

1

席勒的《女人的尊严》全诗内容丰富，对仗工整，但在我看来，远不如朱伊下列词句更能表达女人的美德：[8]没有女人，我们人生的开端就没了安全，中途少了欢乐，终点缺了安慰。拜伦在《萨丹纳帕勒斯》[9]里更为深情地说道：

稚嫩的生命生长在女人的怀里

是她亲自教你牙牙学语

是她拭去你最初的泪滴

也往往是她

倾听你最后的叹息

当生命垂危

曾经追随她的男人

嫌脏怕苦，纷纷退避

两者都恰如其分地评价了女人的价值。

2

只要看一下女人受造的方式，就可了解女人生来不适合精神或肉体的劳动。她赎清生命之罪不是通过行动，而是通过受苦。她承受生产的痛苦，养育孩子，服从男人——女人理应耐心而快乐地陪在男人左右。大悲大喜、苦活累活不适合她。与男人相比，她的生命之河应平缓流动，波澜不惊，既非幸福得多，也非不幸得多。

3

女人适合做护士和幼师，恰恰由于她们本来就幼稚、愚蠢、目光短浅。一句话，女人终其一生都是大孩子，位于孩子和男人之间的过渡阶段。男人才是真正的人。你只需看看女孩如何和孩子玩闹，整天又唱又跳，然后自问，一个心地最善良的男人与之易地而处，能否作出同样的举动？

4

造化在女人身上设计了一种戏剧用语叫作舞台效果的东西，它让女人以余生为代价，拥有几年超凡的美貌和魅力，此时她让男人想入非非，神魂颠倒，愿意想方设法照顾她一辈子——如果纯粹出于理性的考虑，他几乎不太可能这么做。像对待所有生灵一样，造化用工具和武器装备女人，让她们在最需要的时候得到稳定的生活，同时造化也秉承了一贯的经济原则。雌蚁交配后翅膀脱落，因为翅膀对养育后代来说成了多余甚至有害的东西。大概出于同样的原因，女人经过一两次生产以后通常也就美貌不再。

5

某物愈高贵，愈完美，它成熟得愈晚、愈慢。男人28岁前，理性思考能力和心智还不甚成熟，而女人在18岁时即已成熟，成熟的也仅是某种理性思考能力，极为有限。如是，女人一生都是孩子，只能看到手边的事物，执着于现在，认表象为真实，宁要细枝末节而不顾切要之事。赖理性之力，男人不仅像动物那样只生活在当下，也思考过去和未来，从中发展出预见能力，也产生忧虑和烦恼，常常感觉焦虑。女人因理性力量较弱，理性带来的优点和缺点都更小。女人就心智而论是近视眼，她们能凭直觉看清周围，但视野太窄，看不到远处。因此，不在眼前的、过去的和未来的事物对女人的影响要比对我们男人的影响小得多，这使她们远较男人容易挥霍无度，有时濒于疯狂。女人从心底觉得：男人的任务是赚钱，而她们的任务是花钱。这在男人活着时还有可能，男人一死便无以为继。男人把挣来的钱交给她们，用作家用，更加深了她们的这种想法。女人的这种做法不管有多少缺点，也都有好的一面：女人比我们更注重现在，因此如果现状差堪忍受，她们就比我们更享受生活，这赋予她们快乐的性格，她们因此非常适合为忧心忡忡的男人带来欢乐，必要时甚至带来安慰。

像古代条顿人那样，遇到困难时咨询女人，这绝不是一个坏主意，因为她们看待事物的方式与我们截然不同，她们尤其善于看到达成目标最便捷的路径，看到手边的事物。而这些事物正因为就在我们眼皮底下，往往被我们忽略。另外，女人绝对比我们更加现实，看到的只是事物原貌，而我们一旦兴起，就容易夸大，耽于幻想。

也正是出于这个原因，女人对待不幸的人比男人显得更仁慈，更有同情心。但另一方面，她们不如男人那样正直、诚实、尽职尽责，这是因为她们理智力较弱，通常也就更容易受到当下的、可见的、直接相关的事物的影响，而不易受到抽象观念、前贤遗教、所作决定的影响，总的说来不去顾及远处的、过去的和未来的事物。因此，她们虽具第一种美德，却缺少第二种美德。第一种美德虽然最重要，要想达成却非第二种美德不可。人们因此可以说，女人性格中最大的缺点是缺少正义感，最重要的原因是她们缺乏理性和反思能力，还有一点也很重要：女性软弱，不能依靠强力，只能依靠狡诈，所以女人生来精明，天生喜欢说谎。正像造化为狮子装备了利爪尖牙，为大象装备了长牙，为野猪装备了獠牙，为牛装备了牛角，为乌贼装备了墨汁，它也为女人装备了伪装的能力，供其攻防之用。造化给了男人强壮的体魄和聪明的头脑，但又通过女人伪装的天赋，变相地把男人的力量给了女人。伪装是女人根深蒂固的天性，最愚蠢的女人和最聪明的女人在这方面往往一样。女人一有机会就伪装，这对她们来说就像动物一遇攻击就采取防卫一样天经地义，而且她伪装时感觉好像只是在行使她的权利。不去伪装、完全真实的女人几乎没有。正因为这样，女人能轻易地看穿他人的伪装，想在女人面前装假委实不明智。不过，上述女人的最大缺点及其他相关缺点产生了虚伪、不忠、背叛和忘恩负义。做伪证的女人要比男人多得多，是否应该允许女人宣誓都值得怀疑。

6

为保证人类的繁衍，造化选择了年轻、精壮、英俊的男人，这样种族才不会退化。这是大自然确定不移的意志，意志的表现则是女人的激情。这一法则最为古老，也最为有力。让我们为那些想在这一法则支配下谋求权益的人哀悼吧，因为一旦与此法则抵触，无论他们说什么，做什么，都会被无情地粉碎。因为女人的道德观念虽然隐秘，未曾说出甚至未被觉察，但确是根深蒂固的：“我们有理由欺骗那些把个体权利凌驾在种族利益之上的人，因为他们对女人贡献太少。未来一代要由我们生产，因此种族的强弱和兴衰交付到我们手里，由我们培育。让我们尽职尽责地承担起这个责任吧。”不过，女人不是凭借抽象观念而是凭借个人直觉意识到这一最高法则，她们只能待机会来临用行动来体现这一法则。之后，女人并不像我们设想的那样受到良心的谴责，因为她们心底最黑暗的角落明白：虽然她们的责任与个体相悖，但她们能更好地担负起种族的责任，相比之下，种族的福祉要重要得多。

女人基本上只为种族的繁衍而活，并以此为全部事业，所以她们更关注种族而不是个体，心里也以种族为重，个体为轻。这让她们的性情和举止略显轻佻，总的说来与男人倾向不同。这就是为什么夫妇不和经常发生，甚至司空见惯了。

7

男人和男人天生仅是陌生人，但女人和女人天生就是敌人，原因无疑是同行相轻。男人相轻仅限于同行之间，女人相轻则包括全部女性，因为女人的行业都是一样。就算只在街上走走，她们打量对方的眼神也像归尔甫派和吉伯林派[10]。两个女人第一次见面，肯定比男人见面要多些矜持和虚伪。两个女人互相赞扬，听起来要比男人之间的赞扬更可笑。另外，男人面对地位比自己低得多的人，通常都保留些体恤和人情，上流社会的女人对地位低于自己的人（非指仆人），那种高高在上、不屑一顾的样子让人难以忍受。也许这是因为在女人那里，不同地位的差异更难保持，改变或推翻得更快，因为改变我们地位的因素有上百条，对女人来说却只有一个决定因素：她吸引到的是哪个男人。另一个可能原因是，因为女人都从事同样的职业，她们之间的距离要比男人小得多，因此也就更强调地位的差异。

8

女人矮小、削肩、肥臀、短腿，只有被情欲冲昏头脑的男人才会称其为美，女人的美都来自男人的情欲。女人不应被称为美，而应被叫作不懂审美。无论是音乐、诗歌，还是造型艺术，她们都无动于衷或麻木对待。如果她们装作喜欢，那不过是为了取悦他人而装腔作势。这是因为她们不能对任何事情产生纯客观的兴趣，我想原因如下：男人无论做什么，都力图对事物取得直接的控制，或知晓其意义，或驾驭以强力；但无论何时何地，女人都退而求得间接的控制，通过男人来控制事物，因此女人直接控制的只有男人。因此，出于天性，女人把一切都看成俘虏男人的手段，她们对其他事物的兴趣都是假的，都是迂回路线，无非是卖弄风骚，惺惺作态。看看女人在戏院、歌剧院或者音乐厅里的表现吧，她们像孩子一样漠不关心，即便是最伟大的作品最华彩的段落，她们照旧聊个不停。古希腊人不让女人进戏院，如果真是这样，那他们做对了——人们至少应该能听到演的是什么。实践证明，世界上最聪明的女人也不能在艺术上独树一帜，有所造诣，甚至也不能制造出任何有持久价值的东西，考虑到这一点，人们又能对女人指望什么？这在绘画上尤其突出。女人像我们一样能够掌握绘画技能，事实上也画个不停，但连一幅杰作也画不出，原因正在于她们的头脑全无客观可言，而客观恰是绘画最基本的要求。偶有例外并不能改变这种情况：女人就整体而言，是俗不可耐、不可救药的非利士人，并将一直如此。由于一种荒唐透顶的安排，她们可以享有丈夫的头衔和称号，所以她们不停地鼓动丈夫去实现那些卑劣的野心。从任何一方面说，她们都是第二性，劣等性别。人们可以对女人的弱小怀有同情，但尊重她们则太过荒谬，即便是女人也会因此认为我们自降身份。古人和东方人就是这样看待女人的，他们给女人一个合适的位置，做得比我们强得多。我们还固守古代法国的骑士精神，以及无聊的尊重女人的观念，这是基督教——日耳曼式愚蠢的登峰造极之作，这只会让女人粗鲁傲慢，有时让我们想起贝拿勒斯[11]的神猴——那些猴子知道自己是神圣不可侵犯的，就以为可以为所欲为。

西方的女人，即“太太”，她们的位置摆错了——因为女人绝不应成为我们尊重的对象，不应比男人更趾高气扬，或者享有和男人一样的权利。摆错位置的后果是非常明显的。在欧洲，如果也能让女人这种次等人重归其位，并对尊其为“太太”这种不正常的现象加以限制，那将是一件大好事，欧洲的社会生活、公众生活和政治生活都将大为改观。所有的亚洲人对“太太”现象都会发笑，希腊人和罗马人如果能看到，也会笑出声来。欧洲的太太本不该存在，应该存在的是家庭主妇和希望成为主妇的少女，因此少女应受的教育不是傲慢自矜，而是家政和顺从。正因为欧洲有太太的存在，女性中地位较低者，即大多数，要比同样地位的东方女人不幸得多。

9

在我们实行一夫一妻制的社会里，结婚意味着享有一个人的权利，却担负两个人的义务。不过，法律在承认男女平权的时候，也应同时赋予女人男性的理性思考能力。实际情况是：法律赋予女人不正当的权利越多，实际享受其好处的女人越少。其他女人被剥夺了正当的权利，其人数与享有不正当权利的女人相同。原因在于，一夫一妻制和相应的婚姻法认为女人和男人完全平等（实际绝非如此），结果女人享有本不该属于她们的特权，结婚意味着签订了极不平等条约，小心谨慎的男人在作出如此大的牺牲之前往往犹豫再三。在一夫多妻制的社会里，每个女人都能得到充分的照料，而在一夫一妻制的社会里，已婚女人的人数是有限的，总有很多女人无依无靠，她们若处在上流社会，则孑然终老；若处在底层社会，则被迫从事力所不逮的体力劳动，或被迫卖笑为生，其生活既无欢笑亦无尊严，但由于风气使然，她们对男人的满足是必要的，因此也就形成了一个阶层，得到承认。正因为她们的存在，有男人依靠或有望依靠男人的女人才得以保全脸面。仅伦敦一地便有八万妓女。如果不是成了一夫一妻制的牺牲品，她们的生活又会是什么样子？这些可怜的女人不可避免成了傲慢虚伪的欧洲太太的对照和补充。一夫多妻制对女性整体是件好事。另外，妻子长期患病，或不能生育，或日渐衰老，男人为什么不能再找一个妻子？这样做没有理性的根据。

毫无疑问，一夫多妻制处处可见，应该实行，问题只是如何规范。谁又真正实行一夫一妻制呢？我们都生活在一夫多妻制的社会，至少曾经如此，而结果通常不错。既然每个男人都需要很多女人，那么男人有权利，实则有义务养活更多的女人，这再合理不过了。这也意味着，女人回归本该属于她们的位置，顺从男人，无端索求尊敬和礼遇的太太制度废除了，世界上将只有女人，不再有不幸的女人——这样的女人在欧洲遍地皆是。

论独立思考

1

最大的图书馆如果摆放混乱，还不如小图书馆合用，同样，你可以积累大量知识，但如果不动脑思考，远不如只掌握少量知识，因为只有通过比较各个事实，所知才井然有序，知识才被完全掌握，为你所用。所思必为所知，故应求知；反过来，唯思之方能知之。

你可以自发致力于阅读和学习，但无法致力于思考，思考须被激发，正如火焰须借风势。对思考的对象有兴趣，思考才会继续。兴趣也许是客观的，也许仅是主观的。主观的兴趣仅针对与己相关的事物，客观的兴趣则只属于生而好思之人，对他们来说，思考就像呼吸一样自然。此类人少之又少，正因为这样，大多数学者都难得思考。

2

独立思考和阅读别人的思想，两者对头脑的作用迥异。因此，一开始决定一个人思考或者阅读的因素，差别会越来越大。阅读把不合头脑心境或意愿的思想强加给头脑，就像印章把图案印在石蜡上。头脑全然受制于外部的压力，被迫这样想或那样想，而头脑对此并无意愿或情感上的准备。相反，独立思考时，头脑遵循自己的意愿，思考更大程度上取决于切近之物或者某种记忆。与阅读不同，眼前的事物不会把任何思想强加给头脑，只是提供思考的环境和内容，让头脑去想适合其本性和心境的事物。因此，读得太多会让头脑僵化，正如不断对弹簧施压会让它失去弹性。要想一点自己的想法都没有，最好的方法就是手不释卷。故而，博览群书让大多数人变得更加乏味和愚蠢——他们本不该如此——也剥夺了他们的写作能力。用蒲柏的话说，他们永远在读别人，却从来没人读他们。

3

概而言之，只有我们自己的基本观点才真切，才有生命力，因为我们彻底了解的只有这些。我们读到的他人思想是别人桌子上掉落的面包屑，是陌生来客丢掉的旧衣服。

4

阅读只是独立思考的替代品，阅读意味着让别人左右你的思想。此外，很多书只不过为了说明错误的路有那么多条，听从其指导会怎样误入歧途。只有在自己思想枯竭的时候——这在最智慧的人身上也时有发生——才应该读书。不过，驱除自己的思想来为书籍让路是对圣灵的犯罪，这就好像是抛弃缤纷万象，以便观看植物标本或风景雕刻。

有时，自己苦思良久发现的真理或洞见，可在书中轻易找到，但独立思考得出的结论要宝贵一百倍。只有这样，真理或洞见才能进入你的思想体系，成为不可分割的一部分，成为其中的一员，它和你的思想体系严丝合缝，与其他推断和结论和谐共存，带有你自己思想模式的色彩和印记。它随叫随到，将牢牢扎根在你的头脑中，永不磨灭。这极好地印证乃至诠释了歌德的诗句：

遗产虽为先辈所留

唯先争取方能占有

独立思考者先得出观点，才知道权威说法，因此权威说法无非印证自己的观点。书斋里的哲学家却从权威说法出发，通过收集别人的观点形成自己的观点。后者与前者相比，正如机器人与活生生的人。

学而知之的真理之于我们，正如假肢、义齿、蜡制的鼻子，充其量像移植的皮肤。思而得之的真理则像生来就有的四肢，只有它真正属于我们。这也是思想家和纯学者之间的差别所在。

5

把时间花在阅读上，从书中获取智慧，就像从旅游手册上了解某个国家一样，人们可以得到很多事物的信息，但归根结底，他们对那个国家是什么样子却没有真切、明确、彻底的了解。相反，把时间花在思考上则像亲自造访一个国家，他们熟悉该国，对它有真切的认识，身处其中如鱼得水。

6

独立思考的人之于一般书斋哲学家，就如亲历者之于历史学家，前者用切身体会说话。因此，一切独立思考者原则上都是一致的，歧异只来自立场的不同，因为他们都只是表达他们的客观理解。反之，书斋哲学家记录此人如何说、彼人如何想、他人如何反对，等等，然后他比较、权衡、批评这些论述，以图达到真理，这一点他正像历史批评家。

7

经验本身如阅读一样，只是思考的替代品。经验之于思考，正如吃饭之于消化和吸收。经验主义吹嘘只有它通过种种发现才推进了人类的知识，就像嘴巴吹嘘只有它才延续了躯体的生命。

8

一流头脑的特征是，凡有判断都出自第一手资料。这样的头脑产生的思想都是独立思考的结果，从他们对思想的表达上也处处可以看出这一点。真正独立思考的人像是君王，不肯居于人下。他的判断，就像君王的决定，直接来自他的绝对权能。他不再接受权威，正如君王不受命于人。除了他自己确定的，他不承认任何事物是有效的。

9

在现实领域，不管我们觉得生活多么美好，多么幸福和快乐，我们仍始终处在重力的影响之下，对此我们要不断克服。相反，在思想领域，我们是无躯壳的灵魂，摆脱了重力，没有需求也没有忧虑。这就是为什么世上没有任何快乐能比得上优美多产的思想的灵光闪现。

10

很多思想对思考者来说具有价值，但只有其中一小部分写下来能引起读者的兴趣。

11

只有当出发点是为了给自己提供导引的时候，你的思考才有价值。思想家可分两类：第一种出发点是为了指导自己，第二种是为了指导他人。前者是真正的独立思想家，当得起“独立”和“思考”两个词。他们是真正的哲学家。他们本就认真，他们生活的乐趣和幸福在于思考。后者则是诡辩家，他们想装得像思想家，他们的快乐来自他们希望从别人那里得来什么，这才是他们看重的。一个人属于前者还是后者，可从他的整体风格和方式一眼看出。利希腾贝格是前者的典型，赫尔德[12]无疑属于后者。

12

生存暧昧不清，充满痛苦，转瞬即逝，犹如幻梦。生存问题如此严峻和迫切，一想到它，其他问题和目标都相形见绌。除了极少的例外，人们对此并无明确的认识，甚至好像全无觉察，而只关心此外的种种，或仅为今日及今生动动脑筋。他们或者断然拒绝考虑生存问题，或者满意于一些流行的形而上学观点。我想，每念及此你都会认为：人类被称为“思考着的生灵”，是仅就该词的最广义而言。再见到人们不思考或做蠢事，你也会见怪不怪。相反，你会认识到，动物的整个生命仅是一连串的现在，对过去和未来毫无觉察，一般人的智力范围虽然大于动物，但并不像通常所想的那样大得没有边际。

箴言集

论哲学及智力

1

认识和求知的基础在于不可解之物。每一条解释，中间阶段或多或少，最终都引向这里，正如触探海底的铅锤，或深或浅，但迟早会在某个地方触到海底。对不可解事物的研究衍生了形而上学。

2

当智力服务于意志即实用时，只存在个别的事物；当智力醉心于艺术和科学，即因其自身而活跃时，只存在普遍观念和整体类别，以及关于事物的理式。即便雕塑家在雕刻个别物体时，他也在试图刻画理式和类别。究其原因，意志之所图所求只是个别事物，只有个别事物才具有经验意义上的真实性。相反，观念和种属只能非常间接地成为意志的对象。这就是为什么常人不懂普遍真理，而天才则忽略个别事物——对于天才来说，被迫要与实际生活中的个别事物打交道，是个不堪其负的苦差事。

3

哲学思考的两个基本要求是：第一，直面问题，绝不退缩；第二，不言而喻的，要清醒对待，加以质疑。最后，头脑若要进行真正的哲学探讨，必须无拘无束——它不能有特定的目的或目标，因此也就摆脱了意志的诱惑，从而彻底接受可感世界和自身意识的导引。

4

诗人用意象来展示自己的想象，意象来自生活、人的性格或境遇。他们调动意象，让意象尽可能占据读者的心灵。故而，虽然贤愚殊途、才具迥异，人皆受诗人吸引。相反，哲学家展示的不是生活本身，而是从生活中提取的完成了的思想，因此要求读者也能如己一般严密而深入地思考。唯其如此，哲学的读者少之又少。诗人好比示人以花朵，哲人好比示人以花香。

5

哲学有一个古怪而不足取的定义：纯由观念构成的科学，连康德也如此定义哲学。观念所包含的，仅是从感性知识那里乞讨和借用来的东西，感性认识才是所有洞见真正的不竭之源泉。因此，真正的哲学不能来源于纯抽象的观念，而应立足于内在和外在的观察的经验。将实验和概念相结合，也不能取得任何有价值的哲学成就，但这种做法在古代很常见，当代的诡辩家尤爱采用——我指的是费希特和谢林，黑格尔所做的尤其令人反感，施莱尔马赫在伦理学领域也是这样做的[13]。哲学恰如艺术和诗歌，必须根植于对世界的感知。不管大脑多想高高在上，哲学也不应该是冷冰冰的——整个人，包括大脑和心灵，自始至终都冷眼旁观，不为所动。哲学不是代数，相反，正如沃韦纳格[14]所说：“伟大的思想来自心灵。”

6

仅有敏锐，能使你成为怀疑论者，却不能让你成为哲学家。从另一个方面看，怀疑主义之于哲学，正如反对派之于议会，不仅是有益的，而且是必要的。怀疑主义无所不在，因为哲学无法提供数学所提供的那种证据。

7

我们把一些命题叫作理性的必然要求。对这些命题，我们未经审查即认其为真，我们对此深信不疑，即便想要对其认真审查也无能为力，因为那样做我们就得暂时对其存疑。我们完全听信这些命题，因为当我们刚刚说话和思考的时候，就有人不停向我们灌输这些命题，使之根深蒂固。因此，思考这些命题就像思考本身一样古老，乃至二者不可分离。

8

人们喋喋不休地说：自然科学成就巨大，相比之下，形而上学进展甚微。但又有哪种科学能像形而上学那样，无时无刻不受到权贵、公众、保皇党人全副武装的反对？只要人们要求形而上学去适应教条，它就不能发挥全部力量。各种各样的宗教，或在早期将教条加诸形而上学而使之僵化，或禁止、压制形而上学自由无碍的表达，从而占据了人类的形而上学倾向。因此，人类对最重要和最有趣事物的考察，对其自身存在的考察，或被间接阻碍，或因思想受制而无力实行，人最崇高的倾向乃被重重枷锁禁锢。

9

我们很难发现真理，最主要的原因并非事物呈现假象而导致谬误，也非直接源于推理能力的薄弱，而是由于成见和偏见——这些伪前提挡住了通往真理的道路，就像逆风将船吹离陆地，扬帆转舵均无济于事。

10

普遍真理之于个别真理，正如金币之于银币。普遍真理能转化成诸多相关的个别真理，正如一枚金币可以兑换成一些零钱。

11

从一个命题只能引出此命题所蕴含的东西，即其显义与隐义。但两个命题如构成三段论的前提，则可引出两个命题均不具有的东西，正像身体乃各部件凑合而成，但其性质则为任一部件所不具备。逻辑推论的价值正在于此。

12

光明之于外部的自然界，正如智力之于内部的意识界。智力关乎意志，因此也就关乎身体机能——客观看来，意志即身体机能。这种关系类似光明与可燃物及助燃的氧气的关系。可燃物产生的烟雾愈少，光明愈纯粹；同样，智力与产生它的意志脱离得愈完全，智力愈纯粹。不妨打个更宽泛的比喻：可以把人生看作燃烧的过程，智力就是此过程产生的光明。

13

结合解剖学发现的事实，对自身稍作客观观察，即可得出结论：智力、其物质载体大脑，以及附属的感觉器官，无非是对外部影响的强烈领受，并不构成我们本原的实在。因此，智力之于我们，并不如动力之于植物，或重力与化学力之于石头，在这些形式中只有意志存在。我们的智力无非相当于植物对外部影响的领受，对物理作用和化学作用、对促成或阻碍其生长繁茂的一切的领受。只不过，在我们身上，这种领受升至极高的强度，整个客观世界和理式世界都借此显现。因此，这也是理式世界得以客观化的原因。更形象一点，你可以想象世界上并无动物，那世上便没有可以感知世界的东西，因此世界实则根本没有客观存在。现在设想一些植物紧紧挨着破土而出，各种事物开始作用于它们：空气、风、此植物对彼植物的压力、湿度、温度、光照、电流，等等。设想植物对此类影响的领受渐次增强，将发展出感觉，以及将感觉归因的能力，最终将发展成知觉。世界因而在时间、空间和因果关系中显现。然而，知觉仍只是外部影响对植物领受能力作用的结果。这一图景很好地说明了外部世界仅是现象的存在，使之变得可解。究其原因，知觉无非来自外部影响与积极领受之间的关系，的确没人愿意断言：假定作用于植物的所有自然力，其客观、内在和本原的构成即是如此，即自在之物的世界即是如此。这一图景因此也揭示了：为什么人类智力的范围如此狭窄，正如康德在《纯粹理性批判》中所说的那样。

14

不消说，一有好的想法便应用笔记下。我们有时会忘记做过什么，因此更常忘记想过什么。不过，想法并非我们招之即来，而是遵从自己的意愿。相反，对于那些我们从外界接收来的完备的思想，我们只是学而知之的东西，我们能从书本上再次遇到的观点，最好不要记下，因为一旦记下什么，你就把它付诸遗忘。对待记忆，你得苛刻而专制，这样记忆才能俯首帖耳。例如，有时候我们记不起一行诗句或一个单词，你不应该去查书，而应数周时间不时绞尽脑汁，直到记忆履行其职责。你为某事物开动脑筋的时间越长，一旦获得它就会越牢固。

15

思想的质量（思想的形式价值）来自内部，来自思想的方向；思想的内容则来自外部。因此，我们某时的想法是两种截然不同的因素的产物。正因为这样，思想的对象与头脑的关系正如琴拨和琴弦的关系。这也是为什么看到同样的事物，不同的人会有不同的想法。

16

从以下事实即可见出，常人的智力多么琐碎和片面，人类意识又是多么含混不清：尽管人生朝生暮死、充满变数、迷雾重重，人们却都不去进行坚持不懈的哲学探索。除了极少的例外，大多数人浑浑噩噩地过此一生，与动物没有多大区别，他们与动物的最终区别只是他们能为未来几年作一些筹备。如果他们偶有思考形而上问题的需要，也有各种宗教自上而下事先提供给他们思考的结果。他们有宗教就够了，不管是什么样的宗教。

17

人们几乎相信，我们的思考有一半是不自觉地发生的。我们达成一个结论时，通常并未认真地思考引出此结论的前提。这明显体现在下列事实中：有时某事发生了，我们不可能预知其后果；它对我们自身会有什么影响，我们更不可能作出估计；但它却对我们的整个情绪造成了实实在在的影响，让我们由喜转悲，或由悲转喜，这只能是不自觉思考的结果。在下述事例中这一点体现得更加明显：我对一些理论问题或实践问题掌握了一些实际资料，我并没有再去想它，但几天以后，问题的答案不请自到，呈现在我的脑海中，然而，为什么会这样，对我来说，就像加数机一样，是个不解之谜。这又是一个不自觉思考的例子。几乎可以作一个大胆的生理学假设：自觉思考发生在大脑表面，不自觉思考发生在大脑内部。

18

生活单调沉闷，一段时间以后，人们会发现生活枯燥得难以忍受。幸好，知识和洞见不断推进，我们对事物的理解甚至变得更好、更清晰，这或是经验使然，或是因为我们在不同的人生阶段也在经历着变化，观点或多或少总在改变，因此事物向我们呈现出未知的方面。因此，虽然我们的心智能力在退化，“苟日新，日日新，又日新”仍颠扑不灭，同一事物显得新鲜和不同，带给人生常新的兴味。

19

我们对某事物已有一定之见，对与之相关的新观点就会采取防卫和否定的态度，这很自然。新观点像一个敌人，突破进入我们自身信条的封闭体系，打破了我们由此体系而得的心灵的平静，要求我们付出额外的努力，并宣布此前的努力作废。因此，将我们从错误中拯救出来的真理就像药水，不仅味道苦涩难忍，而且不能立竿见影，须经一段时间才发挥效力。

如果说，一个人容易抱残守缺，一群人情况则更糟。一旦人们有了某种观点，不管经历多少，无论怎样引导，均是徒劳。因此，有一些谬见极为普遍，根深蒂固，无数人每天都在心满意足地重复。我列了一个谬见的清单，其他人可以续写：

1.自杀是懦弱之举。

2.不信他人是因为自己不诚实。

3.真正的价值和才能都是朴实无华的。

4.疯子极其不快乐。

5.可以学会哲学思考，但学不会哲学（反之亦然）。

6.悲剧比喜剧好写。

7.哲学会让人远离上帝，深研哲学会让人重归上帝——自弗朗西斯·培根之后人们一直这样说。

8.知识就是力量。一派胡言！有人学识渊博，但知识没给他一点权力；也有人权势熏天，却几乎没有知识。

这些大多是鹦鹉学舌，未经深入思考，仅仅因为人们第一次听说时，觉得这些观点听起来很睿智。

20

智力是强度的单位，不是广度的单位，就智力而论，一人可抵千人，但一千个蠢人加起来也顶不上一个智者。

21

可怜的平庸之辈到处泛滥，他们缺乏两种密切相关的能力：达成判断的能力和形成自己观点的能力。但不是平庸之辈，就无从了解他们能力的缺乏，也无从了解他们生活的可悲。不过，正因为能力的缺乏，胡涂乱写才能在各国大行其道，超凡脱俗之人才命途多舛。真正的思想和艺术在某种程度上都试图将伟大的头脑置于渺小的人群之上，无怪乎此类尝试难以实现。作家要提供乐趣，须在其思考方式和读者的思考方式之间取得某种一致，两者越是一致，提供的乐趣越大。伟大的心灵只能对另一个伟大的心灵心领神会。出于同样的原因，拙劣或平庸的作家在深思的心灵中引起的是反感和厌恶。和大多数人谈话甚至也有同样的效果，每一步都感觉格格不入。

22

植物的生命只是简单的生存，因此植物生命的乐趣完全是主观、麻木的满足。动物有了认识，但认识仅为其动机服务，实际上服务于当前的动机。这就是为什么动物和植物一样，只要活着，活完一生，就感到心满意足。因此，它们可以几个小时一动不动，并不思考，只是观望，但并无不满或者不耐。只有极聪明的动物，如狗和猿，才会感觉无聊，才有行动的需要，因此它们喜欢游戏，因此它们盯着过路的人看，以此自娱。这方面它们很像随处可见、透过窗户盯着我们看的人，但当我们发现它们是学生，我们就会气愤不已。

只有在人身上，认识，即对他物而不仅仅是自身的意识，才达到了一个高度，并借理智上升为思想。结果，除了单纯的存在，人的生活也有了认识本身。在某种意义上，认识使他超越了自身存在，而在其他事物中获得了第二个存在。不过，人的知识也大多限于为其动机服务，虽然并非总是当下的动机。动机总的来说被称为“实用知识”。相反，受到好奇心鼓动或者需要消遣时，人通常会有自由的，即无目的的知识。不过，这种知识每个人都有，即便仅限于此。同时，当动机消歇，人的生命很大程度上只是单纯的存在，人们的交际即是明证：人们迎来送往，照章办事，主要是待在一起，他们根本不交谈，顶多言辞空洞地说上几句。事实上，大多数人即便不自觉，心底也决意“得过且过，动脑越少越好”，他们把这当作最高行为规范，当作自己的座右铭，因为思考对他们来说太过沉重和艰巨。因此，他们只想谋生糊口所必需之事，只想消遣娱乐所要求之事，这也是他们交谈和娱乐的内容，但交谈和娱乐必用最少的思考就能办到。

只有智力超出生存所需时，认识才多少成为自身的目的。智力的天职是为意志服务，仅仅体察事物之间的关系，因此，如果智力擅离职守以保持纯粹的客观，那将是相当罕见的，艺术、诗歌和哲学的起源正在于此，乃无意得之。就其本质而言，智力是劳工，意志是监工，让它从早到晚忙个不停。但如果有一天，这任务繁重的劳工利用空闲时间主动创作一件作品，出于自己的意愿，没有什么目标，只想做点什么让自己满足和开心，那他创作的必是一件真正的艺术品，推而极之，一件天才之作。

像这样纯客观地运用智力，不仅见于一切艺术、诗歌和哲学成就，总的说来也见于一切纯科学的成就。在纯科学的研究和学习中，在对任何主题的自由思索（即无关个人功利的思索）中，这样的智力运用已经出现。即便几句简单的交谈，如果主题是纯客观的，无关谈话者的利益因此也无关其意志，同样需要客观地运用智力。纯客观运用智力与主观运用智力——即为个人利益运用智力，不管多么间接——相比，如同舞蹈与走路之间的关系。像舞蹈一样，客观运用智力是多余精力的释放，没有什么目的；相反，主观运用智力显然合乎天性，因为智力就是为服务意志而产生的。在工作和个人努力中，在一切关乎个人事物和物质的谈话中，在吃喝玩乐中，在有关谋生的种种事物中，在任何一种功利的考虑中，都有智力的主观运用。的确，大多数人不能将智力用作他用，因为对他们来说，智力只是服务于意志的工具，智力全部用于这个任务，毫无保留。正因为这样，他们才变得这么乏味，这么古板，不能进行客观的交谈。从他们的脸上似乎可以看到，智力被牢牢捆在意志之上。因为这样，他们的表情常常给人目光短浅的印象，令人压抑，但这无非表明：他们整个知识储备受制于自身意志。我们可以看出，特定意志为达成其目的需要多少智力，他们就有多少智力，多一点也没有。因此，他们外表粗俗，一旦没有意志的驱使，智力就停滞不动。他们对什么都没有客观的兴趣。如果事物与他们没有直接的或者至少是可能的关系，就引不起他们的注意，更不必说触动他们的心灵。机智或幽默甚至显然都不能打动他们，需要动一点脑筋的事情他们都痛恨。低俗的滑稽顶多让他们大笑几声，除此之外，他们就是麻木的野人。凡此种种，都是因为他们只能产生主观的兴趣。这也正是打牌为什么成了最适合他们的娱乐，因为打牌赌钱和舞台剧、音乐、交谈不同，它不属于纯粹的认识，而是对意志的调动——意志是无所不在的首要因素。除此之外，他们从生到死都是商人，是天生为生活奔波的苦工。他们的一切快乐都来自感官，其他快乐他们感觉不到。和他们交谈只能谈生意，不能谈别的。和他们交往是自降身价。相反，两个能对智力进行某种纯客观运用的人，他们的交谈是自由的智力游戏，虽然他们谈话没有实质内容，只是嬉笑怒骂。这样的交谈实际上像双人舞或群舞，而另外一种交谈则像正步走：一个挨一个或一个跟一个，只为了到某个地方去。

天才喜欢对智力进行自由的因此也是超常的运用，而且他们有这个能力，这样在天才那里，知识成了整个人生最重要的事情和目的，他自身的生存反倒退居其次，仅仅是一种手段。这样，正常的次序完全颠倒了。有了对世界的认识和理解，天才不是生活在一己之内，而是生活在世界之中。他的认知能力完全向着超常的方向发展，因此他不可能把时间都花在单纯的生存及其目的上，他的头脑需要保持充实和活力。他因此不能淡然经历人生百态，像常人一样对日常生活热衷关切。一般的智能适合一般的现实生活，因此天分在常人眼中成了病态，甚至像所有超常之物一样，成了阻碍。由于智能的增强，对外部世界的直觉体认极为客观明晰，远远超过意志所需，反倒妨碍了智力为意志服务，因为他们考虑的是现象本身，为现象本身而考虑，而不去考虑现象与个人意志的关系，或现象与现象的关系，因此也就干扰和妨害了对这些关系的考虑。要服务意志，对事物作些肤浅的思考就足够了。我们只需考虑事物与目的的关系，以及目的与什么有关。因此，我们考虑的只是关系，此外的一切一概视而不见。客观充分地思考事物的本质，会削弱这种认识，使之陷入混乱。

23

诚然，天才与常人的智力只有量的区别，即只是程度的区别。不过，常人尽管个个不同，却都有固定的思维模式，因此常常众口一词，赞同一些实则错误的判断，乃至怀抱一些基本观念，一代代流传重复；而每个时代的伟大思想家都或公开或秘密地反对这些观念。考虑到这一点，我们难免要说：天才与常人的智力是质的区别。

24

在天才的头脑里，理式世界极为清晰，并鲜明地显现出来。最有分量和最深刻的思想不是通过对个别和孤立的事物苦苦观察而得的，而是要尽量全盘考虑。故而，人类有望从天才那里得到最深刻的指导。因此也可以说，天才对事物有极为清醒的认识，所以对与事物相对的人也有着清醒的认识。有能力揭示事物及人类本质的天才，人类应当崇敬。

25

若要赢得同时代人的感激，你要与他们步调一致，但这样你就无所建树。若有不凡的想法，你得对后代说。的确，这也许会使你在同时代人中默默无闻。你好像被迫在荒岛上度过一生，辛辛苦苦树立起纪念碑，好让后代的海员知道你曾经存在过。

26

能人为金钱和名誉而工作，但天才苦苦耕耘的动机却不容易确定。不是钱，因为天才很少有钱；也不是名，名誉太不确定，更深一层考虑，价值甚少。严格地说，天才工作也不是为了自己的乐趣，因为付出的大量辛劳几乎超过了获得的乐趣。不妨说，天才工作是出于某种奇特的本能，他们对其他动机并不了解，只是不得不付出长期的劳作，表达他们的所见所感。笼统而论，树木结果也出自同样的必要，它向世界索取的只是一块土壤，好让它开花结果。更深一层考虑，似乎在天才身上，生存意志像人类精神一样发觉，智力罕见地暂时明澈起来，现在它要为全人类索取明澈思想之所得——这实则也是天才的本性——以便让天才的思想之光照亮常人暗昧无知的头脑。正是这个目的驱使天才孤军奋战，不求回报、掌声和同情，甚至忽略个人安乐，更多地想着后代而不是当代，因为他的时代只会把他引入歧途。天才把他的工作当成神圣的事业，当成自己存在的真正目的，当成全人类的财产，他留下作品，为了更能理解他的后代。这成了天才最重要的目标，为此目标，他头戴荆冠，但荆冠总归会长成桂冠。他努力完成并守护着他的作品，坚定得就像守护虫卵、孵育未来族群的昆虫——虽然它看不到那一天。它把卵产在一个地方，知道那里有一天会有新的生命茁壮成长。然后，它心满意足地死去。

论美学

1

美的形而上学，其核心问题可简述如下：客体与欲望无关，如何能引起我们的愉悦？

我们都认为：某物只有与我们的意志或我们习惯所称的目的发生关系，我们对其才能产生愉悦，因此有愉悦而无意志的激发，听起来像是自相矛盾。美与我们的个人目的即意志无关，但显然能引起愉悦。

我对这一问题的解答是：在美的事物中，我们总能觉知生物界与非生物界内在和本原的形式，即柏拉图所说的理式，由此衍生了无意志参与的认识主体，即无关目的或意愿的纯粹智能。这样，当审美发生时，意志完全从意识中消失，而意志是我们所有烦恼和痛苦的唯一根源，审美伴随的愉悦感由此产生。痛苦连根去除，愉悦因此建立。有人也许会反对：如果那样，愉悦也会连根除掉。不要忘记，我常说，喜足无非是痛苦的消歇，其本质是否定的，痛苦则是肯定的。因此，当欲望全从意识中消失时，仍有愉悦产生的条件——愉悦是无痛苦，此时痛苦甚至无从产生，人从意欲着的主体一变而为纯认知的主体，但仍对自身及其行动了然于心。我们知道，作为意志的世界是第一世界，作为理式的世界是第二世界。前者是欲念的世界，因此有痛苦，有重重磨难；后者实无痛苦，另含一奇妙境界。此境界意义非凡，至少悦人耳目，对此境界的欣赏就产生了审美愉悦。

2

想象力隶属于意志，它之所以产生和存在，即是为意志或个人服务，这是它唯一的天职和常务。若个体意志能放任想象力片刻，使其暂免职责，全获自由，又不失充沛活力，或尽力发挥知觉能力，则想象将立刻变得完全客观，成为忠实反映客体的镜子，更确切地说，意志以想象为媒，客观化为或此或彼的客体，客体的核心本质借由想象呈现，知觉时间越久，呈现得越完全，直至知觉穷尽。有纯主体，才有纯客体，即意志在所知之物中的充分显现，这正是（柏拉图的）客体的理式。不过要有此觉知，思考客体时便须将客体在时空中的位置剥离出去，因此也就剥离了其个体性——正是这种恒受因果律支配的位置，使得客体与作为个体的我发生某种关系，因此只有将此位置与意志分离，客体才成为理式，我才因此成为纯粹的认识主体。正因为这样，一幅画将飞逝的瞬间永远固定下来，因而将其从时间中解救出来，它所展现的不是个体，而是理式，是变动中的不变因素。不过，这种假定的主体和客体的改变要实现，不仅需要将认识能力从原本的从属地位中解放出来，完全听命于自己，还需要认识能力保持最大程度的活力，尽管此时缺少自然激发其活动的东西，即意志的刺激。这正是为什么主体和客体难以改变，也很少改变。因为我们的所想所图，所闻所见，本质而言都直接或间接地服务于数不胜数、或大或小的个人目的，因此正是意志激发了认识能力充分发挥其功用，没有意志的激发，认识能力立刻减弱。此外，受意志激发而得的认识，对现实生活，甚至对各种科学门类，便已足够，因为各类科学都指向事物之间的关系，而不是本质和内在的存在。只要知识关乎因果，或关乎依据和结论，也就是说，属于自然科学和数学，或关乎历史和发明，所求之认识必为意志的目的；意志越是努力寻求认识，得到认识的速度越快。同样，在国家事务、战争、财政、商业以及种种谋划方面，意志必先运用其欲望的威力，驱使智力全力探求所考察问题的前因后果。此时意志的激发力如此巨大，能让智力超常发挥，实在惊人。

当觉知事物客观、本质的存在时，情况极为不同。事物客观、本质的存在构成事物（柏拉图式的）理式，也存在于一切美术成就之中。前一种情况，意志鼓动人去努力，意志与努力不可分离；后一种情况，意志毫不介入，只有智力依靠自力，用自己的方式自愿无偿展现它取得的成果。只有把意志及其目的从人身上彻底去掉，同时去掉人的个体性，具备纯粹认识的条件，纯客观的觉知才能出现，事物（柏拉图式的）理式才能被理解。然而，此觉知必先于概念，即最初的直觉认识。这一认识继而构成内在的质料及核心，它是真正艺术品、诗歌乃至真正哲学的灵魂。天才可遇而不可求的灵光闪现总是为人称道，正因为最初的艺术认识与意志完全分离，完全独立，是非意志的。

3

可以说，该审美的客观方面，即（柏拉图式的）理式，便是去除我们知识的形式条件和主观条件——时间以后呈现在我们面前的东西，正如去掉万花筒的镜片后呈现在眼前的东西。例如，我们看到蓓蕾长成花朵，然后结成果实，惊叹生生不息的动力。如果我们了解到，虽有上述生长变异，我们面前却有唯一不变的植物的理式，惊奇便会消失。不过，我们不能把植物的理式觉知为蓓蕾、花朵和果实的统一体，而只能通过时间形式加以了解。通过时间，智力把理式看作从蓓蕾到果实的一连串状态。

4

诗歌和造型艺术总以个别事物为主题，不厌其详地展现其独特性，甚至最无关紧要的细节也不放过。科学借概念而行，一劳永逸地将独特之处加以界定并描述，将其归为一类，每个概念都代表无数个体。考虑到这些，你也许会觉得艺术创作琐碎、微不足道，甚至幼稚。然而，艺术的特质在于，艺术以一代多，它对个体精描细摹，目的在于揭示个体所属种类的理式。因此，一件事，一个生活场景，经过准确充分的刻画，即通过对个体的细致描述，从某个侧面体察人性本身，从而产生对人性本身清晰深刻的认识。正像植物学家从万绿丛中撷取一朵花，加以分析，以便向我们展现植物的共同特点，诗人也从躁动纷繁、无休无止的生活中选择一个场景，有时仅是一种情绪或感觉，以便向我们展示生活和人性。正因为如此，我们看到，莎士比亚、歌德、拉斐尔、伦勃朗等大师不耻描摹单个、甚至不引人注意的事物。他们殚精竭虑，穷其根本，探幽发微，因为特殊、个别的事物只有变得显明才能把握。正因为如此，我把诗歌定义为一种用语言让想象动起来的艺术。

5

一件造型艺术品并不像实际事物一样，向我们展示昙花一现的东西，即构成具体事物和个别事物的特定质料与特定形式的结合，它向我们展示的仅仅是形式；若艺术品完整赅备，则向我们展示理式本身。因此，一看到画面，我们立刻离开个体事物，走向纯粹形式。形式与质料的分离是迈向理式的一大步，每件造型艺术品，无论绘画还是雕塑，都体现了这种分离。艺术品的美学目的在于让我们认识（柏拉图式的）理式，理式的特点就是形式与质料的脱离和分立。艺术品的本质是仅仅展现形式而不展现质料，并展现得鲜明了然。这正是为什么蜡像不能带来审美感受，因此也不是（美学意义上的）艺术品。制作精美的蜡像比最出色的画作或雕像显得真实得多，如果对现实的模仿是艺术的目的，蜡像可拔头筹。但蜡像展现的不仅仅是纯粹形式，还有质料，因此产生一种假象，好像原物就在眼前。真正的艺术品带我们远离那些昙花一现的东西，即个体，走向长存不变并不断重现的东西——纯粹形式或理式；但蜡像展现的似乎是个体本身，即昙花一现的东西，而不展现能为朝生暮死带来意义的东西。蜡像没有生命。唯其如此，蜡像勾起一种恐怖感——它仿佛一具僵尸。

6

我们年轻时的观感之所以重要，在人生的黎明，一切之所以像是沐浴着完美无缺的光辉，都是因为那时我们刚刚通过个别事物对类别开始熟悉，类别对我们还是新鲜事物，所以每个个体事物都代表其种类。在此我们掌握了种类的（柏拉图式的）理式，理式即是美的本质构成。

7

人的形体美丽与优雅合一，是意志客观化最高阶段的最显明形式，因此成为造型艺术的最高成就。另外，每个具体事物都是美的，因此每个动物也是美的。如果某些动物似乎不那么美，那是因为我们未能纯客观地看待它们，因此不能理解其理式。我们总不免有一些联想，通常是胡乱类比，阻碍了我们对动物之美的感受。例如，我们把猿同人类相比，不去把握猿的理式，而把猿看成夸张丑陋的人。蟾蜍与泥土的类比也产生同样的效果，虽然这不足以解释很多人看到这种动物为什么会感到极度厌恶，甚至感到惧怕和恐怖，就像另一些人看到蜘蛛一样——这似乎肇始于更深、更玄、更神秘的联系。

8

无机界若没有水，呈现不出生命的迹象，会给我们一种非常阴郁甚至压抑的印象，其中一例是土伦[15]附近的长峡谷，岩石荒凉，通往马赛之路从中穿过；但非洲的沙漠给人的印象则远为宏大和震撼。无机界给人的印象之所以悲凉，最主要是因为无机界全然受制于重力，而地心引力支配一切。相反，一看到草木，我们油然而生欣快之情，植被越是葱茏繁盛，越是自由生长，欣快之情便越强烈。最直接的原因是，植物似乎克服了地心引力，生长的方向恰与被重力左右的物体相反，因而明确宣布：生命现象是更新更高级的事物等级。人类自身便是这种等级的一部分，生命现象是我们的本性所在，也是我们存在的要素，有了它我们便欣欣然。因此，看到植物世界，最让我们愉快的是植物垂直向上，树林中有杉木拔地而起，会让树林增色不少。相反，伐倒的树不能打动我们。

事实上，歪歪斜斜的大树产生的效果要远小于挺直的树。柳树枝条低垂，听命于地心引力，才得了“弱柳”的称号。水也是无生命的，但水流动性强，总是波光闪耀，很大程度上抵消了它产生的阴郁感觉。水流给人生命的感觉，此外，水也是我们生命的首要条件。

9

人谋生靠缪斯的恩赐，我是说诗才，对我来说，就像女子谋生靠美貌，两者都是亵渎自身天赋，换取卑劣好处，两者都易色衰力弛，蒙羞收场。别把诗神贬低为妓女。

10

音乐是真正的通用语言，无论哪里的人都能理解。因此，每个国家，每个时代，总有人热切而严肃地讲这门语言。一段意蕴丰厚的旋律很快能传遍全球，一段言之无物的旋律立刻销声匿迹，这说明，旋律的内容很容易理解。不过，音乐讲述的不是事物，而是纯粹的悲喜。悲与喜，对意志而言是唯一的真实。因此，虽然音乐不直接诉诸头脑，对心灵却有千言万语。要求音乐打动头脑是滥用音乐，画面音乐就是这样，因此总是遭到反对。即便海顿和贝多芬，也曾误入歧途，创作画面音乐，据我所知，莫扎特和罗西尼则从不这样做，因为表达激情和描绘事物是截然不同的两码事。

11

大歌剧算不上真正的纯艺术作品。相反，它堆砌各种方法，拼凑迥然不同的印象，以人数取胜强化效果，试图提高审美愉悦，可谓粗俗不堪。而音乐是最有力量的艺术，仅凭音乐本身就牢牢抓住敏锐的心灵。事实上，若要正确理解和欣赏音乐杰作，需要全神贯注，好把全部身心都交给音乐，涵泳其中，以便理解音乐那至为亲切的语言。与此相反，高度复杂的歌剧场面宏大，舞台绚丽，灯光和色彩缤纷生动，这一切都通过眼睛侵入观赏者的内心，同时头脑要兼顾剧情，这都让头脑变得散乱迷惑，注意力不能集中，因而对神圣、神秘、亲切的音乐语言感之甚少。这些附加的东西都与音乐目标的实现背道而驰。

严格说来，歌剧可谓不合音乐本质的发明，为不懂音乐的人而设——音乐首先得借助与之格格不入的媒介蒙混过关，如伴随一个冗长、老套、酸溜溜的爱情故事和打油诗。富有生气、言简意赅的诗歌与歌剧音乐长度不相匹配，因此对歌剧剧本毫无用处。

只有弥撒和交响乐才能带来专定完整的音乐享受，而在歌剧中，音乐不幸与无聊的戏剧及讽刺诗结伴而行，必须尽力承受本不属于它的负担。伟大的罗西尼在剧本中有时也失之尖刻，尖刻绝非音乐的特点。

大歌剧长达三个小时，让我们的感受力越来越麻木。一场琐碎的戏往往慢似蜗牛，考验我们的耐心。大歌剧总体而言，其本质就是沉闷。只有个人成就超强，才能弥补这一缺陷。这就是为什么在歌剧这种艺术形式中，只有上乘之作才令人赏心悦目，一切中等水平的作品都让人无法忍受。

12

戏剧是人类存在的最佳反映。总的说来，有三种理解戏剧的方式。第一阶段，也是最常见的阶段，戏剧限于趣味——我们关注剧中人物，因为他们在追求与我们类似的目标，情节靠谋划、角色性格和巧合来推动，全剧靠机智和幽默调节。第二阶段，戏剧诉诸情感——英雄引起我们的怜悯，我们从英雄身上看到自己，情节的特点是悲怆，最后复归平静释然。在悲剧力图达到的最高也是最难的阶段，呈现在我们眼前的是悲伤苦难，生活的不幸，最终的结果是挣扎的徒劳。我们深受触动，受到直接影响或感同身受，对生活产生厌离之情。

13

常言道：万事开头难，但在表演艺术中情况正好相反——结尾是最难的。无数戏剧前半部分让人充满期待，但到了恶名昭著的第四幕，就变得混乱、动摇、摇摆不定，结尾生硬、令人不满，或者是所有人早就想到的结局。有时候，就像《爱米丽娅·迦洛蒂》[16]一样，结局甚至让人生厌，观众满心沮丧地离开剧场。结尾的难度部分在于把水弄混总比弄清容易，也部分因为，在戏剧开头，我们允许剧作家自由发挥，但到了结尾我们则有了明确的要求。我们要求结尾要么大喜，要么大悲，但人情百态很难如此泾渭分明。我们进而要求结尾要自然，要公平，要水到渠成，但同时又要出乎观众的意料。

小说描绘的内在生活越多，外在生活越少，就越高级。这种关系应成为每种小说的标志，不管是《项狄传》还是粗俗野蛮、情节夸张的传奇。的确，《项狄传》没有情节，但《新爱洛绮丝》和《威廉·迈斯特》[17]的情节又如何之少！甚至《堂吉诃德》的情节也很少，仅有的情节也无关紧要，和几个笑话差不多。这四部作品都是小说的巅峰之作。再想想让·保罗，他那些精彩的小说栩栩如生地描写了多少内在生活，对外在的依赖又何其少！即便是瓦尔特·司各特的小说对内在生活的重视也远远超过外在生活，后者无非作为背景出现，好让内在生活生动起来。而在拙劣的小说中，外在生活只为自身存在。艺术就是让内在生活尽可能地生动，因为内在生活才是我们真正的兴趣所在。小说家的任务不是叙述大事，而是让小事变得有趣。

论书籍与写作

1

作家可分为流星、行星和恒星三种。第一种效果短暂，你抬头凝望，叫声“看啊”，它们就永远消失了。第二种是行星，持续的时间要长得多。因为离得近，它们往往要比恒星更亮，无知的人误以为它们就是恒星。但它们必定也会迅速退场，何况它们的光亮是借来的，它们的影响仅限于同行者（同时代的人）。只有第三种始终不变，牢踞天宇，靠自身发亮，影响遍及各个时代。由于没有视差，它们的外观不会随着我们视角的改变而改变。与其他星体不同，它们不仅仅属于一个系统（国家），而是属于整个宇宙。正因为太高，它们的光线才需要那么多年才能到达地球人的眼睛。

2

作家总共分两种：一种不得不写，一种为写而写。前者有一些想法和经验，自觉需要与人分享；后者缺钱，他们写作的目的就是赚钱。他们思考是为了写作。你可以根据以下特点认出他们：他们竭尽全力把观点拖长，他们的观点半真半假、暧昧不清、做作多变，他们通常更爱暮色沉沉，以便蒙混过关。正因为这样，他们的作品既不精确也不清晰。你很快就会发现：他们写作仅仅是为了用字把纸填满。一旦看清这一点，你就会把他们的书扔到一边，因为时间宝贵。稿酬和版权实际上害了文学。只有不得不写，才能写出有价值的作品。金钱好像带有某种诅咒，只要一为报酬写作，任何作家都写不出好作品。最伟大的作家创作最杰出的作品时，都没有报酬或报酬极少。西班牙的一句谚语说得很妙：荣誉和金钱装不进同一个口袋。

大众有一种愚蠢的愿望——只读印出来的东西，一大群拙劣的作家以此为生，他们叫作报刊作家。真是个好名字！英语中“报刊作家”的意思就是“日工”。

3

作家也可以分为以下三类。第一类作家写作但不思考，他们的写作素材取自记忆、回忆录，甚至直接取自别人的著作，此类作家人数最众。第二类作家边写作边思考，他们为了写作而思考，这样的作家很常见。第三种作家动笔之前先已思考，他们写作只是因为之前的思考，此类作家很罕见。

即便那些动笔之前已认真思考的少数作家，思考主题本身的人也少之又少，其他人思考的都是书，都是他人对主题说过什么。也就是说，得有他人的想法在旁边用力推一下，他们才能思考。于是这些想法成了他们直接的话题，因此他们总受别人影响，也就永远不能有创见。相反，上述少之又少的作家，他们思考是受到主题本身的触动，因此他们的思考紧紧围绕着主题。只有在他们当中才能找到生命力长久乃至不朽的作家。

作家所写直接出自自己的头脑，他的书才值得一读。

4

书无非是作者思想的记录。这些思想的价值或在质料，或在形式。质料是指作者的思考建立在什么之上，形式是指作者处理质料的方法，即对质料的思考是什么。

思考所由建立的质料多种多样，这是它赋予书籍的优点。一切经验的素材，即狭义或广义上符合历史或自然规律的事物，都属此类。质料的特征在于客体，因此一本书可以很重要而无论其作者为谁。

至于对质料的思考，其特征则在于主体。所写题目可能所有人都懂，所有人都熟悉，但这里带来价值的是理解质料所采取的形式，是思想的内容，这取决于主体。因此，这样的书如果值得称道、卓尔不群，其作者也是如此。因为这个原因，一个值得一读的作家得益于质料越少，甚或质料越为人熟知，越被广泛采用，该作家便越是伟大。因此，古希腊三大悲剧家都采用同样的质料。

一本书出名以后，你应该分清楚是因为其质料还是形式。

大众对质料远比对形式感兴趣。这种倾向表现在对待诗歌作品的荒诞态度上。他们费尽心机，四处搜罗触发作品创作的真实事件或个人经历，是的，他们对这些东西比对作品本身更感兴趣。因此，他们更多的是在读歌德其人而非其书，他们付出更多辛苦研究浮士德的传说而不是浮士德这个人物。毕尔格曾说：“他们会一本正经地研究莱诺蕾到底是谁。”[18]我们看到，这句话再次在歌德身上应验了。重质料而轻形式，这就好比一个人看到美丽的伊特鲁里亚古瓮，只为对颜料和黏土作化学分析，对其造型和图案视而不见。

5

思想一经说出即丧失其实际生命，变为化石，就此死去，但也不可朽坏，就像史前动植物化石。一旦我们的思想付诸言辞，思想便不再代表我们的想法，或者说实际上变得不再重要。当思想开始为别人而存在，它就不再存于我们内心，就像婴儿有了自己的生命就脱离母体。

6

文学期刊应是一道水坝，挡住胡乱草就、汹涌而上、有害无益的当代书籍。期刊的判断应正直、明智、苛刻，应该无情地鞭挞一切无能之辈的拼凑之作，一切头脑空空、钱袋空空、凑字赚钱的行为——百分之九十的书都是这样写出来的。期刊应因此反对无病呻吟、欺世盗名，这是其职责所在。但恰恰相反，期刊却在助长这一切，对此听之任之，反倒与作者、出版商结成同盟，占有公众的时间和金钱。期刊撰稿人一般为教授或文人，他们工资不高或报酬微薄，因为目标一致，利益一致，他们联合起来，互相帮衬，彼此吹捧，这就是为什么文学期刊对坏书一片赞誉之声。他们的人生格言是：让自己活，也得让别人活！

匿名写作是一切文学无赖行为的保护伞，必须废除。文学期刊引入匿名写作的背景是，它能保护正直的批评家不被作者及其保护人的怒火所伤。但百倍于此的是，它的作用只是让评论家完全不负责任。若没有匿名写作，评论家将不能为自己的言行开脱。有些腐化堕落的评论家向公众推荐坏书，换取出版商的一点好处，这种可耻行径也就无所遁形。匿名写作仅仅掩盖评论家的含糊其辞、平庸少才和言之无物。一旦他们知道自己可以躲在暗处匿名写作而没有危险，他们就会变得难以置信的无耻和无赖。

卢梭曾在《新爱洛绮丝》的序言中写道：“正直的人都会在作品上写下自己的名字。”一切正话均可反说。评论常为论战之作，情况要糟糕不知多少倍。

7

风格是思想的脸，比身体更少欺骗性。模仿他人的风格好比戴了面具，面具不管有多美，它都没有生命，很快就变得索然寡味，难以忍受。因此，最丑陋的活人的脸也胜过面具。

矫揉造作的风格好比做鬼脸。

8

要对一个作家的价值暂作评价，不必了解他思考了什么，以及他的思考建立在什么之上，因为那样就得读遍他所有的作品。第一步，了解他怎样思考就够了。作家的风格提供了一个确切的参照，可以了解他是怎样思考的，他思考的内在本质和总体风格是什么。因为风格解释了一个人全部思想的形式特点，不管他思考什么，思考建立在什么之上，形式特点都始终不变，这就好比塑造的人物虽然各异，但用来塑造的泥团却都是一样的。当有人问奥伊伦斯皮格尔[19]到下一个镇子还需要多长时间时，他的回答显然莫名其妙：“走走看！”意思是说，要从提问人的步伐确定他在一定时间内能走多远。因此我读几页某位作家的书，就已多少知道我能从中得到什么。

好的风格的第一个标志是言之有物，实际上这也足以构成好的风格。

庸常之人言语乏味，也许是因为他们说话时不够清醒，也就是说，不真正理解用词的意义，因为这些用语他们通盘照搬，所以他们组织在一起的是惯用语（老生常谈）而非一个个词语。正因为这样，他们的作品明显缺乏清晰的观点，因为他们的作品里没有构成清晰观点的东西，即明晰的个人思考。相反，我们看到的是一大堆含糊不清的词，现成的短语，陈腐的表达，还有时髦的措辞。这种暧昧的作品因此好比铅字磨损的印版。

从以上关于作品乏味的讨论可以推见，乏味总体而言有两种：客观的和主观的。客观上的乏味是因为没有提出问题，作者没有明确的观点或信息需要表达。因为如果有的话，他就会直接说出，从而处处给出清晰无误的概念，既不模棱两可，也不莫衷一是，更不含糊其辞，因此也就不会乏味。即便他的主导思想是错的，仍经过清楚的思考和审慎的考虑，即至少形式上是正确的，他的作品因此仍具有一定价值。相反，出于同样的原因，客观上乏味的作品一无是处。主观上的乏味则仅是相对的，其原因在于读者对论题缺少兴趣，当然这源于读者的局限。因此，最值得称道的作品从主观角度看可能是乏味的，即此读者或彼读者认为它乏味；相反，最差的作品从主观角度看可能是有趣的，因为此读者或彼读者对论题或作者感兴趣。

矫揉造作的作家好比一个人装扮起来，以免混同于大众，而绅士不管如何衣衫褴褛也不愿冒此风险。正像过分花哨、华而不实的着装暴露了普通人的身份，矫揉造作的风格也暴露了平庸的头脑。

不过，想让写作和说话一模一样，未免误入歧途。每种写作风格都应略带雅训，雅训实乃一切写作之源。说话像写文章，则显卖弄、晦涩；写文章像说话，一样遭人唾弃。

不论何时何地，晦涩和含混均是大敌，因为言语的含混绝大多数源自思想的含混，而思想的含混又来自思想本身的冲突和矛盾，进一步来自思想的虚假。头脑中如果有了真实的想法，头脑就会力求明晰，并能很快达到这个目标：经过清晰考虑的思想很容易找到适当的语言。一个人所能想的，总能用清晰易懂、明白晓畅的语言表达出来。措辞艰深、混乱暧昧的人并不真正知道自己要说什么，他们对要说的只有点朦胧的意识，还算不上一个想法。不过，他们也想对自己、对他人隐瞒他无话可说的事实。

真理是最为赤裸裸的，其表述越简洁，影响越深远。例如，关于人生之虚无，滔滔雄辩也没有约伯的话更有力量：“人为妇人所生，日子短少，多有患难。出来如花，又被割下；飞去如影，不能存留。”[20]正因为此，歌德的质朴之诗远高于席勒的雕琢之作，这也是很多民歌影响巨大的原因所在。凡属冗余，皆为有害。

从事文学的男女，九成以上除了报纸什么也不读，因此他们的拼写、语法、文风完全取法报纸。因为报纸文字的简洁，他们甚至把报纸对语言的戕害视为短小精悍、措辞文雅、新奇精巧。事实上，才学不足的文学青年总的说来把报纸视为权威，仅仅因为报纸是印刷出来的东西。因此，国家应采取有力措施，确保报纸绝无文字差错。应该设立审查官，他不应领取工资，而应按挑出的错误取酬：发现一个草率使用或风格可憎的词，一个语法或句法错误，或者一个用错的介词，都领一个金路易；发现一处严重违反文风语法的地方，领三个金路易；若发现重复犯的错误，则报酬翻倍。所获报酬应由始作俑者承担。德语难道可以是随便什么人的玩物？甚至粪堆都受法律保护，难道德语就不应该？何其目光短浅！如果每个三流文人和报刊作家都可以任意妄为，不加节制，德语究竟会变成什么样子？

9

文学在衰落，古代语言被人淡忘，一种风格上的缺陷变得越来越普通，但只有在德国才大行其道，这便是主观性。作家认为，他的意思只要自己明白就行了，任由读者自生自灭。作者对读者的困难不予理会，自行其是，仿佛自说自话。而真正该有的是对话，甚至，说者因听不到听者的问题，须将自己的意思表述得更加清楚。出于这个原因，风格不应是主观的，而应是客观的。客观的风格是，词语的组织让读者只能被迫和作者进行完全一样的思考。但要实现这一点，作者须时刻牢记：思想也遵循重力法则——思想从头脑传递到纸上，要比从纸上传递到头脑容易得多，因此为了保证后一种传递，我们得为思想提供力所能及的援助。如若实现，词语将呈现纯客观的状态，就像一幅完成了的油画；而主观的风格其影响力无非像墙上的斑斑污点，仅当想象力碰巧被激发时，人们才能从污点中看出形状和图案，其他情况下它们只是污点而已。我们所讨论的这种区别适用于整体叙述模式，但通常也体现在个别段落。例如，我刚在一本新书中读到：“我写作，不是为了让世上的书再多一本。”这和作家的意图完全相反，而且毫无意义。

10

草率动笔等于坦承作者并不看重自己的思想。只有坚信自己思想的分量和真实性，作家才能产生热情，才有不屈不挠的意念，去探索如何将思想表达得尽量精巧、有力和动人，就像我们只为圣物或无价艺术品使用金银制成的匣子。

11

像建筑师盖房那样写作的人少之又少。建筑师要事先画图纸，考虑到最小的细节；大多数人写作则像玩多米诺骨牌，他们把句子像骨牌一样一个个摆在一起，一半有意为之，一半无心使然。

12

写作艺术的基本原则是：一心不可二用；因此不能要求作家同时思考——更不必说同时表达——两个念头。但割裂句子，加上插入语，就是要求作家一心二用，这种做法导致不必要且荒谬的混乱。德国作家在这方面表现最差，原因可能是德语比其他语言更容易割裂，但这并不值得称道。没有一种语言读起来像法语那样悦耳晓畅，因为法语通常没有这样的缺陷。法国作家注意写下自己的想法，排列顺序最为合理、自然，因此读者对每个想法都心无旁骛。相反，德国作家让想法彼此交错，句子套句子再套句子，因为他们坚持要一下子说六件事，而不是逐一把六件事说完。

德国人真正的民族性格是蠢重[21]，清楚地表现在他们的步态、行为、语言、言辞、叙述方式、理解方式和思考方式上，尤其表现在写作风格上，表现为乐此不疲地使用笨重复杂的长句，读者得花足足五分钟记住这些句子，得在孤立无援时保持耐心，直到句子结尾才真相大白。这就是德国人欣赏的东西，如果文章同时矫揉造作、夸大其词，作者就会喜不自胜。但上天站在读者一边。

一个想法与另一个想法像十字架一样交叉，这样做明显有悖常理，但作家就是这么做的：一件事刚起头便，立刻打断，在句子中间又说迥然不同的另一件事，留下没有意义的半个句子让读者思量，直到下半句出现，这就好像递给客人一个空盘子，让他去猜盘子里会出现什么。

这种大煞风景的造句方式的登峰造极之处在于，有时插入语并非句子的有机部分，而是生硬嵌入，造成刺目的断裂。如果说打断别人说话是失礼，那打断自己说话也同样失礼。出现这种遣词造句的方式已有多年。现在，所有胡涂乱写、一心想着报酬的作家每一页都要打断自己六次，并以此为乐。理无例不明——他们的做法就是拆散一个短语，以便插入另一个短语。他们这样做不仅出于懒惰，也由于愚蠢，他们以为这样可以使文笔生动、摇曳生姿。除极个别的例外，这种做法不可原谅。

13

读作家的作品，并不能学会任何文学手法，如说服力强、想象丰富、譬喻巧妙、文笔流畅、文风峻厉、言辞简明、优美雅致、表现力强、机智风趣、对比鲜明、惜字如金、朴实稚拙。但若你已掌握这些手法，已有此倾向和潜质，通过阅读，使已有的手法得以加强，我们知道如何运用，更愿乃至更有勇气调动这些手法，评价其得失，因而学会如何正确运用。这时我们才真正掌握这些手法。这是通过阅读学习写作的唯一方法，借此我们知道我们如何利用自己的天赋。如果我们不具备这些素养，我们从阅读中学到的只有冰冷僵死的套路，成为肤浅的模仿者。

14

地层中保留着过去时代的生物谱系，同样，图书馆的书架上也保留着过去时代的谬误谱系及其说明。像古生物一样，这些谬误曾一度光鲜，名噪一时，但现在已僵化固定，只有古生物学家才加以关注。

15

根据希罗多德的记载，薛西斯一世看到自己的大军，想到众人当中没有一个能活过一百年，不禁落泪。看到汗牛充栋的书籍，没有一本能活过十年，谁又能不潸然泪下？

16

不读书的诀窍十分重要，要点在于，对那些红极一时的书要不去理会。有些宣扬政治或宗教的小册子，或者小说和诗歌，造成很大的轰动，这时应该记住：为蠢人写作总不乏读者。读书的前提是读好书，不读坏书，因为人生苦短。

17

买书是件好事，如果同时能买到读书时间的话。但人们通常误以为，买了书就等于拥有了书的内容。

18

就世界史而言，50年是相当长的时间，因为世界的质料一直在变，总有新事发生。就文学史而言，50年微不足道，因为什么也没发生，事情还是50年前的样子。

与事物的这种状态相适应，科学、文学和艺术的时代风气大约每30年就瓦解一次，因为期间谬误发展壮大，愈益荒谬，时代风气终于不堪其负；与此同时，相反意见也因谬误而加强。于是乃有突变，但继之而来的常为相反的错误。展现事物状态的阶段性重复应是文学史真正应该研究的内容。

我希望有一天有人尝试写一部文学的悲剧性历史，表现各国在其引以为荣的伟大作家和艺术家尚在人世时是如何对待他们的。这部文学史中，作者应该呈现给我们的是：任何国家，任何时代，善与真如何忍受恶与假的统治；每一位真正开启人类心智的人，每一个艺术大师，几乎都成了殉难者；除了极少例外，他们饱受折磨，贫穷凄惨，不被承认，无人同情，无人追随，无能之辈却名利双收；他们的命运就像《圣经》中的以扫，在出门狩猎、为父亲打野味时被雅各骗走了长子的继承权；尽管如此，他们对事业的热爱支撑他们继续艰苦的斗争，直到教导人类的使命终于完成，永不凋谢的桂冠向他们伸手召唤，钟声敲响，宣布光荣的时刻：

沉重的铠甲变作孩童的轻装，

痛苦短暂，欢乐绵长。

[1]梵天是印度教的主神，阿胡拉·玛兹达和安格拉·曼纽分别是古波斯诺斯替教的善神与恶神。

[2]德谟克里特（活跃于公元前420年前后），希腊哲学家，原子论的创始人。约翰·洛克（1632—1704），17世纪晚期英国代表哲学家。

[3]比沙（1771—1802），解剖学家和生理学家。卡巴尼斯（1757—1808），物理学家和医学作家。

[4]此处叔本华引用《罗马书》第七章，《哥林多后书》第二及第三章。

[5]里希特尔（1763—1825），以笔名让·保罗闻名，是当时最受欢迎的德国作家之一。《塞利娜》在他死后于1827年出版，书中他试图想清楚自己的宗教信仰到底是什么，却没有成功。让·保罗认定，他无法接受基督教，但又发现无法放弃其中的一些信条，比如相信永生，对此除了他排斥的基督教的信条外他别无所获。

[6]柏拉图《理想国》中人物，试图论证“强权即公理”。他传授雄辩术，更关心赢得辩论而不是获知真理。

[7]字面意思为“热爱真理者”，哲学家的统称。

[8]席勒（1759—1805），按传统说法为德国第二大诗人，诗作《女人的尊严（或美德、价值）》曾风靡一时，但他像瓦尔特·司各特一样，大部分诗作都是“劣作中的杰作”。他真正的才华在通俗戏剧，现在他的一些最出色的喜剧仍在上演。维克多·朱伊，剧作家。

[9]第一幕，第二场。

[10]中世纪意大利的两大对立派别。归尔甫派反对神圣罗马帝国皇帝，效忠教皇；吉伯林派正好相反。——译者注

[11]印度东北部城市，现称瓦腊纳西。——译者注

[12]利希腾贝格（1742—1799），格言作家，讽刺作家。赫尔德（1744—1803），神学家，哲学家，文人。

[13]费希特（1762—1814）、谢林（1775—1854）、黑格尔（1770—1831）都是当时最有影响的哲学家，也是叔本华不断攻击的对象。施莱尔马赫（1768—1834），神学家，叔本华批评宗教上的“唯理主义”时，指的就是施莱尔马赫。

[14]沃韦纳格侯爵（1715—1747），法国意义上的“道德学家”。

[15]法国南部城市，濒地中海，是法国重要的军港。——译者注

[16]莱辛创作的悲剧。莱辛是德国启蒙运动的领军人物，也是歌德和席勒之前重要的剧作家。

[17]《新爱洛绮丝》为卢梭所作，《威廉·迈斯特》为歌德所作。

[18]毕尔格（1747—1794），诗人，其谣曲《莱诺蕾》是德语名篇，讲述少女莱诺蕾苦等情人，等来的却是装扮成她情人样子的魔鬼，带领她骑马奔向黑暗的坟墓。

[19]蒂尔·奥伊伦斯皮格尔是德国民间故事中的人物，是个机智、爱搞恶作剧的孩子。——译者注

[20]《约伯记》，14：1—2，此处译文引自《圣经》（新标准修订版简化字和合本）。

[21]德语Schwerfälligkeit有沉重、笨拙、缓慢、丑陋、蠢重等多重意思。

导读

弗里德里希·尼采（Friedrich Nietzsche，1844—1900），德国著名的哲学家与语文学家，也是哲学史上最具争议的传奇人物之一。尼采生于普鲁士的一个牧师家庭，父亲在他五岁时就早早去世，因此尼采成长于一个几乎充满女性的环境中；不过颇为反常的却是，尼采终其一生都十分崇尚力量与阳刚。十分聪慧的少年尼采痴迷于神学与宗教，并立志成为一名像父亲那样的牧师，因此进入伯恩大学修习神学与语文学。不过在一段时间之后，尼采反而开始对基督教产生厌恶的情绪，而这种情绪也贯穿了他的一生，这极有可能是源于他大学时的一些阅读以及家庭变故。放弃神学的尼采转而投入了哲学的怀抱，而叔本华则是此时对尼采影响最大的哲学家。

1869年大学毕业之后，尼采在教授的帮助与推荐之下，以本科的学历便取得了巴塞尔大学古典哲学教授的职位。刚刚搬到巴塞尔的尼采便宣布永久放弃普鲁士公民权，不过在1870年，尼采还是以军医的身份加入了普鲁士军队，短暂见证了普法战争的残酷，这段经历也被认为是影响了他的性格。1872年，尼采出版了首部作品《悲剧的诞生》，这是一部关于美学的著作，探讨悲剧的起源，不过他在书中表现出的对于语文学的抛弃，却让他受到了学界同行们空前的孤立。而1878年的《人性的，太人性的》一书，则又宣告尼采正式抛弃了他曾经十分欣赏的叔本华的哲学思想。此时期的尼采，身体健康每况愈下，终于不得不于1879年辞去了教授之职，并开始四处寻找适宜居住的定居地，他遍游欧洲、不断搬迁，直到1889年在意大利发疯住院为止。

在这漂泊的十年间，尼采虽然健康状况不佳，不过始终保持着旺盛的创作精力，佳作不断，相继出版了《快乐的科学》《扎拉图斯拉的独白》《善恶的彼岸》《道德谱系学》《瓦格纳事件》《偶像的黄昏》《反基督》《瞧，这个人》与《尼采反对瓦格纳》，以及大量并未出版的笔记（他去世后被集结成《权力意志》一书）。终于，在学界极力排斥、健康长期不佳、居所漂泊不定、内心极度失调等多重因素的共同冲击下，尼采在1889年完全失控发疯了；直到1900年，尼采终于走完了他动荡不堪的一生。

“伟大的思想”系列编选《天才，舍我其谁》一书，节选尼采的两部作品《瞧，这个人》与《偶像的黄昏》中的相关章节。

《瞧，这个人》，另有副标题为“人如何成其所是”，是尼采创作的形式独特的自传，也是他发疯之前的最后一部作品，书名与各节标题中的“自大”情绪很可能表现出了他已然十分不稳定的精神状况。他在书中回顾了自己哲学思想的变化历程，其中绝大多数章节以回顾其往昔作品为题，不过本书则节选了另外的五章，即“序言”“天才，舍我其谁”“机灵，岂但如此”“佳作，何以迭出”与“天运，我自晓得”。这部自传是一本体现了无限哲学智慧的书籍，当我们跳脱开尼采文字流露的那种病态的自信之后，我们会发现，他只是在向读者陈述一个哲学命题——“尼采是如何成为尼采的”。

尼采在1886年就开始筹备《权力意志》一书，不过最终放弃了写作计划，反而将未完成的文稿编辑成了《反基督》与《偶像的黄昏》两部书。《偶像的黄昏》原本定名为《一个心理学家的闲逛》，另有副标题为“或怎样用锤子从事哲学”。尼采在这部篇幅不大的书中，以格言式的精炼语言，集中地抨击了一位位传统意义上的文化“偶像”们。尼采把自己比作“锤子”，去全力击碎这些旧秩序的形象，去重估一切价值，才能解放人类的自由意志。本书节选“箴言，足以抒怀”“贻误，独有四遭”与“铁锤，为我代言”三节。

尼采，无疑是整个人类历史上最为自大，也因此而最具个人魅力、最具争议的人物之一，他也无愧于那自封的“天才”之名！尼采是最坚定的、最极端的唯意志论者，他反对任何形式的理性主义、反对基督教、反对传统价值、反对传统道德，也进而创造了“权力意志”的“超人”理论。尼采的文字中时刻杂糅着自大、阳刚、坚强、批判、孤独的情绪，而读者也往往很容易被尼采的这种病态情绪所诱导，而忽略了其中的哲学思维。希望读者可以在充分理解尼采一生经历的前提下，静心品读这部节选作品，一窥那真正伟大的思想。

柴尔

瞧，这个人
——人如何成其所是

序言

I

深知，为人类之前途提出一个最高目标，是一件以往从未有过的事情，也是一件刻不容缓的事情。于是，诠释鄙人，为“何许人也”便是一件义不容辞的事情了。

其实，这本应是一个不言自明的道理，因为鄙人早已用赤裸裸的事实，回答了这个“何许人也”的问题。然而，问题在于：鄙人所负责任之重大同所处同辈之渺小，相去甚远，令人见所未见，闻所未闻。我活着，乃是靠我的信誉——或许，仅仅是因为某种“偏执”的原因，我——还活着……或许，只需要向夏日里专程赴上恩加丁河谷的任何一位所谓“文化人士”之规劝妥协一下，承认鄙人已经故去便是了……于是，我这里便有了一种叛逆的义务——表现出某种违背自我意愿乃至天性的傲慢，并且就此宣布：听好！尼采便是尼采，最重要的是，不得与他人同日而语。

II

不过，尼采绝非凶神恶煞之鬼，亦非道德败坏之人——相反，他天生就是一个无神论者，并且始终都以善行为荣。在同辈之间，似乎对我来说，是值得自豪的一点。我，是哲学家狄俄尼索斯的信徒。所以，我宁做好色之徒，不为圣之仁人。但，你一定得读读这本论著——或许我已经幽默地、平易地表达出了这一对立；或许，你会因此而折服；或许，舍此别无选择。我最不愿意承诺的可能就是“改造”人类了。并未树立新的偶像——只是让陈腐的偶像懂得泥塑的双腿意味着什么罢了。摒弃陈腐的偶像（并以此替代“理想”一词）——这，便是鄙人所事之事。我深知：在人们塑造一个理想世界的同时，现实世界已经从某种程度上失去了它原有的价值和本来的意义，因而便丧失了其真实性。其实，所谓“理念世界”和“表象世界”的区别，简言之，便是“人为世界”和“真实世界”之区别而已……足见，理念世界的谎言，始终都是对真实世界的诅咒——在这种谎言的包围中，人类自身的灵魂深处发生了扭曲。于是，他们的价值观被颠倒了——他们顶礼膜拜，提升未来，以为只有这样，才足以保证社会的繁荣、未来的美好——这，便是他们的权力。

III

一个懂得从鄙人著述中汲取营养的人，便知道那是一种顶级的营养，一种健康的营养。人，生来就需要这种营养，否则就会伤风感冒——因此，他绝无必要去冒这个风险。冰冷世界并不遥远，与世隔绝危险重重——但是，阳光下的万物却是平和幸福的！因为在这里，人可以自由地呼吸！也不会有社会地位参差不齐的感受！您可知道，这意味着什么？按照鄙人的理解和诠释，哲学，乃是一种甘愿在冰雪和大山中度过的生活，乃是一种对生活中一切未知和疑惑的追问——一种对一切及伦理学道德说教所排斥的理念的追寻。正是从这种对禁锢的惊诧中得来的长期经验，使我学会了寻找“道德”与“理想”之源的方法，并由此发现“道德”与“理想”同人们的期望相去甚远：哲学家们不为人所知的阅历，乃至他们伟大姓名背后的心路历程，在鄙人面前一览无遗。一种精神能够承载多少真理？一种精神又敢于承载多少真理？这就逐渐成为我测量真理“价值”的尺度。相信理想，是错误——虽不是盲目的，但却是懦弱的……每一点知识的获得，每一次知识的进步，都是勇敢的结果，自我严苛的结果，自我净化的结果……我并不排斥什么“理想”，只想增强一下“理想”之免疫力罢了……“人们在禁锢中挣扎”[1]（奥维德语）——这便预示着，鄙人的哲学总有一天会获得成功，因为在真理面前，一切被理想主义原则所禁锢的东西都算不得什么。

IV

在鄙人所有著述中，《扎拉图斯拉的独白》[2]堪称一枝独秀之作，是鄙人馈赠人类最富意义的礼物——因为人类从未接受过这样一个礼物：她，不仅是现存书籍中最令人亢奋的著述，有极好的营养；她，用穿越千年之声宣告，用全部的事实证明：人类脚下还有一段漫长的路途要走，而且，值得称道的是，从其问世的那一天起，便以其真理的含量无穷而著称；她，像一口取之不尽用之不竭的水井，只要你将手中的吊桶放下去，便不愁没有金银财宝捞上来。这里，既不需要先知们的预见，也不需要宗教领袖们的提示，只要有病魔的“协助”和冲创意志[3]的提升便足够了。最重要的是，人们务必听清楚从扎拉图斯拉口中传来的声音，只要你不至于曲解它智慧的意味，她——简直就像一只“翠鸟”发出的乐音。“只有来自鸽子脚尖的、最平静的语言，才足以激起最激烈的暴风雨和最深刻的思考，从而为世界导航。”

树上掉落的无花果最香甜，因为果实红色的皮被擦破了。我愿做一缕清凉的北风，催熟那香甜的无花果。

此时此刻，这里的劝导是否像香甜的无花果一般掉落在您的身边？朋友，请吮吸它醉人的果汁，品尝它香甜的果实！秋天来了——秋高气爽，正是午后之天啊！

这里，没有盲目热衷的必要；这里，没有布道说教的场地；这里，没有信徒虔诚的戒律：无限充裕的阳光和无比深厚的幸福，一滴滴、一句句洒向人间——柔情而缓慢的步伐，恰似这轻盈话语的节奏。这些，都是精心挑选的结果。在这里，做一个静心的倾听者，那是一种无上的权益。没有人不可以自由地倾听扎拉图斯拉的独白……除非，扎拉图斯拉的独白丧失了他诱人的魅力！然而，一旦他再度回归独处的时候，他——又会说些什么呢？毫无疑问，即便在这种情况下，同任何“先哲”“圣人”“救世主”以及其他“颓废者”相反，他的话语是与众不同的，因为他——是与众不同的……

我，要独自离开了，我的拥护者们！你们，也各自离开吧——好让我心安理得。

离开我吧，不要接受扎拉图斯拉的诱惑！最好是，以其为耻！或许，他已然骗过了你们。

须知——唯有高明之士，必能取敌之长而避友之短也。

如果，一个学生总也无所进取，他又怎么能够回报恩师呢？如此，何不趁早摘掉这顶桂冠？

你，尊重我。但是，有一天，你的尊重失去意义了，怎么办？切记，一尊眼看就要倒塌的塑像，是不会对人产生死亡的威胁！

你说，你笃信扎拉图斯拉？那么，扎拉图斯拉的价值何在？你，是我的信徒，那么信徒的价值又何在呢？

你，找到了我，却迷失了自我。所有的信徒都别无二致，所有的信仰都一文不值。

于是，我求你，放开我，去寻找自我。当所有人都背叛我的那一刻，“余，乃可回归于汝”。

弗里德里希·尼采

当这一天到来的时候，一切都是那么美好——葡萄串露出了棕色的脸蛋儿，生活中充满了阳光的气息，左看看，右瞧瞧，从未见过这么多美好的事物一起涌现。我，绝没有埋葬过去的四十四个春秋。然而，这却是一件出乎意料的事情，当生命的冲动被唤醒时，生命的力量便会焕发出不朽的光芒。第一部《重估一切价值》《扎拉图斯拉的独白》《偶像的黄昏》——所有这些，都是献给这一年，甚至是这一年里最后一个季度的礼物！所图之事，不过借“铁锤”之力，敲醒沉睡之众而已。于是，一旦有感于生命的垂青，必然悦自我以生命的成功。

天才，舍我其谁

I

我存在于世的这份幸运，它的独特之处或许在于它的死亡。用一个谜语来表述，那便是：如果我是我的父亲，我已经死去；如果我是我的母亲，则我依然活着，且已老迈年高。生与死，乃是生命的两极，分布在生命云梯的两端，一端最高，一端最低；一端已然颓废，一端还在延伸。如果还有什么中庸的方式可以借用，或者在生命的终极问题上仍有选择的余地，我会说：正是这个中庸、这个余地成就了鄙人，将我同其他所有人区别开来。对于生命的上升与衰落，我比常人更加敏感。我深谙于此，因为二者我都了解，也是它们造就了我。

我的父亲谢世之际，不过三十六岁而已。他纤细羸弱、讨人喜欢、疾病缠身，似乎注定成为这个世界的匆匆过客——与其说那是生命，不如说那只是对生命友善的提示罢了。也是在我三十六岁的那一年——就是父亲谢世的年龄，我跌落到了人生的最低谷，但我依然活着，只是连离我三步之遥的地方都看不清。那是在1879年，我辞去了巴塞尔大学的教授职务，在圣莫里茨度过了那一年的夏天，又在瑙姆堡度过了随后的冬天，那是我人生中最灰暗的时光，过着幽灵一般的生活，《彷徨者和他的独居生活》[4]便是这一时期的著述。毋庸置疑，在那些日子里我饱尝了独居的滋味……

第二年冬天，是我在意大利热那亚度过的第一个冬天——温和而甜蜜，超凡而脱俗。其实，这一切都是我撰写《黎明》所付出的心血带来的必然结果。《黎明》的问世，带给我光明和兴奋，甚至带给我生机勃勃的精神力量。在我看来，这一切恰恰是生理上的极度亏欠，乃至精神上的无限痛楚所换来的补偿。在经历那些痛苦的过程中，我遭受了连续三天三夜的头痛，同时遭遇了难以忍受的痰喘折磨。然而，这一时期，我却多有超常的辩证能力，处理问题坚决果断，毫不迟疑。相反，在我健康状况稍好的时候，我却不够野心勃勃，不够缜密，不够客观。或许，只有我的那些读者们才知道我是如何将辩证法视为颓废的征兆，最有说服力的情形莫过于对待苏格拉底的那个例子了。至于，那些原本影响智力的病魔，乃至由发烧引起的半昏迷状态，为什么足以引起我思维的神奇变化——所有这些，对我来说至今仍然是个“谜”。为了弄清那些病魔的性质及其发生的规律，我首度求诸于学究的方法。

我的心脏，总是跳动得很慢。因而从来没有医生诊断出我发高烧的病症来。有位大夫，甚至一度将我当作精神病人来对待，可临了，他却说：“不！不是你的精神出了问题，而是我的神经出了差错！”其实，身体局部的任何病变都可能失去其症状的。比如，过度疲劳，就会引起消化功能的极度衰退，从而引起胃部的病变，但是却不至于会有什么生理器官表现出胃病的症状来。有时，眼睛的症状会严重到接近失明的地步，但是这不过是病变的过程而已，并非病变的原因所在。因此，一旦其他生命指数得以提高，视力就会随之恢复。

对我而言，康复过程简直像一条经久不断的锁链一样，其中很不幸地伴随着旧病复发和病情恶化，这是一段很颓废的时期。至此，我所亲身遭遇的颓废情节，还需要更多的补充吗？我以为，我已经彻彻底底地交代清楚了。而且，可以毫不夸张地说，从整体把握事物的微妙技术到通过直觉发现细微差别的能力，从“明察秋毫”的心理战术到所有决定我性格特质的生理规律，都是我在这一时期里学来的。换言之，正是在这一时期，我的一切——观察能力及其感觉系统，都变得更加敏感、精微和周到。所有这些，都是这一特殊时期所赋予我的特异禀赋。如果从病理学的视角上考察这些相对健康的价值和观念，同时又从相反的视角上将充裕而有保障的富人生活看作是人类本能颓废的秘密所在，那么，这些就是我着力最多的地方，也是我阅历独到的特殊领域。在这个特殊的领域中，我是大师。我现在已经具备扭转观点的知识和技巧，这也是我认为于我而言“重估价值”或许完全可行的原因之一。

II

暂不论我颓废的一面，我也有积极的一面。对此，别的不说，这里的证据是，在同病魔抗争时，我总会本能地选择对自己有益的方式，而在同样的情况下，对于颓废者来说，他们总会选择对自己有害的方式。总体而言，我是健康的；局部而论，我又是虚弱的。从自己习惯的生活环境中绝对地脱离出来，并且坚持不再接受照顾、伺候和家庭医生的护理——这样就脱离了对本能的无条件依赖，从而懂得了什么才是当时最需要的。由于对自身了如指掌，即便在颓废之际，我也能够让自己健康起来。做到这一点的先决条件——任何生理学家都不会排斥的——便是你的身体基本上是健康的。一个通常多病的身体是健康不起来的，自然也就难以再使自己健康起来了；相反，对于一个通常健康的身体，生病反而会成为他生命的兴奋剂，使其生命力更加旺盛。事实上，我那一段长时期的病情，对自己的健康来说似乎正是如此：我发现自己的生活新鲜了许多，甚至连自身的状态也改变了许多。我用他人难得的方式品味着生活中所有美好的事物乃至无足轻重的小事，凭借的无非是向往健康的意愿，无非是憧憬生命的意志——一言以蔽之，无非是我生命哲学的力量。

值得注意的是，正是在那些生命处于最低潮的岁月里，我摒弃了悲观厌世的情绪，才没有沿着这个路子滑下去。对我而言，正是自我恢复的本能使我的生活信念免于向贫乏而悲观的方向滑落……那么，一个人成功的秘诀是什么？一个成功人士给我们的感觉是舒服的——他，好似一块神奇的木材，整体雕琢而成，看上去坚硬、雅致、香气扑鼻；他，只品读对身心有益的事物。一旦什么地方对身心的益处超越了限度，他的喜悦和兴趣便会停止；总为治病疗伤而预言，常化恶遇劣境为契机——只要不被恶劣的境遇所击溃，他便会十足地坚强。在所见、所闻和所历中，他本能地汇集了如下的结论：他有自己取舍的原则，他能抵御许多事物。无论是在阅览书籍，还是在游历盛景，或者在审度人群，他永远与己为伴。凡是他选择的、承认的和信任的，他都予以尊重。

对外界刺激的反应，他总是迟钝的。正是这种反应的迟钝，造成了他性格上的过于谨慎和妄自尊大——当刺激向他袭来时，他总是先要间接地试探，从来不会迎上去直接面对。他从不相信“厄运”和“罪孽”；相反，他懂得如何忘却那些负面的东西。然而，只要是对他发展有益的事物，他总会毫不迟疑地勇敢面对。足见，他绝非什么颓废之人；相反，他总是站在颓废的对立面——好吧，我是与颓废相对立的人：因为我描述的正是本人。

III

我以为，能有这样一位父亲，乃是我得天独厚的特权：父亲在奥登堡宅邸生活了几年之后，做了牧师，那是在他生命中最后几年里的事情。听他布道的农民们说，天使应该就是父亲那个样子。由此，我便开始了种族问题的探究。原来，鄙人乃是波兰的贵族出身，且没有半点的混血成分，压根儿就不是什么德意志人。而当我寻找与我完全对立的东西，那些数不尽的卑劣天性时，我总可以在母亲和妹妹身上找到。和她们有血缘关系，这一点对我圣洁的血统简直是一种亵渎。时至今日，我想起母亲和姐姐是如何待我时，心中仍然充满了说不出的恐惧。在我身体最脆弱、最需要静养的时候，总觉得什么地方就好像偏偏安放了一台魔鬼般的机器准确无误地工作着。每每在这样的场合，我总得使出全身的力气，就像抵御毒蛇的侵入一般……或许，这种高度失衡的不和谐现象得从生理学的视角上去介入，才可能解释得清楚……不过，我对“永久轮回”的深恶痛绝，是我打从地狱中走过之后才得来的真实感觉，不过，这些全都是拜母亲和姐姐所赐了。然而，即使作为一个波兰人，我的出生也是一个异乎寻常的返祖现象。不过，要弄清这个地球上曾经有过的、顶级高贵的种族的原始天性，何以达到我所描述的人一般的巅峰水准，或许人们还得追溯到几个世纪以前才能实现。

同当下一切贵族阶层的观念背道而驰，鄙人总有一个感觉，这个感觉至高无上而又与众不同——当今年轻的德意志皇帝，连做鄙人的马车夫都是一种“荣誉”，还得看鄙人愿不愿授予他呢。不过，也有一个例外，我会感激我的同仁——我深怀感恩之心，也深谙此间之理。瓦格纳夫人科茜玛，无疑是出身最高贵的人。于是，我不能不多说几句了，理查德·瓦格纳绝对是同我关系最密切的人，没有人可以跟他相提并论。在一个不可超越的意义上，一切流行的亲疏远近理念，在生理学上都是无稽之谈。可谁知道，罗马教皇如今仍然在经营这种子虚乌有的理念。人类是同父母关系最为疏远的动物，于是，认为同父母关系接近的观念，便沦为了最极端、最庸俗的表现。越是高级的种族，越是需要追溯其起源，这样她便会集合更多的优点，保留更好的传统，储备更大的能量。最伟大的群体是最古老的种族，虽然我并不完全知晓，但是古罗马尤利乌斯·恺撒，或许就是鄙人的祖先，或许，马其顿亚历山大（大帝），那个狄俄尼索斯酒神的化身，也跟我有关……不信你瞧——就在我写作的时候，邮递员给我送来了一封印有狄俄尼索斯头像的信件。

IV

给自己树敌，这种玩意儿，鄙人从来不懂——即便在非常必要的情况下，鄙人也不会为自己树敌的。毫无疑问，这一点也得归功于我的父亲。虽然我看上去不大像基督的信徒，但是鄙人怎么也不会干出伤害自己的事情。人们可以任意设想鄙人的生活，但却很难（其实，只有一次）发现什么人对鄙人抱有恶意。不仅如此，或许人们还会表现出良多的善意呢……甚至，根据鄙人的经验，每一个人都会毫无例外地有过为个人利益辩护的经历。鄙人能够驯服每一只狗熊，甚至还能让小丑们检点自己的行为。在巴塞尔文法学校任教的七年里，鄙人教授过（古）希腊语中最难理解的语法现象。即便如此，鄙人也从未惩罚过那里的学生。只要在我班里学习过的学生，再懒的也能勤奋起来。平日里，总得经常处理一些意料之外的事情——如果只顾教书而不闻窗外之事，那么面对突如其来的事情，常常会令人措手不及。乐器毕竟是乐器，如果跑了调子，那一定是演奏乐器的人跑了调。如此，我真的该生一场病，便可避免跑调的问题，自然也省得那声音不堪入耳了。我常常听到“乐器们”抱怨，说什么从来没有哪个器乐师能从它们身上弹出过最美妙的音乐来……要说最好的器乐师，那非海因里希·冯·斯坦因莫属了，遗憾的是，他英年早逝。海因里希·冯·斯坦因，曾难得获此允准，在锡尔斯—玛利亚逗留过三天——他自称，并非为上恩加丁河谷而来。就在那短短的三天里，这位难得的高人，以他普鲁士容克贵族的全部冲动和毫无掩饰的激情，深深地走进了瓦格纳风格的神秘世界，涉入了杜林音乐的精神天地而情不自拔，恰似凭借着狂风一般的威力，其乐音的余韵在天空中自由地翱翔，他本人也如虎添翼，一瞬间便飞黄腾达。不过，鄙人还得不断地提醒他，这只是清爽空气的微妙功效，谁都会有同样的感觉，你不能高居于拜罗伊特六千英尺以外的天空而无视这个事实。然而，他偏偏就不信这个“邪”……如此也罢，因为我知道：即便大大小小的不端行为全都冲我而来，那也不是故意而来，至少不是恶意所致。相反，值得我抱怨的倒是许许多多的“善意”，我已谈及许多，却招致我生命中不少的“厄运”。鄙人的阅历足以令人怀疑一切所谓无私的动机，怀疑一切言行中的“博爱”。在我看来，那便是一种软弱的表现，一种无力接受刺激的表现——只有在颓废者之间，怜悯才被唤作美德。对于那些施舍怜悯的人士，我的非难是：羞辱和敬畏，后者在距离上的微妙感觉最容易迷惑他们，怜悯总有乌合之众的味道，因而就会像粗俗的行为一样为他们所误解。而在某种情况下，施舍怜悯的手甚至会以直接侵入的方式葬送一个伟大的命运，破坏一个疗伤人独处的空间，剥夺一个人自责的权力。鄙人以为，在高贵的德行中绝不应该包容怜悯的行为，在“扎拉图斯拉的诱惑”一节中，我创设了这样一个情节：由于痛苦的折磨他大声呼叫，“怜悯”就像终极的罪孽侵袭着他，引诱他走向堕落，背叛自我。于是，为了坚守自我，坚守崇高的使命，必须摆脱所谓无私行为中诸多低劣而短视的行为。这些行为的表现非常活跃，因而要摆脱其恶劣的影响，对扎拉图斯拉来说乃是一个必经的考验。或许，是终极的考验。自然，这也是对其真实能力的最好证明了。

V

其实，从另一个视角上看，我不过是父亲的翻版，不过是父亲过早谢世的生命延续而已。就像人们从来没有生活在平等的群体中一般，对他们而言，“补偿”就像权利平等一样遥不可及。因此，在大大小小冒犯自身权益的愚蠢行为发生在身边时，鄙人一概不采取什么反抗的手段，或者保护的措施，即便鄙人是有理的，也绝不以所谓正当防卫一类的行为进行反击。鄙人所谓的补救办法是：在愚蠢行为发生之后，尽早作出睿智的样子，这样，周围的人们或许还会高看你一眼。打个比方说吧，假若我狼吞虎咽地吃下一瓶果酱，我会说是为了驱除胃里酸味之类的东西……于是，你便树立了自信——随他们去吧，反正鄙人总可以“补偿”的。只要抓着机会，鄙人总会感谢那些“冒犯者”的，乃至于有时简直就是因为冒犯本身而感谢，或者还可以找机会求助于“冒犯者”。这样，总比反过来帮他们的忙更体面一些吧……而且，在鄙人看来，即便是最粗俗的言辞、最鄙陋的信件也要比沉默寡言善解人意一些，实诚一些，因为那些喜欢沉默寡言的人常常是缺乏敏锐之见和礼貌之心的人。沉默便是反抗，而且将本该一吐为快的东西再吞噬下去，养成了坏的习性，乃至于损坏了好端端的胃口。难怪，凡是沉默寡言的人都有消化不良的毛病。人们总会发现的，我不想“粗鲁”的价值被看低，因为这是迄今为止，在处理冲突上最为仁义的方式了。于是，即便在当今优雅的举止中，“粗鲁”——也当数最佳德行之一了。要知道，对于一个足够富裕的人而言，犯错或者被人冤枉一类的事情，甚至是一种幸运。上帝光临人间，难免会犯错误，毕竟上帝的形象就是：承担罪过而不承担惩罚。

VI

试图摆脱怨恨，却总是得益于怨恨——谁知道，这也是鄙人那些痼疾所带来的效应，乃至于鄙人终生都得感激涕零！然而，事情却并非那么简单：为了这个效应，你必须经历由至盛到至衰的生命历程。不管你得了什么样的疾病——只要在同病势、弱势相悖而行的情况下，体内原有的抗体，其抵御或者抵抗病情的能力就会减弱。你会浑身疼痛难忍，却不知何以摆脱痛楚、应付痛楚、击退痛楚。总之，病魔缠身，无以脱体，以至于病入膏肓，连记忆力也会严重减退。体弱多病，原本就是一种怨恨。对付它，患者唯有良药一剂——俄罗斯之宿命论。须知，本宿命论是不由反抗的，一个信奉它的俄国士兵，一旦在战役中支撑不住，便会倒在雪中，不吃不喝，不受外物，不汲取任何养料。自然，最终便不再有生命的迹象……这种宿命论最大的合理性在于，它不仅不会直接摧残人的意志，而且即便在你生命垂危之际，仍然能够延续你的生命。然而，这种宿命论的危害却在于，它仅仅通过降低人的新陈代谢功能，使之缓慢运作，最终麻醉人的意志。在逻辑上，如果给以上流程再加上几个步骤，那么，人们就完全可以推测出：即便你被送进了坟墓，你仍然可以再睡上几个礼拜……因为，人如果处处都得作出快速的反应，其生命就会枯竭，最终便会完全丧失肌体的反应能力，这便是宿命论的逻辑。其实，没有什么东西比怨恨更能消耗生命的火焰了。恼怒、对病魔的敏感、无力复仇的抱怨、欲望的失落、复仇的怒火、任何意义上的造孽——这些，对一个精疲力竭的人来说，无疑是对其反应最具副作用的因素，比如，它足以招致神经能量的快速消耗，同时导致病人排泄量增大，入胃胆汁多。怨恨，乃是患者的禁忌，患者的魔鬼；可悲的是，怨恨又是患者难以克制的情绪。深谙此道者，莫过于那位渊博的生理学家——佛陀释迦牟尼，他紧紧地抓住了人性的这个弱点。释迦的“宗教”，以消弭怨恨而著称，不如叫作“系统的卫生术”便妥了，也省得人家将其同以怜悯著称的基督教混为一谈，为求心灵之自由，必得先求躯体之健康，这是不言而喻的。“以怨报怨，怨重怨；以德报怨，怨消怨”，这是释迦“卫生术”的第一条教义，它不是道德的说教，而是生理学的原理。怨恨的天性是脆弱，因而到头来伤害最大的不是别人，而是意志薄弱、怨天尤人者本人。相反，富裕的天性则是预设，而试图成为这种预设的主宰者，却几乎是所有富人的特征。其实，这是一种自作多情的表现。主张向复仇心理和报复行为作斗争，乃至于向“自由意志”论宣战，乃是鄙人全部的哲学逻辑，而反对基督教的斗争只是其中一次特殊的战役而已。只要懂得这一思想严肃性的人，便会明白正是在这些问题上，表现着我个人的社会承担和我人性哲学的实践意义。然而，在那些颓废的日子里，鄙人只能将所有这些，视若有害的东西而不得远离了它们；而生活变得充裕并值得骄傲的时候，我又将它们置于脑后而暂时忘却它们。多年来，所谓“俄罗斯宿命论”之于鄙人，总是一旦抓住机会就紧紧地纠缠着我，而且，年复一年地，几乎总是在痛楚难熬的时间和地点，总是在疼痛难忍的住所里和人群中发生。还好，不必改变它们，也不必为它们所改变，更不必固执地反抗它们……奇怪得很，在那些日子里，时而自己好似已被宿命论所击败，时而又似乎还在宿命论的包围中挣扎，并企图拼命地苏醒过来。谁知道，每一次这样的试探，都是一件冒着生命危险的事情。认命，不再奢望自身的“改变”——这里，正是理性本身的力量。

VII

至于战争，却是另一码事。鄙人，天性好战，本能好攻。能够与人为敌，成为他人的敌人——或许，是需要某种与生倶来的天性作为其强悍的支撑的。换言之，强悍的天性在任何情况下，都足以成为“与人为敌”的必要条件。强悍的天性需要耐力的支持，因此必须培养耐力。好战心的必要性之于强者，恰如报复与复仇心理之于弱者，这是自不待言的。比如，女人的报复心理，是以其柔弱的生理条件为前提的，正如她们对别人的同情心是以其心理上的敏感性为条件一样。同样，一个好攻的强者必定以力量为前提，而且必须达到一定的标准。每一次力量的增强都意味着就对手或者问题的一次挑战。对一个好战的哲学家来说，有一个挑战的问题，才能与劲敌决斗。决斗即便征服了对手，也绝非单凭耐力便可以奏效，需要以全部的力量、坚韧的毅力以及驾驭武器的能力通览全局，才足以在势均力敌的情况下克敌制胜……而一场势均力敌的决斗，其先决条件是，它必须是一场正当的决斗。若一个人鄙视对手，他就不能向他挑战；若一个人发号施令或期待某些东西不如自己时，他也不能发起挑战。根据鄙人的经验，提出如下四条战略建议。首先，鄙人主张只攻击战绩显赫的目标，在特殊情况下，还可以待到对方战绩显赫时再进行攻击。其次，鄙人主张只攻击孤立的或者尚未结成同盟的目标，以便各个解决。一旦招致失败，还可以进退两便，决不在敌众我寡、敌勇我疲的情况下作战，这便是鄙人的作战原则。再次，鄙人决不主张实行个人攻击——对于个人，鄙人只将他们用作放大镜一般的工具，以便探知那些难以察明、难以接触的丑恶。那便是鄙人击败大卫·斯特劳斯的战术，准确地说那便是鄙人取胜于德意志老年修养术的诀窍——正是鄙人当场揭穿了那种修养术的秘密……那也是鄙人取胜于瓦格纳的秘诀，准确地说那便是鄙人揭穿我们“文化”之虚伪乃至将精明与富裕、后期与伟大混为一谈之混血天性的妙方。最后，鄙人主张只抨击那些抛开不良背景不谈、排除个性区别不论的事与物。其实，就鄙人而言，攻击是为了求证善意，在特殊情况下，乃是为了表达感恩。只要将鄙人的名字同一个人、一件事联系在一起，鄙人都会引以为荣，都会倍觉骄傲——无论这个人是志同道合之辈还是离经叛道之流，我完全不在乎。果真向基督教宣战，鄙人是有这个权利的，因为在反对基督教义的征途上鄙人从未经历过失意的事情，即便是最虔诚的基督徒，也能同鄙人和平相处。于是，作为基督强制教义的敌对者，鄙人绝不会因世纪的命运问题，而对一个特定的个体[5]怀恨在心。

VIII

这里，还得冒昧介绍鄙人性格上的最后一个特点，因为正是这一点造成了鄙人同他人交往中不小的麻烦。好洁净，乃鄙人与生倶来之脾性，甚至可以说是一种非常离奇的癖好，这让我的生理感觉——嗅觉——近似于……或是……怎么说呢？对于人体内部的各类构件——内脏的每一个细微部分，鄙人均能借助于这个敏感的生理触觉，深入并且探知其每一个角落的秘密：所有隐藏在灵魂深处的丑陋东西——无论是先天血统的遗传或是后天教育的禀赋，只要通过一次直接的接触，鄙人几乎都可以准确地觉察出来。如果这些觉察是正确的，洁癖的嗅觉就会对其所觉察到的东西产生本能的抵触，而相应的大脑器官则会小心翼翼地对其作出厌恶的反应，于是，它们绝不会错误地发出扑鼻的香气来……就这样，习惯养成自然。一个对环境苛刻的要求便成了我生命中不可缺少的元件，舍此，在一个肮脏的环境中，我便无法生存。足见，鄙人只能在清澈的水中，或是在近乎透明、发光的自然环境中游弋、沐浴和嬉戏。由于这一癖好，在同他人相处时，鄙人务必持有极大的耐性，于是，鄙人的博爱，便不仅要表现在宽容地同他人相处，还得表现在耐心地同别人交流……博爱，简直是一个对鄙人长期自持能力的考验。好在，鄙人常常需要与世隔绝，换言之——鄙人得恢复健康，回归自我，还得呼吸一点儿自由、轻松而愉悦的空气……整部《扎拉图斯拉的独白》，就是一首关于独居生活或是对“与世隔绝”的赞歌或是狂想曲什么的，或者不如直接说，《扎拉图斯拉的独白》就是一首关于“洁癖的赞美诗”。但愿它绝不是在赞美白痴。只要不是色盲的人，都能辨别得出，它是一颗璀璨钻石。见不得人类，见不得“乌合之众”，乃是鄙人人性中最大的弱点。因为，它会招来人生最大的危险……如此，您还愿意倾听《扎拉图斯拉的独白》，以资赎回那些“见不得”的代价？

我，怎么了？怎么才能摆脱那“见不得”的窠臼？谁，足以使我双眼复明？怎么才能飞往那理想的高度？那里，“乌合之众”不再坐上辩护人的席位。

诸多的“见不得”，可曾为我插上飞翔的翅膀？可曾为我增添潜水的能量？没错，我得飞至巅峰，以便再一次找至欢乐的源泉。

哦，我找到啦，我的兄弟们！这里就是巅峰！瞧，欢乐的泉水，正向我涌来！生命的泉水，没有乌合之众与我共饮。

欢乐的泉水啊，您不必过于性急！因为，越是急着倒满，越容易全部洒出。

我，小心翼翼地向您靠近：心，依然向您飞去，不过，也显得过于性急。

我的心，像火热的夏天，短暂、滚烫、忧郁而过于乐观；我的心，像炎热的夏天，渴望那泉水带来的清凉！

春天里，缠绵的苦恼，随和风而离去！六月里，多情的怨恨，像雪花一样飘去！我，全然地来到了夏天——炎热的仲夏。

巅峰的夏日，伴之以清凉的泉水，随之以天堂的静谧。来吧，朋友！静谧将带来良多的福分！

这里是我们的巅峰，这里是我们的家园。在这里，我们超然物外，让宵小之辈望尘莫及。

朋友，快将你纯洁的目光投向这欢乐的源泉！别担心，它闪烁的光华不会黯然失色！否则，它纯洁的秉性会嘲笑你胆量不足。

在未来的大树上，我们将筑好自己的“家”，孤独时，雄鹰必定会衔着食物飞来！

不错，宵小之辈哪能享得了这种福分？因为吃了这里“火”，便会烧坏了他们的胃。

不错，我们没有在这里为宵小之辈们预留他们的“窝”！我们的福窝，便是他们的冰窖，必定会冻坏了他们的“灵”与“肉”。

让我们像疾风一般，傲居在宵小之辈的头顶之上。以雄鹰为伴，以冰雪为邻，在阳光的沐浴中生活，那便是疾风生命的轨迹。

像疾风一般——总有一天，我会穿梭于宵小之辈的腰间与背上，用我的精神窒息他们灵魂的呼吸。总有一天，我会实现自己的夙愿。

不错，《扎拉图斯拉的独白》就是一股强劲的疾风，它将吹遍地球上所有的角落；它将告诫对手及其所有以唾沫伤人的人：尔等小心为妙，不得迎风而唾！

机灵，岂但如此

I

论智力，总比别人多根筋；论机灵，总比别人多根弦，诸如此类的问题，总也不曾少打搅人。不过，对于那些没什么实际意义的问题，那些无聊的事情，鄙人从不白费工夫去考虑、去涉足便是了。譬如，鄙人从不涉足什么宗教难题之类的破烦事儿。至于，像在何种意义上，人应该有什么“负罪”感之类的问题，鄙人便全然不知所以了。同样，鄙人更没有什么良心自责一类的内疚可言：什么扪心自问，哪来的道听途说？对此，鄙人毫无敬意可言。不过，这里实不该留一手，以便后发制人，我宁愿当场将邪恶的结果揭露于世，并从价值观上剖析邪恶的过程，这才是鄙人做事的原则。因为，一旦知道了邪恶的结果，人们便会怀疑他们做过的事情。在鄙人看来，所谓良心的自责，实际上是一种相信邪恶的心理反应。越是错了，越是要提醒自己错了，这便是一种自我尊重，换言之，这便是符合我认为的伦理学原则的做法。什么“上帝”，什么“灵魂不死”，什么“赎罪”，什么“来世”，对于这些观念，鄙人从来都没有兴趣，也没有时间去理睬它们，鄙人从小就是这个脾气。或许，对付这一类事情，鄙人从来都不敢“孩子气”十足！因为我根本不知道无神论是推理的产物，更不知道它是事件的产物。在我看来，它显然出于本能。这，显然也是鄙人的天性所致了。鄙人好奇、多疑、目空一切，那些不成熟的结论，从来都不能满足鄙人的胃口。譬如，信奉上帝，便是一个不成熟的结论——一个同思想家的观念背道而驰的粗率结论。这甚至在本质上，便是对思想家们的一个赤裸裸的禁令：不许你们思考！按照神学家们的诠释，“拯救人类”的不是别的，而是他们的奇谈怪论，这是一个异乎寻常的说法，是一个关于人类“精神”营养的问题，对此鄙人便不能不发生极大的兴趣。为了方便起见，按照常规我们可以这样设想：“为了获得最大的体力、最好的文艺复兴时期的艺术品、最为脱俗的德行，人们该怎样修炼自己呢？”在这些方面，鄙人的经验简直贫乏极了。鄙人接触这类问题太晚，无从尽快获得经验，对于这一点，连我自己也感到惊讶。唯有一文不值的德意志教育及其“理想主义”可以从某种程度上解释为什么偏偏在这一点上，鄙人怎么也赶不上“教皇”的要求。这种“教育”，从一开始就教导鄙人忽略现实，一味地追逐虚无缥缈的、“理想”的人生目标。譬如，德意志的“古典教育”就是一个例子——似乎，企图将“古典”和“德意志”从概念上合而为一，并不是一件毫无收获的事情！再说，一个生活在现代社会的莱比锡人，却得接受古典式的德意志教育，这难道不是一件滑稽可笑的事情吗？！说老实话，为了赎回厨师和那些基督教徒们的面子，鄙人从小到大都没吃过几顿像样的饭。按照所谓伦理学的术语说，那便是“非我主义”“忘我主义”“利他主义”云云。然而，正是在莱比锡人膳食的陪伴下，鄙人完成了早期的叔本华研究（1865年），而且认真地改变了自己的“生命意愿”。以伤害自己的胃口为代价，去接受一种不合时宜的营养观念——在鄙人看来，上述的烹调术足以完美地回答这个问题了。那么，一般意义上的德意志烹调术，在什么地方昧了它的良心呢？！

餐前羹——直到十六世纪，在威尼斯食谱中依然含有“去德意志”的意思：肉片、油面菜、（镇纸压制的）变质布丁！如此食谱，如果用上古兽性十足的餐饮方式用膳，那就绝不仅仅是古德意志人才了解德意志精神的渊源了，此乃伤肠害胃之道也……德意志精神是一种食古不化的典型，谁也对付不了。不过，相对于德意志人乃至法兰西人的饮食习惯，英吉利人的饮食习惯则大有“回归天性”或是“同类相餐”的味道。不管怎样，鄙人的胃口是受不了的。在鄙人看来，这似乎像在精神的躯体上添加了一双沉重的脚丫——一双英吉利女人的脚丫。不过，最佳的饮食习惯，大概要算是皮德蒙特人了。

我不胜酒力，一杯红酒或是啤酒下肚，都足以让我一整天都在“云里雾里”中度过，那是谁都不情愿做的事情。懂得这一点，虽然迟了一些，却是我从孩提时起就有过的事。就像抽烟一般，小时候只觉得喝酒不过是年少轻狂的举止而已，后来不知不觉地便养成了喝酒的坏习惯。得到如此严肃的教训，或许还是拜瑙姆堡葡萄酒所赐呢。如果真的相信喝酒会使人精神振奋起来的话，说不定鄙人早已变成一个基督徒了——那便是让鄙人去相信连自己都以为是最荒唐的事。不过，奇怪的是，只要少许饮用一点度数很低的烈酒，自己便会感到浑身不自在；如果再稍稍地多来一点儿，那更足以令人晕头转向了。

然而，在写作方面，鄙人却从小便表现出非凡的意志来——雄心勃勃，笔耕不辍，立志模仿偶像塞勒斯特[6]严谨而简明的写作风格。为了用拉丁文写就一篇巨制论文，鄙人常常会伏案写作，彻夜不眠，之后还得接着将文中的内容写成报道材料，以备报刊发表之用。而且，文章脱稿之后，还得在写好的拉丁文上涂一层上好的保护膜，以防文本损坏。这些事，在鄙人还是著名的（舒尔）普福塔[7]中学学生的时候，就开始做了。或许，这些都同鄙人的生理学观念直接相关；或许，并不见得同塞勒斯特的生理学观念有所相悖——尽管这同（舒尔）普福塔中学的办学理念在很大程度上是不相吻合的。说实话，直至后来人到中年的时候，鄙人才从严格意义上远离了任何“高酒精成分的”饮料。但是，因为在生活经验上反对素食主义，鄙人便不能郑重其事地劝诫那些超凡脱俗的人们滴酒不沾。这一点，或许同理查德·瓦格纳只能改变鄙人志趣而不能改变鄙人志向是一个道理。水足以满足人的各种需要，因而谁都喜欢住在处处都有清水流动的地方（如尼斯、都灵、锡尔斯等地）；一杯清水，会像一只爱犬一般每每陪伴在你的身边——那是多么惬意！常言道“酒后吐真言”，然而，在这一点上，关于什么是“真言”的问题，鄙人又该同世界较真了——在鄙人这里，“真言”是像流水一般运动的，这里的教训足以给人们更多的启示。

谁知道，一次盛宴要比一顿素餐容易消化得多？消化良好的前提是，胃口的各项功能都能协调发挥。首先，你得知道你胃口的大小。为了避免消化不良，你得回避那些单调乏味、耗时过多的聚餐，这里不妨称之为“间歇式献祭宴会”，就像那些旅馆或者饭店中的客饭席一般的小宴会。两餐之间，不用零食，不喝咖啡——咖啡会使你忧郁沮丧、精神不佳。早晨用茶，好处最多，量不必大，味却得浓。沏茶过淡，不利健康，甚至会让人整天都面带病容，萎靡不振。万事万物皆有度，恰到好处最难得。天气不佳时，早晨便不宜用茶了，只需在平日用茶时间的前一个小时，喝上一杯浓浓的去脂可可茶便可以了。小坐，不必幻想户外会有气象万千，因为思绪若不定，筋骨便不安。偏见，无不源自消化不顺。勤勉，我前面曾提过，是对圣灵真正的冒犯。

II

跟营养问题最接近的，自然是地理和气候问题了。对于居住之地，谁都不能没有自己的选择；可是，就一个肩负使命的人而言，他得付出九牛二虎之力才足以了事，因为对这类人而言，居住地的挑选余地，实在是太小了。譬如，他们得考虑那里的气候会不会影响新陈代谢的节奏，会减慢，还是加快，甚至，连同居住点和气候状况相关的大大小小的问题全都要考虑进去，因为任何一次不经意的疏漏，都可能使他们疏远自己的工作，甚至还可能使他们终身放弃自己的社会职责。当然，他们自己也可能从来都没有意识到这一点——生命的活力，为什么不足以使其得心应手地进入自己所熟稔的精神领域呢？在这方面，又是非鄙人莫属了。不过，在鄙人看来，单单一个新陈代谢的节奏问题还是微不足道的，因为它还不至于酿成一种不良的积习，乃至将一位天才人物变成一个庸碌之辈——一个“德意志”般的庸才；或许，唯有德意志的天气，才足以损害强健神奇的五脏功能。新陈代谢的节奏，同一个人精神气质的动与静有着密切的关系，其实，精神本身就是新陈代谢的一种反映。如果我们将这些不同的反映，用表格的方式排列出来，就会发现有的地方是天才正在居住或曾经居住过的，有的地方适宜居住视拥有智慧、优雅、谋略为幸福的人，有的地方则总是会有天才们安家，这些地方都拥有无与伦比的干爽空气。巴黎、普罗旺斯、佛罗伦萨、耶路撒冷、雅典，这些地名都足以告诉人们：天高气爽、万里无云的地方，乃是天才的摇篮。换言之，快节奏的新陈代谢，汲取无穷能量的几率才是孕育天才的先决条件。曾经有过这样一个例子，有一位本应成为重量级人物的自由人士，最终却竟然成了一个心胸狭窄、孤陋寡闻、脾气暴躁的家伙，其原因不过是由于缺乏感觉的本能性灵敏，而选择了气候不宜居住的地点而已。幸亏病魔让鄙人变得理智而聪慧，并且学会了用推理的方式辨别现实，否则难保鄙人不会遭此下场。如今，经由长期的实际磨练，鄙人依靠自己已经能够像从一台精确而可靠的气象仪器上读数一样，说出各地气候的基本情况来。甚至，在短途旅行中，鄙人还能够根据自身的生理体验，觉察出空气湿度的变化来，譬如从都灵到米兰的旅程就是这样。

想起近十年不可思议的生活来，我至今还会后怕。那十年，是我生命的危险期，生活在一个与生命需求根本不适宜的地方——自然，肯定是选错了地方。瑙姆堡、（舒尔）普福塔、图林根、莱比锡、巴塞尔、威尼斯——就鄙人身体的生理状况而言，这些都是不该去的地方。

至于，童年和青年时期，是根本不值得回忆的，而如果将这些都归咎于所谓道德教育的缘故，那就未免太愚蠢了。譬如，鄙人没有志同道合的伙伴，这是无可非议的，因为，至今鄙人仍然没有志同道合者相随，或许永远都不会有，可是这些还不至于妨碍鄙人勇敢无畏、兴高采烈地生活。不懂生理学，憎恶“理想主义”，是鄙人生命中两个难以回避的致命弱点，其中有冗余的东西，也有愚蠢的表现，二者都不是善举，因为它们既无以补偿，又无从反驳。

所有人生中的失误，乃至所有致使离开人生目标的本性和态度上的变化，鄙人都将它们看作是“理想主义”招致的后果。譬如，在鄙人为什么会成为一位语文学家的问题上，或许，有人会说，尼采起码可以成为一位内科医生或是别的什么足以惊人耳目的人物，为什么没有呢？等等。在巴塞尔大学的那些日子里，鄙人的精力非常充沛，但是鄙人的整个精神生活，却是一塌糊涂的。生命的意义何在，从不考虑，从不反省。在每天的时间安排上，全是重复性的内容，从来都不会用什么别的内容替换那些重叠的东西。不过，那时候却没有什么肮脏的自私心理，也没有什么所谓发自本能的自我保护意识什么的，可以说人人都是平等的，一切都是“无私”的，一切都是“忘我”的。然而，到头来，这些却都成了鄙人永远也不能原谅自己的地方，因为差一点儿，便到了生命的终点。就这样，我便开始反省那些生命中本来就不合理的东西——“理想主义”。谢天谢地！是“病魔”将我带上了回归真实世界的路。

III

一是，选择养分；二是，选择气候和居住地；三则，必定是选择一种修身养性的方式了，这样，人生就不至于再犯大大小小的毛病了。所有这些，对于自成一类的人物来说，要求便会更苛刻一些。然而，就他们本身的利益而言，却会更有用一些。就鄙人而言，广泛的阅读乃是自我修养的方式之一，因此，凡能给鄙人自由的书籍，凡能让鄙人在奇怪的学科和思想之间闲庭信步的书目，总之，凡此种种都是鄙人阅读的对象，不过，鄙人不再对它们过于当真。准确地说，正是广泛的阅读，将鄙人从一本正经的较真中解救了出来。平日里，在埋头工作的时候，鄙人身边是不留书的，也不允许任何人在身边说话，甚至连在身边思考问题也不行。然而，这正是我阅读的奥妙之所在。读者可曾注意到，在大脑高度集中的状态下，整个思维乃至整个肌体都处于一个精神酝酿的过程之中，任何偶发事件、任何外部的刺激都会对主体构成一个意外的刺激，都会引起主体的激烈反应。于是，主体必须尽可能避免任何突发的事件、任何强烈的刺激。筑起一道自我保护的壁垒，乃是培养灵感，孕育精神的本能的、明智的策略之一。那么，要不要特许某个奇异的思想，悄然地爬过这个自我保护的壁垒呢？毋须讳言，这便是阅读的初衷了。劳动与收获同修身与养性，应当交替而行，轮换而做，因为同修身养性为伴的是快乐，是智慧，是智慧的结晶——书！然者，是德意志的书吗？这便得从半年前打鄙人手上滑过的一本书说起。那是一本什么书呢？那是维克托·布罗夏德的一项杰出的研究成果，书名是《古希腊怀疑论者（研究）》，其中引用了我在《第欧根尼·拉尔修论集》[8]中的不少观点。古希腊的怀疑论，在是它两倍甚至五倍模糊的哲学思想中，是唯一值得尊崇的！否则，鄙人大概就会永远在几本鄙人同类的书中周旋，也只能仅对这类书籍的内容了如指掌了。或许，鄙人生性不愿多读、滥读，如果老是闷在书房里自会受不了的。鄙人生来也不愿多爱、泛爱，对于新书，鄙人的态度是——与其“忍”着读，放心看，或者存点儿敬意耐心看，倒不如小心一点儿，乃至敌对一些的好。说真的，在古典法兰西作家中，只有为数不多的几个，值得人们爱不释读。鄙人仅笃信法兰西文化，并且认为将所有欧洲的东西全都称之为“文化”是一个误会，更不必提德意志文化了。在德意志的文化高人中，鄙人所知者并不多，而且究其根底，他们还都是曾受过法兰西文化熏陶的人。首屈一指的，自然是瓦格纳夫人科茜玛了。她嗓音的天资，的确是一流的。鄙人虽不读帕斯卡，但却喜欢帕斯卡，因为在为基督捐躯者中他是最有启发性的人物，先是生理的牺牲，后是心理的逐杀，他都无一幸免——这，便是基督教残无人性的全部逻辑所在。或许，鄙人天生便有蒙田[9]的任性，生来便知蒙田的放荡。是也，非也，天晓得？在艺术家的气度上，鄙人则颇有几分莎士比亚的放荡不羁和愤世嫉俗，即便如此，即便如彼，却毫不影响鄙人对法兰西晚期贤达的敬仰，他们的人数是不在少数的，鄙人仍得维护莫里哀、柯奈和拉辛等法兰西名流的高洁，抵制莎士比亚之流天才的无序，即便如彼，却毫不影响鄙人对法兰西晚期一诸贤达的敬仰。真不敢想象，历史上还有哪个时代，同当今巴黎一样拥有如此好奇而精明的心理学家。这里，试举几例——其人数的确不少——如保罗·布尔热（1852—1935，法国作家、批评家。——译者注）、皮埃尔·洛蒂（1850—1923，法国小说家。——译者注）、吉普、美拉克、阿纳托尔·法朗士（1844—1924，法国小说家。——译者注）、朱尔·勒梅特尔（1800—1876，法国喜剧演员。——译者注），或许还可以举出一位出身显赫的人物来，他便是鄙人特别垂青的拉丁文天才居伊·德·莫泊桑（1850—1893，法国作家。——译者注）。对于他们，我们宁肯偏信后代，而不轻信前代——所谓他们的导师那一代人，因为所谓导师那一代尽为德意志哲学所毒害的人。譬如，M.泰纳（1828—1893，另译“丹纳”，法国文艺理论家、史学家。——译者注）便是受了黑格尔毒害的人，他对伟人及其时代的误解大概都是拜黑格尔所赐。凡德意志影响所及之处，其文化无不受其侵害。不要忘了，法兰西乃是用战争“赎回”其文化精神的。司汤达（1783—1842，又译“斯丹达尔”，法国作家。——译者注）乃是鄙人人生路上难得的遇合之一，因为凡是鄙人人生中具有里程碑意义的东西都是偶然发生的，绝无什么他人的指点之类。而司汤达对心理学的见地是独具慧眼的，他对事态的悟性，则足以使你离真实的伟人最近——看到鹰爪，便知道拿破仑要来了，其价值是无法估量的。最后，必须提及的便是，法兰西历史上难得的稀罕人物——鄙人得另眼看待的、可敬的无神论者普罗斯佩·梅里美。或许，在二人之间，鄙人还是偏重于司汤达，因为，在无神论的境界上，司汤达与我，或者我与司汤达殊途同归了，司汤达笑道：“上帝最好的借口，便是他并不存在。”而我，竟也在什么地方说过：“而今，存在的威胁者，是谁？曰：上帝……”

IV

我在所有千年的王国里追寻，追寻那种美妙而富有激情的乐章，最终都以徒劳而告终。抒情诗人，乃是海因里希·海涅（1797—1856，德国诗人、政论家。——译者注）给我的最高的称谓。海涅借给鄙人一种天赐的怨恨，离开了这个怨恨，鄙人便无以完成那美妙的想象，因为在判断人类及其种族的价值时，便是看他们能不能将上帝与萨梯（希腊神话中半人半兽的森林之神。——译者注）区分开来。海涅的德语造诣极高！总有一天，会有人宣布鄙人和海涅都是一流的德文大师——无论在哪一方面，都是德意志本土人望尘莫及的。世人必将以我的语言天赋同拜伦《曼弗雷德》[10]的语言艺术相提并论，鄙人早已独自发现了万恶之渊，而那时，鄙人不过十三岁而已。我无言以对，只是想看看是什么人胆敢在《曼弗雷德》的面前重提《浮士德》[11]的大名。德意志人是无以得知“伟大”概念的内涵的：舒曼（1810—1856，德国作曲家。——译者注）便是一例。

出于对口蜜腹剑的撒克逊人[12]的愤慨，鄙人为《曼弗雷德》作了“跋”。对此，汉斯·冯·比洛却质疑说，他不曾在原稿中见过此类“跋”文，这简直是对神灵的冒犯。于是，当鄙人在莎士比亚的创作范式中寻找最适合鄙人的格式时，发现凯撒（大帝）的形象乃是莎翁独到的笔触，绝不是他人照猫画虎便足以得来的笔墨——人们绝不敢想象连这样的事情也会发生。于是，要么就是它，要么绝不是它。伟大诗人的创作是唯一的，因为他依据的是自己的亲身经历。在作品完成之后，即便是作者本人也不能再一次经历同样的境遇，以便复制作品的原貌了。鄙人，曾试图再次经历《扎拉图斯拉的独白》的“坎坷”，然而，即便在书屋中踱步半晌，也只能以一阵难以控制的抽噎无果而终了。不知世间还有什么著述能比读莎士比亚的戏剧更让人撕心裂肺。试想：使一个滑稽戏剧中的小丑感人至此，作家要经受多大的磨难！哈姆雷特感人吗？使读者发狂的，不是疑惑，而是信以为真……然而，要察觉到人物的真实性，读者还得有这个造诣，有这个修养，还得有一个推理正常的头脑，所有的人，都会敬畏真理。而且，说实话，鄙人从不怀疑培根先生乃是此类怪诞文学的开创者、自戕者，既如此，又何须在乎美利坚那些知识浅薄、头脑不清的可怜虫呢？然而，想象中的真实之所以感人，是因为它来自事实中的真实感受，甚至后者乃是前者的先决条件。无论在何种意义上，培根先生都是首屈一指的唯实论者，但是实际上人们对他要做什么，做了些什么，他的内心世界又是什么？都还知之甚少……见鬼去吧，可爱的批评家们！

假若，当初鄙人予“扎拉图斯拉”的取名不是如此，而是叫“理查德·瓦格纳”，那么，就算修炼了两千年的洞察力也难以看出，《人性的，太人性的》[13]的作者是扎拉图斯拉的幻影……

V

这里，在涉及鄙人生命创造力的问题之前，先得说句感恩的话，以便对改变鄙人人生价值观发生过影响的方方面面，表达真诚的、意味深长的感激之情。毫无疑问，这里最亲密的关系都是和理查德·瓦格纳的名字联系在一起的。至于，所欠其他人的情谊，鄙人都可以一笔带过。然而，不管怎样，在特里布森的那些日子，鄙人是决不会忘记的，那是彼此信任的时光，那是令人兴奋的时光，那是无上崇高的时光，那是弥足珍贵的时光……鄙人，虽不知别人同瓦格纳相处的经历，但鄙人却见证了我俩彼此友谊的象征，乃是万里无云的长空。说到这里，又得提起法国了，对瓦格纳的粉丝还有其他的追随者来说，只要他们觉得瓦格纳身上还有什么同他们相似的地方，那便是他们在向瓦格纳先生表示敬慕了。对此，鄙人该有千条理由拥护，没有半点借口妒忌。其实，鄙人也是一样的——骨子里从不接受德意志的东西，甚至连见到一个德意志般的人影，也会觉得倒胃口。于是，同瓦格纳的第一次接触，便注定要成为鄙人人生中大口吸氧的头一回：在鄙人的眼中，瓦格纳便像是外星来客一般，像是德意志人的对立面，乃至于简直是所有德意志德行的反面案例。“德意志人”这个概念，对从小呼吸“沼泽空气”长大的五十多岁的人来说，简直是悲观主义者的代名词。这些人，除了成为“德意志人”的革命者以外，别无选择。无论怎样，这些人都绝不会对那些固执偏见的现象保持沉默的——即便他们会改头换面，即便他们身披红装，再着以（欧洲）轻骑兵式的制服，在鄙人看来，那也是完全无关大局的事情。谁都知道，瓦格纳也是一位叛逆者，也逃离过德国人的藩篱。除了巴黎以外，艺术家便无以在欧洲找到自己的栖身之地。因为只有在巴黎，艺术家才能找到瓦格纳所设想的五种柔和的感觉，如手指上的细微差别、心理上的病态感觉等。在艺术激情的表现力上，在艺术摄制的严肃性上，绝没有什么地方可以同巴黎同日而语——那是典型的巴黎式“严肃”，是绝无仅有的艺术语言。惊世骇俗的抱负，乃是法兰西艺术家的灵魂，而在德意志却连这种概念也不曾有过。德意志人，本性“从善”，而瓦格纳却偏偏生来便不知“从善”为何物。好在，鄙人已多次交代了瓦格纳的人格以及什么人同他来往最多的问题：瓦格纳是法国后期的浪漫主义艺术家，像德拉克洛瓦和柏辽兹（1803—1869，法国作曲家。——译者注）一样，也是那种野心勃勃，令人亢奋的艺术家。他们天生病态，无药可救，是滔滔不绝的狂热分子，是彻彻底底的艺术名家。那么，谁是瓦格纳最虔诚的首席信徒呢？那无疑是查尔斯·波德莱尔了，不过他也是第一个解读德拉克洛瓦的人。德拉克洛瓦是一个典型的颓废者，一个足以让所有艺术家认识自己的人。或许，他也是瓦格纳的最后一个信徒……尽管如此，在某些方面我却永远也不能原谅瓦格纳——他屈尊于德意志人，乃至于变成了德意志之外的德意志人。足见，只要在德意志影响可以延伸到的地方，文化便难免遭殃。

VI

不管怎样，离开了瓦格纳的音乐，鄙人是熬不过那病魔缠身的青年时代的。鄙人，生而屈尊为德意志人，一个人想要摆脱难以忍受的屈辱，必得求助于精神上的麻醉。于是，鄙人便找到了瓦格纳。在我眼中，瓦格纳乃是德意志绝无仅有的解毒之物。不过，它本身也是一种毒物，这是毋庸置疑的。只要一听到《特里斯坦》的钢琴乐曲响起，鄙人便会随之而成为瓦格纳的同路人——我的冯·比洛先生，这可不是我的恭维话！不过，对于瓦格纳早期的作品，鄙人却实在是不敢恭维的，因为它们实在是太普通，太“德意志”化了……尽管这样，我今日仍然企望还能找到像《特里斯坦》那样令人惊魂动魄，那样余音绕梁的佳作——鄙人翻遍了所有的“艺术”作品，然而还是得认输了。在《特里斯坦》的第一个音符面前，列奥纳多·达·芬奇所有的“奇特”都会黯然失色。《特里斯坦》是瓦格纳的登峰造极之作，之后他又接着创作了《迈斯特的歌手》和《指环》，希望能赶上《特里斯坦》的辉煌。然而，使瓦格纳始料未及的是，结果偏偏不能如他所愿，这，大概也是天资使然……鄙人，可算是生逢其时，还能偏偏在德意志人群中幸运地存活下来，以便来日有所担当。鄙人，心智敏捷而好奇善问，足以完成天赋的使命——此乃鄙人三生有幸之遇合也。对于一个从未病至“快意癫狂”的人，世界是不会眷顾的，因为，那几乎是一种必须履行的义务，是一种必须以神奇的方式才足以奏效的结果。瓦格纳之所以能取得惊人的成就，是因为唯有他长满了足以在千奇百怪、若喜若狂的大千世界里遨游的羽翼。这一点，鄙人比谁都心知肚明；而鄙人，则有足够的能力将问题最多、危险最大的劣势化为自身的优势，从而使自身倍加强大起来。不难想见，瓦格纳注定会成为鄙人生命中的施主。于是，我们相依为命，承受了这个世纪常人所不能承受的磨难，我们苦得其所，我们的名字将永远写在一起。自然，也像瓦格纳常常会被德意志人误读一样，鄙人也绝不会逃过这一劫的，永远也逃不过这一劫。不过，我的德意志人啊，要理解这两位大师，你们还得花上两个世纪的心智和艺术的修行啊！只怕你们还是达不到这个境界。

VII

对那些特别优异的读者，鄙人这里还得多说上几句：音乐到底给了鄙人什么呢？恰似十月里的一个午后，音乐给了鄙人愉悦的情怀和微妙的感觉。恰似一个小巧而迷人的女人，音乐给了鄙人个性、奢侈和温婉，鄙人，从未奢望过德意志民族中会出一个懂得音乐的人。通常，所谓德意志的音乐家，特别是最有名望的那些人，如果要究其出身的话，偏偏他们一个也不是真正的德意志人？要么是斯拉夫人，要么是克罗地亚人，要么是意大利人，要么是荷兰人，甚至是犹太人。不然的话，便是德意志高贵血统的人，或是已经绝后的德意志人，如海因里希·舒尔茨、巴赫和亨德尔等。至于我本人，足以称得上是一个地道的波兰人，因而又足以步肖邦音乐之后尘了。基于三个理由，鄙人要将瓦格纳的《西格弗里德田园曲》（牧歌）排除在高雅音乐之外，这里或许还应该包括李斯特（1811—1886，匈牙利钢琴家和作曲家。——译者注）的几个作品。虽然李斯特以其管弦乐队的高雅器乐的格调，略胜其他音乐家一筹。最后，还必须提到的，是阿尔卑斯山脉那边的音乐人。说到这里，便不能不提到罗西尼（1792—1868，意大利作曲家。——译者注），更不能不提南部的音乐家——威尼斯音乐大师皮特洛·加斯蒂。鄙人之所谓阿尔卑斯山脉的那边，其实仅仅是指威尼斯而已。而当鄙人试图以另外一个名词去替代“音乐”二字时，恐怕也只有“威尼斯”一词足以担当此任了。在鄙人的音乐世界里，音乐和眼泪，总是难解难分；在鄙人音乐的词典中，幸福同“南部”总是紧紧地联系在一起，而那幸福的南部，又总是同微微颤动的心灵连接在一起的。

近日，[14]

一个茶褐色的夜晚，

独自地，我伫立在桥头儿，

从远方，传来一阵悠扬的歌儿：

宛如一颗金色的水珠儿，

颤抖着，打水面滚来——越滚越近。

艘艘狭长的船儿，道道夜晚的光儿，声声飞来的音儿——

醉了一般，游进那朦胧的夜……

我的心，是一把上了弦儿的琴，

一双无形的手——拨动着那根敏感的弦儿——

奏出一首美妙的歌儿，附和着——那船上的曲儿，

我的心，颤抖着，颤抖着——那是幸福的炫耀。

——有人，

——听到否？

VIII

前述诸项选择——养分、气候和居地的选择，乃至修养方式的选择，都与人类自我保护的天性息息相关。人类需要对这些条件进行自我选择，说明自我保护乃是人类自卫的天性，这是毋庸置疑的。不必亲眼看到许多，不必亲耳听见许多，也不必亲自做过许多，只要有一次经验便能够足智多谋，只要有一回事实便足以证明本能的自卫不是可有可无的儿戏，而是务必实现的条件。关于自卫的天性，最能说明问题的例证莫过于味觉的灵敏了。在紧急情况下，尽管说“是”，可能是一种“正常”的反应，可人们常常还是会情不自禁地说“不”，而且总是要把说“不”的声音压得很低。于是，人们便会设法躲开或者回避那些常常需要说“不”的场面。这里的理论依据是，自卫是一种消费性的东西，而且还不是一种低消费，这种消费会形成一种潜规则，一种坏习惯，从而导致某种特殊的、完全没有必要的窘境或者发生尴尬情形。可见，人们最大的损失，常常是因为最小或者最寻常的毛病所招致的。避开那些小毛病，远离那些小毛病，也是需要花费代价的。在这个问题上，人们是不该自欺欺人的，因为，那便是在不必要的问题上耗费精力。但是，如果仅仅靠一味回避毛病来解决问题，人们便会无力自卫。假如，鄙人迈出了房门，出现在眼前不是幽静而富有贵族气派的都灵，而是德意志的某个地方城市，我辈便会本能地封闭自我，以便排除由眼前这个懦弱而乏味的世界所带来的一切压力。假如，出现在鄙人眼前的是某个德意志的大都会，其建筑风格不雅，且众木不生、良莠不齐、杂乱无章——如是，鄙人或许得变作豪猪，背着身子，退避三舍了。然而，如此弄得浑身是刺，恐怕是一种恣意妄为。即便允许你浑身无刺，只剩一双慷慨之拳，或许那是一种加倍的奢侈……

另一种明智的自卫方式是，尽可能不做任何反应，或尽可能远离复杂的局面和人际关系，免得自身的“自由”和“主动”被人剥夺，又从而成为别人的囊中之物。以书代游，便是鄙人的教义。在鄙人看来，学者不过是“翻动”书本的人物而已，一位文献学家，每天少说也得“翻动”二百本书，可最终他自己却丧失了思考的良机；一旦翻书停止了，他便无从思考了；即便他思考了，也不过是对某种刺激，某种他所翻动过的内容的反应而已。显然，文献学家的一次思考不过是一个反应罢了。学者们只会将自己毕生的精力都耗费在对现成思想的肯定或否定上，而他们所批判的也不过是别人已经思考过的东西——他自己是不必思考（没有思想的）的。正是在这种情形下，学者们自卫的本能便被削弱了，要不然，他们便会跟书过不去。足见，学者们是一个堕落的群体。这些，便是鄙人亲眼所见：本来天资聪颖，生活富有，而且人格自由的青年人，早已在他们三十多岁的黄金时段，因为“读”书而“毁”掉了他们的前程。他们活着的意义，仅在于像火柴棍一样，只需在既定要为之点燃的那一刻轻轻一划，擦出“思想”火花。

清晨，天刚破晓，万象俱新，谁人不是精力正旺，哪个不是神情正好？偏偏得用这一段最佳的时光，去读书，真乃罪过也！

IX

至此，鄙人便必须切实面对如何兑现自我价值的问题了。为此，鄙人精心撰写了关于自我维持的方式问题，即关于“自私”的艺术问题，那是别人的得意之笔。假若我们的使命、职业和天命都在相当程度超越了一般的意义，那么我们最大的风险，莫过于在使命的关照下认知自我。之所以需要兑现个体的价值，是因为人们往往不能从最长远的意义上读懂自己。换言之，人们并不懂得“自我”意味着什么。正是在这个意义上，即便是生命中的跌跌撞撞——一时的失足、失误、贻误、羞怯，乃至过于拘谨等，都会以外因的方式影响到使命的进程。其实，这些看似消极的阅历，都是有其积极意义和价值的。都是大智，乃至特智的另一种表达方式[15]：因为，“懂我”或许正是对付“毁我”的妙方，而“忘我”“误我”“虐我”“贬我”“庸我”的做法则无一不是“毁我”的根源所在。如果用道德主义者的说法，则是：只要爱他人，为他人、他物而生存，再严重的利己主义都足以得到保护。显然，这是站在“无私”的立场上说话的。这是一反鄙人往常做法和信念的情形，不过只是一个例外而已。其实，所谓的道德主义者，本来就是以自私自利为行，以自我教养为业的。人类的意识必须完全摆脱外部命令的强行制约，因为意识本来就是一个客观、外在、不受约束的存在物。另外，还必须提防不实之辞、不妥之念的负面干扰。可见，只有排除了所有的“风险”，天性方会“自我觉醒”。同时，那些注定要指挥你行为的组织“观念”便会越来越根深蒂固，开始居高临下，发号施令，并逐渐将你从边道、弯路上拽回，激活你足以独立的资质和能力。总有一天，这些资质和能力会化为成就你事业不可或缺的积淀乃至手段。除了足以为你的使命、目标、目的及其意义提供有益启示外，还表现出其他的辅助功能来。由此看来，鄙人的生活是简单的，也是奇妙的。既然需要重新估定所有的价值，就得有超乎常人的能力。不过，这些能力却不得自相矛盾，自相对立。能力要有秩序，有区别（差异）；分类方式不能相互抵触；能力之间必须相互协调，不得互为混淆；诸多能力的结构绝对不能杂乱无章——所有这些便是鄙人成功的先决条件，也是鄙人天生的艺术工作，乃至长期积淀的劳动秘密。至于对自身的内在修养，鄙人却从来都不做最明确的规划和设计。这个事实说明，能力的增长只能通过对天性的善加呵护去实现。懂得这一点是重要的，但是，也必须明白：总有一天，鄙人所有的能力都会在一夜之间趋于成熟，达到巅峰，达成终极的完美。正因为这样，鄙人从来也不曾觉得生命中会有什么烦恼的事情，更找不到什么强勉奋争的痕迹，因为鄙人天生就不是一块什么英雄的料。要“得到”什么，要“追求”什么，立什么“目标”，树什么“夙愿”之类的宏图大志，鄙人生命的过程中，从来都没有这般的事。即便在此刻，眺望生命的未来——遥远的未来！也恰似眺望那空空如也的大海，大风吹皱了所有的海面，却不见一丝奢望。一切便是一切，不必作丝毫的变动；我便是我，何须作多余的润色？谁都可以存疑，不过那便是鄙人永久的生命方式。鄙人，心无鸿鹄之志，何必躲躲闪闪！若夫，岁逾不惑之年，谁人不追名逐利？哪个不图女人欢？不过，我尚无此愿也。虽曾荣获过学府里的教授头衔，却也未曾奢望过那档子事。那阵子，我不过一个二十四岁的人而已。

X

有人一定会问：尼采怎么就会讲述些传统上微不足道的事情？我的回答是：既然注定要担当人间之大任，我便得通过讲述这些微不足道的小事加倍“考验”自己。在我眼中：关于营养、地域、气候、修身之方式乃至对自我中心主义之诡辩，这些常人所微不足道的，其意义超越了所有概念的重要性，远不是迄今为止人们以为最重要的东西所能比。准确地说，人们务必学会用新的、不同的方式，重新审度以往的事与物，而且，务必从当下便开始。其实，迄今为止，人们所信以为真的东西，也绝非全然属实，乃至尚有纯属臆测者耳——如果从更为深刻的意义上说，那些所谓臆测之事物，不过是渊源于人性之病态乃至劣根性的谎言罢了——诸如“上帝”“灵魂”“美德”“罪孽”“来世”“真理”和“永生”一类的概念，全都是谎言。问题在于，人们却偏偏要从这里找出一个人性的“伟大”和“神圣”来不可。于是，害群之马便被奉为贤达之士。结果，所有政治的问题，社会的秩序，乃至教育的制度都从根本上扭曲了——审度以往的是非，蔑视一切的谎言，则被说成是生命中无足轻重的“琐事”而加以非难……于是，鄙人便不得不将自己同古往今来的名流贤达置于同一个天平之上——区别，乃是显而易见的。好在，鄙人并没有将这里天平上的名流及其贤达划归于人类的范畴，因为在鄙人的眼中，他们生性有病，图谋有毒，是人类的渣子，是发育不良的怪胎，完全是一群恶贯满盈、不可救药的怪兽，而其所为之事，不过是对人类进行的报复而已，鄙人必以这群怪兽为敌。于是，无以伦比的机敏，便是鄙人健全天性的反应，便是鄙人与众不同的殊能。鄙人之健体，绝无病态之倾向，即便在病魔缠身的时期，也绝没有疾殇之心态。至于对宗教的狂信、盲信，那更是与鄙人生性无关的了。鄙人，无须屈尊，何必傲慢？怜悯，从来都不是伟大的表现。高呼怜悯者，必是虚伪之辈，谨防一切口蜜腹剑之流！于鄙人，生活是简单的；而生活给我出了最大的难题时，却也成了我最轻松的时候。就在今秋的七十多天里，基于对未来数千年的责任之心，为了撰写那部一流的、空前绝后的著述，鄙人几乎与世隔绝。这期间，只要见过一面的人，谁都知道，鄙人并没有丝毫的紧张；相反，鄙人却倍感精神抖擞，兴致勃勃，从来也没有吃得那么香甜，睡得那么踏实。表现伟大的使命，除了用游戏的方式外，鄙人着实不知道还有什么更好的选择，它是伟大的象征，它是先决的条件。一丝轻微的紧张，一副沮丧的面容，一点嗓门不适的轻咳都会影响一个人的全神贯注，何况我是在做一项前无古人的工作呢！千万不必神经过敏……自然，独居也有独居的苦处，独居也会干扰你的正事，然而，鄙人总是多苦于尘世之“喧闹”……

还是很小的时候——七岁那一年，鄙人便知道，我注定不是一个安分的人。世界现有的语汇中，哪一个也不足以形容我。然而，谁又见过我因此而闷闷不悦呢？时至今日，鄙人依然会平等对待身边的每一个人，与他们和睦相处，即便是社会底层的平民老百姓，我也会抱有恻隐之心。总之，待人接物，明里绝无傲慢之气，暗中亦无诋毁之心。鄙视他人，他人必能察觉。终其一生，鄙人都会对一切存心不良的行为感到愤怒。在鄙人这里，衡量一个人是否“伟大”的标准是：看他是否“知命”[16]，谁也不必梦想超越天性，过去是这样，将来是这样，永远是这样。对待必然的事物，不必忍受，更不必掩盖，而是要热爱它——在它面前，所有的理想主义都是谎言……

佳作，何以迭出

I

鄙人是鄙人，作品是作品，所谓人为一事，物则为另一事耳。于是，在涉及著述本身之前，先将它们是读得懂还是读不懂，做一个“安民告示”为好，不过，点到为止便可。其实，必须正式回答这个问题的时机尚未到来，况且鄙人自身的机遇，也未必到来——有些问题恐怕从一开始便注定了——必定要待到鄙人离世之后，才会有一个清晰的答案。然而，总有一天，总有一个地方，人们会像鄙人所预见的那样去传道授业，甚至还会建立大学教职来讲解《扎拉图斯拉的告白》。然而，如果企望鄙人的逻辑在当今便能够为人所乐听、为人所乐取，那么鄙人便全然地错了。因为，事实是没有人会听鄙人的，没有人会知道如何从鄙人这里获益——反正，人们尚且不能明白鄙人那些深奥的道理。况且，于我来说，那些道理也尚且有未尽之宜。谁也不企望被人家误解，于是，鄙人自然要好自为之，不敢自作聪明了。需要重申的是，鄙人平生不存半点“恶意”，也无从将半点“恶意”付诸于鄙人的文章。相反，却将太多的“迂腐”注入了鄙人的著述！在我看来，对任何人而言，持有一本鄙人的著述，都是一件千载难逢的幸事。甚至可以这样设想，他必定会兴奋得跳起了脚而甩丢了鞋，即便甩丢了人家的靴子，那也是预料之中的事。

海因里奇·冯·斯泰因博士曾经诚实地抱怨说，鄙人的《扎拉图斯拉的独白》，他连一个字都没有读懂。其实，问题并没有那么严重。然而他若是果真读懂了，即便是阅历过其中六句忠言的意味也罢，他便会从“凡人”的位置上升到一个相当的高度——即便是这样的高度，也不是“当代人”所能企及的。有了这样一层感觉上的隔膜，何敢奢望鄙人所了解的“当代人”去识读鄙人的著述呢？严格地说，鄙人要走的成功之路和叔本华走过的成功之途乃是恰恰相反的，有道是“不生育，不轻浮”。人们在否定我的著作时总是作出无辜的样子，我不想贬低这种无辜以求自己的快感。就是在这个刚刚过去的夏天，因为著述任务过重，手头需要处理的文字太多，鄙人已经将其中冗余的部分略去，也算是求个平衡吧。一位柏林大学的教授好心劝鄙人换一种方式著书，说什么没有人会接受那种叙事的方式，同时还希望鄙人理解这一点。

之后，恰好碰到了两个典型的“例子”，但这两件事情，都不是发生在德意志，而偏偏是在瑞士。一个是某个“联盟”的V.威德曼[17]博士以卡尔·斯比特勒先生（同为该“联盟”的成员）的名义，以“尼采的书是危险的”为题，就《善恶论》[18]发表短文，对鄙人的著述作了一个总体性评价，那简直是一件鄙人人生中登峰造极的事情——他们居然说出了连作者本人都不敢奢望的“疯话”。另一个，则将《扎拉图斯拉的独白》说成是“一个高级语体的问世”，并且要鄙人随后为他们提供必要的说明。V·威德曼博士还说他钦佩鄙人的勇气，为此鄙人还努力克制过那种体面的感觉呢。虽然其中的话语尚不露天机，连作者本人都得佩服他们的严密，但是，那只不过是秃子头上的虱子——明摆着的事实。值得重申的是，人们务必“对以往的价值观念作出重新估定”，以便将钉子钉在鄙人的头上，而不是让鄙人的头碰在钉子的尖上。因为，对鄙人而言，所有要做的事情加在一起，无非是做好一个说明罢了。最重要的是，任何人都不可能从事物中（包括书籍）提取他不知道的东西。一件不可能阅历的事情，岂可以用耳朵听说？这里随便设想一个极端的例子吧：如果一本书连什么问题都没有涉及，只是用第一人称的方式编造了一种似乎用新的经验堆积起来的事情，那么就连常识乃至稀有的经验都不足以证明那些事情是真实的。在这种情况下，人们又怎么可能听到事实呢？这是一个极为简单的道理，因为没有人听到，便是没有发生，于是只能称之为道听途说了。其实，这不过是鄙人普通阅历之内的事情而已，或者说，最多不过是鄙人阅历的出处罢了。

一个对鄙人有所了解的人，在经过他自己的判断后，常常未必一定要成为鄙人的对立面，或许还会多少接受一些鄙人的影响呢，比如一个所谓的“理想主义者”常常就是这样。而一个对鄙人毫无了解的人，则一定会从根本上否认鄙人的东西——鄙人的思想结晶。

“超人”[19]是一个“类型”，而且是一个至善至美的“类型”——同“现代人”、“善人”、基督徒以及其他虚无主义者毫无共同之处。在《扎拉图斯拉的独白》中，正是这个“超人”颠覆了传统的道德观念。于是，“超人”便自然而然地变成了一个非常有思想的词语。而在价值观的意义上，又正是这种同传统道德观念毫无共同之处的“对立性”，构成了扎拉图斯拉个性的基本特征，并且几乎处处都会因此而招致与生倶来的非难，甚至将其归属于理想主义“高品位”人群那一类，说什么他是一半“圣人”，一半“天才”的集合……而其他文明一类的畜生们则以他们物以类聚的方式将鄙人猜疑为达尔文主义者。尽管鄙人曾无情地驳斥过卡莱尔的英雄崇拜主义思想，却仍然有人猜疑鄙人的思想有大骗子卡莱尔（或许他自己并没有意识到这一点，也不情愿让自己成为骗子）英雄崇拜主义的成分。对于这类人，鄙人曾悄悄地提醒他们说：要看看周围的世界，不要因为西泽·博尔贾或者巴尔锡福尔的影响不相信自己的耳朵。

对于舆论，特别是报刊关于我著述的议论，鄙人向来都不感兴趣，这一点，朋友们、出版商他们也是知道的，只是没有告诉鄙人罢了。因此，舆论界原本应该是饶了鄙人的。不过，在一个特殊的情况下，鄙人曾亲眼见证了他们仅就鄙人一本书发表了种种非议——那本书便是《善恶论》。关于这件事，这里简直可以讲出一个奇妙的故事来。

还有一家叫作《国民报》的普鲁士周报，那自然是给鄙人那些国外的读者们看的。巧得很，鄙人也读过国外的东西，可以说只有《辩论日报》，竟大着胆子宣称：尼采的书乃是“时代的产物”，乃是真正的容克贵族的哲学。不过，这个胆量，可是《十字报》所没有的。这样说，或许读者还未必相信呢……

II

以下的话语，就写给德意志的国民看一看吧。鄙人的书，哪里都有读者——其优选者，唯有出身高贵的智慧之士，且其中还不乏真正的天才人物。在维也纳、圣彼得堡、斯德哥尔摩、哥本哈根、巴黎、纽约，到处都可以找到鄙人的读者，显然，鄙人完全不必将自己的读者群限制在欧洲的德意志境内。说实在的，鄙人偏为那些间接的读者们倍受鼓舞。因为这类读者，有的连鄙人的姓名都不曾听说，有的甚至连什么是哲学也不知道，然而鄙人每到一地，就说在鄙人所暂且栖身的意大利都灵吧，人们只要看到尼采抛头露面，一个个脸庞上便会洋溢着平日里少有的兴奋和善意。给鄙人印象最深的，要算那位超市里年迈的妇人了，每每见到我，她总会使出浑身的力气，将柜子里最甜的葡萄挑给我品尝，在鄙人看来，这便是对一个哲学家最大的奖赏。足见，波兰人被称作斯拉夫人眼中的法兰西公民[20]，并非虚言了。

在鄙人的经验中，一位讨人喜欢的俄罗斯女士，是绝不会错过任何一次盘问鄙人国籍的机会的。这件事，常使鄙人因腼腆而不善言辞，谁都知道那是最尴尬的局面。对付德意志人，处理德意志事，鄙人决无输招，然而此时此刻，鄙人竟束手无策了。鄙人原先的恩师里奇尔曾用心良苦地夸鄙人，说凭鄙人的语文才华足以把一篇论说文，写得像发生在巴黎街道上浪漫故事一般精彩，令人觉得荒诞而又兴奋不已。即便在巴黎，人们也会面对M.泰恩“所有勇气和计谋”一般的描述感到惊讶。怕只怕，对古希腊酒神极端的狂热一旦变成一种“永不浸水的盐类混合物”，即德意志精神，鄙人便真不知该如何是好了，救救我，上帝！阿门！

长长的耳朵，意味着什么？谁都知道，有人甚至还有过切身的体验呢。于是，鄙人便可以断言，鄙人的耳朵，是世界上最短的了。这对于女士们来说，是无关要紧的，因为在鄙人看来，她们都以为尼采已经向她们表示了足够的善意。鄙人是一个卓越的反对愚昧的人，同时又是一个人类历史上的大怪人——用希腊语，不仅仅用希腊语来说，鄙人完全是一个反对基督的人。

III

作为一个作家，鄙人有自己特殊的禀赋，这并非夸大其辞。而在个别情况下，鄙人写作所独有的极大的“摧毁”性品味，则是与生倶来的秉性。人们可以不再理会鄙人的著述，最起码可以摆脱尼采哲学的折磨，这是一件极其简单的事情。

来到这个高贵而美妙的世界，是无以伦比的殊荣，但只要不沦为德意志的人，那么最终必定会成为一个杰出的人物。但是，当一个人从鄙人的著述中真正读出欣喜若狂的感觉时，他便足以通过某种高尚的意识经验和鄙人联系在一起，因为，鄙人来自连鸟儿都无以飞抵的高空，而鄙人所了解的地狱，人类是未曾涉足的。读我的书你会爱不释手，我的书甚至会扰乱夜间的静谧。总之，没有什么书籍比鄙人的著述更高傲、更精妙的了。人们足以从中获得世界上最有价值的东西——愤世嫉俗；谁要得到这些，谁就得有十个最敏感的手指和一双最强悍的拳头。任何灵魂的脆弱，都会让他丧失这个机会，甚至永远都得不到它——连一次小小的“消化不良”也不例外，你的神经必定是麻木的，你的胃口必定是兴奋的。除了灵魂的贫乏外，连精神上的每一点空虚都可能致使你丧失这里的机会——懦弱、肮脏，乃至内心深处的复仇心理都可能丧失机会。听我一句劝诫，便足以将所有本能的污秽驱逐于身体之外。在鄙人的同仁中，有几个经验型的人物，由他们那里，鄙人获得了许多——许多对鄙人著述有益的反馈信息。至于那些不愿意同鄙人著述扯上关系的人，比如鄙人那些所谓的朋友们，便不必受什么个人因素的影响了。每当鄙人有一部著作问世时，他们只需要以欢欣鼓舞的语气，祝贺作者又完成了一部著作，说说“进步还是明显的”一类套话便是了。

全然恶意的“精神”、经由美化的“灵魂”、彻头彻尾的虚假——岂堪应对鄙人的著述？于是，他们眼中所见的，恰似他们脚下所踩的，那便是对他们美化了的“灵魂”所作的绝妙的脚注。鄙人那些善于挑刺的同仁们，其实不客气地讲，全是些德意志同胞们，他们总是说未必赞成鄙人的观点，虽然有时候他们也能理解鄙人的难处——这，无非是要鄙人理解他们的难处。据说，甚至连鄙人的《扎拉图斯拉的独白》，他们也无法容忍。任何一个持有“女权主义”观点的人，或者干脆说任何一个“女权主义”的男人吧，同样会将鄙人拒之门外，因为他们永远都不能走出那个愤世嫉俗的智慧迷宫。如果人们注定要幸福快乐的话，就必须与艰难的真理同归于途，舍此便没有别的选择。或许，人们从不吝惜自我，但是他们从来都不曾知晓自己还缺乏严厉的习惯。对于一个优秀读者，鄙人的期望是：一个既有勇气又有好奇心的庞然大物，一个聪明无比、反应敏捷、胆大心细的巨人——一个天生的探险者兼发现者。打心底讲，至此，鄙人依然不知道怎么对自己的读者说才会更好些，就让扎拉图斯拉替鄙人来代言——唯不知单单为了这里的事，扎拉图斯拉是不是愿意将他的“谜语”再重述一遍？

对那些勇敢的探险者和发现者们；对那些已经登上灵巧的航船正在波涛汹涌的海面上搏击的勇士们——

对那些陶醉于谜语，沉迷于曙光，其灵魂已随着长笛的乐音到达那变化莫测之深渊的人们——

没有人会奢望以懦夫的双手去抚摩一条长长的绳索，难道有什么人会情愿破费去丈量那条绳索到底有多长？

IV

这里，还得就鄙人著述的体裁和风格问题说几句话。通过语言符号，包括使用这些符号的节奏，传达某种心理的状态，某种内心的悲怆，此乃体裁之意义所在了；在鄙人这里，人物心理状态的变化是复杂的、特别的，因此体裁的适应性、多样性便是不可避免的。总之，体裁的变化是随人物性格的变化而变化的，只要能够恰到好处地传达人物心理的状态，任何一种体裁都是合适的，都不至于同语言符号的使用发生错位，每一个符号、每一个节奏、每一个姿势——所有修辞的规则，都得服从于艺术表达的需要。好的体裁，恰似一则优美的曲调，一个单纯的“理想”，足以与“美”同价，与“善”同格，与“物”同值者也。鄙人之天性，岂敢误人乎？

期待着：乐音总有听众，悲怆可逢奇人，忠言单遇知音——眼下，鄙人的扎拉图斯拉依然在追寻他自己的知音。天哪！那还得花费多长的时间！但愿，未来的知音值得他追寻。到那时，人们才会如实地理解这里被挥霍了的艺术，才会更多地领略这种全新的、从未听说的风格，才会真正接受这种在艺术手段上直接革新了的风格；到那时，鄙人的艺术才会不至于为之荒废。然而，如果这种事情发生在讲德意志语言的人群之中，那便需要考究一番了。对此，本人理应事先就给予激烈驳斥。在鄙人面前，他们还不至于用德意志的语言捡到什么便宜的。其实，他们又何曾用这种语言做成过什么？因为这种艺术的韵律、庄重的文体，足以传达情感升降的微妙，足以焕发超人的激情。这种著述的体裁及其风格的独到，唯有鄙人的笔触才足以独立地创造；如同《扎拉图斯拉的独白》第三版最后一节——《七只海豹》一般的酒神赞美诗，比迄今为止的所谓“诗歌”，不知早已超出了多少倍。

V

读鄙人的书，好比聆听天下顶好的心理学家讲演一般，或许，这便是一个优秀读者的第一感觉。只要他们像作者一样去体味，读鄙人的书，便会如同一位资深的语文学家在诵读罗马诗人贺拉斯[21]的诗歌一般。在鄙人看来，相信“自我主义”与“非自我主义”的对立，本来便是一个天真的错误，因为所谓“自我”本身就是一个“高级骗局”，一个虚构的“观念”而已。这一点，是不需要什么哲学背景或者道德说教的理论支持的，因为那是一个连思想肤浅的俗人，乃至于傻瓜也能明白的道理，谁都知道：基本上是没有人会持反对意见的。

无所谓自我主义，也无所谓非自我主义，在心理学的意义上，二者都是无稽之谈。什么“人类要为幸福而奋斗”，什么“幸福就是对德行的报偿”，什么“愉快和不愉快是对立的”，如此说法，不一而足。对人类的蛊惑，对道德的诠释，从根基上扭曲了整个心理学的基础——心理学完全被道德概念化了，以至于到了可怕、荒唐的地步，说什么“爱情是非利己主义的”，人必须坚守自我，坚定立场，否则人便索性不必爱了。不过，这种事终究是精明的女人们心里最明白的，她们玩上一把“非我”的游戏，不过是为了让毫无偏见的男人们领略一下大丈夫的滋味而已。恐怕鄙人还真不敢冒昧地自称已经看透了女人的心？不过，果真如此，那便是狄俄尼索斯酒神的眷顾了。天晓得？说不定鄙人便是第一个女人心中灵魂不朽的心理学大师。恰似一个遥远的故事所讲述的那样，除去那些发育不全、丧失了生育能力的自由女士们，哪个敢说不喜欢我？幸运的是，鄙人并没有注定被女人们撕得粉碎，因为一个十足的女人，只要她高兴，便会将你撕成碎片的……鄙人，是了解那些温柔而又没有理智的女人的。天哪，那多像一只危险而隐蔽的爬行动物啊！你可以惬意地和她相处！一个精明的女人，其复仇的欲望是会超越其天性的。毋庸讳言[22]，女人比男人聪明，也比男人恶毒，女人的善意往往是恶情的端倪，所谓“美丽的心灵”常常掩饰着生理上的缺陷。这样说，并非因鄙人愤世嫉俗、玩世不恭所致。为平等的权力而奋争乃是病魔的症结所在。这个道理，只要是做医生的，谁都知道。一般说来，一个女人越是具备女人的天性，她就越是会为了保护自己而拼命地同权利斗争。正是由于天性的缘故，迄今为止，在男女永久的性别之争中，女人总是处于优势地位的。鄙人这里的“爱”情观，不知读者是否还可以听得下去？唯有这里的“爱”情观，才值得用哲学的头脑去思考。然而，在方法论上，在根本意义上，关于“爱”情的战争，应该源于道德观念上对性意识的厌恶。鄙人的陈辞，是否击中了问题的要害，从而使人们聊以解决或者补救女人带来的问题呢？扎拉图斯拉说，男人给女人带来孩子，因为女人需要孩子。足见，男人只是一种工具而已。对于病态或者无法受孕的女人来说，“女人的解放”只会引起她们本能的厌恶，而对于常态或者健康的女人来说，同男人决斗则会成为她们独有的手段——或巧立名目，或独用战术，那便是很寻常的事了。而当她们将自己升格为“自为女人”“高级女人”“理想主义女人”的时候，她们实际上已经降低了自己作为女人的基本品味。这些无疑都是文法学校的栽培——妇女要掌权、妇女要当家、妇女要有政治投票权等导致的。其实，那些主张妇女解放的人们，即便是在纯粹的女人世界里，也不过都是些无政府主义者罢了。她们也属于被剥夺了基本社会权利的人群，其歇斯底里的“本事”，不过是向男人世界的复仇罢了。顺便说一下，在整个人群中最恶毒的“理想主义者”其实还是男人，比如亨里克·易卜生便是个例子。他提倡什么典型的老处女主义，其结果无非是玷污了人类的良心，破坏了天然的性爱罢了。这，原本是一件坦诚而严肃的事情。为了将这一思想说得透彻一些，关于鄙人的道德准则，这里有必要再多说几句，以便将它同“罪恶”的东西严格地区分开来。“罪恶”一词的本意无非是要揭露违背天性的东西，如果需要说得典雅些，那便是要揭开“理想主义”的底子。这里的附言是：做“贞洁”的布道，便是公开地煽动对天性的对抗。所有以“下流”“不道德”为借口，轻蔑性生活、诽谤性生活的人，都是对人类生命的犯罪、对人类生命神圣精神的亵渎。

VI

要对作为心理学家的鄙人作一个概括的叙述，得用《善恶之外》中一段有关心理学的文字，读者大概会难以理解。顺便说一下，鄙人并不赞成将本人同文中人物简单联系在一起的不实猜测，“心灵之天性，唯天下最大之隐者所独有，诱惑之神和天籁之音的交响曲吹奏者，最善于将他们的声音吹抵每一颗心灵的深处。不用言语，不必盼顾，毫无怂恿之意，毫无煽动之情，聆听者却偏偏深知其中的意味，无关乎吹奏者怎么样，有关于追随者怎么行，原本是被动而来，如今却铁了心去。心灵之天资，足以令一切必张扬而自足的事物，都变得须静谧才便于倾听，足以安抚人浮躁的心灵，赋予人崭新的期望，以便憧憬那遥远的未来——期望，犹如镜面一般的平静，透过它足以看到蓝天的深邃。心灵之天资，足以让笨拙而匆忙的人群有机会停一停，想一想，再从容地上路；心灵之天资，足以推测那隐匿而被人们遗忘了的瑰宝，足以感知那深压在冰山底下的仁慈和神圣；心灵之天资，宛如一根奇妙的‘魔杖’，足以将泥沙筑成的监狱中搁置了许久的每一颗金粒都打捞上岸；心灵之天资，只要你沾到它的边，富裕便会不期而至——那不是偏爱，你不必惊奇，不是上帝的保佑，不是别人的恩惠——是你自身的财富，是你自为的改变，恰似一股融冰的和风，迎面吹来，你受到触动，你变得开朗，你一鸣惊人，你不必意外。或许，你依然不够确定，不够完美；或许，你依然比较稚嫩，比较脆弱。然而，你一定充满了不可名状的冲动，充满了崭新的意愿和朦胧的欲望，充满了你从未意识到的、奇怪的意志——冲创意志[23]，兼有逆反的心思……”

天运，我自晓得

I

我的命运，我知晓——总有一天，尼采的名字会同那些可怕的记忆联系在一起。那将是一场空前的灾难，那将是一次良心深处的碰撞，那将是一个对迄今为止的所信、所愿及其所尊崇的背叛。我，不是一个人，我，是一剂炸药。如此，鄙人何以成为某一宗教的发起人？宗教，乃是下等人的事。在同宗教人士接触之后，鄙人还得清洗自己的手。鄙人并不需要“信奉者”，因为鄙人从不信奉什么人，即便同下等人说话的事，鄙人也懒得动嘴去做。总有一个可怕的感觉，有一天，鄙人会被众人称作圣人。人们会说，难怪尼采老早就将那本书公诸于世，其实，那都是为了避免他人伤害我。鄙人不企图做“圣民”，也不希望成小丑。或许鄙人便是一个小丑，是小丑也罢，不是小丑也好，总之，迄今为止，没有什么人要比圣徒更虚伪的了。真理，必将出自“小丑”，也就是鄙人之口。不过，鄙人的真理是令人敬畏的，那是因为，所有迄今为止的谎言全被唤作真理了。重估一切价值，这便是鄙人——“小丑”治愈人类过激行为的药方——“回归自我”乃是至上的原则。于我，便是精神和血肉的见证。鄙人，注定要成为人间第一个体面的人，知晓自己务必站在千年“虚假”的对立面。鄙人，第一个发现了真理就是真理的天机。不！鄙人，第一个嗅出了谎言就是谎言的味道，鄙人的嗅觉，便是鄙人的天赋，站在虚假真理的对立面上，揭穿从来没有为人所揭穿过的“谎言”，传诵从来没有为人传诵过的喜讯，此乃鄙人之天运啊。此一番天降之大任，舍我其谁？非斯人，何足堪肩？鄙人出世了，喜讯传来了，指望便有了。于是，天数注定，鄙人必成为真理的代言人。

当真理步入同千年“谎言”的搏杀时，人们必然要感到强烈的震撼，如地球在抽搐、在痉挛一般，像峡谷和大山在移位、在迁徙一般，那，便是人类生来都没有做过的梦。到那时，政治，将全然成为一种精神的战争；所有以往社会的权力结构，都将被抛入历史的垃圾堆，躺在“谎言”的沙滩上安息。地球上，将会发生一场从未有过的战争，唯有在鄙人出现之后，地球上才会产生一个“宏大的”政治。

II

假若命运的方舟，足以运载真正的伟人，何不寻而得之？鄙人的扎拉图斯拉，便会为你揭开这里的秘密。

假若要成为善恶的操控者，何不先做一个坚决的破坏者——破坏原有的价值观？

足见，大善与大恶同处一寓。然而，大善务必大扬之，大恶务必大抑之。

鄙人，乃史间最令人敬畏之人，然而，这并不意味着鄙人便是人间最慈善的人。我懂得，破坏足以带来快乐。在某种意义上，破坏越大，快乐越多。是破坏，是快乐？二者均依他狄俄尼索斯的天性而定。然而，这一天性却不便于区分“口是”和“行非”。鄙人，乃是首屈一指的非道德主义者，实至名归的破坏主义者。

III

首屈一指的非道德主义者：君所名之曰扎拉图斯拉的大人物，其名其姓意味着什么？这里，本该问津者，却无人问津，于是鄙人便自问自答了：在善与恶的抗争中，乃是扎拉图斯拉第一个看到了事物发展的真实轨迹，并且将道德理念区分为动力、原因和自我消失三个范畴，纳入玄学的领域，这些便是扎拉图斯拉的贡献所在，同史间波斯人的最大特点是大相径庭的。其实，在这里，问题的本身便是问题的答案。正是扎拉图斯拉本人首先触动了道德理念的致命弱点，因此他必须首先认识到问题的严重性。而在这方面，扎拉图斯拉不仅具有比其他任何思想家更长、更多的经验——实际上整个人类历史，便是一个对所谓“世界道德秩序”命题的实验性反驳，更重要的是，扎拉图斯拉比历史上任何一个思想家，都更加接近真理。他的教义，也唯有他的教义，维持了真理的尊严，那是一个至高的德行。换言之，那是一个同懦弱的、逃避现实的“理想主义”截然相反的理念。即便将所有思想家的胆量叠加在一起，也比不了扎拉图斯拉的胆略。说老实话，或者不如直截了当地说，“理想主义”不过是波斯人的德行而已。鄙人说清楚了吗？试以扎拉图斯拉的真理观，对道德理念进行相反的自我克制，对道德主义者进行相反的自我抵御，使之向扎拉图斯拉贴近，向鄙人贴近——这，便是扎拉图斯拉其名其姓之真实意味所在了。

IV

实际上，所谓非道德主义者，是包含两层否定含义的。首先，鄙人否认那些迄今为止总被奉为高人、善人及慈善者一类的人。其次，鄙人还否认那些生来便被尊为贵人并且具有支配地位的人物，所谓道德的化身——颓废的道德主义者，倒不如直截了当地说，鄙人所否认的第二类，便是那些基督教卫道士一类的人。

这里的第二类人，可被拟定为主导阶层，他们往往对慈善价值的估计过高。而这些在鄙人看来，偏偏基本上都是颓废的根源、体弱的症结，都是同健康向上的生命水火不相容的东西：岂不知，否定和破坏乃是肯定和建设的一种存在方式，是一种极其合理状态？首先，对待那些善者，鄙人得用心理学的方式。而要辨别一个人是属于哪个类型的人，人们得先估计一下他的自身价值。而要知道他的自身价值，便又得了解他的生存方式。谁晓得善者们的生存方式原来是扯谎。换言之，无论如何他们的生存目的绝不是考察现实社会的基本构成。彻言之，不管何时，他们也没有唤醒过人们慈善的本性，乃至于不管在什么情况下，他们连一个虽无远见却够善意的“干预”也决不会允许。将悲情从普遍意义上看作“异议”，看作某种必须废除的东西，那便是“愚顽透顶”了。而从一般意义上讲，其后果无异于一场真实的灾难，一次愚昧的厄运，几乎同一个驱除阴天的拙劣意欲相差无几。或许，不是“可惜”，便是“可怜”了。在整个社会的总体结构中，对现实的恐惧（如在情感、情欲以及冲创意志方面）在很大程度上，都变成了比微薄的幸福（所谓“善行”）更为重要的生命必需品。因为后者（幸福）总是被本能的虚假所限制，即使为了获得少许的自由的空间，人们都得小心翼翼。假若需要展示一下人类历史盲目乐观之后果，就既无法估量，也不可思议，却又大有必要。首先，乐观主义同悲观主义一样是颓废的，或许还是更有害的。扎拉图斯拉说道：“善人是从不说真话的。”善人教给你的不是虚假的“保护”，便是虚假的“安全”。人们生来就被包围在善者的谎言中，一切都被善者的谎言彻底扭曲了。好在世界并不仅仅为了善者的需要而缔造，温存的动物还足以从夹缝中找到自己狭小的存身之处。而一旦到处都成了“善者”、受骗者、温存的动物及慈善人士乃至“美丽的灵魂”，或者，像赫伯特·斯宾塞所希望的利他主义者的世界，那便意味着伟大人格的丧失，美好人类的阉割。于是，人类的地位将会变得无足轻重。这些，便是基督教卫道士们意图达到的目的！准确地说，这便是卫道士们道德“真谛”之所在。正是在这个意义上，扎拉图斯拉将善者称为“灭亡之端倪”——“最后之人”。总之，在扎拉图斯拉的眼中，所谓“善者”，乃是人类最危险的族群，因为他们维护自己的存在是以牺牲社会的真理、人类的未来为代价。

“善者”是不会有什么新招的，他们永远是灭亡的端倪。“善者”将“主”钉上了十字架，“主”便将新的价值“钉”在了新的法案上。他们为了自己而牺牲未来，他们将人类的未来钉上了十字架！

“善者”，永远是灭亡的端倪……

无论世界的诽谤者们做过的伤害有多大，“善者”们所为的伤害，都是奇大无比的。

V

扎拉图斯拉，既然是“善者”的第一位心理医师，便必然是“恶者”的第一位知心朋友。堕落的族群要升格为最高的人群，必定要以其对立面——具有强大生命力和自信心的族群为牺牲代价。于是，温存的动物要发出其德行最辉煌、最灿烂的光芒时，那些异常的族群，便必得贬为“恶人”了。无论在何种意义上，只要“虚假”以“真理”的面目出现，“真实”便会从实际意义上肩负最坏的名声。对此，扎拉图斯拉坚信不疑：他说准确意义上的善识，即所谓“最好”的知识，使他对普通人群深感厌恶。也正是这种深恶痛绝的感触给他添上了“飞向遥远未来”的翅膀。他并不掩饰，正是在同“善者”人格相对立的意义上，他形成了自身超乎常人的秉性，即所谓“超人”的人格。而“善者”与所谓“正义”之士却将这个超凡之人——“超人”，唤作魔鬼……

你们是最“高大”的人，鄙人目所未及、眼所未见！然而，疑云却由此而生。我偷偷地笑了，因为，我猜到你们会将“超人”称为魔鬼的！

在“高大”面前，你们的灵魂是那样的不堪入目，总以为“超人”会在所谓的“善行”面前，深感汗颜。

果真想知道扎拉图斯拉的真实人格吗？其实也不难，他笔下的人，便是活生生的人——现实中的人。在现实中，他毫不示弱，不疏远现实，也不迷恋现实，因为他便是现实。大家怕的，扎拉图斯拉也会怕；大家疑惑的，扎拉图斯拉也会疑惑。唯有这样，人类才会伟大起来。

VI

不过，在另一个意义上，鄙人之所谓“非道德主义者”这一概念，还可以作为区别的标志乃至荣誉的象征。为有这样一个概念，鄙人甚感骄傲，因为它使鄙人远离了整个基督的泛爱与仁慈。没有人会觉得基督的说教是真实的。于是，便需要从一个史间绝无仅有的心理学高度和深度上考察问题。基督的道德说教，对迄今为止的思想家来说，恰似荷马史诗中的女魔一般，有着蛊惑人心的意味。而当损害人类思想的毒素像泉水一般涌来时，在鄙人之前，何曾有人深入过炮制毒素的洞穴——世界毒流的源头，寻根问底？何曾有人以身存疑——猜想过毒素之洞穴、毒流之源头的真实存在？在鄙人之前，何曾有人成为哲学史上的心理学大师，又幸免于站在它的反面而堕落为“高级骗子”——理想主义者的命运？在鄙人之前，何曾有人见过真正的心理学说？于是，首当其冲者，便招来莫名的横祸，不由分说，这也是天命了。好在，鄙人也会第一个鄙视鄙视者的。自然，鄙视人家，必然给鄙人带来厄运。

VII

鄙人有讲明白吗？——鄙人，何以定格？何以区别于他人？唯有免戴了基督道德说教的面具而已。于是，鄙人便需要一个词语，这个词语或者说这个概念，足以炫耀鄙人对任何人都无以幸免的“火药”味儿。对于鄙人，不能尽快打开这个词语的慧眼，便无异于在人性纯洁的良心表面涂上了一层厚厚的污泥，无异于将自我欺骗蜕变成了本能，无异于要泯灭了考察每一个事件、考究每一个原因、尊重每一个现实之冲创意志的基因[24]，无异于一个心理学家在犯罪问题上造了假。对基督教徒的道德说教视而不见，乃是不折不扣的犯罪——对生命的犯罪。在千年的历史上，在民族的兴亡中，最先和最后之间，哲学家和老夫人之间，如果仅仅区分了“五”到“六”个历史的瞬间，鄙人便要理所当然地坐在那第七个瞬间的席位上。所以，从这一点上看，人们相差无几。基督教徒，是迄今为止的“道德人”，是无以伦比的“奇怪人”。然而，无论是作为“道德人”还是“奇怪人”，他们荒唐、虚假、空虚、轻浮，因为他们连自己都要伤害——这一点，甚至连史间最大的骗子都得在梦中才足以做到。基督的道德说教，乃是“扯谎意志”[25]最恶毒的表现形式，乃是人类生命中不折不扣的喀耳刻女巫。因为它，人类便会走向灭亡。至此，令人震惊的不是贻误本身，也不是整个精神领域“善意”“修行”“体面”和“勇气”的千年匮乏，致使它们背叛了自身的价值，而是天性的缺失，准确地说，是天性的扭曲，致使人们将基督的教义奉为最高义理，并且以法律的方式凌驾于社会，迫使人们无条件地履行基督教的诫命，这无疑是一个可怕的事实！既然如此，大错所殃及的便不仅仅是某一个人，某一个民族，而是整个人类了！蔑视别人原本是生命的本能；“灵魂”与“精神”原本是毁坏肌体的元素；生命的某些先天状态原本是污秽的，比如性行为；甚至在那些为成功所做的基本努力中，也能找出个龌龊的本源来，说什么那都是不折不扣的利己主义。须知，“利己主义”这个概念的本身便有诋毁中伤的意味！另一方面，我们还可以通过那些诋毁和违背天性的概念符号看出问题，譬如什么“无私”“失重”“去个性”及“爱朋友”（交朋友的欲望），还有什么“高价值”和“价值的价值”之类，哟！这里都说了些什么呀？不对！莫非是人类自己要走向衰微？总得这样吗？不对！他们总是将颓废的东西奉为至上的法宝。这一点，难道有错？所谓无私的道德说教，其实是不折不扣的价值贬值，譬如，将陈述句“我要死去”转换为祈使句“你们去死吧”，其实说教者的语气又何止于“祈使”而已！这，难道不是事实？这便是史间所兜售的道德逻辑，“唯一”的逻辑，所谓“无私”的道德义理压根儿就违背了生命的意志，摧残了生命的根基。是，谓之“泯灭意志”[26]也。

——话头儿暂且搁在这里，这里不妨设定不是人类在退化，而是那些人类的寄生虫——神父、牧师及教徒们，借助于道德理念的威力，将他们自己提升为决定人类命运的群体——在基督教的道德理念中，他们凭着直觉神化了自己的权力。于是，鄙人的顿悟便由此而生了：人类的教导者们、领导者们，还包括那些神学研究者们，你们个个都是颓废的人。因此，务必对有碍于人类生命的一切价值（观）进行重新估定，对所有道德理念进行确切定义。道德理念，是颓废者们特有的癖性，其中隐藏着他们向人类生命复仇的阴谋，而且，隐藏得非常之巧妙。对于这一定义，鄙人非认真对待不可。

VIII

鄙人有讲明白吗？此前，并没有借扎拉图斯拉之口，说出五年前尚不得脱口而出的那句话。揭去基督道德理念的假面具，乃是一件绝不会有平静结局的事件，甚至会酿成一场空前的大灾难。谁揭开这个秘密，谁便是一支不可忽视的力量，谁便会像命运之神一般，主宰命运的沉浮，并由此，将人类历史一分为二。有人要生活在他之前，有人必生活在他之后。那是一次真理的电闪雷鸣，不偏不倚，撞击着基督立足的制高点。谁抓住了为之击毁的目标，谁便会清楚地看到握在手中的真谛。此刻，史间一贯被呼之为“真理”的东西，在一瞬间将被认定为最有害、最恶毒、最秘密的谎言。原来，“促进”人类的发展，不过是一个冠以“神圣”二字的托词，目的又无非是为了巧妙地吮吸生命本身，使之贫血化而已——基督的道德理念不过是叫人们去相信吸血鬼的那些把戏罢了。谁揭穿了道德理念的假面具，谁便同时揭开了所有价值观念的遮羞布；谁不再敬畏那些所谓最可尊敬，乃至已被宣告为圣徒一类的人，谁便会发现他们的致命伤——致命，乃是因为他们在玩弄把戏。“上帝”的问世，从一开始便构成了生命的对立面——一切都是有害的、有毒的、造谣中伤的，整个世间的敌意全冲着生命而来，从而构成了一个可怕的统一体！“此岸世界”和“彼岸世界”的割分，从一开始便剥夺了“唯有世界”[27]的真实价值，最终免除了人间真实生活的目标、理由和功课！“灵魂”“精神”，乃至“不死的灵魂”，从一开始便忽略了躯体的价值，从而使之独具“神圣”而不得健康。于是，生命中所有的事情都得严肃地对待，唯独养分、居所、整洁乃至气候，偏偏成了无足轻重之事！不是使之健康，而是救其“灵魂”，岂不构成了一个不断谢罪同耶稣救赎之间的无限循环！“罪孽”连同惩罚罪孽的手段——“严刑”，乃至“自由意志”的创造，其目的无非是将它们同人类的天性相混淆，从而将对天性的怀疑变成人类的第二天性！在“忘我”和“非我”的概念中，其颓废的实际象征性在于：迫于有害事物之引诱，而无以发现自身优势之所在。而“毁我”的实际象征性则在于：使症结的意义一般化，从而使“责任”“神圣”和“牧师”的概念深入化！最终，最可怕的是，在“善者”的概念里，一切公共的事业都变得脆弱、病态、建构不良，一切都因自我而遭罪，一切都因自我而灭亡。选举法被取消，一个同荣耀和高贵相对立、同拥护者相对立、同相信未来和保护未来的人相对立的思想被唾弃，之后，后者便被呼作罪人。所有这一切，便是为人所信的基督道德理念之所为！

——无耻！见鬼去吧！

IX

鄙人有讲明白吗？一个同十字架水火不相容的狄俄尼索斯信徒……

注释

[1]此为原文注释，英文原文是“We strive after the forbidden”（Ovid）。

[2]Zarathustra原译：《扎拉图斯拉如是说》，见陈鼓应著《尼采新论》之“尼采年谱”（世纪出版集团&上海人民出版社，2006年第一版，第156—122页）；其他相关译著也多依这个译法，比如杨恒达等译《尼采生存哲学》（九州出版社，2003年第一版，第268页）。另外，“扎拉图斯拉”尚有其他译法，如“查拉图斯特拉”“查拉图斯拉”等，这里采用了《辞海》（上海辞书出版社，1979年第一版，第2246页）的说法。——译者注

[3]“will to power”是尼采哲学中的重要概念，原译为“权力意志”，陈鼓应先生以为不妥，因为在《扎拉图斯拉的独白》中，这种意志，乃是一种“创造生命的意志”，见陈鼓应著《尼采新论》之“序一：生命的驱动力——‘冲创意志’的理解”（世纪出版集团&上海人民出版社，2006年第一版，第1—2页），与权力并无牵连；现依陈说，译为“冲创意志”。另外，周国平先生则将其译为“强力意志”，亦无不妥，见周国平著《尼采：在世纪的转折点上》（世纪出版集团&上海人民出版社，1986年第一版，第87页）；刘娟译《尼采传》（贵州人民出版社，2004年第一版）中也采用了“强力意志”的译法，见该书“目录”。——译者注

[4]The Wanderer and His Shadow是尼采三十六岁时的著述，原译《漂流者与其影子》，见张秀章等选编《尼采箴言录》（吉林人民出版社，2003年第一版，第202页）；另有《漫游者及其影子》的译法，见陈鼓应著《尼采新论》之“尼采年谱”（世纪出版集团＆上海人民出版社，2006年第一版）。——译者注

[5]这里虽将“the individual”译为“一个特定的个体”，但是依据这里的语用环境，这个“特定的个体”实际上应该就是指“上帝”而言的。——译者注

[6]塞勒斯特（公元前86—前34），罗马历史家，著有《喀提林阴谋》《朱古达战争》等。——译者注

[7]Schulpforta，原译“普福塔”，是尼采所在的中学校名，这里依音译采用了“舒尔普福塔”的地名译名（见《外国地名译名手册》，商务印书馆，1993年第一版），并在“舒尔”二字上加了括弧，以免误解。——译者注

[8]尼采的Laertiana全称应该是ANALECTA LAERTIANA。他的文章先附Diogenes Leartius（即《第欧根尼·拉尔修论集》）（Laer tiana）的若干古希腊语文本，然后是分析性文字，而分析文字则多是拉丁语。足见，尼采语文学造诣之深厚。

[9]蒙田（Montaigne，1533—1592），又译“蒙台涅”，文艺复兴时期法兰西思想家和散文作家，详见《辞海》（上海辞书出版社，1970年，第一版）第3725页。——译者注

[10]《曼弗雷德》，是拜伦于1817年发表的诗剧，反映他对欧洲民族解放运动的悲观失望情绪。——译者注

[11]浮士德，欧洲中世纪传说中的人物，为获得知识和权力，向魔鬼出卖自己的灵魂；德国作家歌德创作同名诗剧《浮士德》，这里的字里行间均流露出尼采并不看好歌德才华的情绪。——译者注

[12]撒克逊人是五六世纪入侵不列颠并定居在那里的日耳曼民族，他们曾洗劫城镇和乡村，不列颠人或被杀戮，或沦为奴隶，或被驱赶至西部、西北部山区，大部分人则同入侵者融合，形成了后来的英格兰人（或称为英吉利人）。这里，尼采或许是因为撒克逊人的野蛮入侵而对其存有偏见。参见《中国大百科全书》（外国历史II）：英国历史（第1095页），中国大百科全书出版社，北京，上海，1990年1月第一版。——译者注

[13]Human，All Too Human。从原译：《人性的，太人性的》，见陈鼓应著《尼采新论》之“尼采年谱”，世纪出版集团＆上海人民出版社，2006年第一版。——译者注

[14]这里的诗句已有一个译文，可以参阅，见张秀章等选编《尼采箴言录》（吉林人民出版社，2003年第一版），第161—162页。——译者注

[15]这里所述的道理，恰同国人之所谓“大智若愚”一般；于是，“特智”便“若灾”“若难”了。——译者注

[16]“amor fati”，是一个拉丁语汇，其大意是“love of fate”或者“love of one's fate”，这里姑且译作“知命”，但并不等同于中国文化中的“知（天）命”。依据全书的语境，结合尼采的观点，这里的“知命”，应该解释为“知天性”才对，因为“知天性”便会爱生命，从而激活“创造生命的意志”（Der Wille zur Macht，即英文的“The Will to Power”），以资成就未来。——译者注
the will to power，仍译为“冲创意志”，参见前文第11页注释2。
——译者注

[17]V.Widmann，又译惠特曼、魏得曼。——译者注。

[18]Beyond Good and Evil，一译《善恶的彼岸》、一译《善与恶之外》、一译《尼采论善恶》，分别见：张秀章等选编《尼采箴言录》之“尼采年谱”（吉林人民出版社，2003年，第一版）；陈鼓应著《尼采新论》之“尼采年谱”（世纪出版集团＆上海人民出版社，2006年，第一版）和朱泱译《尼采论善恶》（团结出版社，2006年，第一版）。——译者注

[19]“超人”（superman），是尼采哲学中的重要概念，是他在新的世界观、人生观和价值观的基础上所设定的新价值的创造者。尼采的理想人格是由“超人”来代表的，尼采的哲学理念是由“超人”去体现的，因而尼采的哲学也是以超人学说而著称的。——译者注

[20]尼采自称波兰人的后裔，又以法兰西人为至尊，于是，当受到斯拉夫人群的敬重时，自然会感慨一番了。——译者注

[21]贺拉斯（Horace，公元前65—前8），又译“霍瑞斯”，原名Quintus Horatius Flaccus，罗马诗人及讽刺文学家。——译者注

[22]毋庸讳言，这里用“她”指代《扎拉图斯拉的独白》一书是不大恰当的，因为尼采的骨子里是蔑视女性的，姑且用之。——译者注

[23]这里将“new ill will”译为“从未意识到的、奇怪的意志”。其实，依据这里的语境，这种意志就是陈鼓应先生所译的“冲创意志”，即所谓“创造生命的意志”，参见前文第11页注释2。——译者注

[24]这里，依据上下文将“fundamental will”译为“冲创意志的基因”，可参考前文第11页注释2。——译者注

[25]同上文的“冲创意志”（the will to the power）相对，这里将“the will to the lie”译为“扯谎意志”，以构成一对相反相成的汉译概念，因为在尼采那里二者本来就是一对因对立而存在的哲学概念；另外参见前文第11页注释2。——译者注

[26]依据行文的逻辑，先有“冲创意志”，后有“扯谎意志”，故将这里的“a will to the end”再译为“泯灭意志”，相为呼应。——译者注

[27]将“the only world”译为“唯有世界”，以区别于基督世界的“此岸世界”与“彼岸世界”，从而凸显尼采的真实世界观。——译者注

偶像的黄昏
——怎样用锤子从事哲学

箴言，足以抒怀

1.心理学起步于无所事事。

什么是心理学？——一种恶习？

2.勇者未必勇于其所知。

3.遁世者，不为畜牲，必为上帝——亚里士多德如是说。不过，也有例外，那便是：既为畜牲，又为上帝——一位哲人补充道。

4.“是真理，皆朴素”——莫非是谎言不成？

5.够了，烦死人了——智慧，绝非卖弄之所及也。

6.听其“自然”——身，便不“紧张”；心，则会自由。

7.告诉我——那到底是：上帝造就人类之误，还是人类崇信上帝之错？

8.在生命的战场上驰骋——不被枪杀，便会强大。

9.自助者，人助之——基督慈善者之原则。

10.行动起来吧，勇敢地！不要见死不救！——事后忏悔，无济于事！

11.驴子尚堪悲哀乎？为包袱所压，不可忍受，亦不可摆脱？哲人的困境。

12.知道了活着的理由，何必在乎活着的方式？人，何必为福分所累？不过，对于英吉利人，则另当别论了。

13.男人造就了女人——所用何物？上帝的肋骨，上帝的“理想”……

14.汝，追寻什么，十倍于汝，百倍于汝，鲜花于汝？岂不水中捞月，一场空也！

15.生不逢时者，不如时髦之士为人所信；然则，为人所闻者，多不胜数矣！鄙人，便是了。准而言之：鄙人一方，不求人知。此，为官者尚不例外。

16.女流之际，可有“真理”？哟，她们并不晓得真理，对吧？这样说，还不至于造成彼此廉耻之心的伤害吧？

17.艺术家便是艺术家，其要求总是低微的，其奢望总是简单的：面包与艺术，生计与追寻……

18.不善养意志者，必善找借口——意志是不养自成的（“信仰”的原则）。

19.奇怪！有德行和博大襟怀的人，眼睛偏偏盯上了老百姓度日的那点儿优越性。这些人到底要做什么？有“德行”，弃“实惠”（反犹太主义者的家门上都这么写）。

20.一个十足的女人糟蹋学问，便像踩死了一只脚下的蚂蚁一般若无其事。试想，她像在做什么试探一般小心翼翼，东张张，西望望，瞧瞧有什么人在“回眸”，如此便引起人家的再“回眸”。

21.虚幻的德行，在以下的情形下是吃不开的：一个在钢丝上走路的人，要么走稳了，要么便会掉下来，要么还得跳下来。

22.“不法分子无遁词”——怎么俄罗斯人偏偏尽废话？

23.“德意志的智慧”：熬过十八年，干戈化玉帛。

24.寻找初始者的踪迹，常常得学着螃蟹横向而行；寻找历史的轨迹，偏偏得学会逆流而上。于是，一位历史学家，往往是一个宁信前贤，不信后秀的人。

25.据说，惬意的感觉足以抵御流感的袭击。谁见过一位穿着时髦的女人得了感冒症？！其实，女人几乎是不必装扮的。

26.对于主张条理化者，鄙人一概表示怀疑，并敬而远之。因为，接近条理化，必然疏远综合化。

27.女流多“深沉”——何以见得？谁都很难摸清她们的“底”。其实，不如说女流从来不肤浅便是了。

28.一个阳刚气十足的女人，你要远离她；一位阴柔气饱满的女子，她会撇开你。

29.“良心之前咬你咬得多么重啊！真这样的，是好牙吗？今天，又是哪里不舒服？”——牙科大夫如是说。

30.鲁莽而轻率之举，少有一而止者也。何？首举，损多而益少，不安。故，举其二，随乃慎而为之者也。

31.遭遇践踏之际，蠕虫便会卷起身来。此，精明之举也，足以减少为人蹂躏之几率。依伦理学之术语而言：乃“谦卑”者也。

32.对谎言和伪装的憎恶源自强烈的荣辱观。该憎恶亦源于卑怯，诚如谎言为圣训所不容。故，既为懦夫，岂可扯谎？

33.幸福的代价太低了，不过一个风笛的价值而已。没有音乐的生活是悲哀的，不过，德意志人则会把上帝的声音当作音乐的。

34.虚无主义是不让“人们思考和写作”（G.弗劳伯特），因为那是没有意义的。鄙人，终于了解了你，虚无主义的同胞！刻苦、勤奋，乃至兢兢业业，都是对神圣精神的冒犯，唯有那马路边的逛游中得来的主意才是最有价值的。

35.心理学家们，常常像马匹一般焦虑不安而难以驾驭，看着自己的影子在面前晃动。谁晓得，他们得离开原本固定的位置，便可以欣赏到更为广阔的景象。

36.非道德主义者，在多大程度上伤害了所谓的德行？哪知道远不如无政府主义者伤害了所谓的王权。一旦他们王冠的权威受到了冲击，他们一定会加固自己王权的宝座。所谓的德行，必须受到冲击。

37.你，又要走啦？这回，该像牧人一般了？难道是偶然间，就这一回了？不过，要是第三回的话，你还可以像逃兵一般。良心第一问。

38.你是在玩真的？还是在演戏？是代替别人？还是被别人代替？噢，原来你不过是在模仿演戏而已。良心第二问。

39.鄙人，寻找过伟人的踪迹，不过，除了其理想的光环以外，便一无所获了。——失落者如是说。

40.你是要旁观，还是要介入，还是要离开远观？良心第三问。

41.是留下来彼此相伴，还是继续前行，还是选择独行？一个人，必须明白自己要做什么、自己在做什么。良心第四问。

42.于我，这些不过是台阶而已。攀上台阶，只是要越过台阶。奇怪的是，有人总以为鄙人要定居在台阶之上。

43.证明你对了，又能怎么样！鄙人的问题是，对的次数太多了。现在，你笑得最好；最后，你还得笑得最好。

44.鄙人，幸福的妙诀——是也，非也，一条直线、一个目标。

贻误，独有四遭

I

首误者，乃原因结果之错位也。没有什么贻误比将原因同结果相混淆更危险的了。鄙人将它看作颓废的内在原因所在。而且，从古至今，它都足以称得上是最古老而又最年轻的习惯性贻误了。因为，在人们的心中它已经被正当化，乃至于被奉若神明，名之曰“宗教”，名之曰“道德”。每一条宗教和道德的教义中都包含着这些内容，神父及其道德条律的制定者们都是颓废的炮制者。这里，试举一例，以便说明这个道理。众所周知，在《科尔纳罗节食主义》一书中，作者将其“痩身食谱”作为长寿和幸福的秘诀推销给读者，而且，是作为最有效力的道德处方兜售给读者。很少有什么书会流传如此之广泛。即便在今天，在英格兰每年都有成千上万册的《痩身食谱》付梓印刷。鄙人从不怀疑除了《圣经》以外，没有任何书的危害会比《痩身食谱》更大，缩短寿命的几率会比《痩身食谱》更多。这是奇迹，名副其实的奇迹，其伪装是何等的巧妙，以至于无人可以察觉。究其理论原因之所在，无非是将结果误以为是原因罢了。聪明的意大利人从其食谱中悟出了“长寿”的秘诀：要“长寿”者，必备一个迟缓的新陈代谢系统；要“长寿”者，必具一个偌小的消化能量——此便是《痩身食谱》的先决条件。吃多，吃少，不由食者自己决定；省食，节约，也不是食者自己的“意愿”。因为，多吃了，食者便会得病。相反，如果食者没能成为那种骨痩如柴的人，就还得继续按部就班地依食谱用膳。于是，一个我们这个时代的学者，如果需要大量的智能消耗，他便只能成为科尔纳罗主义摄生法的牺牲品了。

这便是科尔纳罗节食主义的信条。

II

各种宗教及其教义最普遍的布道方式是：“做……，如此这般；忍……，如此这般，你便会幸福！否则……如此这般……”每一种教义，每一种宗教都是必须履行的责任。鄙人将此唤作原罪恶的起因——不朽的荒唐，莫名的失常。谁晓得，这种布道的方式已经走向了它的反面，成为鄙人“重估一切价值”的第一个案例。一个神志清楚的人，一个“幸福的人”，必定做出某种行为，而对其他行为又必定做出某种本能的回避，同时将这种生理感受的过程传递给与他相关的人和事。在这一过程中，他的德行便是他幸福的结果。长寿和多子多孙并不是对德行的奖赏，因为德行本身意味着新陈代谢的降低，而新陈代谢的降低也会长寿，也能多子多孙。简言之，这便是科尔纳罗节食主义的结果。教会及其教义都认为：“罪孽和奢华足以使一个种族、一个民族灭亡。”鄙人的回答则是：从生理学的意义上讲，当一个民族走向退化、濒临灭亡时，罪孽和奢华便油然而生了。换言之，一旦一个民族有对奢侈物的需求越来越强、越来越大的时候，其心灵便会感到极度的疲劳。而一个年轻人，则会过早地憔悴和衰老。于是，他的朋友们便会说，那都是某种疾病所致。可是，鄙人认为：一个人得了病而无力抵抗，乃是他生命枯竭和遗传性疲劳的表现。有报纸读者说，如果总是这样的阴差阳错，这个群体便会毁灭自身。一位高级政治人士则会说，一个经常阴差阳错的群体实际上已经结束了自己的生命，因为，就其本能而言，这个群体已经不再安逸。每一个贻误，不管是什么样的贻误，都是本能退化的结果。都是意志退化的结果。因此，人们需要从德行上给“坏事”（贻误）下一个定义。每一件善事都是生性如此，因而也是轻松的，必要的，自由的。而每一次尝试，则都是有缺陷的，上帝同勇士不同，要特别地加以区分（用鄙人的话说便是：脚轻，乃上帝之重要属性也）。

III

二误者，乃因果关系之不实也。

人们总以为自己是知道事情原委的，然而，人们的知识从何而来？准确地讲，人们为什么要相信自己所拥有的知识呢？是从宗教王国的“灵光”里来的吗？迄今为止的事实，尚不足以证明这些都是真的。在意愿行为中，人们总以为自己是事物的动因，至少会以为自己是在这一过程中捕捉事物的因果关系。于是，人们从不怀疑意识活动便是在寻找所有行为的“前提”，也就是原因。而且，只要人们寻找它们，人们便会发现它们，即行为的动机。因为，一旦离开了动机，人们便不能自由行为，自然也便谈不上为行为负责了。既然如此，谁还会争辩思想是由什么引起的呢？谁还会怀疑思想便是“自己”产生的命题呢？在以上三个直接同因果关系相连的“内因”中，最重要且最富说服力的原因便是意志。作为原因的意识（思维）和作为原因的自我（主体），不过是因果关系中作为经验主义，在意志的基础上建立起来的一个已知事实所产生的附属概念而已。之后，人们便可以较好地思考了。如今，人们绝不轻信只言片语。因为，“内部世界”充满了不确定的因素和不可靠的线索：意志便是其中之一。意志不会激活什么，因而便不再说明什么。意志只是事件的伴随物而已，因而便可以忽略不计。而所谓“动机”，其实又是一个误会。因为它不过是意识的一个表面现象，行为的一个伴随物罢了，与其说它揭示了行为的“前提”，不如说它隐蔽了行为的“前提”，这样更准确一些。至于“自我主义”，则完全是一个无稽之谈，一个虚构的概念，一个文字游戏罢了。正是它全然窒息了思维、感觉和意志！之后，还会发生什么呢？其实，从来就没有什么精神的理由！让一切支撑精神理由的所谓经验主义见鬼去吧！这便是随后发生的事！人们巧妙地滥用了“经验主义”，而正是在经验主义的基础上，人们创设了一个新的世界——一个理由的世界，一个意志的世界，一个精神的世界。还好，一个最为古老而长寿的心理学在这里发生了作用。的确，它并不神秘，对于它，每一个事件都是一个行为，每一个行为都是一个意志的反映。于是，整个世界便构成了一个多元的动因复合体，一个附着在每一个事件上的动因（“主体”）复合物。人们在其自身之外，设计了三个“内因”——“意志”“精神”和“自我”，并且对其深信不疑。同时，还由“自我”的概念中导出“存在”的概念来，并且根据自己的形象假定“物”便是人们所拥有的东西，根据“自我”的概念假定“物”便是引发事件的原因。难怪，后来人们从“物”中所发现的总是他们原来置入的东西！需要重申的是：“物”本身，或者“物”这个概念不过是作为“自我”信念对原因的反映而已。机械论者、物理学家，先生们，你们可曾晓得：即便是你们的原子论学说，依然存在不少疑问，依然包含了不少基本的心理学问题！这里姑且不论“具体”怎么样了，难道你们不会“脸红”，不会“惊诧”吗？尊敬的玄学家们，将精神领域的贻误，当作事物发生的理由，从而加以实地应用，并以此来度量现实！这，便是人们奉之为“上帝”的精神境界了！

IV

三误者，乃事物原因之虚构也。

这里，就从一个梦中的故事说起吧，比如在某种意义上，一个远程炮弹的射程，总会被顺理成章地误计为发射炮弹的原因所在。其实，准确地说，在这个滑稽的故事中，其主人公不过是做梦者一人而已，颇有点耸人听闻的味道。不仅如此，这种“感受”还会被当作一种共鸣而继续流传。一般都是维持现状，一旦有了机会，这种“虚构原因”便会自动占据突出的地位。于是，这便不再是一个偶然的事件，而是一个必须追究“意味”的问题了。炮弹的射入是有原因的，又是逆时序而展开的，这是显而易见的。然而，动机作为后来的东西却被首先经历了，而且常常像电闪雷鸣一般被数以百计的细节所掩盖，随之炮弹才射入的。究竟发生了什么？概念被误解了，由某种状态所引起的结果，被人们以引起这种状态的原因而接受。其实，人们完全可以在梦醒之后，试做同一件事情。这样，人们就会发现，在这一过程中，大多数人的一般感觉都是抑制、压迫、紧张和突然，人们的器官，特别是神经系统便会做出相应的反应，从而激活体内虚构原因的心理机制。在这一过程中，人们总想知道引起各种感觉的原因——为什么会感觉良好，又为什么会感觉不好？然而，仅仅知道人们在感觉这个事实，还是很不够，人们还得接受这个事实。因为，只有人们带着某种动机完成了这一事件，才能意识到这个事实。在这种情况下，记忆会在人们并没有意识到的情况下，回忆起先前的同类情形，并且将这种状态所产生的结果翻译成“原因”，而不是因果关系。毫无疑问，认为这些观念（即在意识中所伴随发生的观念），都是原因的观点，也是由记忆所唤醒的东西。因此，将某种状态产生的结果解读为“原因”的情形，便形成了定势，乃至于从事实上阻碍或者阻止了人们探知事物真正原因的通路。

V

关于原因虚构的心理学诠释。

从未知，追溯已知，乃是一种消解痛楚、抚慰心灵，从而使人的欲念得以满足的心理过程。而且，这一过程还足以给人充实的感觉。危险、骚扰和焦虑伴随未知——第一天性之功用在驱除这些消极的情绪。于是，这里的第一原则便是：有所解释总比无所解释好。因为，实际上，这是一个如何摆脱无以忍受之观念的问题。而为了摆脱这些观念，人们并不十分在乎用什么手段。第一种观点认为，其实，未知就是已知，只是因为该观点对他们有太多的好处，所以人们将其奉为“真理”而已。快乐和效力，乃是一个真理的准则。可见，虚构原因的心理机制便是靠可怕的感觉来维持并激活的。其实“为什么”这个问题，并不为自身之故去阐解缘由，倒是围绕着抚慰心灵、释放积怨、舒缓压力的原因。一切已知的、已经历的和贮存在记忆之中的事物都被设定为原因，这便是需要的第一个结果。而一切新的、未经历的、奇怪的东西又都被排除在原因之外。于是，就不仅需要对原因进行解释，对精选或优选类型进行解释，而且还需要对以最快速度和最高频率将新的、未经历的、奇怪的感觉排除在外的过程进行解释，这些便是最普通的解释类型了。而进行这些解释的结果则会导致一种特殊的原因归属型解释越来越占优势，并且集中于一个系统之中，从而最终支配其他类型的解释。换言之，原因归属型解释便会直接将其他原因及其解释类型全都排除在外。

一位银行家，最先想到的一定是他的生意；一个基督徒，最先想到的一定是他的罪孽；而一位美女，最先想到的一定是她的爱情。

VI

整个道德和宗教的王国都应该归属于原因虚构的范畴之内。

关于心理“不悦”感的阐释。

“不悦”或者“不快”的感觉可能来自他人对我们的敌意（或者邪念——最富有宗教意味的情形，常被误以为是女巫歇斯底里的发作）。这种感觉，也可能来自我们无以证明的行为（譬如“罪孽”感、由于生理不适而引起的“自责”感，因为人们总会为自己不如意的事情找个理由）。这种感觉，可能来自惩罚，来自“报应”，人们本不应该欠的债、本不应该还的情（在叔本华的概括中这些都是厚颜无耻的东西，其哲学命题是它反映了基督道德的真实面目，是对生命的亵渎与中伤。“每一次剧痛——无论是生理的还是心理的，都是人们理应承受的。因为若非如此，它便不会问津于人。”《意志与理想的世界》第二部分第666页）。这种感觉，还可能由草率的、拙劣的行为所诱发（被设定为“原因”而“应该责备”的情绪、情感和意识，被解读为由心理上理应承受的忧伤所引起生理痛苦）。关于心理“愉悦”感的阐释。这种感觉，可能来自对上帝的信任；这种感觉，可能来自对善行的意识（有时，就连一个诸如良好消化一类的生理状态，也会被误以为是所谓的“良心”）；这种感觉，可能来自成功的喜悦（一个天真的谬论——在自疑病或者帕斯卡症的状态下，即便成功了也绝不会带来什么愉快的感觉）；这种感觉，还可能来自信任、希望和基督教徒之间的兄弟之爱——所谓基督之德行。实际上，所有这些预设性的阐释都是从结果上考虑问题的，而且似乎将“愉悦”感和“不悦”感全都解读为某种虚伪的“方言”。人之所以处于希望的状态，乃是因为作为其生理基本的感觉是强悍的、充裕的；人之所以相信上帝，乃是因为丰富而强悍的感觉足以使之平静下来。足见，道德与宗教完全陷入了错误的心理学阐释之中。在每一种具体的情形下，它们把原因错误地当成了结果，或者将这个信以为真的结果错误地当成了真理，或者将某种意识下的状态错误地当成了这一状态的因果关系。

VII

四误者，乃自由意志之失也。

如今，无论在什么意义上，人们都已经不再赞同“自由意志”的观念了，因为“自由意志”意味着什么，人们是非常清楚的。神学之士们，在其所有的手段中最声名狼藉的一点，不过是为了使人类在神学的意义上负有他们自己的责任和义务罢了。换言之，不过是为了使人类紧紧地依附于“神”的威力而已。于是，鄙人的责任便在于对此作一个心理学的解读。

世上充满着对责任和义务的拷问。如果考察一下一个人处在某种状态下的意志、意图及其责任和义务行为的话，便足以察觉其天真无邪的本性已然被剥夺殆尽。其实，“意志”教义所创设的基本目的原本便是为了惩罚人们。换言之，原本便是为了让人们找到负罪的感觉。整个旧日的心理学——关于意志的心理学，都是以作者及处于社会上层之牧师们的主观期望为出发点的，以便为他们自己设定了颁布惩罚条例的权力，甚至还期望同时再为上帝设定一个颁布惩罚条例的权力。在这些条例中，人被认为是“自由的”，这是为了让他们找到负罪的感觉。于是，每一个行为都被认为是自愿的。换言之，每一个行为都是发自个体自我意识的。就这样，心理学中最虚伪的东西竟变成了最基本的东西，从而编入了心理学的每一条原则。如今，当人们从相反的立场上审度问题的时候，特别是当我们非道德主义者竭尽全力，以便从地球上驱除伏罪和惩罚的理念，从而净化心理学、史学、人性，乃至社会诸部门及其法令条款环境时，扑入我们视野的依然是神学之士们的激进主张。这些主张，依然无从与世俗的观念同日而语，依然在利用道德秩序的理念，通过“惩罚”和“伏罪”的手段，浸染着人类天真无邪的心灵。

足见，基督教之品性不过是刽子手们独有的形而上学罢了。

VIII

那么，我们的学说又该是什么呢？

从来便没有什么救世主足以改变人类的禀性，上帝不会，社会不会，父母不会，祖上不会，人类自己也不会（康德提出过一个最终为人们所拒绝的荒谬概念，叫做“概念自由”。在康德之前，或许柏拉图也曾涉及过这一概念）。没有人可以对自身的存在、自身的模样、或者其所生存的环境，负有什么责任和义务之类的事情。决定人类天性的东西是很难同决定其阅历和命运的东西分得清楚的。人类的命运，不是靠一个特殊的设计、意愿、企图便可以决定的；人类的问题，也不是靠实现几个“人之典范”“福之样板”乃至“德之化身”便足以解决的。足见，企图给人类的天性设定某种人为的“目标”之类的东西，乃是一种荒唐的做法。这里，之所以借用“目标”这个概念是因为，在现实中是没有什么目标的。“一”是必要的，“一”是未来的一部分，“一”属于整体，“一”在整体之中，从来就没有什么能够判断、测度、比喻，乃至惩罚我们人格的。因为，那样会导致人类整体为之所判断、揣度、比喻，乃至惩罚。离开了人类整体，一切都将不复存在！于是，谁都不再负有责任和义务，而所谓人格的表现也将无以追溯其恰当的原因，作为整体的世界便既不是感觉的中枢，也不再有“精神”的问题，唯此，方是伟大的革命；唯此，才足以恢复人性之清白与无辜。足见，“上帝”才是迄今为止人类生存的最大障碍。我们否认上帝，而在否认上帝的同时，便否认了上帝赋予人类的责任和义务。唯此，方足以救赎世界的未来。

铁锤，为我代言！

“何以如此之坚硬？”木炭曾对钻石说，“莫非是因为彼此尚不够亲近？”

“何以如此之软弱？”哟，我的兄弟们，我这里还得问问你们呢，“莫非是因为彼此尚不是兄弟？”

何以如此之软弱？无以抵抗，还是卑躬屈节？何必抑郁，何必克制？莫非命运之前景，如此之渺茫？

如果你不是命运之神，如果你不够百折不挠，你，何以同鄙人分享胜利之喜悦？

如果你的“坚硬”不足以击败对手，而是被对手击得溃不成军，有一天，你又何以同鄙人一起，再造那崭新的世界？

如果所有的创造都是“坚硬”的。那么何不将你的手紧贴在千年祈福的祭坛上？恰似紧贴在平日里祈福的烛台前。那种感觉，一定是幸福的。

将你千年至福的意愿记下来，恰似记录在金属制成的模板上，比金属要“坚硬”，比金属要高贵，因为最高贵的，乃是最“坚硬”的。

这，便是新制的法台，我一定要将它递给您。哟，我的兄弟们，“坚硬”起来吧！

Ecce Homo

How One Becomes What One Is

Foreword

1

SEEING that I must shortly approach mankind with the heaviest demand that has ever been made on it, it seems to me indispensable to say who I am. This ought really to be known already: for I have not neglected to 'bear witness' about myself. But the disparity between the greatness of my task and the smallness of my contemporaries has found expression in the fact that I have been neither heard nor even so much as seen. I live on my own credit, it is perhaps merely a prejudice that I am alive at all?... I need only to talk with any of the 'cultured people' who come to the Ober-Engadin in the summer to convince myself that I am not alive... Under these circumstances there exists a duty against which my habit, even more the pride of my instincts revolts, namely to say: Listen to me! for I am thus and thus. Do not, above all, confound me with what I am not!

2

I am, for example, absolutely not a bogey-man, not a moral-monster - I am even an antithetical nature to the species of man hitherto honoured as virtuous. Between ourselves, it seems to me that precisely this constitutes part of my pride. I am a disciple of the philosopher Dionysos, I prefer to be even a satyr rather than a saint. But you have only to read this writing. Perhaps I have succeeded in giving expression to this antithesis in a cheerful and affable way - perhaps this writing had no point at all other than to do this. The last thing I would promise would be to 'improve' mankind. I erect no new idols; let the old idols learn what it means to have legs of clay. To overthrow idols (my word for 'ideals') - that rather is my business. Reality has been deprived of its value, its meaning, its veracity to the same degree as an ideal world has been fabricated... The 'real world' and the 'apparent world' - in plain terms: the fabricated world and reality... The lie of the ideal has hitherto been the curse on reality, through it mankind itself has become mendacious and false down to its deepest instincts - to the point of worshipping the inverse values to those which alone could guarantee it prosperity, future, the exalted right to a future.

3

He who knows how to breathe the air of my writings knows that it is an air of the heights, a robust air. One has to be made for it, otherwise there is no small danger one will catch cold. The ice is near, the solitude is terrible - but how peacefully all things lie in the light! how freely one breathes! how much one feels beneath one! - Philosophy, as I have hitherto understood and lived it, is a voluntary living in ice and high mountains - a seeking after everything strange and questionable in existence, all that has hitherto been excommunicated by morality. From the lengthy experience afforded by such a wandering in the forbidden I learned to view the origin of moralizing and idealizing very differently from what might be desirable: the hidden history of the philosophers, the psychology of their great names came to light for me. - How much truth can a spirit bear, how much truth can a spirit dare? that became for me more and more the real measure of value. Error (- belief in the ideal -) is not blindness, error is cowardice... Every acquisition, every step forward in knowledge is the result of courage, of severity towards oneself, of cleanliness with respect to oneself... I do not refute ideals, I merely draw on gloves in their presence... Nitimur in vetitum:[★] in this sign my philosophy will one day conquer, for what has hitherto been forbidden on principle has never been anything but the truth.-

4

- Within my writings my Zarathustra stands by itself. I have with this book given mankind the greatest gift that has ever been given it. With a voice that speaks across millennia, it is not only the most exalted book that exists, the actual book of the air of the heights - the entire fact man lies at a tremendous distance beneath it - it is also the profoundest, born out of the innermost abundance of truth, an inexhaustible well into which no bucket descends without coming up filled with gold and goodness. Here there speaks no 'prophet', none of those gruesome hybrids of sickness and will to power called founders of religions. One has above all to hear correctly the tone that proceeds from this mouth, this halcyon tone, if one is not to do pitiable injustice to the meaning of its wisdom. 'It is the stillest words which bring the storm, thoughts that come on doves' feet guide the world -'

The figs are falling from the trees, they are fine and sweet: and as they fall their red skins split. I am a north wind to ripe figs.

Thus, like figs, do these teachings fall to you, my friends: now drink their juice and eat their sweet flesh! It is autumn all around and clear sky and afternoon -

Here there speaks no fanatic, here there is no 'preaching', here faith is not demanded: out of an infinite abundance of light and depth of happiness there falls drop after drop, word after word - a tender slowness of pace is the tempo of these discourses. Such things as this reach only the most select; it is an incomparable privilege to be a listener here; no one is free to have ears for Zarathustra ... With all this, is Zarathustra not a seducer?... But what does he himself say when for the first time he again goes back into his solitude? Precisely the opposite of that which any sort of 'sage', 'saint', 'world-redeemer' and other décadent would say in such a case... He does not only speak differently, he is different...

I now go away alone, my disciples! You too now go away and be alone! So I will have it.

Go away from me and guard yourselves against Zarathustra! And better still: be ashamed of him! Perhaps he has deceived you.

The man of knowledge must be able not only to love his enemies but also to hate his friends.

One repays a teacher badly if one remains only a pupil. And why, then, should you not pluck at my laurels?

You respect me; but how if one day your respect should tumble? Take care that a falling statue does not strike you dead!

You say you believe in Zarathustra? But of what importance is Zarathustra? You are my believers: but of what importance are all believers?

You had not yet sought yourselves when you found me. Thus do all believers; therefore all belief is of so little account.

Now I bid you lose me and find yourselves; and only when you have all denied me will I return to you...

FRIEDRICH NIETZSCHE

On this perfect day, when everything has become ripe and not only the grapes are growing brown, a ray of sunlight has fallen on to my life: I looked behind me, I looked before me, never have I seen so many and such good things together. Not in vain have I buried my forty-fourth year today, I was entitled to bury it - what there was of life in it is rescued, is immortal. The first book of the Revaluation of all Values, the Songs of Zarathustra, the Twilight of the Idols, my attempt to philosophize with a hammer - all of them gifts of this year, of its last quarter even! How should I not be grateful to my whole life? - And so I tell myself my life.

Why I am So Wise

1

THE fortunateness of my existence, its uniqueness perhaps, lies in its fatality: to express it in the form of a riddle, as my father I have already died, as my mother I still live and grow old. This twofold origin, as it were from the highest and the lowest rung of the ladder of life, at once décadent and beginning - this if anything explains that neutrality, that freedom from party in relation to the total problem of life which perhaps distinguishes me. I have a subtler sense for signs of ascent and decline than any man has ever had, I am the teacher par excellence in this matter - I know both, I am both. - My father died at the age of thirty-six: he was delicate, lovable and morbid, like a being destined to pay this world only a passing visit - a gracious reminder of life rather than life itself. In the same year in which his life declined mine too declined: in the thirty-sixth year of my life I arrived at the lowest point of my vitality - I still lived, but without being able to see three paces in front of me. At that time - it was 1879 - I relinquished my Basel professorship, lived through the summer like a shadow in St Moritz and the following winter, the most sunless of my life, as a shadow in Naumburg. This was my minimum: 'The Wanderer and his Shadow' came into existence during the course of it. I undoubtedly knew all about shadows in those days... In the following winter, the first winter I spent in Genoa, that sweetening and spiritualization which is virtually inseparable from an extreme poverty of blood and muscle produced 'Daybreak'. The perfect brightness and cheerfulness, even exuberance of spirit reflected in the said work is in my case compatible not only with the profoundest physiological weakness, but even with an extremity of pain. In the midst of the torments which attended an uninterrupted three-day headache accompanied by the laborious vomiting of phlegm - I possessed a dialectical clarity par excellence and thought my way very cold-bloodedly through things for which when I am in better health I am not enough of a climber, not refined, not cold enough. My readers perhaps know the extent to which I regard dialectics as a symptom of décadence, for example in the most famous case of all: in the case of Socrates. - All morbid disturbances of the intellect, even that semistupefaction consequent on fever, have remained to this day totally unfamiliar things to me, on their nature and frequency I had first to instruct myself by scholarly methods. My blood flows slowly. No one has ever been able to diagnose fever in me. A doctor who treated me for some time as a nervous case said at last: 'No! there is nothing wrong with your nerves, it is only I who am nervous.' Any kind of local degeneration absolutely undemonstrable; no organically originating stomach ailment, though there does exist, as a consequence of general exhaustion, a profound weakness of the gastric system. Condition of the eyes, sometimes approaching dangerously close to blindness, also only consequence, not causal: so that with every increase in vitality eyesight has also again improved. - Convalescence means with me a long, all too long succession of years - it also unfortunately means relapse, deterioration, periods of a kind of décadence. After all this do I need to say that in questions of décadence I am experienced? I have spelled it out forwards and backwards. Even that filigree art of grasping and comprehending in general, that finger for nuances, that psychology of 'looking around the corner' and whatever else characterizes me was learned only then, is the actual gift of that time in which everything in me became more subtle, observation itself together with all the organs of observation. To look from a morbid perspective towards healthier concepts and values, and again conversely to look down from the abundance and certainty of rich life into the secret labour of the instinct of décadence - that is what I have practised most, it has been my own particular field of experience, in this if in anything I am a master. I now have the skill and knowledge to invert perspectives: first reason why a 'revaluation of values' is perhaps possible at all to me alone. -

2

Setting aside the fact that I am a décadent, I am also its antithesis. My proof of this is, among other things, that in combating my sick conditions I always instinctively chose the right means: while the décadent as such always chooses the means harmful to him. As summa summarum I was healthy, as corner, as speciality I was décadent. That energy for absolute isolation and detachment from my accustomed circumstances, the way I compelled myself no longer to let myself be cared for, served, doctored - this betrayed an unconditional certainty of instinct as to what at that time was needful above all else. I took myself in hand, I myself made myself healthy again: the precondition for this - every physiologist will admit it - is that one is fundamentally healthy. A being who is typically morbid cannot become healthy, still less can he make himself healthy; conversely, for one who is typically healthy being sick can even be an energetic stimulant to life, to more life. Thus in fact does that long period of sickness seem to me now: I discovered life as it were anew, myself included, I tasted all good and even petty things in a way that others could not easily taste them - I made out of my will to health, to life, my philosophy... For pay heed to this: it was in the years of my lowest vitality that I ceased to be a pessimist: the instinct for self-recovery forbade to me a philosophy of indigence and discouragement... And in what does one really recognize that someone has turned out well! In that a human being who has turned out well does our senses good: that he is carved out of wood at once hard, delicate and sweet-smelling. He has a taste only for what is beneficial to him; his pleasure, his joy ceases where the measure of what is beneficial is overstepped. He divines cures for injuries, he employs ill chances to his own advantage; what does not kill him makes him stronger. Out of everything he sees, hears, experiences he instinctively collects together his sum: he is a principle of selection, he rejects much. He is always in his company, whether he traffics with books, people or landscapes: he does honour when he chooses, when he admits, when he trusts. He reacts slowly to every kind of stimulus, with that slowness which a protracted caution and a willed pride have bred in him - he tests an approaching stimulus, he is far from going out to meet it. He believes in neither 'misfortune' nor in 'guilt': he knows how to forget - he is strong enough for everything to have to turn out for the best for him. Very well, I am the opposite of a décadent: for I have just described myself.

3

I consider the fact that I had such a father as a great privilege: the peasants he preached to - for, after he had lived for several years at the court of Altenburg, he was a preacher in his last years - said that the angels must look like he did. And with this I touch on the question of race. I am a pure-blooded Polish nobleman, in whom there is no drop of bad blood, least of all German. When I look for my profoundest opposite, the incalculable pettiness of the instincts, I always find my mother and my sister - to be related to such canaille would be a blasphemy against my divinity. The treatment I have received from my mother and my sister, up to the present moment, fills me with inexpressible horror: there is an absolutely hellish machine at work here, operating with infallible certainty at the precise moment when I am most vulnerable - at my highest moments... for then one needs all one's strength to counter such a poisonous viper... physiological contiguity renders such a disharmonia praestabilita possible... But I confess that the deepest objection to the 'Eternal Recurrence', my real idea from the abyss, is always my mother and my sister. - But even as a Pole I am a monstrous atavism. One would have to go back centuries to find this noblest of races that the earth has ever possessed in so instinctively pristine a degree as I present it. I have, against everything that is today called noblesse, a sovereign feeling of distinction - I wouldn't award to the young German Kaiser the honour of being my coachman. There is one single case where I acknowledge my equal - I recognize it with profound gratitude. Frau Cosima Wagner is by far the noblest nature; and, so that I shouldn't say one word too few, I say that Richard Wagner was by far the most closely related man to me... The rest is silence... All the prevalent notions of degrees of kinship are physiological nonsense in an unsurpassable measure. The Pope still deals today in this nonsense. One is least related to one's parents: it would be the most extreme sign of vulgarity to be related to one's parents. Higher natures have their origins infinitely farther back, and with them much had to be assembled, saved and hoarded. The great individuals are the oldest: I don't understand it, but Julius Caesar could be my father - or Alexander, this Dionysos incarnate... At the very moment that I am writing this the post brings me a Dionysos-head.

4

I have never understood the art of arousing enmity towards myself - this too I owe to my incomparable father - even when it seemed to me very worthwhile to do so. However unchristian it may seem, I am not even inimical towards myself, one may turn my life this way and that, one will only rarely, at bottom only once, discover signs that anyone has borne ill will towards me - perhaps, however, somewhat too many signs of good will... My experiences even of those of whom everyone has bad experiences speak without exception in their favour; I tame every bear, I even make buffoons mind their manners. During the seven years in which I taught Greek to the top form of the Basel grammar school I never once had occasion to mete out a punishment; the laziest were industrious when they were with me. I am always up to dealing with any chance event; I have to be unprepared if I am to be master of myself. Let the instrument be what it will, let it be as out of tune as only the instrument 'man' can become out of tune - I should have to be ill not to succeed in getting out of it something listenable. And how often have I heard from the 'instruments' themselves that they had never heard themselves sound so well... Most beautifully perhaps from that Heinrich von Stein who died so unpardonably young and who, after cautiously obtaining permission, once appeared for three days at Sils-Maria, explaining to everyone that he had not come for the Engadin. This excellent man, who with the whole impetuous artlessness of a Prussian Junket had waded into the Wagnerian swamp (- and into the swamp of Dühring in addition!), was during those three days as if transported by a storm-wind of freedom, like one suddenly raised to his own heights and given wings. I kept telling him it was the result of the fine air up here, that everyone felt the same, that you could not stand 6,000 feet above Bayreuth and not notice it - but he would not believe me... If, this notwithstanding, many great and petty misdeeds have been committed against me, it was not 'will', least of all ill will that was the cause of it: I could complain, rather - I have just suggested as much - of the good will which has caused me no little mischief in my life. My experiences give me a right to a general mistrust of the so-called 'selfless' drives, of the whole 'love of one's neighbour' which is always ready with deeds and advice. It counts with me as weakness, as a special case of the incapacity to withstand stimuli - it is only among décadents that pity is called a virtue. My reproach against those who practise pity is that shame, reverence, a delicate feeling for distance easily eludes them, that pity instantly smells of mob and is so like bad manners as to be mistaken for them - that the hands of pity can under certain circumstances intrude downright destructively into a great destiny, into a solitariness where wounds are nursed, into a privilege for great guilt. I count the overcoming of pity among the noble virtues: I have, as 'Zarathustra's Temptation', invented a case in which a great cry of distress reaches him, in which pity like an ultimate sin seeks to attack him, to seduce him from allegiance to himself. To remain master here, here to keep the elevation of one's task clean of the many lower and more shortsighted drives which are active in socalled selfless actions, that is the test, the final test perhaps, which a Zarathustra has to pass - the actual proof of his strength...

5

In yet another point I am merely my father once more and as it were the continuation of his life after an all too early death. Like anyone who has never lived among his equals and to whom the concept 'requital' is as inaccessible as is for instance the concept 'equal rights', I forbid myself in cases where a little or very great act of folly has been perpetrated against me any countermeasure, any protective measure - also, as is reasonable, any defence, any 'justification'. My kind of requital consists in sending after the piece of stupidity as quickly as possible a piece of sagacity: in that way one may perhaps overtake it. To speak in a metaphor. I dispatch a pot of jam to get rid of a sour affair... Let anyone harm me in any way, I 'requite' it, you may be sure of that: as soon as I can I find an opportunity of expressing my thanks to the 'offender' (occasionally even for the offence) - or of asking him for something, which can be more courteous than giving something... It also seems to me that the rudest word, the rudest letter are more good-natured, more honest than silence. Those who keep silent almost always lack subtlety and politeness of the heart; silence is an objection, swallowing down necessarily produces a bad character - it even ruins the stomach. All those given to silence are dyspeptic. - One will see that I would not like to see rudeness undervalued, it is the most humane form of contradiction by far and, in the midst of modern tendermindedness, one of our foremost virtues. - If one is rich enough, it is even fortunate to be in the wrong. A god come to earth ought to do nothing whatever but wrong: to take upon oneself, not the punishment, but the guilt - only that would be godlike.

6

Freedom from ressentiment, enlightenment over ressentiment - who knows the extent to which I ultimately owe thanks to my protracted sickness for this too! The problem is not exactly simple: one has to have experienced it from a state of strength and a state of weakness. If anything whatever has to be admitted against being sick, being weak, it is that in these conditions the actual curative instinct, that is to say the defensive and offensive instinct in man becomes soft. One does not know how to get free of anything, one does not know how to have done with anything, one does not know how to thrust back - everything hurts. Men and things come importunately close, events strike too deep, the memory is a festering wound. Being sick is itself a kind of ressentiment. - Against this the invalid has only one great means of cure - I call it Russian fatalism, that fatalism without rebellion with which a Russian soldier for whom the campaign has become too much at last lies down in the snow. No longer to take anything at all, to receive anything, to take anything into oneself - no longer to react at all... The great rationality of this fatalism, which is not always the courage to die but can be life-preservative under conditions highly dangerous to life, is reduction of the metabolism, making it slow down, a kind of will to hibernation. A couple of steps further in this logic and one has the fakir who sleeps for weeks on end in a grave... Because one would use oneself up too quickly if one reacted at all, one no longer reacts: this is the logic. And nothing bums one up quicker than the affects of ressentiment. Vexation, morbid susceptibility, incapacity for revenge, the desire, the thirst for revenge, poison-brewing in any sense - for one who is exhausted this is certainly the most disadvantageous kind of reaction: it causes a rapid expenditure of nervous energy, a morbid accretion of excretions, for example of gall into the stomach. Ressentiment is the forbidden in itself for the invalid - his evil: unfortunately also his most natural inclination. - This was grasped by that profound physiologist Buddha. His 'religion', which one would do better to call a system of hygiene so as not to mix it up with such pitiable things as Christianity, makes its effect dependent on victory over ressentiment: to free the soul of that - first step to recovery. 'Not by enmity is enmity ended, by friendship is enmity ended': this stands at the beginning of Buddha's teaching - it is not morality that speaks thus, it is physiology that speaks thus. - Ressentiment, born of weakness, to no one more harmful than to the weak man himself - in the opposite case, where a rich nature is the presupposition, a superfluous feeling to stay master of which is almost the proof of richness. He who knows the seriousness with which my philosophy has taken up the struggle against the feelings of vengefulness and vindictiveness even into the theory of 'free will' - my struggle against Christianity is only a special instance of it - will understand why it is precisely here that I throw the light on my personal bearing, my sureness of instinct in practice. In periods of décadence I forbade them to myself as harmful; as soon as life was again sufficiently rich and proud for them I forbade them to myself as beneath me. That 'Russian fatalism' of which I spoke came forward in my case in the form of clinging tenaciously for years on end to almost intolerable situations, places, residences, company, once chance had placed me in them - it was better than changing them, than feeling them as capable of being changed - than rebelling against them... In those days I took it deadly amiss if I was disturbed in this fatalism, if I was forcibly awakened from it - and to do this was in fact every time a deadly dangerous thing. - To accept oneself as a fate, not to desire oneself 'different' - in such conditions this is great rationality itself.

7

War is another thing. I am by nature warlike. To attack is among my instincts. To be able to be an enemy, to be an enemy - that perhaps presupposes a strong nature, it is in any event a condition of every strong nature. It needs resistances, consequently it seeks resistances: the aggressive pathos belongs as necessarily to strength as the feeling of vengefulness and vindictiveness does to weakness. Woman, for example, is vengeful: that is conditioned by her weakness, just as is her susceptibility to others' distress. - The strength of one who attacks has in the opposition he needs a kind of gauge; every growth reveals itself in the seeking out of a powerful opponent - or problem: for a philosopher who is warlike also challenges problems to a duel. The undertaking is to master, not any resistances that happen to present themselves, but those against which one has to bring all one's strength, suppleness and mastery of weapons - to master equal opponents... Equality in face of the enemy - first presupposition of an honest duel. Where one despises one cannot wage war; where one commands, where one sees something as beneath one, one has not to wage war. - My practice in warfare can be reduced to four propositions. Firstly: I attack only causes that are victorious - under certain circumstances I wait until they are victorious. Secondly: I attack only causes against which I would find no allies, where I stand alone - where I compromise only myself... I have never taken a step in public which was not compromising: that is my criterion of right action. Thirdly: I never attack persons - I only employ the person as a strong magnifying glass with which one can make visible a general but furtive state of distress which is hard to get hold of. That was how I attacked David Strauss, more precisely the success with German 'culture' of a senile book - I thus caught that culture red-handed... That was how I attacked Wagner, more precisely the falseness, the hybrid instincts of our 'culture' which confuses the artful with the rich, the late with the great. Fourthly: I attack only things where any kind of personal difference is excluded, where there is no background of bad experience. On the contrary, to attack is with me a proof of good will, under certain circumstances of gratitude. I do honour, I confer distinction when I associate my name with a cause, a person: for or against - that is in this regard a matter of indifference to me. If I wage war on Christianity I have a right to do so, because I have never experienced anything disagreeable or frustrating from that direction - the most serious Christians have always been well disposed towards me. I myself, an opponent of Christianity de rigueur, am far from bearing a grudge against the individual for what is the fatality of millennia. -

8

May I venture to indicate one last trait of my nature which creates for me no little difficulty in my relations with others? I possess a perfectly uncanny sensitivity of the instinct for cleanliness, so that I perceive physiologically - smell - the proximity or - what am I saying? - the innermost parts, the 'entrails', of every soul... I have in this sensitivity psychological antennae with which I touch and take hold of every secret: all the concealed dirt at the bottom of many a nature, perhaps conditioned by bad blood but whitewashed by education, is known to me almost on first contact. If I have observed correctly, such natures unendurable to my sense of cleanliness for their part also sense the caution of my disgust: they do not thereby become any sweeter-smelling... As has always been customary with me - an extreme cleanliness in relation to me is a presupposition of my existence, I perish under unclean conditions - I swim and bathe and splash continually as it were in water, in any kind of perfectly transparent and glittering element. This makes traffic with people no small test of my patience; my humanity consists, not in feeling for and with man, but in enduring that I do feel for and with him... My humanity is a continual self-overcoming. - But I have need of solitude, that is to say recovery, return to myself, the breath of a free light playful air... My entire Zarathustra is a dithyramb on solitude or, if I have been understood, on cleanliness... Fortunately not on pure folly. - He who has eyes for colours will call it diamond. - Disgust at mankind, at the 'rabble', has always been my greatest danger... Do you want to hear the words in which Zarathustra speaks of redemption from disgust?

Yet what happened to me? How did I free myself from disgust? Who rejuvenated my eyes? How did I fly to the height where the rabble no longer sit at the well?

Did my disgust itself create wings and water-diving powers for me? Truly, I had to fly to the extremest height to find again the fountain of delight!

Oh, I have found it, my brothers! Here, in the extremest height, the fountain of delight gushes up for me! And here there is a life at which no rabble drinks with me!

You gush up almost too impetuously, fountain of delight! And in wanting to fill the cup, you often empty it again.

And I still have to learn to approach you more discreetly: my heart still flows towards you all too impetuously:-

my heart, upon which my summer burns, a short, hot, melancholy, over-joyful summer: how my summer-heart longs for your coolness!

Gone is the lingering affliction of my spring! Gone the snowflakes of my malice in June! Summer have I become entirely, and summer-noonday -

- a summer at the extremest height with cold fountains and blissful stillness: oh come, my friends, that the stillness may become more blissful yet!

For this is our height and our home: we live too nobly and boldly here for all unclean men and their thirsts.

Only cast your pure eyes into the well of my delight, friends! You will not dim its sparkle! It shall laugh back at you with its purity.

We build our nest in the tree Future: eagles shall bring food to us solitaries in their beaks!

Truly, food in which no unclean men could join us! They would think they were eating fire and bum their mouths.

Truly, we do not prepare a home here for unclean men! Their bodies and their spirits would call our happiness a cave of ice!

So let us live above them like strong winds, neighbours of the eagles, neighbours of the snow, neighbours of the sun: that is how strong winds live.

And like a wind will I one day blow among them and with my spirit take away the breath of their spirit: thus my future will have it.

Truly, Zarathustra is a strong wind to all flatlands; and he offers this advice to his enemies and to all that spews and spits: take care not to spit against the wind!...

Why I am So Clever

1

WHY do I know a few more things? Why am I so clever altogether? I have never reflected on questions that are none - I have not squandered myself. - I have, for example, no experience of actual religious difficulties. I am entirely at a loss to know to what extent I ought to have felt 'sinful'. I likewise lack a reliable criterion of a pang of conscience: from what one hears of it, a pang of conscience does not seem to me anything respectable... I should not like to leave an act in the lurch afterwards, I would as a matter of principle prefer to leave the evil outcome, the consequences, out of the question of values. When the outcome is evil one can easily lose the true eye for what one has done: a pang of conscience seems to me a kind of 'evil eye'. To honour to oneself something that went wrong all the more because it went wrong - that rather would accord with my morality. - 'God', 'immortality of the soul', 'redemption', 'the Beyond', all of them concepts to which I have given no attention and no time, not even as a child - perhaps I was never childish enough for it? - I have absolutely no knowledge of atheism as an outcome of reasoning, still less as an event: with me it is obvious by instinct. I am too inquisitive, too questionable, too high spirited to rest content with a crude answer. God is a crude answer, a piece of indelicacy against us thinkers - fundamentally even a crude prohibition to us: you shall not think!... I am interested in quite a different way in a question upon which the 'salvation of mankind' depends far more than it does upon any kind of quaint curiosity of the theologians: the question of nutriment. One can for convenience' sake formulate it thus: 'how to nourish yourself so as to attain your maximum of strength, of virtù in the Renaissance style, of moraline-free virtue?' - My experiences here are as bad as they possibly could be; I am astonished that I heard this question so late, that I learned 'reason' from these experiences so late. Only the perfect worthlessness of our German education - its 'idealism' - can to some extent explain to me why on precisely this point I was backward to the point of holiness. This 'education' which from the first teaches one to lose sight of realities so as to hunt after altogether problematic, so-called 'ideal' objectives, 'classical education' for example - as if it were not from the first an utterly fruitless undertaking to try to unite 'classical' and 'German' in one concept! It is, moreover, mirth-provoking - just think of a 'classically educated' Leipziger! - Until my very maturest years I did in fact eat badly - in the language of morals 'impersonally', 'selflessly', 'altruistically', for the salvation of cooks and other fellow Christians. With the aid of Leipzig cookery, for example, which accompanied my earliest study of Schopenhauer (1865), I very earnestly denied my 'will to live'. To ruin one's stomach so as to receive inadequate nutriment - the aforesaid cookery seems to me to solve this problem wonderfully well. But German cookery in general - what does it not have on its conscience! Soup before the meal (in Venetian cookery books of the sixteenth century still called alla tedesca); meat cooked to shreds, greasy and floury vegetables; the degeneration of puddings to paperweights! If one adds to this the downright bestial dinner-drinking habits of the ancient and by no means only the ancient Germans one will also understand the origin of the German spirit - disturbed intestines... The German spirit is an indigestion, it can have done with nothing. - But to the English diet too, which compared with the Germans, even with the French, is a kind of 'return to nature', that is to say to cannibalism, my own instinct is profoundly opposed; it seems to me to give the spirit heavy feet - the feet of Englishwomen... The best cookery is that of Piedmont. Alcoholic drinks are no good for me; a glass of wine or beer a day is quite enough to make life for me a 'Vale of Tears' - Munich is where my antipodes live. Granted I was a little late to grasp this - I experienced it really from childhood onwards. As a boy I believed wine-drinking to be, like tobacco-smoking, at first only a vanity of young men, later a habit. Perhaps the wine of Naumburg is in part to blame for this austere judgement. To believe that wine makes cheerful I would have to be a Christian, that is to say believe what is for precisely me an absurdity. Oddly enough, while I am put extremely out of sorts by small, much diluted doses of alcohol, I am almost turned into a sailor when it comes to strong doses. Even as a boy I showed how brave I was in this respect. To write a long Latin essay in a single night's sitting and then go on to make a fair copy of it, with the ambition in my pen to imitate in severity and concision my model Sallust, and to pour a quantity of grog of the heaviest calibre over my Latin, was even when I was a pupil of venerable Schulpforta in no way opposed to my physiology, nor perhaps to that of Sallust - however much it might have been to venerable Schulpforta... Later, towards the middle of life, I decided, to be sure, more and more strictly against any sort of 'spirituous' drink: an opponent of vegetarianism from experience, just like Richard Wagner, who converted me, I cannot advise all more spiritual natures too seriously to abstain from alcohol absolutely. Water suffices... I prefer places in which there is everywhere opportunity to drink from flowing fountains (Nice, Turin, Sils); a small glass runs after me like a dog. In vino veritas: it seems that here too I am again at odds with all the world over the concept 'truth' - with me the spirit moves over the water... A couple more signposts from my morality. A big meal is easier to digest than one too small. That the stomach comes into action as a whole, first precondition of a good digestion. One has to know the size of one's stomach. For the same reason those tedious meals should be avoided which I call interrupted sacrificial feasts, those at the table d'hôte. - No eating between meals, no coffee: coffee makes gloomy. Tea beneficial only in the morning. Little, but strong: tea very detrimental and sicklying o'er the whole day if it is the slightest bit too weak. Each has here his own degree, often between the narrowest and most delicate limits. In a very agaçant climate it is inadvisable to start with tea: one should start an hour earlier with a cup of thick oil-free cocoa. - Sit as little as possible; credit no thought not born in the open air and while moving freely about - in which the muscles too do not hold a festival. All prejudices come from the intestines. - Assiduity - I have said it once before - the actual sin against the holy spirit. -

2

Most closely related to the question of nutriment is the question of place and climate. No one is free to live everywhere; and he who has great tasks to fulfil which challenge his entire strength has indeed in this matter a very narrow range of choice. The influence of climate on the metabolism, its slowing down, its speeding up, extends so far that a blunder in regard to place and climate can not only estrange anyone from his task but withhold it from him altogether: he never catches sight of it. His animalic vigor never grows sufficiently great for him to attain to that freedom overflowing into the most spiritual domain where he knows: that I alone can do... A never so infinitesimal sluggishness of the intestines grown into a bad habit completely suffices to transform a genius into something mediocre, something 'German'; the German climate alone is enough to discourage strong and even heroic intestines. The tempo of the metabolism stands in an exact relationship to the mobility or lameness of the feet of the spirit; the 'spirit' itself is indeed only a species of this metabolism. Make a list of the places where there are and have been gifted men, where wit, refinement, malice are a part of happiness, where genius has almost necessarily made its home: they all possess an excellent dry air. Paris, Provence, Florence, Jerusalem, Athens - these names prove something: that genius is conditioned by dry air, clear sky - that is to say by rapid metabolism, by the possibility of again and again supplying oneself with great, even tremendous quantities of energy. I have in mind a case in which a spirit which might have become significant and free became instead narrow, withdrawn, a grumpy specialist, merely through a lack of instinctive subtlety in choice of climate. And I myself could in the end have become this case if sickness had not compelled me to reason, to reflect on reason in reality. Now, when from long practice I read climatic and meteorological effects off from myself as from a very delicate and reliable instrument and even on a short journey, from Turin to Milan for instance, verify on myself physiologically the change in degrees of humidity, I recall with horror the uncanny fact that my life up to the last ten years, the years when my life was in danger, was spent nowhere but in wrong places downright forbidden to me. Naumburg, Schulpforta, Thuringia in general, Leipzig, Basel, Venice - so many ill-fated places for my physiology. If I have no welcome memories at all of my whole childhood and youth, it would be folly to attribute this to so-called 'moral' causes - the undeniable lack of adequate company, for instance: for this lack exists today as it has always existed without preventing me from being brave and cheerful. Ignorance in physiologis - accursed 'idealism' - is the real fatality in my life, the superfluous and stupid in it, something out of which nothing good grows, for which there is no compensation, no counter-reckoning. It is as a consequence of this 'idealism' that I elucidate to myself all the blunders, all the great deviations of instinct and 'modesties' which led me away from the task of my life, that I became a philologist for example - why not at least a physician or something else that opens the eyes? In my time at Basel my entire spiritual diet, the division of the day included, was a perfectly senseless abuse of extraordinary powers without any kind of provision for covering this consumption, without even reflection on consumption and replacement. Any more subtle selfishness, any protection by a commanding instinct was lacking, it was an equating of oneself with everyone else, a piece of 'selflessness', a forgetting of one's distance - something I shall never forgive myself. When I was almost done for, because I was almost done for, I began to reflect on this fundamental irrationality of my life - 'idealism'. It was only sickness that brought me to reason. -

3

Selectivity in nutriment; selectivity in climate and place; - the third thing in which one may at no cost commit a blunder is selectivity in one's kind of recreation. Here too the degree to which a spirit is sui generis makes ever narrower the bounds of what is permitted, that is to say useful to him. In my case all reading is among my recreations: consequently among those things which free me from myself, which allow me to saunter among strange sciences and souls - which I no longer take seriously. It is precisely reading which helps me to recover from my seriousness. At times when I am deeply sunk in work you will see no books around me: I would guard against letting anyone speak or even think in my vicinity. And that is what reading would mean... Has it really been noticed that in that state of profound tension to which pregnancy condemns the spirit and fundamentally the entire organism, any chance event, any kind of stimulus from without has too vehement an effect, 'cuts' too deeply? One has to avoid the chance event, the stimulus from without, as much as possible; a kind of self-walling-up is among the instinctual sagacities of spiritual pregnancy. Shall I allow a strange thought to climb secretly over the wall? - And that is what reading would mean... The times of work and fruitfulness are followed by the time of recreation: come hither, you pleasant, you witty, you clever books! Will they be German books?... I have to reckon back half a year to catch myself with a book in my hand. But what was it? - An excellent study by Victor Brochard, les sceptiques Grecs, in which my Laertiana are also well employed. The Sceptics, the only honourable type among the two- and five-fold ambiguous philosophical crowd! ... Otherwise I take flight almost always to the same books, really a small number, those books which have proved themselves precisely to me. It does not perhaps lie in my nature to read much or many kinds of things: a reading room makes me ill. Neither does it lie in my nature to love much or many kinds of things. Caution, even hostility towards new books is rather part of my instinct than 'tolerance', 'largeur du coeur' and other forms of 'neighbour love'... It is really only a small number of older Frenchmen to whom I return again and again: I believe only in French culture and consider everything in Europe that calls itself 'culture' a misunderstanding, not to speak of German culture... The few instances of high culture I have encountered in Germany have all been of French origin, above all Frau Cosima Wagner, by far the first voice I have heard in questions of taste. - That I do not read Pascal but love him, as the most instructive of all sacrifices to Christianity, slowly murdered first physically then psychologically, the whole logic of this most horrible form of inhuman cruelty; that I have something of Montaigne's wantonness in my spirit, who knows? perhaps also in my body; that my artist's taste defends the names Molière, Corneille and Racine, not without wrath, against a disorderly genius such as Shakespeare: this does not ultimately exclude my finding the most recent Frenchmen also charming company. I cannot at all conceive in which century of history one could haul together such inquisitive and at the same time such delicate psychologists as one can in contemporary Paris: I name as a sample - for their number is by no means small, Messrs Paul Bourget, Pierre Loti, Gyp, Meilhac, Anatole France, Jules Lemaitre, or to pick out one of the stronger race, a genuine Latin to whom I am especially attached, Guy de Maupassant. Between ourselves, I prefer this generation even to their great teachers, who have all been ruined by German philosophy (M. Taine for example by Hegel, whom he has to thank for this misunderstanding of great human beings and ages). As far as Germany extends it ruins culture. It was only the war that 'redeemed' the spirit in France... Stendhal, one of the fairest accidents of my life - for whatever marks an epoch in my life has been brought to me by accident, never by a recommendation - is utterly invaluable with his anticipating psychologist's eye, with his grasp of facts which reminds one of the proximity of the greatest man of the factual (ex ungue Napoleonem -); finally not least as an honest atheist, a rare, almost undiscoverable species in France - with all deference to Prosper Mérimée... Perhaps I am even envious of Stendhal? He robbed me of the best atheist joke which precisely I could have made: 'God's only excuse is that he does not exist'... I myself have said somewhere: what has hitherto been the greatest objection to existence? God...

4

The highest conception of the lyric poet was given me by Heinrich Heine. I seek in vain in all the realms of millennia for an equally sweet and passionate music. He possesses that divine malice without which I cannot imagine perfection - I assess the value of people, of races according to how necessarily they are unable to separate the god from the satyr. - And how he employs German! It will one day be said that Heine and I have been by far the first artists of the German language - at an incalculable distance from everything which mere Germans have done with it. - I must be profoundly related to Byron's Manfred: I discovered all these abysses in myself - I was ripe for this work at thirteen. I have no words, only a look for those who dare to say the word Faust in the presence of Manfred. The Germans are incapable of any conception of greatness: proof Schumann. Expressly from wrath against this sugary Saxon, I composed a counter-overture to Manfred, of which Hans von Bülow said he had never seen the like on manuscript paper: it constituted a rape on Euterpe. - When I seek my highest formula for Shakespeare I find it always in that he conceived the type of Caesar. One cannot guess at things like this - one is it or one is not. The great poet creates only out of his own reality - to the point at which he is afterwards unable to endure his own work... When I have taken a glance at my Zarathustra I walk up and down my room for half an hour unable to master an unendurable spasm of sobbing. - I know of no more heartrending reading than Shakespeare: what must a man have suffered to need to be a buffoon to this extent! - Is Hamlet understood? It is not doubt, it is certainty which makes mad... But to feel in this way one must be profound, abyss, philosopher... We all fear truth... And, to confess it: I am instinctively certain that Lord Bacon is the originator, the self-tormentor of this uncanniest species of literature: what do I care about the pitiable charter of American shallow-pates and muddle-heads? But the power for the mightiest reality of vision is not only compatible with the mightiest power for action, for the monstrous in action, for crime - it even presupposes it... We do not know nearly enough about Lord Bacon, the first realist in every great sense of the word, to know what he did, what he wanted, what he experienced within himself... And the devil take it, my dear critics! Supposing I had baptized my Zarathustra with another name, for example with the name of Richard Wagner, the perspicuity of two millennia would not have sufficed to divine that the author of 'Human, All Too Human' is the visionary of Zarathustra...

5

Here where I am speaking of the recreations of my life, I need to say a word to express my gratitude for that which of all things in it has refreshed me by far the most profoundly and cordially. This was without any doubt my intimate association with Richard Wagner. I offer all my other human relationships cheap; but at no price would I relinquish from my life the Tribschen days, those days of mutual confidences, of cheerfulness, of sublime incidents - of profound moments... I do not know what others may have experienced with Wagner: over our sky no cloud ever passed. - And with that I return again to France - I cannot spare reasons, I can spare a mere curl of the lip for Wagnerians et hoc genus omne who believe they are doing honour to Wagner when they find him similar to themselves... Constituted as I am, a stranger in my deepest instincts to everything German, so that the mere presence of a German hinders my digestion, my first contact with Wagner was also the first time in my life I ever drew a deep breath: I felt, I reverenced him as a being from outside, as the opposite, the incarnate protest against all 'German virtues'. - We who were children in the swamp-air of the fifties are necessarily pessimists regarding the concept 'German'; we cannot be anything but revolutionaries - we shall acquiesce in no state of things in which the bigot is on top. It is a matter of complete indifference to me if today he plays in different colours, if he dresses in scarlet and dons the uniform of a hussar... Very well Wagner was a revolutionary - he fled from the Germans... As an artist one has no home in Europe except in Paris: the delicatesse in all five senses of art which Wagner's art presupposes, the fingers for nuances, the psychological morbidity, is to be found only in Paris. Nowhere else does there exist such a passion in questions of form, this seriousness in mise en scène - it is the Parisian seriousness par excellence. There is in Germany absolutely no conception of the tremendous ambition which dwells in the soul of a Parisian artist. The German is good-natured - Wagner was by no means good-natured... But I have already said sufficient as to where Wagner belongs, in whom he has his closest relatives: the French late romantics, that high-flying and yet exhilarating kind of artists such as Delacroix, such as Berlioz, with a fond of sickness, of incurability in their nature, sheer fanatics for expression, virtuosi through and through... Who was the first intelligent adherent of Wagner? Charles Baudelaire, the same as was the first to understand Delacroix, that typical décadent in whom an entire race of artists recognized themselves - he was perhaps also the last... What I have never forgiven Wagner? That he condescended to the Germans - that he became reichsdeutsch... As far as Germany extends it ruins culture. -

6

All in all I could not have endured my youth without Wagnerian music. For I was condemned to Germans. If one wants to get free from an unendurable pressure one needs hashish. Very well, I needed Wagner. Wagner is the counter-poison to everything German par excellence - still poison, I do not dispute it... From the moment there was a piano score of Tristan - my compliments, Herr von Bülow! - I was a Wagnerian. The earliest works of Wagner I saw as beneath me - still too common, too 'German' ... But I still today seek a work of a dangerous fascination, of a sweet and shuddery infinity equal to that of Tristan - I seek in all the arts in vain. All the strangenesses of Leonardo da Vinci lose their magic at the first note of Tristan. This work is altogether Wagner's non plus ultra; he recuperated from it with the Meistersinger and the Ring. To become healthier - that is retrogression in the case of a nature such as Wagner... I take it for a piece of good fortune of the first rank to have lived at the right time, and to have lived precisely among Germans, so as to be ripe for this work: my psychologist's inquisitiveness goes that far. The world is poor for him who has never been sick enough for this 'voluptuousness of hell': to employ a mystic's formula is permissible, almost obligatory, here. I think I know better than anyone what tremendous things Wagner was capable of, the fifty worlds of strange delights to which no one but he had wings; and as I am strong enough to turn even the most questionable and most perilous things to my own advantage and thus to become stronger, I call Wagner the great benefactor of my life. That in which we are related, that we have suffered more profoundly, from one another also, than men of this century are capable of suffering, will eternally join our names together again and again; and as surely as Wagner is among Germans merely a misunderstanding, just as surely am I and always will be. - Two centuries of psychological and artistic discipline first, my Herr Germans!... But one cannot catch up that amount. -

7

I shall say another word for the most select ears: what I really want from music. That it is cheerful and profound, like an afternoon in October. That it is individual, wanton, tender, a little sweet woman of lowness and charm... I shall never admit that a German could know what music is. What one calls German musicians, the greatest above all, are foreigners, Slavs, Croats, Italians, Netherlanders - or Jews: otherwise Germans of the strong race, extinct Germans, like Heinrich Schütz, Bach and Handel. I myself am still sufficient of a Pole to exchange the rest of music for Chopin; for three reasons I exclude Wagner's Siegfried Idyll, perhaps also a few things by Liszt, who excels all other musicians in the nobility of his orchestral tone; finally all that has grown up beyond the Alps - this side... I would not know how to get on without Rossini, even less without my south in music, the music of my Venetian maestro Pietro Gasti. And when I say beyond the Alps I am really saying only Venice. When I seek another word for music I never find any other word than Venice. I do not know how to distinguish between tears and music - I do not know how to think of happiness, of the south, without a shudder of faintheartedness.

Lately I stood at the bridge

in the brown night.

From afar there came a song:

a golden drop, it swelled

across the trembling surface.

Gondolas, lights, music -

drunken it swam out into the gloom...

My soul, a stringed instrument,

touched by invisible hands

sang to itself in reply a gondola song,

and trembled with gaudy happiness.

- Was anyone listening?

8

In all this - in selection of nutriment, of place and climate, of recreation - there commands an instinct of self-preservation which manifests itself most unambiguously as an instinct for self-defence. Not to see many things, not to hear them, not to let them approach one - first piece of ingenuity, first proof that one is no accident but a necessity. The customary word for this self-defensive instinct is taste. Its imperative commands, not only to say No when Yes would be a piece of 'selflessness', but also to say No as little as possible. To separate oneself, to depart from that to which No would be required again and again. The rationale is that defensive expenditures, be they never so small, become a rule, a habit, lead to an extraordinary and perfectly superfluous impoverishment. Our largest expenditures are our most frequent small ones. Warding off, not letting come close, is an expenditure - one should not deceive oneself over this - a strength squandered on negative objectives. One can merely through the constant need to ward off become too weak any longer to defend oneself. - Suppose I were to step out of my house and discover, instead of calm and aristocratic Turin, the German provincial town: my instinct would have to blockade itself so as to push back all that pressed upon it from this flat and cowardly world. Or suppose I discovered the German metropolis, that builded vice where nothing grows, where every kind of thing, good and bad, is dragged in. Would I not in face of it have to become a hedgehog? - But to have spikes is an extravagance, a double luxury even if one is free to have no spikes but open hands...

Another form of sagacity and self-defence consists in reacting as seldom as possible and withdrawing from situations and relationships in which one would be condemned as it were to suspend one's 'freedom', one's initiative, and become a mere reagent. I take as a parable traffic with books. The scholar, who really does nothing but 'trundle' books - the philologist at a modest assessment about 200 a day - finally loses altogether the ability to think for himself. If he does not trundle he does not think. He replies to a stimulus (- a thought he has read) when he thinks - finally he does nothing but react. The scholar expends his entire strength in affirmation and denial, in criticizing what has already been thought - he himself no longer thinks... The instinct for self-defence has in his case become soft; otherwise he would defend himself against books. The scholar - a décadent. - This I have seen with my own eyes: natures gifted, rich and free already in their thirties 'read to ruins', mere matches that have to be struck if they are to ignite - emit 'thoughts'. - Early in the morning at the break of day, in all the freshness and dawn of one's strength, to read a book - I call that vicious! -

9

At this point I can no longer avoid actually answering the question how one becomes what one is. And with that I touch on the masterpiece in the art of self-preservation - of selfishness... For assuming that the task, the vocation, the destiny of the task exceeds the average measure by a significant degree, there wouldbe no greater danger than to catch sight of oneself with this task. That one becomes what one is presupposes that one does not have the remotest idea what one is. From this point of view even the blunders of life - the temporary sidepaths and wrong turnings, the delays, the 'modesties', the seriousness squandered on tasks which lie outside the task - have their own meaning and value. They are an expression of a great sagacity, even the supreme sagacity: where nosce to ipsum would be the recipe for destruction, self-forgetfulness, self-misunderstanding, self-diminution, -narrowing, -mediocratizing becomes reason itself. Expressed morally: love of one's neighbour, living for others and other things can be the defensive measure for the preservation of the sternest selfishness. This is the exceptional case in which I, contrary to my rule and conviction, take the side of the 'selfless' drives: here they work in the service of selfishness, self-cultivation. - The entire surface of consciousness - consciousness is a surface - has to be kept clear of any of the great imperatives. Even the grand words, the grand attitudes must be guarded against! All of them represent a danger that the instinct will 'understand itself' too early - -. In the meantime the organizing 'idea' destined to rule grows and grows in the depths - it begins to command, it slowly leads back from sidepaths and wrong turnings, it prepares individual qualities and abilities which will one day prove themselves indispensable as means to achieving the whole - it constructs the ancillary capacities one after the other before it gives any hint of the dominating task, of the 'goal', 'objective', 'meaning'. - Regarded from this side my life is simply wonderful. For the task of a revaluation of values more capacities perhaps were required than have dwelt together in one individual, above all antithetical capacities which however are not allowed to disturb or destroy one another. Order of rank among capacities; distance; the art of dividing without making inimical; mixing up nothing, 'reconciling' nothing; a tremendous multiplicity which is none the less the opposite of chaos - this has been the precondition, the protracted secret labour and artistic working of my instinct. The magnitude of its higher protection was shown in the fact I have at no time had the remotest idea what was growing within me - that all my abilities one day leapt forth suddenly ripe, in their final perfection. I cannot remember ever having taken any trouble - no trace of struggle can be discovered in my life, I am the opposite of an heroic nature. To 'want' something, to 'strive' after something, to have a 'goal', a 'wish' in view - I know none of this from experience. Even at this moment I look out upon my future - a distant future! - as upon a smooth sea: it is ruffled by no desire. I do not want in the slightest that anything should become other than it is; I do not want myself to become other than I am... But that is how I have always lived. I have harboured no desire. Someone who after his forty-fourth year can say he has never striven after honours, after women, after money! - Not that I could not have had them... Thus, for example, I one day became a university professor - I had never had the remotest thought of such a thing, for I was barely twenty-four years old.

10

- I shall be asked why I have really narrated all these little things which according to the traditional judgement are matters of indifference: it will be said that in doing so I harm myself all the more if I am destined to fulfil great tasks. Answer: these little things - nutriment, place, climate, recreation, the whole casuistry of selfishness - are beyond all conception of greater importance than anything that has been considered of importance hitherto. It is precisely here that one has to begin to learn anew. Those things which mankind has hitherto pondered seriously are not even realities, merely imaginings, more strictly speaking lies from the bad instincts of sick, in the profoundest sense injurious natures - all the concepts 'God', 'soul', 'virtue', 'sin', 'the Beyond', 'truth', 'eternal life'... But the greatness of human nature, its 'divinity', has been sought in them... All questions of politics, the ordering of society, education have been falsified down to their foundations because the most injurious men have been taken for great men - because contempt has been taught for the 'little' things, which is to say for the fundamental affairs of life... Now, when I compare myself with the men who have hitherto been honoured as pre-eminent men the distinction is palpable. I do not count these supposed 'preeminent men' as belonging to mankind at all - to me they are the refuse of mankind, abortive offspring of sickness and vengeful instincts: they are nothing but pernicious, fundamentally incurable monsters who take revenge on life... I want to be the antithesis of this: it is my privilege to possess the highest subtlety for all the signs of healthy instincts. Every morbid trait is lacking in me; even in periods of severe illness I did not become morbid; a trait of fanaticism will be sought in vain in my nature. At no moment of my life can I be shown to have adopted any kind of arrogant or pathetic posture. The pathos of attitudes does not belong to greatness; whoever needs attitudes at all is false... Beware of all picturesque men! - Life has been easy for me, easiest when it demanded of me the most difficult things. Anyone who saw me during the seventy days of this autumn when I was uninterruptedly creating nothing but things of the first rank which no man will be able to do again or has done before, bearing a responsibility for all the coming millennia, will have noticed no trace of tension in me, but rather an overflowing freshness and cheerfulness. I never ate with greater relish, I never slept better. - I know of no other way of dealing with great tasks than that of play: this is, as a sign of greatness, an essential precondition. The slightest constraint, the gloomy mien, any kind of harsh note in the throat are all objections to a man, how much more to his work!... One must have no nerves... To suffer from solitude is likewise an objection - I have always suffered only from the 'multitude'... At an absurdly early age, at the age of seven, I already knew that no human word would ever reach me: has anyone ever seen me sad on that account? - Still today I treat everyone with the same geniality, I am even full of consideration for the basest people: in all this there is not a grain of arrogance, of secret contempt. He whom I despise divines that I despise him: through my mere existence I enrage everything that has bad blood in its veins... My formula for greatness in a human being is amor fati: that one wants nothing to be other than it is, not in the future, not in the past, not in all eternity. Not merely to endure that which happens of necessity, still less to dissemble it - all idealism is untruthfulness in the face of necessity - but to love it...

Why I Write Such Good Books

1

I AM one thing, my writings are another. - Here, before I speak of these writings themselves, I shall touch on the question of their being understood or not understood. I shall do so as perfunctorily as is fitting: for the time for this question has certainly not yet come. My time has not yet come, some are born posthumously. - One day or other institutions will be needed in which people live and teach as I understand living and teaching: perhaps even chairs for the interpretation of Zarathustra will be established. But it would be a complete contradiction of myself if I expected ears and hands for my truths already today: that I am not heard today, that no one today knows how to take from me, is not only comprehensible; it even seems to me right. I do not want to be taken for what I am not - and that requires that I do not take myself for what I am not. To say it again, little of 'ill will' can be shown in my life; neither would I be able to speak of barely a single case of 'literary ill will'. On the other hand all too much of pure folly!... It seems to me that to take a book of mine into his hands is one of the rarest distinctions anyone can confer upon himself - I even assume he removes his shoes when he does so - not to speak of boots... When Doctor Heinrich von Stein once honestly complained that he understood not one word of my Zarathustra, I told him that was quite in order: to have understood, that is to say experienced, six sentences of that book would raise one to a higher level of mortals than 'modern' man could attain to. How could I, with this feeling of distance, even want the 'modern men' I know - to read me! - My triumph is precisely the opposite of Schopenhauer's - I say 'non legor, non legar'. - Not that I should like to underestimate the pleasure which the innocence in the rejection of my writings has given me. This very summer just gone, at a time when, with my own weighty, too heavily weighty literature, I was perhaps throwing all the rest of literature off its balance, a professor of Berlin University kindly gave me to understand that I ought really to avail myself of a different form: no one read stuff like mine. - In the end it was not Germany but Switzerland which offered me the two extreme cases. An essay of Dr V. Widmann in the Bund on 'Beyond Good and Evil' under the title 'Nietzsche's Dangerous Book', and a general report on my books as a whole on the part of Herr Karl Spitteler, also in the Bund, constitute a maximum in my life - of what I take care not to say... The latter, for example, dealt with my Zarathustra as an advanced exercise in style, with the request that I might later try to provide some content; Dr Widmann expressed his respect for the courage with which I strive to abolish all decent feelings. - Through a little trick of chance every sentence here was, with a consistency I had to admire, a truth stood on its head: remarkably enough, all one had to do was to 'revalue all values' in order to hit the nail on the head with regard to me - instead of hitting my head with a nail... All the more reason for me to attempt an explanation. - Ultimately, no one can extract from things, books included, more than he already knows. What one has no access to through experience one has no ear for. Now let us imagine an extreme case: that a book speaks of nothing but events which lie outside the possibility of general or even of rare experience - that it is the first language for a new range of experiences. In this case simply nothing will be heard, with the acoustical illusion that where nothing is heard there is nothing... This is in fact my average experience and, if you like, the originality of my experience. Whoever believed he had understood something of me had dressed up something out of me after his own image - not uncommonly an antithesis of me, for instance an 'idealist'; whoever had understood nothing of me denied that I came into consideration at all. - The word 'superman' to designate a type that has turned out supremely well, in antithesis to 'modern' men, to 'good' men, to Christians and other nihilists - a word which, in the mouth of a Zarathustra, the destroyer of morality, becomes a very thoughtful word - has almost everywhere been understood with perfect innocence in the sense of those values whose antithesis makes its appearance in the figure of Zarathustra: that is to say as an 'idealistic' type of higher species of man, half 'saint', half 'genius'... Other learned cattle caused me on its account to be suspected of Darwinism; even the 'hero cult' of that great unconscious and involuntary counterfeiter Carlyle which I rejected so maliciously has been recognized in it. He into whose ear I whispered he ought to look around rather for a Cesare Borgia than for a Parsifal did not believe his ears. - That I am utterly incurious about discussions of my books, especially by newspapers, will have to be forgiven me. My friends, my publishers know this and do not speak to me about such things. In a particular instance I once had a sight of all the sins that had been committed against a single book - it was 'Beyond Good and Evil'; I could tell a pretty story about that. Would you believe it that the 'Nationalzeitung' - a Prussian newspaper, for my foreign readers - I myself read, if I may say so, only the Journal des Débats - could in all seriousness understand the book as a 'sign of the times', as the real genuine Junker philosophy for which the 'Kreuzzeitung' merely lacked the courage?...

2

This was said for Germans: for I have readers everywhere else - nothing but choice intelligences of proved character brought up in high positions and duties; I have even real geniuses among my readers. In Vienna, in St Petersburg, in Stockholm, in Copenhagen, in Paris and New York - I have been discovered everywhere: I have not been in Europe's flatland Germany... And to confess it, I rejoice even more over my non-readers, such as have never heard either my name or the word philosophy; but wherever I go, here in Turin for example, every face grows more cheerful and benevolent at the sight of me. What has flattered me the most is that old marketwomen take great pains to select together for me the sweetest of their grapes. That is how far one must be a philosopher... It is not in vain that the Poles are called the French among the Slavs. A charming Russian lady would not mistake for a moment where I belong. I cannot succeed in becoming solemn, the most I can achieve is embarrassment... To think German, to feel German - I can do everything, but that is beyond my powers... My old teacher Ritschl went so far as to maintain that I conceived even my philological essays like a Parisian romancier - absurdly exciting. In Paris itself there is astonishment over 'toutes mes audaces et finesses' - the expression is Monsieur Taine's -; I fear that with me there is up to the highest forms of the dithyramb an admixture of that salt which never gets soggy -'German' - esprit... I cannot do otherwise, so help me God! Amen. - We all know, some even know from experience, what a longears is. Very well, I dare to assert that I possess the smallest ears. This is of no little interest to women - it seems to me they feel themselves better understood by me?... I am the anti-ass par excellence and therewith a world-historical monster - I am, in Greek and not only in Greek, the Anti-Christ...

3

I know my privileges as a writer to some extent; in individual cases it has been put to me how greatly habituation to my writings 'ruins' taste. One can simply no longer endure other books, philosophical ones least of all. To enter this noble and delicate world is an incomparable distinction - to do so one absolutely must not be a German; it is in the end a distinction one has to have earned. But he who is related to me through loftiness of will experiences when he reads me real ecstasies of learning: for I come from heights no bird has ever soared to, I know abysses into which no foot has ever yet strayed. I have been told it is impossible to put a book of mine down - I even disturb the night's rest... There is altogether no prouder and at the same time more exquisite kind of book than my books - they attain here and there the highest thing that can be attained on earth, cynicism; one needs the most delicate fingers as well as the bravest fists if one is to master them. Any infirmity of soul excludes one from them once and for all, any dyspepsia, even, does so: one must have no nerves, one must have a joyful belly. Not only does the poverty, the hole-and-corner air of a soul exclude it from them - cowardice, uncleanliness, secret revengefulness in the entrails does so far more: a word from me drives all bad instincts into the face. I have among my acquaintances several experimental animals on whom I bring home to myself the various, very instructively various reactions to my writings. Those who want to have nothing to do with their contents, my so-called friends for example, become 'impersonal': they congratulate me on having 'done it' again - progress is apparent, too, in a greater cheerfulness of tone... The completely vicious 'spirits', the 'beautiful souls', the thoroughly and utterly mendacious have no idea at all what to do with these books - consequently they see the same as beneath them, the beautiful consistency of all 'beautiful souls'. The horned cattle among my acquaintances, mere Germans if I may say so, give me to understand they are not always of my opinion, though they are sometimes... I have heard this said even of Zarathustra... Any 'feminism' in a person, or in a man, likewise closes the gates on me: one will never be able to enter this labyrinth of daring knowledge. One must never have spared oneself, harshness must be among one's habits, if one is to be happy and cheerful among nothing but hard truths. When I picture a perfect reader, I always picture a monster of courage and curiosity, also something supple, cunning, cautious, a born adventurer and discoverer. Finally: I would not know how to say better to whom at bottom alone I speak than Zarathustra has said it: to whom alone does he want to narrate his riddle?

To you, the bold venturers and adventurers, and whoever has embarked with cunning sails upon dreadful seas,

to you who are intoxicated with riddles, who take pleasure in twilight, whose soul is lured with flutes to every treacherous abyss -

for you do not desire to feel for a rope with cowardly hand; and where you can guess you hate to calculate...

4

I shall at the same time also say a general word on my art of style. To communicate a state, an inner tension of pathos through signs, including the tempo of these signs - that is the meaning of every style; and considering that the multiplicity of inner states is in my case extraordinary, there exists in my case the possibility of many styles - altogether the most manifold art of style any man has ever had at his disposal. Every style is good which actually communicates an inner state, which makes no mistake as to the signs, the tempo of the signs, the gestures - all rules of phrasing are art of gesture. My instinct is here infallible. - Good style in itself - a piece of pure folly, mere 'idealism', on a par with the 'beautiful in itself ', the 'good in itself', the 'thing in itself'... Always presupposing there are ears - that there are those capable and worthy of a similar pathos, that those are not lacking to whom one ought to communicate oneself. - My Zarathustra for example is at present still looking for them - alas! he will have to look for a long time yet! One has to be worthy of assaying him... And until then there will be no one who comprehends the art which has here been squandered: no one has ever had more of the new, the unheard-of, the really new-created in artistic means to squander. That such a thing was possible in the German language remained to be proved: I myself would previously have most hotly disputed it. Before me one did not know what can be done with the German language - what can be done with language as such. The art of grand rhythm, the grand style of phrasing, as the expression of a tremendous rise and fall of sublime, of superhuman passion, was first discovered by me; with a dithyramb such as the last of the third Zarathustra, entitled 'The Seven Seals', I flew a thousand miles beyond that which has hitherto been called poesy.

5

That out of my writings there speaks a psychologist who has not his equal, that is perhaps the first thing a good reader will notice - a reader such as I deserve, who reads me as good old philologists read their Horace. The propositions over which everybody is in fundamental agreement - not to speak of everybody's philosophers, the moralists and other hollow-heads and cabbage-heads - appear with me as naive blunders: for example that belief that 'unegoistic' and 'egoistic' are antitheses, while the ego itself is merely a 'higher swindle', an 'ideal'. There are neither egoistic nor unegoistic actions: both concepts are psychologically nonsense. Or the proposition 'man strives after happiness'... Or the proposition 'happiness is the reward of virtue'... Or the proposition 'pleasure and displeasure are opposites'... The Circe of mankind, morality, has falsified all psychologica to its very foundations - has moralized it - to the point of the frightful absurdity that love is supposed to be something 'unegoistic'... One has to be set firmly upon oneself, one has to stand bravely upon one's own two legs, otherwise one cannot love at all. In the long run the little women know that all too well: they play the deuce with selfless, with merely objective men... Dare I venture in addition to suggest that I know these little women? It is part of my Dionysian endowment. Who knows? perhaps I am the first psychologist of the eternal-womanly. They all love me - an old story: excepting the abortive women, the 'emancipated' who lack the stuff for children. - Happily I am not prepared to be torn to pieces: the complete woman tears to pieces when she loves... I know these amiable maenads... Ah, what a dangerous, creeping, subterranean little beast of prey it is! And so pleasant with it!... A little woman chasing after her revenge would over-run fate itself. - The woman is unspeakably more wicked than the man, also cleverer; goodness in a woman is already a form of degeneration ... At the bottom of all so-called 'beautiful souls' there lies a physiological disadvantage - I shall not say all I could or I should become medicynical. The struggle for equal rights is even a symptom of sickness: every physician knows that. - The more a woman is a woman the more she defends herself tooth and nail against rights in general: for the state of nature, the eternal war between the sexes puts her in a superior position by far. - Have there been ears for my definition of love? it is the only one worthy of a philosopher. Love - in its methods war, in its foundation the mortal hatred of the sexes. Has my answer been heard to the question how one cures - 'redeems' - a woman? One makes a child for her. The woman has need of children, the man is always only the means: thus spoke Zarathustra. - 'Emancipation of woman' - is the instinctive hatred of the woman who has turned out ill, that is to say is incapable of bearing, for her who has turned out well - the struggle against 'man' is always only means, subterfuge, tactic. When they elevate themselves as 'woman in herself', as 'higher woman', as 'idealist' woman, they want to lower the general level of rank of woman; no surer means for achieving that than grammar school education, trousers and the political rights of voting cattle. At bottom the emancipated are the anarchists in the world of the 'eternal-womanly', the under-privileged whose deepest instinct is revenge... An entire species of the most malevolent 'idealism' - which, by the way, also occurs in men, for example in the case of Henrik Ibsen, that typical old maid - has the objective of poisoning the good conscience, the naturalness in sexual love... And so as to leave no doubt as to my opinion in this matter, which is as honest as it is strict, I would like to impart one more clause of my moral code against vice: with the word vice I combat every sort of anti-nature or, if one likes beautiful words, idealism. The clause reads: 'The preaching of chastity is a public incitement to anti-nature. Every expression of contempt for the sexual life, every befouling of it through the concept "impure", is the crime against life - is the intrinsic sin against the holy spirit of life.'

6

To give an idea of me as a psychologist I take a curious piece of psychology which occurs in 'Beyond Good and Evil' - I forbid, by the way, any conjecture as to whom I am describing in this passage: 'The genius of the heart as it is possessed by that great hidden one, the tempter god and born pied piper of consciences whose voice knows how to descend into the underworld of every soul, who says no word and gives no glance in which there lies no touch of enticement, to whose mastery belongs knowing how to seem - not what he is but what to those who follow him is one constraint more to press ever closer to him, to follow him ever more inwardly and thoroughly... The genius of the heart who makes everything loud and self-satisfied fall silent and teaches it to listen, who smooths rough souls and gives them a new desire to savour - the desire to lie still as a mirror, that the deep sky may mirror itself in them... The genius of the heart who teaches the stupid and hasty hand to hesitate and grasp more delicately; who divines the hidden and forgotten treasure, the drop of goodness and sweet spirituality under thick and opaque ice, and is a divining-rod for every grain of gold which has lain long in the prison of much mud and sand... The genius of the heart from whose touch everyone goes away richer, not favoured and surprised, not as if blessed and oppressed with the goods of others, but richer in himself, newer to himself than before, broken open, blown upon and sounded out by a thawing wind, more uncertain perhaps, more delicate, more fragile, more broken, but full of hopes that as yet have no names, full of new will and current, full of new ill will and counter current...'

Why I am a Destiny

1

I KNOW my fate. One day there will be associated with my name the recollection of something frightful - of a crisis like no other before on earth, of the profoundest collision of conscience, of a decision evoked against everything that until then had been believed in, demanded, sanctified. I am not a man, I am dynamite. - And with all that there is nothing in me of a founder of a religion - religions are affairs of the rabble, I have need of washing my hands after contact with religious people... I do not want 'believers', I think I am too malicious to believe in myself, I never speak to masses... I have a terrible fear I shall one day be pronounced holy: one will guess why I bring out this book beforehand; it is intended to prevent people from making mischief with me... I do not want to be a saint, rather even a buffoon... Perhaps I am a buffoon... And none the less, or rather not none the less - for there has hitherto been nothing more mendacious than saints - the truth speaks out of me. - But my truth is dreadful: for hitherto the lie has been called truth. - Revaluation of all values: this is my formula for an act of supreme coming-to-oneself on the part of mankind which in me has become flesh and genius. It is my fate to have to be the first decent human being, to know myself in opposition to the men-daciousness of millennia... I was the first to discover the truth, in that I was the first to sense - smell - the lie as lie... My genius is in my nostrils... I contradict as has never been contradicted and am none the less the opposite of a negative spirit. I am a bringer of good tidings such as there has never been, I know tasks from such a height that any conception of them has hitherto been lacking; only after me is it possible to hope again. With all that I am necessarily a man of fatality. For when truth steps into battle with the lie of millennia we shall have convulsions, an earthquake spasm, a transposition of valley and mountain such as has never been dreamed of. The concept politics has then become completely absorbed into a war of spirits; all the power-structures of the old society have been blown into the air - they one and all reposed on the lie: there will be wars such as there have never yet been on earth. Only after me will there be grand politics on earth.

2

Does one want a formula for a destiny that has become man? It stands in my Zarathustra.

- and he who wants to be a creator in good and evil has first to be a destroyer and break values.

Thus the greatest evil belongs with the greatest good: this, however, is the creative good.

I am by far the most terrible human being there has ever been; this does not mean I shall not be the most beneficent. I know joy in destruction to a degree corresponding to my strength for destruction - in both I obey my dionysian nature, which does not know how to separate No-doing from Yes-saying. I am the first immoralist: I am therewith the destroyer par excellence. -

3

I have not been asked, as I should have been asked, what the name Zarathustra means in precisely my mouth, in the mouth of the first immoralist: for what constitutes the tremendous uniqueness of that Persian in history is precisely the opposite of this. Zarathustra was the first to see in the struggle between good and evil the actual wheel in the working of things: the translation of morality into the realm of metaphysics, as force, cause, end-in-itself, is his work. But this question is itself at bottom its own answer. Zarathustra created this most fateful of errors, morality: consequently he must also be the first to recognize it. Not only has he had longer and greater experience here than any other thinker - the whole of history is indeed the experimental refutation of the proposition of a so-called 'moral world-order' -: what is more important is that Zarathustra is more truthful than any other thinker. His teaching, and his alone, upholds truthfulness as the supreme virtue - that is to say, the opposite of the cowardice of the 'idealist', who takes flight in face of reality; Zarathustra has more courage in him than all other thinkers put together. To tell the truth and to shoot well with arrows: that is Persian virtue. - Have I been understood? The self-overcoming of morality through truthfulness, the self-overcoming of the moralist into his opposite - into me - that is what the name Zarathustra means in my mouth.

4

At bottom my expression immoralist involves two denials. I deny first a type of man who has hitherto counted as the highest, the good, the benevolent, beneficent; I deny secondly a kind of morality which has come to be accepted and to dominate as morality in itself - décadence morality, in more palpable terms Christian morality. The second contradiction might be seen as the decisive one, since the over-valuation of goodness and benevolence by and large already counts with me as a consequence of décadence, as a symptom of weakness, as incompatible with an ascending and affirmative life: denial and destruction is a condition of affirmation. - I deal first of all with the psychology of the good man. In order to assess what a type of man is worth one has to compute how much his preservation costs - one has to know the conditions of his existence. The condition for the existence of the good is the lie -: expressed differently, the desire not to see at any price what is the fundamental constitution of reality, that is to say not such as to call forth benevolent instincts at all times, even less such as to permit at all times an interference by short-sighted good-natured hands. To regard states of distress in general as an objection, as something that must be abolished, is the niaiserie par excellence, in a general sense a real disaster in its consequences, a fatality of stupidity - almost as stupid as would be the will to abolish bad weather - perhaps from pity to the poor... In the general economy of the whole the fearfulnesses of reality (in the affects, in the desires, in the will to power) are to an incalculable degree more necessary than any form of petty happiness, so-called 'goodness'; since the latter is conditioned by falsity of instinct one must even be cautious about granting it a place at all. I shall have a grand occasion of demonstrating the measurelessly uncanny consequences for the whole of history of optimism, that offspring of the homines optimi. Zarathustra, the first to grasp that optimism is just as décadent as pessimism and perhaps more harmful, says: good men never tell the truth. The good taught you false shores and false securities: you were born and kept in the lies of the good. Everything has been distorted and twisted down to its very bottom through the good. Fortunately the world has not been constructed for the satisfaction of instincts such as would permit merely good-natured herd animals to find their narrow happiness in it; to demand that everything should become 'good man', herd animal, blueeyed, benevolent, 'beautiful soul' - or, as Mr Herbert Spencer wants, altruistic, would mean to deprive existence of its great character, would mean to castrate mankind and to reduce it to a paltry Chinadom. - And this has been attempted!... Precisely this has been called morality... In this sense Zarathustra calls the good now 'the last men', now the 'beginning of the end'; above all he feels them to be the most harmful species of man, because they preserve their existence as much at the expense of truth as at the expense of the future.

The good - cannot create, they are always the beginning of the end -

- they crucify him who writes new values on new law-tables, they sacrifice the future to themselves, they crucify the whole human future!

The good - have always been the beginning of the end...

And whatever harm the world-calumniators may do, the harm the good do is the most harmful harm.

5

Zarathustra, the first psychologist of the good, is - consequently - a friend of the wicked. When a décadence-species of man has risen to the rank of the highest species of man, this can happen only at the expense of its antithetical species, the species of man strong and certain of life. When the herd-animal is resplendent in the glow of the highest virtue, the exceptional man must be devalued to the wicked man. When mendaciousness at any price appropriates the word 'truth' for its perspective, what is actually veracious must be discovered bearing the worst names. Zarathustra here leaves no doubt: he says that it was knowledge of precisely the good, the 'best', which made him feel horror at man in general; it was out of this repugnance that the wings grew which 'carried him to distant futures' - he does not dissemble that it is precisely in relation to the good that his type of man, a relatively superhuman type, is superhuman, that the good and just would call his superman a devil...

You highest men my eyes have encountered! This is my doubt of you and my secret laughter: I think you would call my superman - a devil!

Your souls are so unfamiliar with what is great that the superman would be fearful to you in his goodness...

It is at this point and nowhere else that one must make a start if one is to understand what Zarathustra's intentions are: the species of man he delineates delineates reality as it is: he is strong enough for it - he is not estranged from or entranced by it, he is reality itself, he still has all that is fearful and questionable in reality in him, only thus can man possess greatness...

6

- But there is also another sense in which I have chosen for myself the word immoralist as a mark of distinction and badge of honour; I am proud to possess this word which sets me off against the whole of humanity. No one has yet felt Christian morality as beneath him: that requires a height, a farsightedness, a hitherto altogether unheard-of psychological profundity and abysmalness. Christian morality has hitherto been the Circe of all thinkers - they stood in its service. - Who before me has entered the caverns out of which the poisonous blight of this kind of ideal - world-calumny! - wells up? Who has even ventured to suspect that these caverns exist? Who before me at all among philosophers has been a psychologist and not rather its opposite 'higher swindler', 'idealist'? Before me there was no psychology. - To be the first here can be a curse, it is in any case a destiny: for one is also the first to despise... Disgust at mankind is my danger...

7

Have I been understood? - What defines me, what sets me apart from all the rest of mankind, is that I have unmasked Christian morality. That is why I needed a word which would embody the sense of a challenge to everyone. Not to have opened its eyes here sooner counts to me as the greatest piece of uncleanliness which humanity has on its conscience, as self-deception become instinct, as a fundamental will not to observe every event, every cause, every reality, as false-coinage in psychologicis to the point of crime. Blindness in the face of Christianity is the crime par excellence - the crime against life... The millennia, the peoples, the first and the last, the philosophers and the old women - except for five or six moments of history, me as the seventh - on this point they are all worthy of one another. The Christian has hitherto been the 'moral being', a curiosity without equal - and, as 'moral being', more absurd, mendacious, vain, frivolous, harmful to himself than even the greatest despiser of mankind could have allowed himself to dream. Christian morality - the most malicious form of the will to the lie, the actual Circe of mankind: that which has ruined it. It is not error as error which horrifies me at the sight of this, not the millennia-long lack of 'good will', of discipline, of decency, of courage in spiritual affairs which betrays itself in its victory - it is the lack of nature, it is the utterly ghastly fact that anti-nature itself has received the highest honours as morality, and has hung over mankind as law, as categorical imperative!... To blunder to this extent, not as an individual, not as a people, but as mankind!... That contempt has been taught for the primary instincts of life; that a 'soul', a 'spirit' has been lyingly invented in order to destroy the body; that one teaches that there is something unclean in the precondition of life, sexuality; that the evil principle is sought in that which is most profoundly necessary for prosperity, in strict selfishness (- the very word is slanderous!); that on the other hand one sees in the typical signs of decline and contradictoriness of instinct, in the 'selfless', in loss of centre of gravity, in 'depersonalization' and 'love of one's neighbour' (- lust for one's neighbour!) the higher value, what am I saying! value in itself!... What! could mankind itself be in décadence? has it always been? - What is certain is that it has been taught only décadence values as supreme values. The morality of unselfing is the morality of decline par excellence, the fact 'I am perishing' translated into the imperative 'you all shall perish' - and not only into the imperative!... This sole morality which has hitherto been taught, the morality of unselfing, betrays a will to the end, it denies the very foundations of life. - Let us here leave the possibility open that it is not mankind which is degenerating but only that parasitic species of man the priest, who with the aid of morality has lied himself up to being the determiner of mankind's values - who divines in Christian morality his means to power... And that is in fact my insight: the teachers, the leaders of mankind, theologians included, have also one and all been décadents: thence the revaluation of all values into the inimical to life, thence morality... Definition of morality: morality - the idiosyncrasy of décadents with the hidden intention of avenging themselves on life - and successfully. I set store by this definition.

8

- Have I been understood? - I have not just now said a word that I could not have said five years ago through the mouth of Zarathustra. - The unmasking of Christian morality is an event without equal, a real catastrophe. He who exposes it is a force majeure, a destiny - he breaks the history of mankind into two parts. One lives before him, one lives after him... The lightning-bolt of truth struck precisely that which formerly stood highest: he who grasps what was then destroyed had better see whether he has anything at all left in his hands. Everything hitherto called 'truth' is recognized as the most harmful, malicious, most subterranean form of the lie; the holy pretext of 'improving' mankind as the cunning to suck out life itself and to make it anaemic. Morality as vampirism... He who unmasks morality has therewith unmasked the valuelessness of all values which are or have been believed in; he no longer sees in the most revered, even canonized types of man anything venerable, he sees in them the most fateful kind of abortion, fateful because they exercise fascination... The concept 'God' invented as the antithetical concept to life - everything harmful, noxious, slanderous, the whole mortal enmity against life brought into one terrible unity! The concept 'the Beyond', 'real world' invented so as to deprive of value the only world which exists - so as to leave over no goal, no reason, no task for our earthly reality! The concept 'soul', 'spirit', finally even 'immortal soul', invented so as to despise the body, so as to make it sick - 'holy' - so as to bring to all the things in life which deserve serious attention, the questions of nutriment, residence, cleanliness, weather, a horrifying frivolity! Instead of health 'salvation of the soul' - which is to say a folie circulaire between spasms of atonement and redemption hysteria! The concept 'sin' invented together with the instrument of torture which goes with it, the concept of 'free will', so as to confuse the instincts, so as to make mistrust of the instincts into second nature! In the concept of the 'selfless', of the 'self-denying' the actual badge of décadence, being lured by the harmful, no longer being able to discover where one's advantage lies, self-destruction, made the sign of value in general, made 'duty', 'holiness', the 'divine' in man! Finally - it is the most fearful - in the concept of the good man common cause made with everything weak, sick, illconstructed, suffering from itself, all that which ought to perish - the law of selection crossed, an ideal made of opposition to the proud and well-constituted, to the affirmative man, to the man certain of the future and guaranteeing the future - the latter is henceforth called the evil man... And all this was believed in as morality! - Ecrasez l'infâme! -

9

- Have I been understood? - Dionysos against the Crucified...

注释

★ 'We strive after the forbidden' (Ovid).